<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-03-11T01:03:17Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:6367609" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:6367609</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-02-13</datestamp>
        <setSpec>tropmed</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Am J Trop Med Hyg</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Am. J. Trop. Med. Hyg</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">tpmd</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">tropmed</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>The American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0002-9637</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1476-1645</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>The American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC6367609</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6367609</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">6367609</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30594260</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30594260</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">tpmd170964</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.17-0964</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Articles</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Increase in Reported Cholera Cases in Haiti Following Hurricane Matthew: An Interrupted Time Series Model</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Hulland</surname>
                    <given-names>Erin</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Subaiya</surname>
                    <given-names>Saleena</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Pierre</surname>
                    <given-names>Katilla</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Barthelemy</surname>
                    <given-names>Nickolson</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Pierre</surname>
                    <given-names>Jean Samuel</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Dismer</surname>
                    <given-names>Amber</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Juin</surname>
                    <given-names>Stanley</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
                    <sup>4</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Fitter</surname>
                    <given-names>David</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
                    <sup>4</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Brunkard</surname>
                    <given-names>Joan</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
                    <sup>5</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Division of Global Health Protection, Center for Global Health, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, Georgia;</aff>
                <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Global Immunization Division, Center for Global Health, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, Georgia;</aff>
                <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>MSPP Haiti, Directorate of Epidemiology, Laboratory and Research, Delmas, Haiti;</aff>
                <aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention Haiti, Tabarre, Haiti;</aff>
                <aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>Division of Foodborne, Waterborne and Environmental Diseases, National Center for Emerging and Zoonotic Infectious Diseases, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, Georgia</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Address correspondence to Erin Hulland, Division of Global Health Protection, Center for Global Health, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, MS E-22, 1600 Clifton Rd. NE, Atlanta, GA 30329. E-mail: <email>e.hulland@gmail.com</email></corresp>
                <fn fn-type="present-address" id="fn1">
                  <p>Disclaimer: The findings and conclusions of this report are those of the authors and do not necessarily represent the official position of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="present-address" id="fn2">
                  <p>Authors’ addresses: Erin Hulland and Amber Dismer, Division of Global Health Protection, Center for Global Health, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA, E-mails: <email>e.hulland@gmail.com</email> and <email>vic3@cdc.gov</email>. Saleena Subaiya, Global Immunization Division, Center for Global Health, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA, E-mail: <email>saleena.subaiya@gmail.com</email>. Katilla Pierre, Nickolson Barthelemy, and Jean Samuel Pierre, MSPP Haiti, Directorate of Epidemiology and Research, Delmas, Haiti, E-mails: <email>katillapierre@gmail.com</email>, <email>nickybea2001@yahoo.fr</email>, and <email>samuel82us@yahoo.fr</email>. Stanley Juin, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention Haiti, Tabarre, Haiti, E-mail: <email>wso7@cdc.gov</email>. David Fitter, Division of Global Health Protection, Center for Global Health, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA, and Centers for Disease Control and Prevention Haiti, Tabarre, Haiti, E-mail: <email>vid3@gov</email>. Joan Brunkard, Division of Foodborne, Waterborne and Environmental Diseases, National Center for Emerging and Zoonotic Infectious Diseases, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA, E-mail: <email>feu4@cdc.gov</email>.</p>
                </fn>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <month>2</month>
                <year>2019</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>26</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2018</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>26</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2018</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. -->
              <volume>100</volume>
              <issue>2</issue>
              <fpage>368</fpage>
              <lpage>373</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>08</day>
                  <month>12</month>
                  <year>2017</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>30</day>
                  <month>9</month>
                  <year>2018</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© The American Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
                <?release-delay 0|0?>
                <license license-type="open-access">
                  <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="tpmd170964.pdf"/>
              <abstract>
                <title>Abstract.</title>
                <p>Matthew, a category 4 hurricane, struck Haiti on October 4, 2016, causing widespread flooding and damage to buildings and crops, and resulted in many deaths. The damage caused by Matthew raised concerns of increased cholera transmission particularly in Sud and Grand’Anse departments, regions which were hit most heavily by the storm. To evaluate the change in reported cholera cases following Hurricane Matthew on reported cholera cases, we used interrupted time series regression models of daily reported cholera cases, controlling for the impact of both rainfall, following a 4-week lag, and seasonality, from 2013 through 2016. Our results indicate a significant increase in reported cholera cases after Matthew, suggesting that the storm resulted in an immediate surge in suspect cases, and a decline in reported cholera cases in the 46-day post-storm period, after controlling for rainfall and seasonality. Regression models stratified by the department indicate that the impact of the hurricane was regional, with larger surges in the two most highly storm-affected departments: Sud and Grand’Anse. These models were able to provide input to the Ministry of Health in Haiti on the national and regional impact of Hurricane Matthew and, with further development, could provide the flexibility of use in other emergency situations. This article highlights the need for continued cholera prevention and control efforts, particularly in the wake of natural disasters such as hurricanes, and the continued need for intensive cholera surveillance nationally.</p>
              </abstract>
              <counts>
                <page-count count="6"/>
              </counts>
            </article-meta>
            <notes notes-type="disclaimer">
              <p>
                <named-content content-type="print-only">Note: Supplemental files appear at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ajtmh.org">www.ajtmh.org</ext-link>.</named-content>
              </p>
            </notes>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro" id="s1">
              <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
              <p>In October 2010, 10 months after the devastating earthquake in metropolitan Port-au-Prince in January, the first cholera cases, later confirmed as <italic>Vibrio cholera</italic> O1 (serotype Ogawa, biotype El Tor), were reported in Haiti in the Artibonite and Centre administrative departments.<sup><xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> In the next 2 years, &gt; 600,000 cholera cases (suspect and laboratory-confirmed) were reported through the Ministry of Public Health and Population’s (French Acronym MSPP) National Cholera Surveillance System (NCSS).<sup><xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>–<xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> In 2016, 41,421 cholera cases were reported to NCSS.<sup><xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> Although the MSPP’s Directorate of Epidemiology, Laboratory, and Research, which is responsible for NCSS, has reported a reduction in the number of cases in recent years, cholera continues to be reported daily from almost all of Haiti’s 10 departments and transmission has recently been considered endemic in Haiti.<sup><xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>–<xref rid="b6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup></p>
              <p>Hurricane Matthew, a category 4 hurricane, made landfall in Haiti on October 4, 2016, resulting in extensive flooding, infrastructure damage, crop loss, and many deaths.<sup><xref rid="b2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup> Haiti’s Grand’Anse and Sud departments, both located in the southwestern tip of Hispaniola, were the most affected departments, with the closure of health facilities, lack of electricity, and shortages of clean water sources leading to increased concern for a secondary cholera epidemic.</p>
              <p>In the weeks following Hurricane Matthew, health facilities in Sud and Grand’Anse began to report an increase in cases of acute watery diarrhea, raising the alarm of possible increased cholera transmission.<sup><xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> To determine whether an increase in cholera suspect cases associated with Hurricane Matthew, we modeled the impact of Hurricane Matthew on reported cholera suspect cases both nationally and by department, controlling for seasonal trends and rainfall.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="methods" id="s2">
              <title>METHODS</title>
              <sec>
                <title>Data sources.</title>
                <p>In NCSS, a suspect cholera case is defined as a person presenting with acute watery diarrhea, with or without vomiting, to a health facility. We analyzed NCSS data from January 2013 to November 19, 2016.<sup><xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> Because of the higher incidence of diarrheal disease from causes other than cholera in young children, we included only suspect cholera cases among persons aged 5 years and older. In addition, the time period of analysis was restricted to include cases after cholera was considered endemic in Haiti, from January 2013 to November 2016.</p>
                <p>Estimated daily rainfall data were acquired from the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration Center for Satellite Applications and Research (STAR).<sup><xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> The rainfall data were presented as average millimeters of daily precipitation of all STAR raster data points within a department. Each department, therefore, had daily-averaged rainfall data for use in the models, except where no data were available, which were considered missing.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Data analysis.</title>
                <p>Data from the cholera surveillance system and rainfall database were imported using R software for cleaning and analysis.<sup><xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> R Markdown codes were created within 2 weeks of the hurricane to automate two different processes: the generation of rate ratios from week-to-week and year-to-year at the departmental and the interrupted time series (ITS) regression models at the national and departmental level. The comparison of institution-collected data versus aggregated departmental-level data is not presented in this article; all data presented were obtained from the aggregated departmental-level data from NCSS.<sup><xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup></p>
                <p>We used ITS regression models using national data to assess the overall impact of Hurricane Matthew on the number of reported cholera cases. Interrupted time series regression models use segmented regression and are used to assess statistical significance of an event with a clearly defined pre- and post-event period. These methods have been used previously to evaluate the impact of public health interventions where randomized controlled trials are not feasible. Interrupted time series regression has also been applied to assess the impact of environmental factors on health outcomes.<sup><xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>–<xref rid="b15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> To compare patterns of cholera cases in regions most heavily affected by Matthew—primarily the Sud and Grand’Anse departments—with those that were not affected, we constructed 10 departmental level models, one for each department in Haiti. Suspect cholera case counts were assumed to follow a quasi-Poisson distribution which allows overdispersion (to overcome the assumption of the Poisson model that variance is equal to the expected case count).<sup><xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> In our models, we considered both a level change—an abrupt rise in cases immediately following the hurricane—and a level-and-slope change—a gradual change in cases over time following the hurricane—while controlling for seasonal variability and rainfall patterns to assess the immediate but also longer term impacts of the hurricane on cholera in Haiti. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref>, the blue line represents a level change alone, whereas the red line considers both a level and slope change, the type of model we used for our ITS regression models.</p>
                <fig id="f1" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 1.</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Two types of interrupted time series regression models used for Hurricane Matthew analysis. The data used in this figure are a theoretical representation of the level-and-slope change model (in red) and the level change model (in blue) and do not represent study data. The grey horizontal line is meant to reflect the intervention period, such as the hurricane in our study. <named-content content-type="print-only">This figure appears in color at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ajtmh.org">www.ajtmh.org</ext-link></named-content>.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="tpmd170964f1"/>
                </fig>
                <p>Each of the 11 generalized linear models (one for a national level, 10 for 10 departments) included time, a continuous numeric variable representing each day since January 1, 2013, average departmental daily rainfall, a dichotomous indicator of the time pre- and post-Hurricane Matthew to assess a level change, and an interaction term between time and the Hurricane Matthew indicator to assess a level-and-slope change. Seasonality was modeled in Fourier terms as a single pair of sine and cosine functions to account for the year-long seasonal pattern seen in Haiti.<sup><xref rid="b15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> Rainfall was modeled using a 4-week lag, a value chosen based on previous research suggesting lags between 0 and 8 weeks, and in particular a 4-week lag in Haiti<sup><xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup>; rainfall, reported in average millimetre per day per department, was scaled by 0.1 for interpretability.<sup><xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>–<xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup>
<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="equ1">Equation 1</xref> identifies the model used for the analysis, where µ is the expected daily suspected cholera case counts at time <italic>t</italic>, either nationally or departmentally, dependent on the model; ln (POP) is an offset used to account for the population <italic>t</italic> risk; β<sub>0</sub> is the intercept, or baseline case counts; Time<sub><italic>t</italic></sub> is the number of days since January 1, 2013; Hurricane Matthew<sub><italic>t</italic></sub> (HM<sub><italic>t</italic></sub>) is a dichotomous indicator variable where 0 is any time before Hurricane Matthew and 1 is any time following Hurricane Matthew; Rain<sub>t</sub> is a continuous variable representing average daily rainfall in millimeters, scaled by 0.1; two seasonality Fourier terms—one sine, one cosine—with a seasonal period of 1 year; Time following HM<sub><italic>t</italic></sub> is a continuous variable tracking days following Hurricane Matthew but is 0 for any period before the hurricane; <italic>e</italic><sub><italic>t</italic></sub> represents the random error at time <italic>t</italic>. All data management, analysis, and visualization were performed using R Studio version 1.0.136.<sup><xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup><disp-formula id="equ1"><mml:math id="mi1"><mml:mtext>ln</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mo>µ</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>ln</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>POP</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mo>β</mml:mo><mml:mi>0</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo>β</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Time</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo>β</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>HM</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo>β</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Rain</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo>β</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Seasonality Fourier sine term, 365 day cycle</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>β</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Seasonality Fourier cosine term, 365 day cycle</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mo>β</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Time following HM</mml:mtext><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><label>(1)</label></disp-formula></p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results" id="s3">
              <title>RESULTS</title>
              <p>The impact of rainfall and cholera incidence rate in the 46-day period following Hurricane Matthew can be seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2</xref>, with the highest levels of rainfall in the Sud-Est, Nippes, and Grand’Anse departments and highest cholera incidence rates occurring in the Sud and Grand’Anse. A total of 133,092 suspect cholera cases in persons aged 5 years and older were reported between January 1, 2013, to November 19, 2016, of which 6,365 (5%) occurred in the 46-day period following Hurricane Matthew. Average daily cholera case counts in the pre- and post-hurricane period can be seen in <xref rid="t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, as well as average daily rainfall and average daily cholera mortality.</p>
              <fig id="f2" position="float">
                <label>Figure 2.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Rainfall and cholera incidence rate in Haiti in the 46-day period during and following Hurricane Matthew. Haiti departmental shapefile obtained from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://HaitiData.org">HaitiData.org</ext-link>, published by Centre National de l’Information Geospatiale en Haiti (CNIGS) on May 9, 2012 and accessed on May 9, 2017. Total rainfall expressed as millimetre over the 46-day period per department. Cholera incidence rate expressed as number of cases over 5 years per population per 46-day period per 10,000 population per department. <named-content content-type="print-only">This figure appears in color at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ajtmh.org">www.ajtmh.org</ext-link></named-content>.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="tpmd170964f2"/>
              </fig>
              <table-wrap id="t1" position="float">
                <label>Table 1</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>National descriptive characteristics of cholera and rainfall pre- and post-hurricane</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Median</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IQR</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daily reported cholera cases ≥ 5 years of age, pre-hurricane</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.3</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.4</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.0</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.0–126.0</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">329.0</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daily reported cholera cases ≥ 5 years of age, post-hurricane</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">138.4</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.5</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">133.5</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">117.2–154.8</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.0</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">214.0</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daily rainfall (in mm)</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.6</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.7</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
                      <td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0–2.7</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,710.5</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daily cholera-related deaths, pre-hurricane</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.5</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0</td>
                      <td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0–2.0</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.0</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Daily cholera-related deaths, post-hurricane</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.7</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0</td>
                      <td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.0–3.0</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.0</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn>
                    <p>IQR = interquartile range; Max = maximim; Min = minimum; SD = standard deviation.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>The ITS regression models revealed a significant increase in suspected cholera cases in the period following Hurricane Matthew both nationally (β<sub>2</sub>: 19.6 [95% confidence interval: 7.3–32.0]) and in the two most heavily hurricane-affected departments (Grand’Anse: 14.8 [1.1–28.5], Sud: 41.5 [31.5–51.6]) when compared with the pre-hurricane period, after controlling for rainfall, time, and seasonality, as assessed by the dichotomous Hurricane Matthew indicator (a level change) (<xref rid="t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). These models, superimposed over the reported cholera case counts between 2013 and 2016, can be seen in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3</xref>, with the period post-hurricane highlighted by the grey box to the far right. The observable significant increase was not uniform across all 10 departments: five of the remaining eight departments did not experience a significant change in case count after Hurricane Matthew, one department experienced a significant decrease in case counts, and two other departments also experienced a significant increase in case counts.</p>
              <fig id="f3" position="float">
                <label>Figure 3.</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Suspect cholera case counts in Haiti with time series regression models, 2013–2016. HM: Hurricane Matthew; grey box: time since Hurricane Matthew; red line: interrupted time series regression model including both a level change and a slope-and-level change. The top panel presents the national time series cholera data between 2013 and November 2016 with the fitted model in red; the bottom left panel presents the time series cholera data for the Grand’Anse department with the fitted model in red, and the bottom right panel presents the time series cholera data for Sud department with the fitted model in red. <named-content content-type="print-only">This figure appears in color at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ajtmh.org">www.ajtmh.org</ext-link></named-content>.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="tpmd170964f3"/>
              </fig>
              <p>In the national model and in the models for three of the four departments with significant increases post-hurricane—Sud, Centre, and Nord-Ouest—there was a significant downward slope in suspect cholera cases following the initial level change (<xref rid="t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), as assessed by the interaction term between time and the dichotomous Hurricane Matthew indicator (the level-and-slope, or post-hurricane slope change). In Grand’Anse, there was no significant observable trend in the post-hurricane slope. The six departments that did not have significant level changes following the hurricane also did not exhibit any post-hurricane slope changes (<xref rid="t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p>
              <table-wrap id="t2" position="float">
                <label>Table 2</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Estimated effects of Hurricane Matthew, assessed both as a level change, and as a level-and-slope change</p>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Level-only change (β<sub>2</sub>)</th>
                      <th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Level + slope change (β<sub>6</sub>)</th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimate</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimate</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">National</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>19.623</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>7.298–31.988</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>0.002</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>−0.014</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>−0.023 to −0.005</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>0.002</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grand’Anse</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>14.829</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>1.126–28.521</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>0.034</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−</bold>0.009</td>
                      <td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−</bold>0.018–0.001</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.083</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sud</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>141.510</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>31.526–51.553</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>&lt; 0.001</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>−0.028</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>−0.036 to −0.021</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>&lt; 0.001</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Artibonite</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.981</td>
                      <td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.060–31.087</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.108</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−</bold>0.010</td>
                      <td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−</bold>0.022–0.003</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.121</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Centre</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>45.635</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>17.670–74.564</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>0.002</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>−0.033</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>−0.054 to −0.013</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>0.002</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nord</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">−9.582</td>
                      <td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−31.278–11.596</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.380</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td>
                      <td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−</bold>0.008–0.022</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.394</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nord-Est</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">−37.078</td>
                      <td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−100.409–20.352</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.223</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026</td>
                      <td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−</bold>0.015–0.071</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.228</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nord-Ouest</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>40.783</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>7.156–75.027</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>0.018</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>−0.030</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>−0.054 to −0.006</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>0.016</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nippes</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">−<bold>66.017</bold></td>
                      <td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>−121.227 to −17.756</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>0.012</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>0.047</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>0.013–0.086</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>0.012</bold>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ouest</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.028</td>
                      <td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.916–48.106</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.071</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−</bold>0.017</td>
                      <td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−</bold>0.035–0.001</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.063</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sud-Est</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.438</td>
                      <td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.217–74.792</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.089</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−</bold>0.025</td>
                      <td align="char" char="ndash" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−</bold>0.054–0.003</td>
                      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.084</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn>
                    <p>Bold face font indicates statistical significance at the <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 level.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
              <p>In all of our models, seasonality was significantly related to cholera case counts. Nationally, there was a significant decrease in suspected case counts over the duration of the study period (as measured by the β<sub>1</sub> coefficient), although this relationship was not uniform across the departments: in those departments that historically were the most impacted by the first cholera epidemic, including Centre and Artibonite, there was a significant downward trend in cases over time; for five other departments, there was a significant upward trend in cases over time. Increased rainfall was significantly related to elevated suspect cholera case counts in two of the 10 departments, Centre and Nord-Est, neither of which were the two primarily impacted departments (See <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="/content/journals/10.4269/ajtmh.17-0964#supplementary_data">Supplemental File 1</ext-link>).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4">
              <title>DISCUSSION</title>
              <p>These models demonstrate that Hurricane Matthew had a significant, immediate impact on reported suspect cholera cases among persons aged 5 years and older; suspect cholera cases increased both at the national level and in the most highly affected departments. These models also suggest that in most of the affected departments, and on a national scale, the suspect cholera cases decreased significantly over the 46-day period following Hurricane Matthew after the observed immediate significant increase, demonstrated by the negative estimates for the level + slope change interaction term. Although not exclusive to Sud and Grand’Anse, the finding that the significant increases in suspected cholera case counts following Hurricane Matthew were not uniform in all departments provides evidence that Hurricane Matthew did have an impact on those highly affected departments or those that have a longstanding history of cholera treatment and transmission, including Centre, a department known for having an established referral hospital and experience with cholera treatment, notable increases in case counts during the rainy season, and high attack rates compared with the rest of the country.<sup><xref rid="b22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="b23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> Possible reasons for the significant decreasing slopes following the immediate increase in case counts include general seasonal trends and decreased rainfall, heightened reporting in the immediate post-storm period that gradually leveled off, or quick response to the emergency preventing further cases and treating those identified.</p>
              <p>We chose to use ITS regression models for this analysis because of their ease of interpretation, rapid code and model development, and the abrupt, clearly defined nature of the hurricane, which allowed us to clearly separate the data into pre- and post-hurricane periods, and because ITS models are most easily implemented with outcomes that change immediately following an event or with a clearly defined lag period, which is true for cholera transmission. We found through this analysis that interrupted time series models are relatively easy to develop and use and allow public health and emergency response personnel to assess in real time how exogenous factors such as hurricanes or other disasters are impacting disease outcomes. As part of the response to Hurricane Matthew, codes were developed in R markdown for future use by Ministry of Health employees, and several trainings in R were conducted so that the models can be used prospectively for other seasonally varying diseases. Furthermore, analyses produced by these models provided evidence of the effect of Hurricane Matthew for the Ministry of Health in Haiti and other emergency response partners. These models highlight the utility of modeling in post-emergency settings and provide a tool for assessing the significance of natural or man-made disasters on disease surveillance.</p>
              <p>There are a number of limitations to these models. It is possible that because of heightened awareness of the risk of cholera following the Hurricane, facilities may have incorrectly been reporting other diarrheal cases as suspect cholera cases. To minimize this, we limited our analyses to cases in children and adults aged 5 years and older. In addition, an oral cholera vaccination campaign began in select communes of the Sud and Grand’Anse departments on November 8; case counts may have declined in these departments as a result of vaccination activities, which are not controlled for in our models. Third, hurricane response activities included bolstered local surveillance in the heavily impacted departments (Sud and Grand’Anse) and, thus, reporting of suspect cholera cases may have been intensified in these departments relative to others. Fourth, only seasonality and rain were included as time-varying covariates, but other factors, including migration and temperature, may have impacted the models in ways we were unable to quantify. However, whereas factors such as migration and temperature which are both temporally and theoretically linked to the hurricane have the potential to bias our results, other factors not linked to the hurricane may not have the same impact on the estimates. Fifth, we used one set of Fourier terms to describe seasonality of cholera in our models, but sensitivity analyses carried out at the national level demonstrated that two or more pairs of terms fit the model significantly better. However, each additional pair increased the model fit significantly, but also reduced interpretability of the model, and thus for parsimony, we ultimately chose the model with one singular pair of Fourier terms. Results did not differ substantially when considering multiple pairs of Fourier terms when compared with a single pair. Similarly, Fourier terms are also not able to capture seasonal variability from 1 year to the next. However, although our data reflect slightly variable seasonal patterns annually, we note similarities in the annual pattern with a peak in winter months and a dip in summer months. Finally, the rainfall data were both experimental in their release and missing some data for 2013 and, thus, may not fully represent the true rainfall observed in Haiti over our study evaluation time period.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusion" id="s5">
              <title>CONCLUSION</title>
              <p>The national ITS regression model developed in this study suggests an immediate increase in reported cholera cases following the hurricane followed by a significant decline in the post-hurricane period; departmental models further demonstrated that this trend was not uniform for the country and that those more highly impacted departments had significantly higher surges in reported cases following the hurricane. These findings demonstrate that there is a need for continued intensive surveillance following a hurricane as increased cholera transmission is likely. Further research could be beneficial to develop similar models for other infectious or vector-borne diseases following a hurricane or modified for other emergencies. These results of this study revealed that ITS regression models can be developed and implemented relatively quickly in the wake of a natural disaster such as a hurricane and should be considered as part of disaster response to identify where disease transmission was significantly increased to help prevent lives lost and reduce the burden of communicable diseases.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
              <title>Supplementary Material</title>
              <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1">
                <p>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="/content/journals/10.4269/ajtmh.17-0964#supplementary_data">Supplemental files</ext-link>
                </p>
                <media mimetype="application/pdf" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="tpmd170964.SD1.pdf" id="S1" xlink:type="simple" position="anchor"/>
                <media mimetype="application/pdf" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="tpmd170964.SD2.pdf" id="S2" xlink:type="simple" position="anchor"/>
              </supplementary-material>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgments:</title>
              <p>We acknowledge the following people for their assistance and contributions to this manuscript: Dennis Chao, Nadia Lapierre Jean Charles, Martin Meltzer, Melissa Etheart, Donald Lafontant, and Robert Barrais.</p>
            </ack>
            <ref-list>
              <title>REFERENCES</title>
              <ref id="b1">
                <label>1.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barzilay</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaad</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Magloire</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mung</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Boncy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahourou</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mintz</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Steenland</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Vertefeuille</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Tappero</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2013</year><article-title>Cholera surveillance during the Haiti epidemic—the first 2 years</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source><volume>368</volume>: <fpage>599</fpage>–<lpage>609</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23301694</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b2">
                <label>2.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2016</year><article-title>Cholera threatens Haiti after Hurricane Matthew</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source><volume>355</volume>: <fpage>i5516</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27729331</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b3">
                <label>3.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Direction d'Épidémiologie de Laboratoire et de Récherches</collab></person-group>, <year>2016</year><source>Rapport du Réseau National de Surveillance. Sites Choléra, 52ème Semaine Épidémiologique 2016</source>. <publisher-loc>Port-au-Prince, Haiti</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ministère de la Santé Publique et de la Population</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b4">
                <label>4.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirpich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Weppelmann</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>JG</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><name><surname>Longini</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2015</year><article-title>Cholera transmission in ouest department of Haiti: dynamic modeling and the future of the epidemic</article-title>. <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><volume>9</volume>: <fpage>e0004153</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26488620</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b5">
                <label>5.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sack</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2015</year><article-title>Updated global burden of cholera in endemic countries</article-title>. <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><volume>9</volume>: <fpage>e0003832</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26043000</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b6">
                <label>6.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group>, <year>2010</year><article-title>Cholera vaccines: WHO position paper</article-title>. <source>Wkly Epidemiol Rec</source><volume>85</volume>: <fpage>117</fpage>–<lpage>128</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20349546</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b7">
                <label>7.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Direction d'Épidémiologie de Laboratoire et de Recherches</collab></person-group>, <year>2016</year><source>Cholera Surveillance Data, 2013–2016</source>. <publisher-loc>Port-au-Prince, Haiti</publisher-loc>: <publisher-loc>Ministère de la Santé Publique et de la Population</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b8">
                <label>8.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>NOAA/NESDIS Center for Satelite Applications and Research</collab></person-group>, <year>2016</year><source>STAR Satellite Rainfall Estimates—Hydro-Estimator for Mexico, Central America, and the Caribbean</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>U.S. Department of Commerce</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b9">
                <label>9.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>R Core Team</collab></person-group>, <year>2016</year><source>R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing</source>. <publisher-loc>Vienna, Austria</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>R Foundation for Statistical Computing</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b10">
                <label>10.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Institut Haitien de Statistique et d'Informatique</collab></person-group>, <year>2015</year><source>Estimation de la Population 2015</source>. <publisher-loc>Port-au-Prince, Haiti</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Ministry of Economy and Finances</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b11">
                <label>11.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hashizume</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hajat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagatsuma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Faruque</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sack</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2008</year><article-title>The effect of rainfall on the incidence of cholera in Bangladesh</article-title>. <source>Epidemiology</source><volume>19</volume>: <fpage>103</fpage>–<lpage>110</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18091420</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b12">
                <label>12.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Milojavec</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashizume</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>McAllister</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Faruque</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yunus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Streatfield</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Moji</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2012</year><article-title>Health effects of flooding in rural Bangladesh</article-title>. <source>Epidemiology</source><volume>23</volume>: <fpage>107</fpage>–<lpage>115</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22082995</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b13">
                <label>13.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lopez Bernal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cummins</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasparrini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2016</year><article-title>Interrupted time series regression for the evaluation of public health interventions: a tutorial</article-title>. <source>Int J Epidemiol</source><volume>0</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b14">
                <label>14.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gasparrini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Barchielli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2009</year><article-title>On the relationship between smoking bans and incidence of acute myocardial infarction</article-title>. <source>Eur J Epidemiol</source><volume>24</volume>: <fpage>597</fpage>–<lpage>602</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19649714</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b15">
                <label>15.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhaskaran</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasparrini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hajat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Smeeth</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2013</year><article-title>Time series regression studies in environmental epidemiology</article-title>. <source>Int J Epidemiol</source><volume>42</volume>: <fpage>1187</fpage>–<lpage>1195</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23760528</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b16">
                <label>16.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barone-Adesi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasparrini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vizzini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Merlettie</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Richiardi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2011</year><article-title>Effects of Italian smoking regulation on rates of hospital admission for acute coronary events: a country-wide study</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><italic>:</italic><fpage>e17419</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21399685</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b17">
                <label>17.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Weppelmann</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Longini</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>De Rochars</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2015</year><article-title>Increased isolation frequency of toxigenic <italic>Vibrio cholerae</italic> O1 from environmental monitoring sites in Haiti</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>10</volume>: <fpage>e0124098</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25853552</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b18">
                <label>18.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huq</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Critical factors influencing the occurrence of <italic>Vibrio cholerae</italic> in the environment of Bangladesh</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><volume>71</volume>: <fpage>4645</fpage>–<lpage>4654</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16085859</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b19">
                <label>19.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hashizume</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Faruque</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagatsuma</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2010</year><article-title>Cholera in Bangladesh: climatic components of seasonal variation</article-title>. <source>Epidemiology</source><volume>21</volume>: <fpage>706</fpage>–<lpage>710</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20562706</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b20">
                <label>20.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eisenberg</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kujbida</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuite</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisman</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name><name><surname>Tien</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2013</year><article-title>Examining rainfall and cholera dynamics in Haiti using statistical and dynamic modeling approaches</article-title>. <source>Epidemics</source><volume>5</volume>: <fpage>197</fpage>–<lpage>207</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24267876</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b21">
                <label>21.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mendelsohn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2006</year><article-title>Climate and cholera in KwaZulu-Natal, South Africa: the role of environmental factors and implications for epidemic preparedness</article-title>. <source>Int J Hyg Environ Health</source><volume>211</volume>: <fpage>156</fpage>–<lpage>162</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b22">
                <label>22.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Partners in Health</collab></person-group>, <year>2017</year><comment><italic>Hôpital Universitaire de Mirebalais</italic>. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pih.org/pages/mirebalais">http://www.pih.org/pages/mirebalais</ext-link>. Accessed 2017</comment>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b23">
                <label>23.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rebaudet</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gazin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrais</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossignol</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Barthelemy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaudart</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Boncy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Magloire</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Piarroux</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2013</year><article-title>The dry season in Haiti: a window of opportunity to eliminate cholera</article-title>. <source>PLoS Curr</source><volume>5</volume>: <comment>pii 2193a0ec4401d9526203af12e5024dd</comment>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
