<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-03-11T01:02:39Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:6433008" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:6433008</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-04-03</datestamp>
        <setSpec>eid</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Emerg Infect Dis</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Emerging Infect. Dis</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EID</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Emerging Infectious Diseases</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">1080-6040</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1080-6059</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC6433008</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6433008</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">6433008</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30882314</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30882314</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">17-2121</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid2504.172121</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Research</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="article-type">
                  <subject>Research</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="TOC-title">
                  <subject>Spatial Dynamics of Chikungunya Virus, Venezuela, 2014</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Spatial Dynamics of Chikungunya Virus, Venezuela,
2014</article-title>
                <alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Spatial Dynamics of Chikungunya Virus,
Venezuela</alt-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Lizarazo</surname>
                    <given-names>Erley</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Vincenti-Gonzalez</surname>
                    <given-names>Maria</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Grillet</surname>
                    <given-names>Maria E.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Bethencourt</surname>
                    <given-names>Sarah</given-names>
                  </name>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Diaz</surname>
                    <given-names>Oscar</given-names>
                  </name>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ojeda</surname>
                    <given-names>Noheliz</given-names>
                  </name>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ochoa</surname>
                    <given-names>Haydee</given-names>
                  </name>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Rangel</surname>
                    <given-names>Maria Auxiliadora</given-names>
                  </name>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Tami</surname>
                    <given-names>Adriana</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="fn" rid="FN2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="aff1">University of Groningen, Groningen, the Netherlands (E. Lizarazo, M.
Vincenti-Gonzalez, A. Tami); </aff>
                <aff id="aff2">Universidad Central de Venezuela, Caracas, Venezuela (M.E. Grillet); </aff>
                <aff id="aff3">Universidad de Carabobo, Valencia, Venezuela (S. Bethencourt, A.
Tami); </aff>
                <aff id="aff4">Fundación Instituto Carabobeño para la Salud, Carabobo,
Venezuela (O. Diaz, N. Ojeda, H. Ochoa, M.A. Rangel)</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1">Address for correspondence: Adriana Tami, Department of Medical
Microbiology, University Medical Center Groningen, Hanzeplein 1 (HPC EB80), 9713
GZ Groningen, the Netherlands; email: <email xlink:href="a.tami@umcg.nl">a.tami@umcg.nl</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2019</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>25</volume>
              <issue>4</issue>
              <fpage>672</fpage>
              <lpage>680</lpage>
              <abstract>
                <p>Since chikungunya virus emerged in the Caribbean region in late 2013, ≈45
countries have experienced chikungunya outbreaks. We described and quantified
the spatial and temporal events after the introduction and propagation of
chikungunya into an immunologically naive population from the urban
north-central region of Venezuela during 2014. The epidemic curve (n = 810
cases) unraveled within 5 months with a basic reproductive number of 3.7 and a
radial spread traveled distance of 9.4 km at a mean velocity of 82.9 m/day. The
highest disease diffusion speed occurred during the first 90 days, and space and
space–time modeling suggest the epidemic followed a particular geographic
pathway with spatiotemporal aggregation. The directionality and heterogeneity of
transmission during the first introduction of chikungunya indicated existence of
areas of diffusion and elevated risk for disease and highlight the importance of
epidemic preparedness. This information will help in managing future threats of
new or reemerging arboviruses.</p>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
                <title>Keywords: </title>
                <kwd>Chikungunya</kwd>
                <kwd>arbovirus</kwd>
                <kwd>outbreak</kwd>
                <kwd>spatiotemporal</kwd>
                <kwd>basic reproductive number</kwd>
                <kwd>Venezuela</kwd>
                <kwd>viruses</kwd>
                <kwd>vector-borne infections</kwd>
                <kwd>mosquitoes</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <p>Chikungunya, a reemerging mosquitoborne viral infection, is responsible for one of the
most explosive epidemics in the Western Hemisphere in recent years. Since its
introduction in the Caribbean region at the end of 2013, chikungunya virus (CHIKV)
rapidly expanded within a year to most countries of South, Central, and North America
(<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><italic>2</italic></xref>). CHIKV belongs to the genus
<italic>Alphavirus</italic> (Togaviridae), first isolated in Tanzania during 1952
(<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr"><italic>3</italic></xref>). Its sylvatic (enzootic)
cycle in Africa involves nonhuman primates; the virus is transmitted by an ample range
of forest-dwelling <italic>Aedes</italic> spp. mosquitoes (<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr"><italic>4</italic></xref>). Within the urban (human) cycle across Asia, the
Indian Ocean, and the Americas, CHIKV is transmitted by <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>
and <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> mosquitoes (<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><italic>5</italic></xref><italic>–</italic><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr"><italic>7</italic></xref>). Most (72%–93%) infected persons develop
symptomatic disease characterized by fever, rash, and incapacitating arthralgia,
progressing in 42%–60% of patients to chronic, long-lasting relapsing or
lingering rheumatic disease (<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr"><italic>8</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr"><italic>9</italic></xref>). The lack of population immunity to CHIKV in the Americas
alongside the ubiquitous occurrence of competent <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> mosquitoes
and human mobility may explain the rapid expansion of CHIKV across the Americas; cases
doubled each month during the epidemic exponential phase (<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr"><italic>10</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><italic>11</italic></xref>). At the end of 2014, &gt;1 million suspected and
confirmed cases, including severe cases and deaths, were reported in 45 countries and
territories; this figure reached almost 3 million cases by mid-2016 (<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><italic>12</italic></xref>). The real number of cases is
most likely higher because of misdiagnosis with dengue virus (DENV) infection and
underreporting.</p>
            <p>In Venezuela, the first official imported chikungunya case was reported in June 2014, and
local transmission followed soon thereafter. Chikungunya quickly spread, causing a large
national epidemic affecting the most populated urban areas of northern Venezuela, where
DENV transmission is high. Given the paucity of official national data, epidemiologic
inference was used to estimate the number of cases. Although nationally the disease
attack rate was estimated at 6.9%–13.8% (<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr"><italic>13</italic></xref>), the observed attack rate in populated urban areas
was ≈40%–50%, comparable to those reported in the Dominican Republic
(<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr"><italic>14</italic></xref>) and Asia and higher
than those in La Reunion (<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr"><italic>15</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr"><italic>16</italic></xref>).</p>
            <p>The rapid expansion and worldwide spread in the last decade make CHIKV one of the most
public health–relevant arboviruses (<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr"><italic>17</italic></xref>). With the reemergence of other arboviruses, new
large-scale outbreaks in the near future seem likely (<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr"><italic>18</italic></xref>). Clarifying and quantifying the introduction and
propagation range in space and time of the initial epidemic wave of chikungunya within
the complex urban settings of Latin America will shed light on arboviral transmission
dynamics and help in managing future threats of new or emerging arboviruses operating
under similar epidemiologic dynamics. We characterized the epidemic wave of chikungunya
in a region highly affected by the 2014 outbreak in Venezuela. To this end, we described
the spatial progression of the epidemic using geographic information systems (GIS),
quantified the global geographic path that CHIKV most likely followed during the first 6
months of the epidemic by fitting a polynomial regression model (trend surface
analysis), determined the general direction and speed of the propagation wave of the
disease, and identified the local space–time disease clusters through spatial
statistics.</p>
            <sec sec-type="materials|methods">
              <title>Materials and Methods</title>
              <sec>
                <title>Study Area</title>
                <p>Carabobo State is situated in the north-central region of Venezuela (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). It is one of the most densely
populated regions (<xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr"><italic>19</italic></xref>).</p>
                <fig id="F1" fig-type="figure" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Area of study on the spatial dynamics of chikungunya virus, Carabobo
state, Venezuela, 2014. Blue shading indicates 2014 population by
parish. Most persons live in the capital city of Valencia (892,530
inhabitants); within the metropolitan area, poorer settlements are
located mainly in the southern area, and the most organized and
urbanized medium- and high-level neighborhoods are situated toward the
north-central part. Insets indicate location of Carabobo state in
Venezuela and Venezuela in South America.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="17-2121-F1"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Study Design and Data Collection</title>
                <p>To determine the spatiotemporal spread of the 2014 chikungunya epidemic at local
and global scales, we conducted a retrospective study of patient and
epidemiologic data collected through the national Notifiable Diseases
Surveillance System (NDSS). Suspected chikungunya was diagnosed in 810 persons
of all ages by their physicians; these patients were reported through the NDSS
to the epidemiologic department of the Regional Ministry of Health of Carabobo
State. Patients suspected of having chikungunya were those with fever of sudden
onset, rash, and joint pain with or without other influenza-like symptoms.
Patients who attended public or private healthcare centers across Carabobo State
municipalities were included in this study. </p>
                <p>Patient data were obtained for June 10–December 3, 2014 (epidemiologic
weeks 22–49), coinciding with the Venezuela chikungunya outbreak. Data
corresponding to the first visit of the patients to a healthcare center were
included and comprised patient address, clinical manifestations, and
epidemiologic risk factors. This information was entered in a database, checked
for consistency, and analyzed anonymously. We defined the index case as the
first chikungunya patient reported by the NDSS within this region.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Temporal Dynamics of CHIKV Spread</title>
                <p>We described the growth rate of the disease by plotting the cumulative cases per
epidemiologic week and fitted a logistic curve after examining the shape of the
epidemiologic curve (<xref ref-type="local-data" rid="SD1">Appendix</xref>
Figure 1). We estimated the average number of secondary cases resulting from a
primary case in a completely susceptible population— the
epidemic’s basic reproductive number (R<sub>0</sub>)—from the
initial phase of the epidemic using the exponential growth method (<xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr"><italic>20</italic></xref>) and then calculated a
real-time estimate of R<sub>0</sub>, called R<sub>t</sub> (<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr"><italic>21</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr"><italic>22</italic></xref>), to explore the time-varying
transmissibility of chikungunya (<xref ref-type="local-data" rid="SD1">Appendix</xref>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Spatiotemporal Trend of the Epidemic Wave of Chikungunya</title>
                <p>We georeferenced the address of every patient into a GIS so that the
<italic>X<sub>i</sub></italic> (east–west) and
<italic>Y<sub>i</sub></italic> (north–south) coordinates of each
chikungunya case were derived. We drew the weekly spatial progression of the 810
reported cases with respect to the index case in a map. To assess the spreading
pattern before the epidemic reached the steady (plateau) state (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>), we selected cases that occurred
0–125 days (up to epidemiologic week 40) after the index case. Within
this time range, the case notification rate maintained a sustained growth.</p>
                <fig id="F2" fig-type="figure" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 2</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Reported chikungunya cases during epidemic, Carabobo state, Venezuela,
2014. Black line with open black dots indicates chikungunya cases; red
line with open red diamonds, cumulative cases.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="17-2121-F2"/>
                </fig>
                <p>To explore the general spatial trend of chikungunya cases (or the movement of the
epidemic wave of infection) across the study area, we developed a map of time of
disease spread using trend surface analysis, a global surface fitting method
(<xref ref-type="local-data" rid="SD1">Appendix</xref>). We created the
variable <italic>time</italic> (in days) using the symptom onset date from the
index case as the baseline date across the 810 case localities; that is,
<italic>time</italic> (<italic>X</italic><sub>i</sub>,
<italic>Y</italic><sub>i</sub>). Thus, <italic>time</italic> is considered
the number of days elapsed between the appearance of a case in a specific
locality <italic>Zi</italic> and the index case. We used results of the trend
surface analysis to generate a contour map or smoothed surface; each contour
line represented a specific predicted time period in this urban landscape
setting since the initial invasion of the virus. The local rate and direction of
the spread of infection was estimated as the directional derivative at each case
using the trend surface analysis fitted model to obtain local vectors that
depicted the direction and speed (inverse of the slope along the direction of
the movement) of infection propagation from each locality in <italic>X</italic>
and <italic>Y</italic> directions. In addition, we used kriging, a local
geostatistical interpolation method, to generate an estimated continuous surface
from the scattered set of points (i.e., <italic>time</italic>) with
<italic>z</italic> value to better capture the local spatial variation of
chikungunya spread across the urban landscape (<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr"><italic>23</italic></xref>). We used ordinary kriging to predict values
of the time period since the initial invasion of the virus. We selected the
model with the best fit out of 3 theoretical variogram models tested by
cross-validation to predict the values at unmeasured locations and their
associated errors (<xref ref-type="local-data" rid="SD1">Appendix</xref>).</p>
                <p>We also obtained an empirical basic baseline rate of disease spread to quantify
the observed velocity for each case <italic>z<sub>i</sub></italic> directly from
the data by measuring the linear distance (meters) of case
<italic>Z<sub>i</sub></italic> to the index case and then dividing it by the
time in days that elapsed since the index case was reported. We assessed
differences between velocities by using the Kruskal-Wallis test, a nonparametric
method to test differences between groups when these are nonnormally distributed
(<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr"><italic>24</italic></xref>).</p>
                <p>Finally, to identify general space–time clusters of chikungunya
transmission, we performed a Knox analysis (<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr"><italic>25</italic></xref>), and to identify interactions at specific
temporal intervals, we used the incremental Knox test (IKT) (<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr"><italic>26</italic></xref>). For general
space–time clusters we selected critical values of 100 m
(<italic>distance</italic>) and 3 weeks (<italic>time</italic>) after
multiple distance and time windows testing (<xref ref-type="local-data" rid="SD1">Appendix</xref> Table 2). Our selection was based on the
<italic>Aedes</italic> mosquito flight range and the maximum duration of the
intrinsic and extrinsic incubation periods of the virus, respectively (<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr"><italic>27</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr"><italic>28</italic></xref>). Upon identification of the cluster,
we calculated the distance between the first case of a cluster
(<italic>C</italic><sub>1</sub>) and the cases within the cluster
<italic>Z<sub>i</sub></italic>, considering this distance as a measure
of virus disease spread. For interactions at specific temporal intervals, we
used the IKT in an exploratory mode over the time intervals from 1 day to 31
days and space distances from 25 m to 500 m (<xref ref-type="local-data" rid="SD1">Appendix</xref>). We conducted spatial analyses using R software
(The R-Development Core Team, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.r-project.org">http://www.r-project.org</ext-link>)
and ArcGIS version 10.3 (ESRI Corporation, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.esri.com">https://www.esri.com</ext-link>) using the
Spatial Analyst Toolbox and generated maps with Quantum GIS 2.14.3 Essen (QGIS
Development Team GNU—General Public License, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.qgis.org">https://www.qgis.org</ext-link>) software). Space-time (Knox) analysis was
performed using ClusterSeer 2.0 (Terraseer, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.biomedware.com/software/clusterseer">https://www.biomedware.com/software/clusterseer</ext-link>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Ethics Statement</title>
                <p>Data were analyzed anonymously, and individuals were coded along with the
information of address with a unique numeric identifier. The epidemiologic
department of the Regional Ministry of Health of Carabobo State approved the
study.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results">
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec>
                <title>Temporal Dynamics of CHIKV Spread</title>
                <p>A total of 810 suspected chikungunya cases were reported in Carabobo State in
2014 during epidemiologic weeks 22–49 (28 weeks), representing the first
introduction and propagation of the virus in the north-central region of
Venezuela. The index case was an imported case (in a returning traveler from the
Dominican Republic) in epidemiologic week 22 in the north-central zone of the
capital city (Valencia) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). The
index case was followed by the other imported cases and soon after by locally
transmitted cases.</p>
                <p>The cumulative cases during epidemiologic weeks 22–49 followed a logistic
growth (<xref ref-type="local-data" rid="SD1">Appendix</xref> Figure 1;
R = 0.99, n = 810; p&lt;0.05). The reported cases displayed a
characteristic epidemic curve with a single wave and peaked at epidemiologic
week 33, eleven weeks after the index case (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure
2</xref>). The epidemic takeoff occurred at epidemiologic week 31 (i.e., 9
weeks after the index case). The total duration of the outbreak was ≈28
weeks; however, the main epidemic curve lasted ≈3 months, from
epidemiologic week 30 until epidemiologic weeks 43–44. The initial global
growth rate of the epidemic was 0.53 cases per week, and
R<sub>0</sub> = 3.7 (95% CI 2.78–4.99) secondary
chikungunya cases per primary case (epidemiologic weeks 22–31). We
obtained comparable results when we calculated the instantaneous reproductive
number (R<sub>t</sub> = 4.5, 95% CI 2.4–7.1) during the
epidemic peak. Beginning with epidemiologic week 34, R<sub>t</sub> values fell
below 1, and they gradually decreased from there onward (<xref ref-type="local-data" rid="SD1">Appendix</xref> Figure 2).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Spatiotemporal Distribution of the Chikungunya Epidemic</title>
                <p>The chikungunya outbreak progressed chronologically and spatially through
Carabobo State (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>; <xref ref-type="other" rid="F6">Video</xref>). The cases reported in Valencia
during the first 6 weeks were located in the central area of the city close to
the index case, whereas a few cases were reported in the southwestern part of
Valencia and in other small urban towns of Carabobo (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>, panel A). The first autochthonous case occurred
during this interval in the south-central area of Valencia, relatively close to
the index case (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>, panel A). During
epidemiologic weeks 28–31, the number of reported cases increased in
parishes around the autochthonous case (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure
3</xref>, panel B). During epidemiologic weeks 32–35, the number of
cases exploded exponentially, and the disease spread rapidly throughout the
capital city and surrounding smaller urban centers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>, panel C). New cases were actively reported during
8 continuous weeks (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>, panels C, D)
to later decrease from epidemiologic week 40 to epidemiologic week 49 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>, panels E, F). The epidemic
progressed in 2 directions (movement axes) in the region: a north–south
direction and a northeastern and southwestern direction. Both shifts
consistently overlapped with the populated centers of the region and the main
traffic routes (motorways and main roads).</p>
                <fig id="F3" fig-type="figure" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 3</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Spatial and temporal spread of chikungunya epidemic, Carabobo state,
Venezuela, June–December 2014. Time is presented at epidemiologic
week intervals as follows: A) weeks 22–27; B) weeks 28–31;
C) weeks 32–35; D) weeks 36–39; E) weeks 40–45; F)
weeks 46–49. Red circles indicate the appearance of new cases for
the given interval; blue indicates the cumulative cases in prior
intervals. Light yellow lines depict the road system of the area of
study; light gray areas represent the populated areas (urban centers)
within the parishes. Yellow star indicates index case; green diamond
indicates first autochthonous case.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="17-2121-F3"/>
                </fig>
                <fig id="F6" fig-type="video" position="float">
                  <label>Video</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Spatial progression of chikungunya outbreak, Carabobo state, Venezuela,
June 10–December 3, 2014 (epidemiologic weeks 22–49).</p>
                  </caption>
                  <media mimetype="video" xlink:href="17-2121-F6.gif" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e537" position="anchor"/>
                </fig>
                <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>, panel A, depicts the general
direction and propagating wave of disease derived from the trend surface
analysis. Contour lines that are far apart indicate that the epidemic diffused
quickly through the area, whereas lines that are closer together show a slower
progression. The direction of diffusion is also given by the edges of the
contour lines. The model located the wave of disease dispersal in the central
part of the region and included the index case and autochthonous case. The bulk
of the outbreak unfolded within 90 days, spreading mainly to the southwestern
and northern parts of the capital city. During this time, the maximum radial
distance traveled was 9.4 km. A slower diffusion was predicted toward the
northeast and southern part of the region. However, the limitation of the method
resulting from edge effects determines that the best area for prediction is the
central one.</p>
                <fig id="F4" fig-type="figure" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 4</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Global and local predicted spreading patterns of chikungunya virus,
Carabobo state, Venezuela, 2014. A) Contour map (global scale) of the
predicted spreading waves and the velocity vector arrows of each case of
chikungunya. The contour map and contour lines in black (traveling
waves) were estimated by the best-fit trend surface analysis (third
order polynomial model) of time (days) to the first reported case or
index case of chikungunya across the landscape. White lines correspond
to the road system of the area. The background gradient of color shows
the probability of chikungunya virus diffusion according to the
prediction of the model: the darker the red, the higher the probability
of spread. Each vector (blue outlined arrows) represents the
instantaneous velocity derived from the partial, differential equations
from the trend surface analysis model (<xref ref-type="local-data" rid="SD1">Appendix</xref>). B) Spatial prediction map for the
ordinary kriging (Gaussian model) interpolation of the time (each color
represents a different number of days) of chikungunya spread. Contour
lines from trend surface analysis depicted in the kriging surface are
shown only for comparison purposes. Yellow star indicates index case;
green diamond indicates first autochthonous case.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="17-2121-F4"/>
                </fig>
                <p>To visualize the local diffusion of CHIKV at each location, we drew the vector
field across the modeled surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>,
panel A). Overall, the model confirms the previous observation of a general
trend or corridor of diffusion of chikungunya cases southwest and northeast of
the capital city within the first 80 days. After 90 days, the epidemic wave
varied its direction and magnitude by location. Although agreeing with the
general pattern shown by the trend surface analysis, the resulting kriging
Gaussian (selected) model interpolation surface (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>, panel B; <xref ref-type="local-data" rid="SD1">Appendix</xref> Table 1) predicts a more heterogeneous spread pattern of
chikungunya cases by matching the patchy (uneven population density)
distribution of human neighborhoods and the road network. In addition, kriging
identified a faster propagation of the epidemiologic wave at the southwestern
and eastern areas where the model showed its best fit (<xref ref-type="local-data" rid="SD1">Appendix</xref> Figure 3, panel A) and a
slower movement to the northeastern and south-central areas than estimated by
the trend surface analysis.</p>
                <p>We calculated the virus diffusion velocities for each parish through the
empirical method (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table</xref>). The mean
velocity of disease spread across the state was 82.9 m ± 53.6 m/day, and
overall, the pattern of diffusion of CHIKV was highest in the suburban and rural
settlements near the capital city. However, the observed velocities varied
significantly by location (n = 735; p&lt;0.05). For instance, the parishes at
the center of the capital (San Jose, Catedral, Candelaria, San Blas, Santa Rosa)
showed velocities &lt;60 m/day, whereas in the remaining localities, including
both rural and suburban towns, the speed was &gt;60 m/day. The maximum velocity
of the outbreak was 483 m/day, measured south of the capital.</p>
                <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
                  <label>Table</label>
                  <caption>
                    <title>Average velocities of chikungunya virus spread across Carabobo state,
Venezuela, 2014</title>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <col width="83" span="1"/>
                    <col width="51" span="1"/>
                    <col width="99" span="1"/>
                    <col width="67" span="1"/>
                    <col width="54" span="1"/>
                    <col width="45" span="1"/>
                    <col width="81" span="1"/>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td rowspan="2" valign="bottom" align="left" scope="row" colspan="1">Civil
parish<hr/></td>
                        <td rowspan="2" valign="bottom" align="center" colspan="1">No. cases<hr/></td>
                        <td valign="bottom" colspan="5" align="center" rowspan="1">Velocity,
m/day<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="bottom" colspan="1" align="center" scope="row" rowspan="1">Mean (95%
CI)<hr/></td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD<hr/></td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum<hr/></td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum<hr/></td>
                        <td valign="bottom" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Location*<hr/></td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Candelaria</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.4 (33.5–45.2)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.3</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Central</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Catedral</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.8 (22.4–35.3)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.5</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Central</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ciudad Alianza</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">146.7</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Not applicable</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">147</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">147</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">East-southeast</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">El Socorro</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.2 (13.5–80.9)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.1</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South-southwest</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Guacara†</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206.2 (−35.1 to 447.6)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">151.7</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">430</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">East-northeast</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Guigue‡</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256.7 (151.7–361.8)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.6</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">163</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">344</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Southeast</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Independencia†</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206.7 (138.8–274.5)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.7</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">138</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">310</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South-southwest</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Los Guayos</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">115.1 (105.3–124.9)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.4</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">East-southeast</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Miguel Peña</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.6 (75.3–86.0)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.6</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">483</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Naguanagua</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.9 (77.3–94.6)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.3</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rafael Urdaneta</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.2 (79.5–94.8)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.3</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">186</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Southeast</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">San Blas</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.6 (39.0–48.3)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.7</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Central</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">San Diego</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.3 (63.5–83.1)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.5</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">150</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North-northeast</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">San Jose</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.6 (21.3–34.0)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.2</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">202</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">North-central</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Santa Rosa</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.4 (55.9–60.9)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.4</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Central</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tacarigua‡</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">197.0 (147.7–246.3)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.0</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">149</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">259</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South-southeast</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tocuyito†</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">149.8 (137.2–162.4)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.8</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">365</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Southwest</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yagua‡</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">111.0 (−3.4 to 225.4)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.7</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">East-northeast</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">735</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.9 (79.0–86.7)</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.6</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">483</td>
                        <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Entire state</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <p>*Location refers to relative locations from the center of the capital
city, Valencia. †Suburban
settlements. ‡Rural settlements.</p>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Spatiotemporal Clusters of the Epidemic Wave</title>
                <p>Results after multiple space and time parameters testing showed that core
clusters remained similar through time (<xref ref-type="local-data" rid="SD1">Appendix</xref> Figure 4), and the relative risk (RR) within the clusters
remained important (RR &gt;1.5) up to 3 weeks (<xref ref-type="local-data" rid="SD1">Appendix</xref> Figure 5). Using selected critical values, we
identified 75 general space–time clusters using Knox analysis (<xref ref-type="local-data" rid="SD1">Appendix</xref> Table 3; <xref ref-type="local-data" rid="SD1">Appendix</xref> Figure 6, panel A). These
clusters included at least 2 space–time-linked cases and a total of 205
(27.9%) cases that showed a space–time relation. The major accumulation
of clusters occurred in the southern and southwestern part of the capital. The
earliest cluster (cluster 7; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>) was
located in the west-central part of the capital and comprised 3 cases, including
the index case. From this cluster, the average distance from each case to the
index case was 32 m, and the cases were reported within 25 days after the index
case. In addition, the major cluster (cluster 57, 12 cases) was located in the
west-central area of the capital 4 km from the index case (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref>). The cases belonging to this cluster occurred
within 9 days (1.3 cases per day); these cases occurred an average of 70 days
(range 69–77 days) after the index case (<xref ref-type="local-data" rid="SD1">Appendix</xref> Table 3). The median time between the first
notified case (symptom onset) and the last case within a cluster was 9 days
(range 3–18 days). Furthermore, the average distance between cases within
the clusters was 75.2 m ± 25.6 m (range 110.6–39.2 m) (<xref ref-type="local-data" rid="SD1">Appendix</xref> Table 4). Furthermore, the
baseline velocity in Carabobo State was similar to the average velocity within
the clusters (69.9 ± 34.4 m/day). These results agree with IKT findings,
where the temporal intervals with the strongest spatial clustering and RR
occurred at 1–7 days and 25–150 m (<xref ref-type="local-data" rid="SD1">Appendix</xref> Figures 7, 8).</p>
                <fig id="F5" fig-type="figure" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 5</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Geographic distribution and significant space–time clustering of
reported chikungunya cases identified in a section of the capital city,
Valencia (metropolitan area), Carabobo state, Venezuela,
June–December 2014. Red dots denote case location; black outlined
circles identify a significant space–time cluster; yellow lines
show the interaction between cases (time–space link). The
analysis was performed using 100 m as clustering distance and 3 weeks as
time window. Significance level for local clustering detection was
p&lt;0.05. Inset depicts the geographic location of Carabobo; black
rectangle indicates highlighted study area.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="17-2121-F5"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>We described and quantified the spatial and temporal events that followed the
introduction and explosive propagation of CHIKV into an immunologically naive
population living in the urban north-central region of Venezuela during 2014. The
main epidemic curve developed within 5 months, with a maximum value of the estimate
of R<sub>0</sub> = 3.7 by epidemiologic week 12. The speed of disease
diffusion was greatest during the first 90 days, and the spatial spread was
heterogeneous following mostly a southwest spatial corridor at a variable local rate
of diffusion across the landscape. The radial spread traveled distance was 9.4 km at
a mean velocity of 82.9 m/day. The chikungunya epidemic showed spatiotemporal
aggregation predominantly south of the capital city, where conditions for
human–vector contact are favorable.</p>
              <p>The temporal dynamics here described, R<sub>0</sub> and its time variable form
R<sub>t,</sub> suggest high transmissibility of CHIKV in this population. These
results agree with previous CHIKV introductions into naive populations (<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr"><italic>29</italic></xref><italic>–</italic><xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr"><italic>31</italic></xref>) and with the 2014 predicted values for the
mid-latitude countries (R<sub>0</sub> = 4–7) of the Americas
(<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr"><italic>31</italic></xref>). High values of
R<sub>0</sub> are also described during first introduction outbreaks of other
<italic>Aedes</italic> mosquito–borne pathogens, such as DENV in Chile
(R<sub>0</sub> = 27.2) (<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr"><italic>32</italic></xref>) and Zika virus in Brazil
(R<sub>0</sub> = 1.5–6) (<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr"><italic>33</italic></xref>) and French Polynesia (<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr"><italic>34</italic></xref>). Yet, overall R<sub>0</sub> estimates for
dengue are ≈2–6 (<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr"><italic>35</italic></xref>). The similarity between the R<sub>0</sub> of CHIKV,
DENV, and Zika virus infections, all transmitted by the same main vector, the
<italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> mosquito, strongly suggests that the major factor
driving the exponential increase of the epidemic curve of arboviruses in naive
populations is the transmission efficiency of the vector.</p>
              <p>Spatially, trend surface and kriging analyses showed a primary wave of disease spread
within the first 80 days in the most likely area of transmission (the southwestern
center of Valencia), whereas a second wave at 90 days showed the spread of cases
toward the southern, western, and northern areas. This sequential pattern is similar
to that of dengue, where transmission within neighborhoods most likely is driven by
mosquito presence or abundance and/or short-distance movement of viremic hosts
(<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr"><italic>36</italic></xref><italic>–</italic><xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr"><italic>38</italic></xref>), whereas long-distance dissemination is
probably generated by human mobility patterns through main roads and motorways. Both
movements powerfully affected disease transmission (<xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr"><italic>39</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr"><italic>40</italic></xref>). Moreover, population density modulates the
chance of vector–host contact (<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr"><italic>30</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr"><italic>41</italic></xref>), a fact reflected in the variation of
calculated velocities across different spatial points and the increased diffusion
speed of the epidemic toward the southernmost populated area.</p>
              <p>Although CHIKV was introduced into a naive population in Venezuela, the distribution
of cases was not random but aggregated into 75 significant space–time
clusters, indicating an increased likelihood of vector–host contact. The area
with most clusters, the southern part of Valencia city, is characterized by densely
populated neighborhoods, lower socioeconomic status, and crowded living conditions.
Similar factors increased the risk for dengue transmission and clustering (hot
spots) in highly endemic urban areas of Venezuela (<xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr"><italic>42</italic></xref>). Poverty and human behavior fostering potential
mosquito breeding sites (such as storing water at home) were linked with a greater
risk for dengue (<xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr"><italic>42</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr"><italic>43</italic></xref>). In Venezuela,
long-lasting deficits in public services, such as frequent and prolonged
interruptions in water supply and electricity, have become regular in recent years.
These inadequacies have obliged residents to store water, maintaining adequate
breeding conditions for <italic>Aedes</italic> vectors during the dry season and
throughout the year (<xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr"><italic>44</italic></xref>).
During the CHIKV epidemic, the proportion of houses infested with
<italic>Aedes</italic> larvae/pupae (house index) in Venezuela was &gt;20%
(<xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr"><italic>45</italic></xref>). The World Health
Organization recommends a house index &lt;5% for adequate vector control (<xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr"><italic>46</italic></xref>).</p>
              <p>In our study, the average distance among cases within chikungunya clusters was 75 m,
which coincided with the reported flying range of urban <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic>
females during mark-release-recapture studies (<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr"><italic>37</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr"><italic>47</italic></xref>). <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> females have been
reported to visit a maximum of 3 houses in a lifetime while not traveling far from
their breeding sites (<xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr"><italic>48</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr"><italic>49</italic></xref>). Thus, the distance traveled by the vector and the
number of possible host encounters with an infected vector cannot explain the entire
disease epidemic spread. Other factors, such as movement of viremic hosts, a widely
distributed vector, and the lack of herd immunity, may play a role, as for DENV, in
long-range spread (<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr"><italic>37</italic></xref>).</p>
              <p>The lack of entomologic data and estimates of human movement limit our study. We
expect that our estimates based on epidemiologic records are accurate because
chikungunya is symptomatic in &gt;80% of cases. Likewise, surveillance in Venezuela
is based on symptomatic patient reporting by treating doctors.</p>
              <p>Our analysis suggests that the epidemic of chikungunya in Venezuela followed a
determined geographic course. This propagation was potentiated south and southwest
of the study area. Chikungunya is now established in Venezuela, along with other
<italic>Aedes</italic> mosquito–borne infections, such as dengue and
Zika. However, further epidemics of these and other reemergent arboviruses (i.e.,
Mayaro virus [<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr"><italic>18</italic></xref>,<xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr"><italic>50</italic></xref>]) are likely to arise. The
insights gained in our study will help identify and predict future epidemic waves of
upcoming vectorborne infections and quickly define intervention areas and improve
outbreak preparedness response in Venezuela and countries with similar settings.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
              <title/>
              <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1">
                <caption>
                  <title>Appendix</title>
                  <p>Full methodologic description and results for an analysis of the spatial
dynamics of chikungunya virus, Venezuela, 2014.</p>
                </caption>
                <media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="17-2121-app-s1.pdf" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e1125" position="anchor"/>
              </supplementary-material>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <fn-group>
              <fn fn-type="citation">
                <p><italic>Suggested citation for this article</italic>: Lizarazo E,
Vincenti-Gonzalez M, Grillet ME, Bethencourt S, Diaz O, Ojeda N, et al. Spatial
dynamics of chikungunya virus, Venezuela, 2014. Emerg Infect Dis. 2019 Apr
[<italic>date cited</italic>]. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3201/eid2504.172121">https://doi.org/10.3201/eid2504.172121</ext-link></p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="FN1">
                <label>1</label>
                <p>These authors contributed equally to this article.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="FN2">
                <label>2</label>
                <p>These authors contributed equally to this article.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgments</title>
              <p>We thank Carenne Ludeña for the support and valuable insights regarding the
analysis in this research. We thank Jared Aldstadt who kindly shared the R code for
the IKT analysis.</p>
              <p>This work was supported by the Fondo Nacional de Ciencia y Tecnología e
Innovación (FONACIT), grant 201100129, 20130020; and by the Department of
Medical Microbiology and Infection Prevention, University Medical Center Groningen
(UMCG), University of Groningen, Groningen, the Netherlands. E.L. and M.V.-G.
received the Abel Tasman Talent Program grant from the UMCG, University of
Groningen, Groningen, the Netherlands. M.E.G. received a travel grant from the
Netherlands Organization for Scientific Research (grant no. 040.11.590/2129), the
Netherlands, 2017.</p>
            </ack>
            <bio id="d35e1155">
              <p>Mr. Lizarazo is a PhD candidate at the University Medical Center Groningen. His
research interests are vectorborne diseases and molecular epidemiology. Dr.
Vincenti-Gonzalez is a postdoctoral researcher at the University Medical Center
Groningen. Her research interests are vectorborne diseases and
spatial–temporal dynamics of infectious diseases.</p>
            </bio>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="R1">
                <label>1. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Forrester</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Chikungunya:
Evolutionary history and recent epidemic spread.</article-title><source>Antiviral Res</source>.
<year>2015</year>;<volume>120</volume>:<fpage>32</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.antiviral.2015.04.016</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25979669?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25979669</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R2">
                <label>2. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Sammon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Dengue, Zika and
chikungunya: emerging arboviruses in the New World.</article-title><source>West J Emerg Med</source>.
<year>2016</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>671</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5811/westjem.2016.9.30904</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27833670?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27833670</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R3">
                <label>3. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>An epidemic of
virus disease in Southern Province, Tanganyika Territory, in 1952-53. I.
Clinical features.</article-title><source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg</source>.
<year>1955</year>;<volume>49</volume>:<fpage>28</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0035-9203(55)90080-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14373834?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14373834</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R4">
                <label>4. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Logue</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Changing
patterns of chikungunya virus: re-emergence of a zoonotic
arbovirus.</article-title><source>J Gen Virol</source>.
<year>2007</year>;<volume>88</volume>:<fpage>2363</fpage>–<lpage>77</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/vir.0.82858-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17698645?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17698645</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R5">
                <label>5. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Kilbourn</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Karesh</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Bosi</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Cropp</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal><article-title>Sylvatic transmission of arboviruses among Bornean
orangutans.</article-title><source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>.
<year>2001</year>;<volume>64</volume>:<fpage>310</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.2001.64.310</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11463123?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11463123</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R6">
                <label>6. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chevillon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Briant</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Renaud</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Devaux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The Chikungunya
threat: an ecological and evolutionary perspective.</article-title><source>Trends Microbiol</source>.
<year>2008</year>;<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>80</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tim.2007.12.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18191569?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18191569</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R7">
                <label>7. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Higgs</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Vanlandingham</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Chikungunya virus
and its mosquito vectors.</article-title><source>Vector Borne Zoonotic Dis</source>.
<year>2015</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>231</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/vbz.2014.1745</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25674945?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25674945</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R8">
                <label>8. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Marimoutou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Ferraro</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Javelle</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Deparis</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Chikungunya
infection: self-reported rheumatic morbidity and impaired quality of life
persist 6 years later.</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source>.
<year>2015</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>688</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmi.2015.02.024</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25752222?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25752222</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R9">
                <label>9. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Elsinga</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Gerstenbluth</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van der
Ploeg</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Halabi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Lourents</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Burgerhof</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal><article-title>Long-term chikungunya sequelae in Curaçao: burden,
determinants, and a novel classification tool.</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source>.
<year>2017</year>;<volume>216</volume>:<fpage>573</fpage>–<lpage>81</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/infdis/jix312</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28931219?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28931219</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R10">
                <label>10. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zeller</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van
Bortel</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Sudre</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Chikungunya: its
history in Africa and Asia and its spread to new regions in
2013–2014.</article-title><source>J Infect Dis</source>.
<year>2016</year>;<volume>214</volume>(<issue>suppl
5</issue>):<fpage>S436</fpage>–<lpage>40</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/infdis/jiw391</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27920169?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27920169</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R11">
                <label>11. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>Pan American Health Organization</collab>.
Number of reported cases of chikungunya fever in the Americas—cumulative
cases (October 23, <year>2015</year>) [cited 2017 Aug 20]. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.paho.org/hq/index.php?option=com_topics&amp;view=readall&amp;cid=5927&amp;Itemid=40931&amp;lang=en">http://www.paho.org/hq/index.php?option=com_topics&amp;view=readall&amp;cid=5927&amp;Itemid=40931&amp;lang=en</ext-link></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R12">
                <label>12. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>Pan American Health Organization</collab>.
Number of reported cases of chikungunya fever in the Americas- cumulative cases
(October 23, <year>2015</year>) [cited 2017 Aug 20]. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.paho.org/hq/index.php?option=com_topics&amp;view=readall&amp;cid=5927&amp;Itemid=40931&amp;lang=en">http://www.paho.org/hq/index.php?option=com_topics&amp;view=readall&amp;cid=5927&amp;Itemid=40931&amp;lang=en</ext-link></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R13">
                <label>13. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Oletta</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Epidemia de
fiebre chikungunya en Venezuela, 2014–2015.</article-title><source>Gac Med Caracas</source>.
<year>2016</year>;<volume>124</volume>:<fpage>122</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R14">
                <label>14. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pimentel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Skewes-Ramm</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Moya</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>[Chikungunya in
the Dominican Republic: lessons learned in the first six
months]</article-title><comment>[in Spanish]</comment>. <source>Rev Panam Salud Publica</source>.
<year>2014</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>336</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>.<?supplied-pmid 25604104?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25604104</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R15">
                <label>15. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gérardin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Guernier</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Perrau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Fianu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Le
Roux</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Grivard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal><article-title>Estimating Chikungunya prevalence in La Réunion Island
outbreak by serosurveys: two methods for two critical times of the
epidemic.</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source>.
<year>2008</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>99</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2334-8-99</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18662384?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18662384</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R16">
                <label>16. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Biology and
pathogenesis of chikungunya virus.</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source>.
<year>2010</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>491</fpage>–<lpage>500</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro2368</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20551973?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20551973</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R17">
                <label>17. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Arrival of
chikungunya virus in the new world: prospects for spread and impact on
public health.</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>.
<year>2014</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e2921</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0002921</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24967777?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24967777</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R18">
                <label>18. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hotez</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>KO</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Dengue, West
Nile virus, chikungunya, Zika-and now Mayaro?</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>.
<year>2017</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e0005462</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0005462</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28859086?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28859086</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R19">
                <label>19. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">Instituto Nacional de Estadística [cited 2017
Nov 18]. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ine.gov.ve">http://www.ine.gov.ve</ext-link></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R20">
                <label>20. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wallinga</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Lipsitch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>How generation
intervals shape the relationship between growth rates and reproductive
numbers.</article-title><source>Proc Biol Sci</source>.
<year>2007</year>;<volume>274</volume>:<fpage>599</fpage>–<lpage>604</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2006.3754</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17476782?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17476782</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R21">
                <label>21. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nishiura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Chowell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Heesterbeek</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Wallinga</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The ideal
reporting interval for an epidemic to objectively interpret the
epidemiological time course.</article-title><source>J R Soc Interface</source>.
<year>2010</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>297</fpage>–<lpage>307</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsif.2009.0153</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19570792?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19570792</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R22">
                <label>22. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Coelho</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de
Carvalho</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Estimating the
attack ratio of dengue epidemics under time-varying force of infection using
aggregated notification data.</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source>.
<year>2015</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>18455</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep18455</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26675824?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26675824</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R23">
                <label>23. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Dale</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Fortin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. Spatial analysis: a guide for
ecologists. 2nd ed. Cambridge (UK): Cambridge University Press;
<year>2014</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R24">
                <label>24. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wallis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Use of ranks in
one-criterion variance analysis.</article-title><source>J Am Stat Assoc</source>.
<year>1952</year>;<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>583</fpage>–<lpage>621</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01621459.1952.10483441</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R25">
                <label>25. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Knox</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The detection of
space–time interactions.</article-title><source>J R Stat Soc Ser C Appl Stat</source>.
<year>1964</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>25</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R26">
                <label>26. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Aldstadt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>An incremental
Knox test for the determination of the serial interval between successive
cases of an infectious disease.</article-title><source>Stochastic Environ Res Risk Assess</source>.
<year>2007</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>487</fpage>–<lpage>500</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00477-007-0132-3</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R27">
                <label>27. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The incubation
periods of Dengue viruses.</article-title><source>PLoS One</source>.
<year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e50972</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0050972</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23226436?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23226436</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R28">
                <label>28. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>David</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Lourenço-de-Oliveira</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Freitas</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Container
productivity, daily survival rates and dispersal of <italic>Aedes
aegypti</italic> mosquitoes in a high income dengue epidemic
neighbourhood of Rio de Janeiro: presumed influence of differential urban
structure on mosquito biology.</article-title><source>Mem Inst Oswaldo Cruz</source>.
<year>2009</year>;<volume>104</volume>:<fpage>927</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0074-02762009000600019</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19876569?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19876569</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R29">
                <label>29. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Boëlle</surname><given-names>P-Y</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Vergu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Renault</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Valleron</surname><given-names>A-J</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Flahault</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Investigating
transmission in a two-wave epidemic of Chikungunya fever, Réunion
Island.</article-title><source>Vector Borne Zoonotic Dis</source>.
<year>2008</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>207</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/vbz.2006.0620</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18171107?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18171107</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R30">
                <label>30. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yakob</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Clements</surname><given-names>ACA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A mathematical
model of chikungunya dynamics and control: the major epidemic on
Réunion Island.</article-title><source>PLoS One</source>.
<year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e57448</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0057448</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23554860?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23554860</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R31">
                <label>31. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Perkins</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Metcalf</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Grenfell</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Tatem</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Estimating
drivers of autochthonous transmission of chikungunya virus in its invasion
of the americas.</article-title><source>PLoS Curr</source>.
<year>2015</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>.<?supplied-pmid 25737803?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25737803</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R32">
                <label>32. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chowell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Fuentes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Olea</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Aguilera</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Nesse</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Hyman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The basic
reproduction number R0 and effectiveness of reactive interventions during
dengue epidemics: the 2002 dengue outbreak in Easter Island,
Chile.</article-title><source>Math Biosci Eng</source>.
<year>2013</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1455</fpage>–<lpage>74</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3934/mbe.2013.10.1455</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24245625?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24245625</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R33">
                <label>33. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Cucunubá</surname><given-names>ZM</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Dorigatti</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Nedjati-Gilani</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Donnelly</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Basáñez</surname><given-names>M-G</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal><article-title>EPIDEMIOLOGY. Countering the Zika epidemic in Latin
America.</article-title><source>Science</source>.
<year>2016</year>;<volume>353</volume>:<fpage>353</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aag0219</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27417493?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27417493</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R34">
                <label>34. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nishiura</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Kinoshita</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Mizumoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Yasuda</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Nah</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Transmission
potential of Zika virus infection in the South Pacific.</article-title><source>Int J Infect Dis</source>.
<year>2016</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>95</fpage>–<lpage>7</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2016.02.017</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26923081?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26923081</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R35">
                <label>35. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Hombach</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Cummings</surname><given-names>DAT</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Models of the
impact of dengue vaccines: a review of current research and potential
approaches.</article-title><source>Vaccine</source>.
<year>2011</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>5860</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2011.06.042</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21699949?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21699949</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R36">
                <label>36. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Waterman</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Novak</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Sather</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Rios</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Gubler</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Dengue
transmission in two Puerto Rican communities in 1982.</article-title><source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>.
<year>1985</year>;<volume>34</volume>:<fpage>625</fpage>–<lpage>32</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.1985.34.625</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 4003671?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4003671</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R37">
                <label>37. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vazquez-Prokopec</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Kitron</surname><given-names>U</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Horne</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Ritchie</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Quantifying the
spatial dimension of dengue virus epidemic spread within a tropical urban
environment.</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>.
<year>2010</year>;<volume>4</volume>:<fpage>e920</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000920</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21200419?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21200419</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R38">
                <label>38. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stoddard</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Forshey</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Paz-Soldan</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Vazquez-Prokopec</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Astete</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal><article-title>House-to-house human movement drives dengue virus
transmission.</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>.
<year>2013</year>;<volume>110</volume>:<fpage>994</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1213349110</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23277539?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23277539</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R39">
                <label>39. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mondini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Moraes
Bronzoni</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names>SHP</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Chiaravalloti Neto</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Massad</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal><article-title>Spatio-temporal tracking and phylodynamics of an urban dengue 3
outbreak in São Paulo, Brazil.</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>.
<year>2009</year>;<volume>3</volume>:<fpage>e448</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000448</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19478848?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19478848</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R40">
                <label>40. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tauil</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>[Urbanization
and dengue ecology]</article-title><comment>[in Portuguese]</comment>. <source>Cad Saude Publica</source>.
<year>2001</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>Suppl</issue>):<fpage>99</fpage>–<lpage>102</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0102-311X2001000700018</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11426270?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11426270</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R41">
                <label>41. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gubler</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Dengue,
urbanization and globalization: the unholy trinity of the 21st
century.</article-title><source>Trop Med Health</source>.
<year>2011</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>Suppl</issue>):<fpage>3</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2149/tmh.2011-S05</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22500131?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22500131</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R42">
                <label>42. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Vincenti-Gonzalez</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Grillet</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Velasco-Salas</surname><given-names>ZI</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Lizarazo</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Amarista</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Sierra</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal><article-title>Spatial analysis of dengue seroprevalence and modeling of
transmission risk factors in a dengue hyperendemic city of
Venezuela.</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>.
<year>2017</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e0005317</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0005317</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28114342?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28114342</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R43">
                <label>43. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Agha</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Tchouassi</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Bastos</surname><given-names>ADS</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Sang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Assessment of
risk of dengue and yellow fever virus transmission in three major Kenyan
cities based on Stegomyia indices.</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>.
<year>2017</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e0005858</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0005858</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28817563?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28817563</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R44">
                <label>44. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Barrera</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Avila</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>González-Téllez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Unreliable supply
of potable water and elevated <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> larval indices:
a causal relationship?</article-title><source>J Am Mosq Control Assoc</source>.
<year>1993</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>189</fpage>–<lpage>95</lpage>.<?supplied-pmid 8350076?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8350076</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R45">
                <label>45. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Grillet</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Del
Ventura</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>.
<article-title>Transmisión del virus Zika: Patrones y mecanismos
eco-epidemiológicos de una arbovirosis.</article-title><source>Tribuna del Investigador.</source><year>2016</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>42</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R46">
                <label>46. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>World Health Organization</collab>.
Guidelines for dengue surveillance and mosquito control. WHO regional
publication, Western Pacific Education in Action Series, no. 8. Geneva: The
Organzation; <year>1995</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R47">
                <label>47. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Harrington</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Lerdthusnee</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Costero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>GG</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal><article-title>Dispersal of the dengue vector <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>
within and between rural communities.</article-title><source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>.
<year>2005</year>;<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>209</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.2005.72.209</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15741559?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15741559</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R48">
                <label>48. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Rodhain</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>. Mosquito vectors and dengue
virus-vector relationships. In: Gubler D, Kuno G, editors. dengue and dengue
haemorrhagic fever. 1st ed. London (UK): CAB International; <year>1997</year>.
p. 45–60.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R49">
                <label>49. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Getis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Characteristics
of the spatial pattern of the dengue vector, <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>,
in Iquitos, Peru.</article-title><source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>.
<year>2003</year>;<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>494</fpage>–<lpage>505</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.2003.69.494</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14695086?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14695086</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R50">
                <label>50. </label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Auguste</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Liria</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Forrester</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Giambalvo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Moncada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>,
<string-name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal><article-title>Evolutionary and ecological characterization of Mayaro virus
strains Isolated during an outbreak, Venezuela, 2010.</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>.
<year>2015</year>;<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>1742</fpage>–<lpage>50</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid2110.141660</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26401714?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26401714</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
