<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-03-11T01:01:51Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:6610860" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:6610860</identifier>
        <datestamp>2019-07-16</datestamp>
        <setSpec>bmcph</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Public Health</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Public Health</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>BMC Public Health</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1471-2458</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC6610860</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6610860</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">6610860</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31272437</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">7224</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-019-7224-0</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Research Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Spatial and temporal analysis of tuberculosis in an area of social inequality in Northeast Brazil</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9062-0742</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Lima</surname>
                    <given-names>Shirley Verônica Melo Almeida</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>shirleymelo.lima@gmail.com</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>dos Santos</surname>
                    <given-names>Allan Dantas</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>allanufs@hotmail.com</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Duque</surname>
                    <given-names>Andrezza Marques</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>andrezza.duque@yahoo.com.br</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>de Oliveira Goes</surname>
                    <given-names>Marco Aurélio</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>maogoes@gmail.com</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>da Silva Peixoto</surname>
                    <given-names>Marcus Valerius</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>peixotovalerius@gmail.com</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>da Conceição Araújo</surname>
                    <given-names>Damião</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>damiao.araujo92@gmail.com</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ribeiro</surname>
                    <given-names>Caíque Jordan Nunes</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>caiquejordan_enf@yahoo.com.br</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Santos</surname>
                    <given-names>Márcio Bezerra</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>bio_marcio2006@hotmail.com</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>de Araújo</surname>
                    <given-names>Karina Conceição Gomes Machado</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>kkkaraujo2006@yahoo.com.br</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Nunes</surname>
                    <given-names>Marco Antônio Prado</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>nunes.ma@outlook.com</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2285 6801</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411252.1</institution-id><institution>Program in Health Sciences, </institution><institution>Federal University of Sergipe, </institution></institution-wrap>Brazil Cláudio Batista, s/n, Cidade Nova, Aracaju, SE 49060-108 Brazil </aff>
                <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2285 6801</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411252.1</institution-id><institution>Nursing Department, </institution><institution>Federal University of Sergipe, </institution></institution-wrap>Avenida Universitária Marcelo Deda Chagas, 330, Lagarto, SE 49.400-000 Brazil </aff>
                <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2285 6801</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.411252.1</institution-id><institution>Department of Health education, </institution><institution>Federal University of Sergipe, </institution></institution-wrap>Avenida Universitária Marcelo Deda Chagas 330, Lagarto, SE 49.400-000 Brazil </aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>4</day>
                <month>7</month>
                <year>2019</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>4</day>
                <month>7</month>
                <year>2019</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2019</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>19</volume>
              <elocation-id>873</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>1</day>
                  <month>10</month>
                  <year>2018</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>21</day>
                  <month>6</month>
                  <year>2019</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© The Author(s). 2019</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="OpenAccess">
                  <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="Abs1">
                <sec>
                  <title>Background</title>
                  <p id="Par1">Tuberculosis is an infectious disease caused by <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>. It is a disease known worldwide for its vulnerability factors, magnitude and mortality. The objective of the study was to analyze the spatial and temporal dynamics of TB in the area of social inequality in northeast Brazil between the years 2001 and 2016.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods</title>
                  <p id="Par2">An ecological time series study with the use of spatial analysis techniques was carried out from 2001 to 2016. The units of analysis were the 75 municipalities in the state of Sergipe. Data from the Notification of Injury Information System were used. For the construction of the maps, the cartographic base of the state of Sergipe, obtained at the Instituto Brasileiro de Geografia e Estatística, was used. Georeferenced data were analysed using TerraView 4.2.2 software (Instituto Nacional de Pesquisas Espaciais) and QGis 2.18.2 (Open Source Geospatial Foundation). Spatial analyses included the empirical Bayesian model and the global and local Moran indices. The time trend analyses were performed by the software Joinpoint Regression, Version 4.5.0.1, with the variables of sex, age, cure and abandonment<bold>.</bold></p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p id="Par3">There was an increasing trend of tuberculosis cases in patients under 20 years old and 20–39 years old, especially in males. Cured cases showed a decreasing trend, and cases of treatment withdrawal were stationary. A spatial dependence was observed in almost all analysed territories but with different concentrations. Significant spatial correlations with the formation of clusters in the southeast and northeast of the state were observed. The probability of illness among municipalities was determined not to occur in a random way.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusion</title>
                  <p id="Par4">The identification of risk areas and priority groups can help health planning by refining the focus of attention to tuberculosis control. Understanding the epidemiological, spatial and temporal dynamics of tuberculosis can allow for improved targeting of strategies for disease prevention and control.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>Spatial analysis</kwd>
                <kwd>Prevention and control</kwd>
                <kwd>Tuberculosis</kwd>
                <kwd>Epidemiology</kwd>
                <kwd>Time series studies</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group>
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100002322</institution-id>
                      <institution>Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                  <award-id>88881.187327/2018-01</award-id>
                  <principal-award-recipient>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lima</surname>
                      <given-names>Shirley Verônica Melo Almeida</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </principal-award-recipient>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>© The Author(s) 2019</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="Sec1">
              <title>Highlights</title>
              <p id="Par20">
                <list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                    <p id="Par21">We studied standardized municipality tuberculosis case notification rates in an area of social inequality in Brazil.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p id="Par22">Between 2001 and 2016, the study identified increasing trends of TB in Sergipe with inequalities between age groups and sex.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p id="Par23">The cure rate presented a worrying decline, countering the steady trend of treatment abandonment.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p id="Par24">Tuberculosis rates were strongly positively spatially autocorrelated.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p id="Par25">Higher rates were associated with population density and socioeconomic conditions.</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec2">
              <title>Background</title>
              <p id="Par26">Tuberculosis (TB) is an infectious disease caused by an intracellular pathogen called <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>. It is a disease known worldwide for its vulnerability, magnitude and morbidity factors. TB is still a serious global public health problem, and it is in the top 10 causes of mortality in underdeveloped countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par27">Brazil has been undergoing a process of epidemiological transition, with the increase of chronic and non-transmissible diseases and the reduction of infectious and parasitic diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. However, TB remains on the horizon of public health, mainly due to its persistence and high rates in communities living in poverty and on the margins of social exclusion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par28">In the world, it is estimated that 10.4 million people became ill with TB in 2015. The highest incidence rates were reported on the Asian and African continents [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. However, Brazil is also considered an endemic country for TB. In 2018, the country presented an incidence rate of 33.5 cases per 100,000 inhabitants and Sergipe, with an incidence rate of 28.8/100,000, had the fourth highest incidence rate of TB in the northeast region, despite the global reduction target of 10/100,000 inhabitants as a strategy for eliminating the disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par29">The probability of an infected person developing the disease depends on several factors, including social determinants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>], socioeconomic characteristics and coinfection by the human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), which are risk factors in the epidemiological chain of TB transmission, infection and dissemination [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. All these factors contribute significantly to the high morbidity and mortality rates of patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par30">It is critical that information about the operational and clinical characteristics of TB are disseminated in order to understand the extent and severity of the disease and its impact on public health. Spatial and temporal approaches help to better understand the distribution, dynamics and risk of diseases, especially TB and its variations over time.</p>
              <p id="Par31">The use of database helps studies that intend to analyse the manifestation of the disease over time. Studies of this nature can predict the probability of events based on continuous data streams [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. In addition, the use of geoprocessing techniques with geographic information systems (GIS) combined with spatial statistics allows for the incorporation of distinct variables, especially demographic and social variables, in health studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], making it possible to generate hypotheses regarding the transmission of diseases in different populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par32">Sergipe, an area located in northeast Brazil, presents a high incidence rate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], a fact that worries us as researchers of the subject. The maintenance of high rates and having practically all the territory affected by the disease motivated us to study this region. The impacts on the health of the population and the frailties faced in the prevention and control of TB also justify the relevance of investigations. In this sense, the objective of the study was to analyse the spatial and temporal dynamics of TB in the area of social inequality in northeast Brazil between the years 2001 and 2016.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec3">
              <title>Method</title>
              <sec id="Sec4">
                <title>Design and location of study</title>
                <p id="Par33">This was an ecological study with temporal and spatial components. We used spatial analysis techniques and time series from 2001 to 2016 in the state of Sergipe, considering the 75 municipalities as units of analysis.</p>
                <p id="Par34">The state of Sergipe has an estimated population of 2,265,779 inhabitants and a population density of 94.3 inhabitants per km<sup>2</sup> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. The state is divided into 75 municipalities with areas that comprise a population with diverse socioeconomic and environmental characteristics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>].</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec5">
                <title>Sample, data collection and outcome</title>
                <p id="Par35">The sample consisted of all confirmed cases of TB, considering the International Classification of Diseases 10th revision (ICD-10). Data recorded in the Notification of Injury Information System (SINAN), made available by the State Health Department of Sergipe, were used. The outcome was the incidence of TB in Sergipe.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec6">
                <title>Epidemiological data analysis</title>
                <p id="Par36">The epidemiological and operational indicators analysed in this study were the annual incidence rates, sex, age group (classified as less than 19, 20–39, 40–59 and 60 years or more). The frequency of abandonment and cure was determined for analysis of time trends. Data were stored in Microsoft Excel spreadsheets (Windows version 2013, Microsoft Corporation; Redmond, WA, EUA).</p>
                <p id="Par37">We used the Joinpoint Regression Program (Statistical Methodology and Applications Branch, Surveillance Research Program of the National Cancer Institute, Bethesda, MD, EUA, June 2017, Version 4.5.0.1) to calculate the temporal trends of TB frequency, abandonment and cure of cases recorded with a model based on the assumption of a minimum number of points (Joinpoint). A logarithmic linear regression model was also performed with the Monte Carlo permutation test [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. The annual percent change (APC) was calculated and a 95% confidence interval was adopted. 95%).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec7">
                <title>Spatial analysis</title>
                <p id="Par38">For construction of the spatial analysis maps, we used the cartographic base of the state of Sergipe, available in the electronic database of the Instituto Brasileiro de Geografia e Estatística (IBGE) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. The cartographic projection corresponds to the SIRGAS 2000 Universal Reference System, and the georeferenced data were analysed by the TerraView software (Instituto Nacional de Pesquisas Espaciais, INPE, SP, BR, Version 4.2.2) and QGIS (Open Source Geospatial Foundation, OSGeo, CHI, US, Version 2.18.2). We also used the Bayesian estimator to minimize the instability caused by the random fluctuation of cases and to smooth the standardized rates by applying weighted averages and creating a third corrected rate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].</p>
                <p id="Par39">The spatial analysis maps, constructed from the annual incidence coefficients, illustrated the mean number of TB cases recorded in each of the five years by municipality, using a moving average between periods which was then divided by the estimated population of the year of the medium and multiplied by 100,000. This process resulted in six maps with new estimated taxa, which were analysed by spatial autocorrelation approaches.</p>
                <p id="Par40">The empirical Bayesian local rate illustrated a correction of the multiplicative rate equal to 100,000, taking into account the population at risk and the number of cases for each five years analysed. To estimate the spatial variability in the data analysis, a proximity matrix was constructed, in which adjacent municipalities were awarded the value 1 (one), and those that did not present adjacent border geometries were awarded the value 0 (zero) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>].</p>
                <p id="Par41">The Global Moran’s Index was used to evaluate the spatial autocorrelation of the TB incidence rate in the geographic space analysed, varying between − 1 and + 1. Values close to 0 indicate spatial randomness; values between 0 and + 1 indicate positive spatial autocorrelation; and values between − 1 and 0 indicate negative spatial autocorrelation. The level of significance of 5% was used [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. The analysis by the Global Moran’s Index investigates whether the distribution occurs randomly or follows some pattern of occurrence in space [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>].</p>
                <p id="Par42">The spatial dependence showed by the Local Moran’s Index provides the local indicator of spatial association (LISA) for the detection of regions with significant spatial correlation and clustering measures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>].</p>
                <p id="Par43">The Moran map was used to indicate the critical and transitional areas that were statistically significant, signalling categories of the clusters and their relations with the neighbours. This analysis verifies the existence of spatial dependence and risk patterns for sickness with the creation of spatial quadrants, Q1 (high/high) and Q2 (low/low), which indicate municipalities with similar values as those of their neighbours, and Q3 (high/low) and Q4 (low/high) with different values. The first two categories represent areas of agreement with aggregates of positive spatial association, and the last two categories represent areas of transition with aggregates of negative spatial association [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec8">
                <title>Ethical aspects</title>
                <p id="Par44">The research was approved by the Committee of Ethics and Research with Humans, under protocol n° 1,768,049. The rules of the Helsinki Convention were followed.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec9">
              <title>Results</title>
              <p id="Par45">A total of 10,883 TB cases were registered in the state of Sergipe from 2001 to 2016. Of those, 9166 were new cases, 559 were relapses, 738 were readmissions after abandonment, 412 were transfers from other states and eight were recorded after death.</p>
              <p id="Par46">The mean TB incidence rate in the study period was 28.35 per 100.000 inhabitants (minimum of 24.49 and maximum of 32.98). The incidence rate also presented a stationary trend during that period (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Similarly, the treatment abandonment rate showed a stationary trend. However, the percentage of cured patients presented a decreasing trend in this period (81.78% in 2001 to 57.81% in 2016).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Temporal trend of TB cases by incidence rate, cure and treatment abandonment, Sergipe, Brazil (2001–2016)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12889_2019_7224_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
              <p id="Par47">The specific temporal trend of TB cases by age group and sex was significantly increased in males and in the 20–39 age group (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). In both sexes, the periods between 2001 and 2005 and between 2010 and 2016 showed statistically significant elevation.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Temporal trend of TB by sex and age group in the state of Sergipe, Brazil (2001–2016)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2"/><th>Segment</th><th>Period</th><th>APC</th><th colspan="2">CI 95%</th></tr><tr><th colspan="3"/><th>Minimum</th><th>Maximum</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="6">Male</td></tr><tr><td>  &lt; 19</td><td>1</td><td>2001–2016</td><td>0.6</td><td>−2.9</td><td>4.3</td></tr><tr><td> 20–39</td><td>1</td><td>2001–2003</td><td>21.8</td><td>− 9.2</td><td>63.2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"/><td>2</td><td>2003–2010</td><td>− 3.4</td><td>−7.4</td><td>0.8</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>2010–2016</td><td>7.7*</td><td>3.6</td><td>11.9</td></tr><tr><td> 40–59</td><td>1</td><td>2001–2016</td><td>−2.3*</td><td>−3.6</td><td>− 1.0</td></tr><tr><td> 60 e +</td><td>1</td><td>2001–2016</td><td>−1.7</td><td>−4.0</td><td>0.6</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">Female</td></tr><tr><td>  &lt; 19</td><td>1</td><td>2001–2016</td><td>0.6</td><td>−2.0</td><td>3.4</td></tr><tr><td> 20–39</td><td>1</td><td>2001–2016</td><td>− 2.4*</td><td>− 4.1</td><td>− 0.7</td></tr><tr><td> 40–59</td><td>1</td><td>2001–2016</td><td>− 2.4*</td><td>−4.4</td><td>− 0.3</td></tr><tr><td> 60 e +</td><td>1</td><td>2001–2016</td><td>− 0.2</td><td>−2.5</td><td>2.1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">Total</td></tr><tr><td>  &lt; 19</td><td>1</td><td>2001–2016</td><td>0.8</td><td>− 1.7</td><td>3.3</td></tr><tr><td> 20–39</td><td>1</td><td>2001–2005</td><td>6.7*</td><td>0.1</td><td>13.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2"/><td>2</td><td>2005–2010</td><td>− 6.5*</td><td>−12.0</td><td>− 0.7</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>2010–2016</td><td>6.3*</td><td>3.1</td><td>9.5</td></tr><tr><td> 40–59</td><td>1</td><td>2001–2016</td><td>−2.4*</td><td>− 3.6</td><td>− 1.2</td></tr><tr><td> 60 e +</td><td>1</td><td>2001–2016</td><td>− 1.2</td><td>− 3.0</td><td>0.6</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>APC</italic> annual percent change, <italic>CI</italic> confidence interval, * = significant for <italic>p-</italic>value &lt; than 0.05</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              <p id="Par48">For the analysis of crude incidence rate, a high concentration of diffusely distributed disease was observed in several regions of the state, with intensity in the southeast region (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). For the Bayesian maps, clusters of risk were visualized in the Northeast of the state (between 2001 to 2009) and the Southeast (between 2001 and 2015) Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Mean incidence rates of TB and rates corrected by empirical Bayesian model, Sergipe, Brazil (2001–2015)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12889_2019_7224_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Global Moran’s Index of the mean incidence rates for TB, Sergipe, Brazil (2001–2015)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Period</th><th colspan="3">Incidence Rate</th></tr><tr><th/><th>I</th><th><italic>p</italic>-value</th><th>min.-max.</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>2001–2005</td><td>0.283</td><td>0.005</td><td>0.0–70.9</td></tr><tr><td>2003–2007</td><td>0.056</td><td>0.205</td><td>0.0–65.2</td></tr><tr><td>2005–2009</td><td>0.137</td><td>0.046</td><td>0.0–83.6</td></tr><tr><td>2007–2011</td><td>0.108</td><td>0.076</td><td>0.0–55.3</td></tr><tr><td>2009–2013</td><td>0.318</td><td>0.001</td><td>0.0–53.0</td></tr><tr><td>2011–2015</td><td>0.256</td><td>0.003</td><td>0.0–60.5</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>I - Global Moran’s Index; min-max: minimum and maximum</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              <p id="Par49">The Moran map analysis allowed for the identification of the municipalities classified according to the level of significance of their local indexes. Two regions with agglomerates were identified: one in the southeast with high incidence rates (Q1) and the other in the north with the lowest incidence of the disease (Q2) (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). The eastern region (2001–2005) presented three municipalities with high incidence rates and, over time, expanded to previously untouched regions in the central and southeast sections of the country.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Moran Local Index with Moran map analysis using the average incidence for TB, Sergipe, Brazil (2001–2015)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12889_2019_7224_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>
              <p id="Par50">The municipalities represented by Q4 indicate areas of transition of the disease, but they deserve attention because they are close to municipalities with a high incidence of TB (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Agglomerates classified with Q3 present a high incidence of TB and can interfere in neighbouring municipalities with a low incidence of TB.</p>
              <p id="Par51">Maps of social inequality and population density, as displayed with higher hue intensity, also indicate population clusters in Sergipe. The human development index showed that the southeast region is the most developed (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Socioeconomic indicators and population density, Sergipe, Brazil (2016)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12889_2019_7224_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec10">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p id="Par52">TB still represents one of the most important infectious diseases in the world/ Even with all the advances made in its eradication, it is a disease that still presents alarming data on morbidity and mortality. In Brazil, TB has an endemic character [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>], and over time, its occurrence has varied, presenting different risks in the regions of the country [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. However, in spite of all the efforts and campaigns of the Ministry of Health to reduce the transmission and the occurrence of TB cases, the state of Sergipe did not show a reduction in the incidence rate between the years of 2001 and 2015. In addition, there are impressive data on the decrease in the cure rate of these patients.</p>
              <p id="Par53">The decreasing trend in patient cure rates is undoubtedly the most alarming data in our study and reveals a bleak and concerning epidemiological scenario for TB in the state of Sergipe. This trend may be justified with withdrawal episodes, which makes the patients resistant to treatment.</p>
              <p id="Par54">In addition, there was also a growing trend for TB cases among men, mainly in the age group between 20 and 39 years of age. This trend was also observed in other studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>] that corroborate our findings. These data signal an alert situation, since they may indicate a high transmission in the population, since most of this group is possibly ill due to recent infections. This finding may also be associated with delays in diagnosis, social factors that make diagnosis and control difficult, and areas with insufficient screening measures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par55">The use of the Geographic Information Systems to identify areas of risk and active transmission of TB has been noted as an effective tool for the monitoring and elaboration of health strategies, especially in regions with high incidence rates and aspects of social vulnerability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par56">The spatial dynamics of the disease has shown a distinct behavior, according to the regions of the state of Sergipe. This finding reflects different risks for illness, showing a high incidence mainly in the South and Southeast regions and show changes in the pattern of the disease over the years. In 2001–2005, TB was concentrated in regions with low economic growth, while in 2011–2015 there was a higher prevalence in more urbanized areas. One hypothesis for this was the migratory process of people from the north to the southeast region of the state looking for better living conditions in the more economically developed areas.</p>
              <p id="Par57">Currently, the peripheries of large urban centres (especially the favelas) present clear economic and social discrepancies. Accelerated urbanization and inadequate infrastructure, common to developing countries, explain an important part of the current epidemiological profile [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. It is known that TB is closely associated with poverty, poor living conditions and housing and human agglomeration [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par58">The disorderly growth of metropolitan cities and the formation of pockets of poverty may leave regions even more susceptible to acquiring the infection. The increase in TB transmission is evident, because the existence of people without the correct treatment contributes to the spread of the bacillus in the population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par59">To Brazil has own characteristics according to the political, social and scientific context. Over the years, important improvements were seen in the therapeutic regimen, the diagnosis process, the treatment time, the identification of new cases and the evaluation of the contacts, and the follow up and support of the health services. However, new historical events emerged and continued to maintain TB as a worldwide epidemic and with difficult control, such as social inequality; the advent of AIDS, the multi-resistance, the aging population and migratory movements [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par60">In this scenario, overly programmatic health services limited the priority themes and did not allow a truly decentralized dynamic of municipal health services, hampering the intelligent confrontation of issues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. These individual and ecological effects have had an important role in the change TB spatial patterns in Brazil and especially in Sergipe.</p>
              <p id="Par61">The correction of the TB incidence rate by the local Bayesian method allowed for the minimization of possible distortions of the variability provided by the calculation of gross rates due to the size of the population at risk. The rate adjustment is more consistent from the epidemiological point of view, since it showed a more uniform pattern of risk, although it presents high and worrying values, since they extrapolate the global goal and the current national situation.</p>
              <p id="Par62">The Moran map pointed to the Southeast region with a higher concentration of cases and significant spatial dependence. Municipal agglomerations in the Southeast region presented similar behaviours for TB, which may induce, in the near future, the continuous spread of the disease and new infections, even in neighbouring municipalities. Areas with a high prevalence of TB over time suggest the existence of a substantial number of latent infections in the population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Identifying the main risk areas based on geographic units is necessary for the formulation of equitable public policies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par63">The identification of clusters indicated an expanded epidemiological view of the areas at greatest risk of transmission. Spatial analyses indicated future, possibly avoidable, risks in areas that require further development in health actions and consolidation of surveillance measures. Health systems need to respond better and faster to the challenges of a changing world [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. In this perspective, health promotion and prevention actions should be planned according to the real needs of the exposed population.</p>
              <p id="Par64">TB is a complex disease that presents control difficulties and is easily spread throughout the world. It is possible to affirm that there is a relation between territorial space and transmission of TB; thus, to understand these dynamics, it is important to move beyond individual level analysis to spatial dimensions in order to receive important input for targeted intervention [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par65">When considering the transcendence of the disease and its geographical exposure, we can suggest alert situations, as they imply greater exposure and possible illness. When observing the main areas of risk, one can observe relations with the population density, since areas with high infection intensity coincided with areas of high population concentration. It is therefore reiterated that prevention and control strategies can be established through spatially dependent relationships between TB and its risk factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par66">The social context certainly undermines the space relations established in this study. It is clear that regions with higher levels of human development also show large income inequalities as seen in Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>. The authors believe that although there is an economic development, large pockets of poverty still prevail in cities with accelerated urbanization. The research provides evidence of how the social determination of municipalities may be related to the increased incidence of TB. This awareness must be present among policy makers so that the proposed improvements are both intersectoral and health service improvements.</p>
              <p id="Par67">Territory-based surveillance replicates more precise disease monitoring [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>], and TB incidence studies will continue to provide the best method to directly measure the disease burden and identify actions necessary for its reduction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>].</p>
              <p id="Par68">The authors understand that there are limitations in the method, such as not differentiating patients deprived of their freedom and not including patients with latent tuberculosis. There are limitations also when analysed only ecological characteristics and not individual characteristics and their risk factors. However, it is believed that the results can bring significant benefits to the control of the disease in Brazil, creating new health practices and strengthening social public policies for the population.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec11">
              <title>Conclusion</title>
              <p id="Par69">The study identified increasing trends of TB in Sergipe with difference between age groups and sex. The cure rate presented a worrying decline, countering the stable trend of treatment abandonment. The spatial findings showed the existence of TB throughout the territory and emphasized space as influential in the onset of the disease. Positive spatial autocorrelation was observed in the Southeast region, characterized by more urbanized municipalities with high population density.</p>
              <p id="Par70">The research expanded knowledge about social conditions and TB infection and strengthened evidence regarding the temporal and spatial dynamics of TB to improve prevention actions and control of the disease. The analysis elucidated discussions of social and structural health system problems, operations, and the need for possible strategic changes to address TB. Further research is needed to address populations younger than 20 years and over 60 years to better determine the environmental and social factors that interfere with the transmissibility of the disease in these groups.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <glossary>
              <title>Abbreviations</title>
              <def-list>
                <def-item>
                  <term>APC</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par5">Annual percent change</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>CI</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par6">Confidence interval</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>GIS</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par7">Geographic information systems</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>HIV</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par8">Human immunodeficiency virus</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>I</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par9">Global moran’s index</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>IBGE</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par10">Instituto brasileiro de geografia e estatística</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>ICD-10</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par11">International classification of diseases 10th</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>LISA</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par12">Local indicator of spatial association</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>Q1</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par13">Quadrant 1</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>Q2</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par14">Quadrant 2</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>Q3</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par15">Quadrant 3</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>Q4</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par16">Quadrant 4</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>SINAN</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par17">Notification of injury information system</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>SIRGAS 2000</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par18">universal reference system</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>TB</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par19">Tuberculosis</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
              </def-list>
            </glossary>
            <fn-group>
              <fn>
                <p>
                  <bold>Publisher’s Note</bold>
                </p>
                <p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgements</title>
              <p>We thank the partnership of the State Department of Health under the coordination of Health Surveillance for the availability of databases, as well as the post-graduation programme in health sciences of the Federal University of Sergipe and CAPES – Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior for support.</p>
            </ack>
            <notes notes-type="author-contribution">
              <title>Authors’ contributions</title>
              <p>SVMAL, KCGMA and MAPN formulated the idea, participated in the analysis and interpretation of the data and the preparation of the manuscript. ADS, AMD, MAOG and MVSP, collaborated for spatial analysis, data interpretation and literature review. DCA, CJNR and MBS contributed to spatial analysis and interpretation of data. All authors contributed to discuss the content and writing of the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="funding-information">
              <title>Funding</title>
              <p>The Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior (CAPES) has opportunized the corresponding author to study abroad to improve the analysis and interpretation of the data. The funding helped in the conception of the study, collection and analysis of the data as well as for the interpretation and writing of the manuscript. Scholarship was provided for the development of scientific research. Process number: 88881.187327/2018–01.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="data-availability">
              <title>Availability of data and materials</title>
              <p>The datasets analyzed during the current study consisted of all confirmed cases of TB, considering the International Classification of Diseases 10th revision (ICD-10). Data recorded in the Notification of Injury Information System (SINAN), that supporting the results of this study are available from [State Health Department of Sergipe]. The data are, however, available by the authors upon reasonable request and with permission of [State Health Department of Sergipe]. For the construction of the spatial analysis maps, we used the cartographic base of the state of Sergipe, available in the electronic database of the Instituto Brasileiro de Geografia e Estatística (IBGE).</p>
            </notes>
            <notes>
              <title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
              <p id="Par71">The research was approved by the Committee of Ethics and Research with Humans, under protocol n° 1.768.049. The rules of the Helsinki Convention were followed.</p>
              <p id="Par72">The data used are in the public domain without identification of the individuals. For this reason, the individual consent form did not need to be applied.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes>
              <title>Consent for publication</title>
              <p id="Par73">Not applicable.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
              <title>Competing interests</title>
              <p id="Par74">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
            </notes>
            <ref-list id="Bib1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="CR1">
                <label>1.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization. Global Tuberculosis Report. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2016.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR2">
                <label>2.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Silva Júnior JB da, Ramalho WM. CENÁRIO EPIDEMIOLÓGICO DO BRASIL em 2033: uma prospecção sobre as próximas duas décadas. 2015; n<sup>o</sup> 17:16.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR3">
                <label>3.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Duarte</surname>
                      <given-names>EC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Barreto</surname>
                      <given-names>SM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Transição demográfica e epidemiológica: a Epidemiologia e Serviços de Saúde revisita e atualiza o tema</article-title>
                  <source>Epidemiol e Serviços Saúde</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <volume>21</volume>
                  <fpage>529</fpage>
                  <lpage>532</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5123/S1679-49742012000400001</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR4">
                <label>4.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Brasil. Ministério da Saúde. Epidemiológico. Ministério da Saúde, Secr Vigilância em Saúde. 2017;48.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR5">
                <label>5.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Brasil. Ministério da Saúde. Implantação do Plano Nacional pelo Fim da Tuberculose como Problema de Saúde Pública no Brasil: primeiros passos rumo ao alcance das metas. Bol Epidemiológico 11. 2018;49:18. 2358–9450.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR6">
                <label>6.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Brasil. Ministério da Saúde. Secretaria de Vigilância em Saúde. Guia de Vigilância em Saúde. 1a edição. 2014. %3Cwww.saude.gov.br/bvs%3E.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR7">
                <label>7.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aldridge</surname>
                      <given-names>RW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zenner</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>White</surname>
                      <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Muzyamba</surname>
                      <given-names>MC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Loutet</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dhavan</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Prevalence of and risk factors for active tuberculosis in migrants screened before entry to the UK: a population-based cross-sectional study</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <fpage>962</fpage>
                  <lpage>970</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(16)00072-4</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 27013215?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27013215</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR8">
                <label>8.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Uthman</surname>
                      <given-names>OA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yahaya</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ashfaq</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Uthman</surname>
                      <given-names>MB</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A trend analysis and sub-regional distribution in number of people living with HIV and dying with TB in Africa, 1991 to 2006</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Health Geogr</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1476-072X-8-65</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 19930689?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19930689</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR9">
                <label>9.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Naidus</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Celi</surname>
                      <given-names>LA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Big data in healthcare: are we close to it?</article-title>
                  <source>Rev Bras Ter Intensiva</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>28</volume>
                  <fpage>8</fpage>
                  <lpage>10</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5935/0103-507X.20160008</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 27096670?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27096670</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR10">
                <label>10.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bailey</surname>
                      <given-names>TC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Spatial statistical methods in health</article-title>
                  <source>CadSaude Publica, Rio Janeiro.</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <fpage>1083</fpage>
                  <lpage>1098</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0102-311X2001000500011</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR11">
                <label>11.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Barcellos</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bastos</surname>
                      <given-names>FI</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Geoprocessamento , ambiente e saúde : uma união possível?</article-title>
                  <source>CadSaude Publica, Rio Janeiro.</source>
                  <year>1996</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <fpage>389</fpage>
                  <lpage>397</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0102-311X1996000300012</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR12">
                <label>12.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Guimarães RB. Geography and public health in Brazil. Saude soc, São Paulo. 2016;25:869–79.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR13">
                <label>13.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Medronho RA, Carvalho DM, Bloch KV, Luiz RR, Werneck GL. Epidemiologia: Análise de dados espaciais em saúde. Rio de Janeiro; 2009.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR14">
                <label>14.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Instituto Brasileiro de Geografia e Estatística. Brasil. 2017. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cidades.ibge.gov.br/xtras/uf.php?coduf=28">http://cidades.ibge.gov.br/xtras/uf.php?coduf=28</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR15">
                <label>15.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sergipe. Secretaria Estadual de Saúde. A reforma sanitária e gerencial do SUS no Estado de Sergipe: saberes e tecnologias para implantação de uma política. Livro do Aprendiz 1. 2011.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR16">
                <label>16.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kim</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fay</surname>
                      <given-names>MP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Feuer</surname>
                      <given-names>EJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Midthune</surname>
                      <given-names>DN</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Permutation tests for JOINPOINT regression with APPLICATIONS to CANCER rates</article-title>
                  <source>Stat Med</source>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <volume>19</volume>
                  <fpage>335</fpage>
                  <lpage>351</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1097-0258(20000215)19:3&lt;335::AID-SIM336&gt;3.0.CO;2-Z</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10649300</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR17">
                <label>17.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pereira AGL, Medronho R de A, Escosteguy CC, Valencia LIO, Magalhães M de AFM. Spatial distribution and socioeconomic context of tuberculosis in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil. Rev Saude Publica. 2015;49.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR18">
                <label>18.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Brasil M da S. Sistemas de Informações Geográficas e Análise Espacial na Saúde Pública. 2007.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR19">
                <label>19.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Werneck</surname>
                      <given-names>GL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Struchiner</surname>
                      <given-names>CJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Estudos de agregados de doença no espaço-tempo : conceitos , técnicas e desafios</article-title>
                  <source>CadSaude Publica, Rio Janeiro.</source>
                  <year>1997</year>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <fpage>611</fpage>
                  <lpage>624</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0102-311X1997000400005</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR20">
                <label>20.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bailey TC, Gratell AC. Interactive spatial data analysis. New York; 1995.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR21">
                <label>21.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Moran</surname>
                      <given-names>P. A. P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The Interpretation of Statistical Maps</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series B (Methodological)</source>
                  <year>1948</year>
                  <volume>10</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>243</fpage>
                  <lpage>251</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR22">
                <label>22.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Câmara</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Monteiro</surname>
                      <given-names>AMV</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Geocomputation techniques for spatial analysis : are they relevant to health data?</article-title>
                  <source>CadSaude Publica, Rio Janeiro</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <fpage>1059</fpage>
                  <lpage>1081</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0102-311X2001000500002</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR23">
                <label>23.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Brasil. Ministério da Saúde. Secretaria de Vigolância em Saúde. Departamento de Vigilância das doenças transmissíveis. Avaliação da Gestão do Programa Nacional de Controle da Tuberculose Avaliação da Gestão do Programa Nacional de Controle da Tuberculose. 1a edição. Brasília-DF; 2015.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR24">
                <label>24.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Brasil. Ministério da Saúde. Secretaria de Vigilância em Saúde. Departamento de Vigilância das doenças transmissíveis. Boletim Epidemiológico: Indicadores prioritários para o monitoramento do Plano Nacional pelo fim da tuberculose como Problema de Saúde Pública 2017;48 no8.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR25">
                <label>25.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ge</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>X</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>X</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wei</surname>
                      <given-names>X</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Spatial and temporal analysis of tuberculosis in Zhejiang Province, China, 2009-2012</article-title>
                  <source>Infect Dis Poverty</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>5</volume>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40249-016-0104-2</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 26906041?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26906041</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR26">
                <label>26.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pezzoli L, Gounder S, Tamani T, Daulako MR, Underwood F, Mainawalala S, et al. Tuberculosis, Fiji, 2002–2013. 2016;22:2012–4.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR27">
                <label>27.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Smith</surname>
                      <given-names>CM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Maguire</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Anderson</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Macdonald</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hayward</surname>
                      <given-names>AC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Multiple large clusters of tuberculosis in London: a cross-sectional analysis of molecular and spatial data</article-title>
                  <source>ERJ Open Res</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>3</volume>
                  <fpage>98</fpage>
                  <lpage>2016</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/23120541.00098-2016</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR28">
                <label>28.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Petersen</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Maeurer</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Marais</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Migliori</surname>
                      <given-names>GB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mwaba</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ntoumi</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>World TB day 2017: advances, challenges and opportunities in the end-TB era</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Infect Dis</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>56</volume>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>5</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2017.02.012</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28232006</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR29">
                <label>29.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Moonan</surname>
                      <given-names>PK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bayona</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Quitugua</surname>
                      <given-names>TN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Oppong</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dunbar</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jost</surname>
                      <given-names>KC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Using GIS technology to identify areas of tuberculosis transmission and incidence</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Health Geogr</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>3</volume>
                  <fpage>23</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1476-072X-3-23</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 15479478?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15479478</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR30">
                <label>30.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tiwari</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Adhikari</surname>
                      <given-names>CMS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tewari</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kandpal</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Investigation of geo-spatial hotspots for the occurrence of tuberculosis in Almora district, India, using GIS and spatial scan statistic</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Health Geogr</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>5</volume>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1476-072X-5-33</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16901341</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR31">
                <label>31.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Herrero MB, Arrossi S, Ramos S, Braga JU. Spatial analysis of the tuberculosis treatment dropout, Buenos Aires, Argentina. Rev Saude Publica. 2015;49.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR32">
                <label>32.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>San Pedro</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gibson</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>dos</surname>
                      <given-names>SJPC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>de</surname>
                      <given-names>TLM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sabroza</surname>
                      <given-names>PC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>de</surname>
                      <given-names>ORM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Tuberculose como marcador de iniquidades em um contexto de transformação socioespacial</article-title>
                  <source>Rev Saude Pública.</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>51</volume>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>10</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S1518-8787.2017051006533</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28099550</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR33">
                <label>33.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huang</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>X-X</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abe</surname>
                      <given-names>EM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xu</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ruan</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cao</surname>
                      <given-names>C-L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Spatial-temporal analysis of pulmonary tuberculosis in the northeast of the Yunnan province, People’s republic of China</article-title>
                  <source>Infect Dis Poverty.</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <fpage>53</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40249-017-0268-4</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 28335803?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28335803</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR34">
                <label>34.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>IBGE</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Base de Informações por Setor Censitário: Censo Demográfico 2000 – Resultados do Universo (Campinas e Paulínia)</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR35">
                <label>35.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mello DC De. A história da tuberculose associada ao perfil socioeconomico no brasil : uma revisão da literatura. 2018;:43–52.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR36">
                <label>36.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bertolli Filho C. História social da tuberculose e do tuberculoso: 1900–1950. 2001.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR37">
                <label>37.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Maciel MDS, Siqueira-batista R. A história da tuberculose no Brasil : os muitos tons ( de cinza ) da miséria *. 2012;10.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR38">
                <label>38.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hijjar</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gerhardt</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Retrospecto do controle da tuberculose no Brasil</article-title>
                  <source>Rev Saude Pública</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <volume>41</volume>
                  <fpage>50</fpage>
                  <lpage>58</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0034-89102007000800008</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18038091</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR39">
                <label>39.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Harling</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lima Neto</surname>
                      <given-names>AS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sousa</surname>
                      <given-names>GS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Machado</surname>
                      <given-names>MMT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Castro</surname>
                      <given-names>MC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Determinants of tuberculosis transmission and treatment abandonment in Fortaleza, Brazil</article-title>
                  <source>BMC Public Health</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <fpage>508</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-017-4435-0</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 28545423?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28545423</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR40">
                <label>40.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Das</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cook</surname>
                      <given-names>AR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wah</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Win</surname>
                      <given-names>KMK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chee</surname>
                      <given-names>CBE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>YT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Spatial dynamics of TB within a highly urbanised Asian metropolis using point patterns</article-title>
                  <source>Sci Rep</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <fpage>36</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-00081-3</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 28232734?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28232734</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR41">
                <label>41.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Organization WH. The world health report 2008 : primary health care now more than ever. 2008.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR42">
                <label>42.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">da Silva TC, Lima Pinto M, Bertolozzi MR, Félix Gomes LC, Mendoza Villavicencio LM, Gomes de Barros P, et al. Analysis of the tuberculosis occurrence through the use of geoprocessing. Int Arch Med. 2016:1–7. 10.3823/2266.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR43">
                <label>43.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sun</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gong</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhou</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhao</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tan</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ibrahim</surname>
                      <given-names>AN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A spatial, social and environmental study of tuberculosis in China using statistical and GIS technology</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <fpage>1425</fpage>
                  <lpage>1448</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph120201425</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25633032</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR44">
                <label>44.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leonor Noia Maciel</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Maia Martins Sales</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A vigilância epidemiológica da tuberculose no Brasil: como é possível avançar mais</article-title>
                  <source>Epidemiol e Serviços Saúde.</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>25</volume>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>10</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5123/S1679-49742016000100018</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
