<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-03-11T00:56:30Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7962635" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7962635</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-03-17</datestamp>
        <setSpec>transmed</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Transl Med</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Transl Med</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Journal of Translational Medicine</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1479-5876</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC7962635</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7962635</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">7962635</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33726787</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2736</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12967-021-02736-2</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Methodology</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>A versatile web app for identifying the drivers of COVID-19 epidemics</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8784-9354</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Getz</surname>
                    <given-names>Wayne M.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>wgetz@berkeley.edu</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Salter</surname>
                    <given-names>Richard</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>richard.salter@numerusinc.com</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Luisa Vissat</surname>
                    <given-names>Ludovica</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>l.luisavissat@berkeley.edu</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Horvitz</surname>
                    <given-names>Nir</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>nirh@berkeley.edu</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.47840.3f</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2181 7878</institution-id><institution>Department of Environmental Science, Policy and Management, </institution><institution>University of California, </institution></institution-wrap>Berkeley, CA 94708-3114 USA </aff>
                <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.16463.36</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0723 4123</institution-id><institution>School of Mathematical Sciences, University of KwaZulu-Natal, </institution></institution-wrap>Durban, 4000 South Africa </aff>
                <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Numerus, Inc., 850 Iron Point Rd., Folsom, CA 95630 USA </aff>
                <aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.261284.b</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2193 5532</institution-id><institution>Computer Science Department, </institution><institution>Oberlin College, </institution></institution-wrap>OH 44074 Oberlin, USA </aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>16</day>
                <month>3</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>16</day>
                <month>3</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>19</volume>
              <elocation-id>109</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>4</day>
                  <month>9</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>2</day>
                  <month>2</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2021</copyright-statement>
                <license license-type="OpenAccess">
                  <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="Abs1">
                <sec>
                  <title>Background</title>
                  <p id="Par1">No versatile web app exists that allows epidemiologists and managers around the world to comprehensively analyze the impacts of COVID-19 mitigation. The <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://covid-webapp.numerusinc.com/">http://covid-webapp.numerusinc.com/</ext-link> web app presented here fills this gap.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods</title>
                  <p id="Par2">Our web app uses a model that explicitly identifies susceptible, contact, latent, asymptomatic, symptomatic and recovered classes of individuals, and a parallel set of response classes, subject to lower pathogen-contact rates. The user inputs a CSV file of incidence and, if of interest, mortality rate data. A default set of parameters is available that can be overwritten through input or online entry, and a user-selected subset of these can be fitted to the model using maximum-likelihood estimation (MLE). Model fitting and forecasting intervals are specifiable and changes to parameters allow counterfactual and forecasting scenarios. Confidence or credible intervals can be generated using stochastic simulations, based on MLE values, or on an inputted CSV file containing Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) estimates of one or more parameters.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p id="Par3">We illustrate the use of our web app in extracting social distancing, social relaxation, surveillance or virulence switching functions (i.e., time varying drivers) from the incidence and mortality rates of COVID-19 epidemics in Israel, South Africa, and England. The Israeli outbreak exhibits four distinct phases: initial outbreak, social distancing, social relaxation, and a second wave mitigation phase. An MCMC projection of this latter phase suggests the Israeli epidemic will continue to produce into late November an average of around 1500 new case per day, unless the population practices social-relaxation measures at least 5-fold below the level in August, which itself is 4-fold below the level at the start of July. Our analysis of the relatively late South African outbreak that became the world’s fifth largest COVID-19 epidemic in July revealed that the decline through late July and early August was characterised by a social distancing driver operating at more than twice the per-capita applicable-disease-class (pc-adc) rate of the social relaxation driver. Our analysis of the relatively early English outbreak, identified a more than 2-fold improvement in surveillance over the course of the epidemic. It also identified a pc-adc social distancing rate in early August that, though nearly four times the pc-adc social relaxation rate, appeared to barely contain a second wave that would break out if social distancing was further relaxed.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusion</title>
                  <p id="Par4">Our web app provides policy makers and health officers who have no epidemiological modelling or computer coding expertise with an invaluable tool for assessing the impacts of different outbreak mitigation policies and measures. This includes an ability to generate an epidemic-suppression or curve-flattening index that measures the intensity with which behavioural responses suppress or flatten the epidemic curve in the region under consideration.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>Numerus Model Builder</kwd>
                <kwd>SARS-CoV-2</kwd>
                <kwd>Israel</kwd>
                <kwd>South Africa</kwd>
                <kwd>England</kwd>
                <kwd>SEIR models</kwd>
                <kwd>Curve-flattening/epidemic-suppression index</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group>
                <award-group>
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000155</institution-id>
                      <institution>Division of Environmental Biology</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                  <award-id>2032264</award-id>
                  <principal-award-recipient>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Getz</surname>
                      <given-names>Wayne M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </principal-award-recipient>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>© The Author(s) 2021</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="Sec1">
              <title>Background</title>
              <p id="Par18">The corona viral disease, 2019 (COVID-19) outbreak that in February, 2020, threatened to overwhelm the healthcare system of Wuhan, China, was brought under control in early March through a combination of social distancing, contact tracing and quarantine measures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Since then, these measures have been used by municipalities, counties, states and countries around the world to bring COVID-19 outbreaks under full or partial control. Many of outbreaks have subsequently experienced prominent second waves, as control measures—which we refer to as drivers—have been prematurely relaxed.</p>
              <p id="Par19">As of late August, 2020, the pandemic state of COVID-19 was closing in on twenty five million recorded cases, and over 800,000 recorded deaths. In the US itself, the number of recorded cases was around 6 million and approaching 200,000 recorded deaths. Though the management of outbreaks has been impressive in some countries, in many others healthcare officials and civic leaders at various administrative levels have been in dire need of quantitative tools to help formulate and implement policies designed to flatten and ultimately extinguish state, provincial, and country level epidemics. Currently, policy assessment tools exist only in the hands of computational epidemiologists and modelling and data analysis groups. These individuals and groups are insufficient to meet the policy development and assessment needs of most communities around the world. Without easy entry, versatile, policy evaluation tools, governors, mayors, and other civic leaders responsible for implementing healthcare policy are flying blind when making critical decisions whether or not to open schools or various business sectors representing different levels of severe acute respiratory syndrome covid virus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) transmission risk.</p>
              <p id="Par20">Here we present an easy entry, user-friendly analytical tool: the COVID-19 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://covid-webapp.numerusinc.com/">http://covid-webapp.numerusinc.com/</ext-link> (Numerus Model Builder Data and Simulation Analysis) web app. It can be used to address questions regarding the impact of social distancing, social relaxation, changes in surveillance, implementation of contact tracing with quarantining, patient isolation, and vaccination (when widely available) on incidence and mortality rates. NMB-DASA does not require the user to have a mathematical or epidemiological modelling background or an understanding of the computational procedures needed to carry out deterministic and stochastic simulations for model parameter estimation or epidemic forecasting. It only requires users to provide a comma-separated values file (CSV: a standard used by all common spreadsheet applications and data management programs) that contains the incidence and mortality time series of the particular outbreak to be analysed, to read this paper, and to undergo less than an hour of training using videos supplied for this purpose at the website. The user is also able to load a set of generic default parameters that come with our COVID-19 NMB-DASA, or modify these by either entering new values or manipulating sliders on web pages. We also illustrate, using data from the Israeli, South African, and English COVID-19 epidemics, how the NMB-DASA web app can be used to: i) forensically analyze the dynamic aspects of outbreaks by identifying implicit drivers (viz., surveillance levels, social distancing and relaxation, quarantining, improvement in therapeutics, rolling out vaccination programs); and, ii) evaluate or forecast the impacts of changes to these drivers.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec2">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <sec id="Sec3">
                <title>Model</title>
                <p id="Par21">The epidemiological simulation and forecasting engine of our website is based on a modified SEIR (Susceptible, Exposed, Infectious, Recovered) formulation called SCLAIV (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), which expands disease class E into a contact class C and latent class L. Individuals in C, having made contact with SARS-CoV-2, can either thwart potential infection (e.g., through physical barriers or operation of the innate immune system) and return to S or succumb and moving onto L. SCLAIV also adds an asymptomatic infectious class A to the general infectious component of an SEIR process, which is known to be important component of SARS-CoV-2 transmission [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Individuals in A are assumed to be less infectious than in the class I [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>] and can either move to I or directly to the acquired immunity (i.e., akin to naturally “vaccinated”) class V. A SCLAIV+D formulation also explicitly separates out the removed class R in the SEIR process into V and the class D of individuals that have died.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>A flow diagram of the SCLAIV+D+response model with its 8 flow parameters identified by numbers 1–8 plus an asymptomatic infection parameter 9. The 8 drivers identified by lower case Roman letters a-h are either zero (apart from surveillance), a positive constant or have the form of a switching function, as described in the text. We have generalized the disease-induced natural mortality flow rate 8 from being a constant to include the possibility of driving (h) the rate down to account for improvements over time in treatment and therapeutics</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
                <p id="Par22">SEIR and SCLAIV+D formulations need to be augmented to include the epidemiological driving process used to “flatten incidence and mortality curves” during outbreaks, if models are used to assess the impacts of healthcare policies on epidemics. The structure and equation details of our full SCLAIV+D+response model are provided in Appendix A of the Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>. Details of our discrete time deterministic and stochastic implementations of our SCLAIV+D+response model, at the computational core of our web app, can be found in Additional file<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Appendix B. This implementation includes 8 response drivers (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), each of which can either be specified as a constant or time varying rate—the latter, specifically, as a five parameter switching function (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Appendix A.3; Fig. A.2). These driving rates are responsible for transferring individuals among basic SCLAIV and SCLAIV-response classes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Specifically, they are a social distancing rate (transfers individuals from the susceptible class S to the susceptible response class <inline-formula id="IEq9"><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {S}_\text{r}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>S</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq9.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>), which involves a possible dynamic change in a contact rate reduction parameter, a social relaxation rate (transfers individuals from <inline-formula id="IEq10"><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {S}_\text{r}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>S</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq10.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> to S), a quarantine rate linked to contact tracing (transfers individuals from C, L and A to <inline-formula id="IEq11"><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {C}_\text{r}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq11.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq12"><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {L}_\text{r}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M8"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>L</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq12.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula id="IEq13"><alternatives><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {A}_\text{r}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M10"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq13.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> respectively), case isolation (transfers individuals from I to <inline-formula id="IEq14"><alternatives><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {I}_\text{r}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M12"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>I</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq14.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) and vaccination rates (transfers individuals from pre-infectious classes to <inline-formula id="IEq15"><alternatives><tex-math id="M13">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {V}_\text{r}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M14"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>V</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq15.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>; see Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), the level of surveillance (i.e., proportion of cases detected) implemented to monitor the state of the outbreak, and the impacts of treatment on disease-induced mortality rates (the latter is also referred to as the virulence).</p>
                <p id="Par23">The number of individuals in each of these classes is denoted by the italic form of these names (e.g., <italic>S</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) and <inline-formula id="IEq16"><alternatives><tex-math id="M15">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$S_r(t)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M16"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq16.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> respectively represent the number of individuals in classes S and <inline-formula id="IEq17"><alternatives><tex-math id="M17">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {S}_r$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M18"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>S</mml:mtext><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq17.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> at time <italic>t</italic>). Further, the proportion of susceptibles in the susceptible-response class over time—i.e.,<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M19">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} c_{{\text{flatten}}}(t)=\frac{S_r(t)}{S_r(t)+S(t)} \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M20" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mtext>flatten</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>is a measure of the degree to which the epidemic is being “curve-flattened” or suppressed through the social distancing and social relaxation drivers. This follows because the infection risk for individuals in class <inline-formula id="IEq18"><alternatives><tex-math id="M21">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {S}_\text{r}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M22"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>S</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq18.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> compared with class S is reduced by a factor <inline-formula id="IEq19"><alternatives><tex-math id="M23">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\delta _\text{con}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M24"><mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mtext>con</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq19.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Appendix A).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Default point estimates of parameters for fitting and simulating a basic COVID-19 SCLAIV outbreak on <inline-formula id="IEq20"><alternatives><tex-math id="M25">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$[0,t_\text{est}]$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M26"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mtext>est</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq20.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>). Also see Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"> Parameter</th><th align="left">Symbol (<inline-formula id="IEq21"><alternatives><tex-math id="M27">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {math}^{\dag }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M28"><mml:msup><mml:mtext>math</mml:mtext><mml:mo>†</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq21.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>)</th><th align="left">Value</th><th align="left">Source/Comment</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Transmission</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Contact <inline-formula id="IEq22"><alternatives><tex-math id="M29">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {rate}^\mathsection$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M30"><mml:msup><mml:mtext>rate</mml:mtext><mml:mo>§</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq22.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left"><inline-formula id="IEq23"><alternatives><tex-math id="M31">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\kappa$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M32"><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq23.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">Estimated</td><td align="left">Incidence <inline-formula id="IEq24"><alternatives><tex-math id="M33">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {data}^{*}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M34"><mml:msup><mml:mtext>data</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq24.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Nominal/effective pop size</td><td align="left"><inline-formula id="IEq25"><alternatives><tex-math id="M35">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$N_0=N_\text{eff}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M36"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mtext>eff</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq25.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left"><inline-formula id="IEq26"><alternatives><tex-math id="M37">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$10^5-10^7$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M38"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq26.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left"><inline-formula id="IEq27"><alternatives><tex-math id="M39">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {Varies}^\P$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M40"><mml:msup><mml:mtext>Varies</mml:mtext><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">¶</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq27.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Asymptomatic reduction</td><td align="left"><inline-formula id="IEq28"><alternatives><tex-math id="M41">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\varepsilon$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M42"><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq28.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">0.1</td><td align="left">Unknown: see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Surveillance</td><td align="left"><inline-formula id="IEq29"><alternatives><tex-math id="M43">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\delta _\text{sur}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M44"><mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mtext>sur</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq29.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left"><inline-formula id="IEq30"><alternatives><tex-math id="M45">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {Unknown}^{**}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M46"><mml:msup><mml:mtext>Unknown</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq30.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Isolation/treatment</td><td align="left"><inline-formula id="IEq31"><alternatives><tex-math id="M47">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\delta _\text{iso}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M48"><mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mtext>iso</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq31.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">0.35</td><td align="left"><inline-formula id="IEq32"><alternatives><tex-math id="M49">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {Varies}^{\ddag }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M50"><mml:msup><mml:mtext>Varies</mml:mtext><mml:mo>‡</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq32.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Contact rate reduction</td><td align="left"><inline-formula id="IEq33"><alternatives><tex-math id="M51">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\delta _\text{con}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M52"><mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mtext>con</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq33.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">0.1</td><td align="left"><inline-formula id="IEq34"><alternatives><tex-math id="M53">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {Varies}^{*\ddag }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M54"><mml:msup><mml:mtext>Varies</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo><mml:mo>‡</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq34.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Progression</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Thwart period</td><td align="left"><inline-formula id="IEq35"><alternatives><tex-math id="M55">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\pi _\text{thw}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M56"><mml:msub><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mtext>thw</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq35.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">Normalised</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Succumb <inline-formula id="IEq36"><alternatives><tex-math id="M57">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {period}^\mathsection$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M58"><mml:msup><mml:mtext>period</mml:mtext><mml:mo>§</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq36.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left"><inline-formula id="IEq37"><alternatives><tex-math id="M59">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\pi _\text{suc}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M60"><mml:msub><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mtext>suc</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq37.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">Estimated</td><td align="left">Incidence <inline-formula id="IEq38"><alternatives><tex-math id="M61">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {data}^{*}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M62"><mml:msup><mml:mtext>data</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq38.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Latent period</td><td align="left"><inline-formula id="IEq39"><alternatives><tex-math id="M63">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\pi _\text{lat}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M64"><mml:msub><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mtext>lat</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq39.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">4<inline-formula id="IEq40"><alternatives><tex-math id="M65">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$^{\dag \dag }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M66"><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>†</mml:mo><mml:mo>†</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq40.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> days</td><td align="left">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Asymptomatic period</td><td align="left"><inline-formula id="IEq41"><alternatives><tex-math id="M67">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\pi _\text{asy}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M68"><mml:msub><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mtext>asy</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq41.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">5<inline-formula id="IEq42"><alternatives><tex-math id="M69">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$^{\dag \dag }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M70"><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>†</mml:mo><mml:mo>†</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq42.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> days</td><td align="left">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Symptomatic/recovery period</td><td align="left"><inline-formula id="IEq43"><alternatives><tex-math id="M71">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\pi _\text{rec}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M72"><mml:msub><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mtext>rec</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq43.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">7<inline-formula id="IEq44"><alternatives><tex-math id="M73">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$^{\ddag \ddag }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M74"><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>‡</mml:mo><mml:mo>‡</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq44.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> days</td><td align="left">[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Immune period</td><td align="left"><inline-formula id="IEq45"><alternatives><tex-math id="M75">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\pi _\text{imm}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M76"><mml:msub><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mtext>imm</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq45.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">1000 days</td><td align="left"><inline-formula id="IEq46"><alternatives><tex-math id="M77">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {Unknown}^\parallel$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M78"><mml:msup><mml:mtext>Unknown</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">‖</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq46.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Disease-induced mort./virulence</td><td align="left"><inline-formula id="IEq47"><alternatives><tex-math id="M79">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\alpha ^{\dag \ddag }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M80"><mml:msup><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>†</mml:mo><mml:mo>‡</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq47.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">Estimated</td><td align="left">Mortality data</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Initial values</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Initial susceptible</td><td align="left"><inline-formula id="IEq48"><alternatives><tex-math id="M81">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$S_0$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M82"><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq48.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left" colspan="2"><inline-formula id="IEq49"><alternatives><tex-math id="M83">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$S_0=N_{\text{eff}}-C_0-L_0-A_0-I_0-V_0$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M84"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mtext>eff</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq49.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Initial contact</td><td align="left"><inline-formula id="IEq50"><alternatives><tex-math id="M85">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$C_0$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M86"><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq50.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">Estimated</td><td align="left">Incidence <inline-formula id="IEq51"><alternatives><tex-math id="M87">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {data}^{*}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M88"><mml:msup><mml:mtext>data</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq51.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Initial latent</td><td align="left"><inline-formula id="IEq52"><alternatives><tex-math id="M89">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$L_0$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M90"><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq52.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left"><inline-formula id="IEq53"><alternatives><tex-math id="M91">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\left( \frac{\pi _\text{asy} }{\pi _\text{rec}}\right) G I_0$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M92"><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mtext>asy</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mtext>rec</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq53.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">Requires <inline-formula id="IEq54"><alternatives><tex-math id="M93">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$G{^+}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M94"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq54.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Initial asymptomatic</td><td align="left"><inline-formula id="IEq55"><alternatives><tex-math id="M95">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$A_0$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M96"><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq55.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left"><inline-formula id="IEq56"><alternatives><tex-math id="M97">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\left( \frac{\pi _\text{lat}\pi _\text{asy} }{\pi _\text{rec}^2}\right) G^2 I_0$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M98"><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mtext>lat</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mtext>asy</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mtext>rec</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mfrac></mml:mfenced><mml:msup><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq56.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">Requires <inline-formula id="IEq57"><alternatives><tex-math id="M99">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$G{^+}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M100"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq57.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Initial symptomatic</td><td align="left"><inline-formula id="IEq58"><alternatives><tex-math id="M101">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$I_0$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M102"><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq58.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left">Estimated</td><td align="left">Incidence <inline-formula id="IEq59"><alternatives><tex-math id="M103">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {data}^{*}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M104"><mml:msup><mml:mtext>data</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq59.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left"> Initial immune</td><td align="left"><inline-formula id="IEq60"><alternatives><tex-math id="M105">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$V_0=0$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M106"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq60.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></td><td align="left" colspan="2">SARS-CoV-2 immunologically naïve pop</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><inline-formula id="IEq61"><alternatives><tex-math id="M107">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$^\dag$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M108"><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>†</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq61.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>Web app symbols are: <inline-formula id="IEq62"><alternatives><tex-math id="M109">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\kappa =\mathtt{kappa}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M110"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="monospace">kappa</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq62.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq63"><alternatives><tex-math id="M111">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\pi _\text{thw}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M112"><mml:msub><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mtext>thw</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq63.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>=P_thw, <inline-formula id="IEq64"><alternatives><tex-math id="M113">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$I_0$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M114"><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq64.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>=I_0, etc., as made clear in text</p><p><inline-formula id="IEq65"><alternatives><tex-math id="M115">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$^\mathsection$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M116"><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>§</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq65.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>See Eq. B.3 in Appendix B of Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref> for relationship to SEIR model parameter <inline-formula id="IEq66"><alternatives><tex-math id="M117">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\beta$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M118"><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq66.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></p><p><inline-formula id="IEq67"><alternatives><tex-math id="M119">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$^*$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M120"><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq67.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>Best values estimated using MLE, ranges estimated using MCMC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]</p><p><inline-formula id="IEq68"><alternatives><tex-math id="M121">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$^\P$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M122"><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">¶</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq68.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>Depends on relative outbreak size (e.g., <inline-formula id="IEq69"><alternatives><tex-math id="M123">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$&lt;10$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M124"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq69.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>% of total pop.) for reliable forecasts</p><p><inline-formula id="IEq70"><alternatives><tex-math id="M125">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$^{**}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M126"><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq70.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>Values fitted to the initial conditions will inversely scale with this value</p><p><inline-formula id="IEq71"><alternatives><tex-math id="M127">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$^{\ddag }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M128"><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>‡</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq71.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>Varies. This value implies individuals isolated within three days of entering class I or <inline-formula id="IEq72"><alternatives><tex-math id="M129">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {I}_\text{r}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M130"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>I</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq72.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula></p><p><inline-formula id="IEq73"><alternatives><tex-math id="M131">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$^{\ddag \ddag }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M132"><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>‡</mml:mo><mml:mo>‡</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq73.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>Varies. This rate assumes that sheltering-in-place reduces contact rates by 90%</p><p><inline-formula id="IEq74"><alternatives><tex-math id="M133">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$^{\dag \dag }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M134"><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>†</mml:mo><mml:mo>†</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq74.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>Sources are highly variable, so we selected integer-valued ball park estimates</p><p><inline-formula id="IEq75"><alternatives><tex-math id="M135">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$^{*\ddag }$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M136"><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo><mml:mo>‡</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq75.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>Value early into epidemic since it depends on hospitalisation/isolation protocols</p><p><inline-formula id="IEq76"><alternatives><tex-math id="M137">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$^\parallel$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M138"><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mo stretchy="false">‖</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq76.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>If sufficiently large, its influence on the initial stage of the outbreak is negligible</p><p><inline-formula id="IEq77"><alternatives><tex-math id="M139">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$^{\dag \ddag }\alpha$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M140"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>†</mml:mo><mml:mo>‡</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq77.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, being a driver, is replaced with <inline-formula id="IEq78"><alternatives><tex-math id="M141">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\delta _\text{vir}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M142"><mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mtext>vir</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq78.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> in Appendix C, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>, and Vir_const in the Web App</p><p><inline-formula id="IEq79"><alternatives><tex-math id="M143">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$^+$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M144"><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq79.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>Requires <italic>G</italic> which, unlike <inline-formula id="IEq80"><alternatives><tex-math id="M145">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$R_0$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M146"><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq80.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, is a rate of increase over recovery rather than “serial” interval [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec4">
                <title>Parameters and data</title>
                <p id="Par24">Many, but not all, of the basic epidemiological parameters used to model COVID-19 and other infectious disease outbreaks can be obtained independently from data on the case histories individuals infected with SARS-CoV-2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>], while others can be estimated by fitting models to incidence, mortality and other types of data. Those estimated prior to model fitting (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) are likely to include the latent, asymptomatic, recovery (i.e., from classes A, <inline-formula id="IEq81"><alternatives><tex-math id="M147">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {A}_\text{r}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M148"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq81.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, I and <inline-formula id="IEq82"><alternatives><tex-math id="M149">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {I}_\text{r}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M150"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>I</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq82.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> to V), and immune periods (the latter can only be estimated from future data, depending on the mean period of acquired immunity that will be realised over time), because these are more directly observable from clinical studies than, for example, contact rates and transmission probabilities associated with particular types of contact events. We also note that many parameters are correlated because they act together to produce particular types of observable phenomena, such as growth rates or changes in incidence or mortality levels from one point in time to the next. Thus, for example, contact rates, probability of pathogen transmission per contact, and average infectious period length are linked when it comes to generating the more directly estimable quantity called <inline-formula id="IEq83"><alternatives><tex-math id="M151">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$R_0$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M152"><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq83.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], which is the average number of individuals an infected individual can expect to infect at the initial stage of an outbreak. So, if a value for the infectious period is selected <italic>a priori</italic> to be higher than it really should be, fitting a contact rate parameter value to the incidence time series using, say, maximum-likelihood estimation (MLE) will yield a concomitantly lower value for this rate than if the <italic>a priori</italic> infectious period had been lower.</p>
                <p id="Par25">In Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> a default set of point estimates of parameter values are listed for modelling the initial phase of a non-specific COVID-19 outbreak (also see Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). These values are used to derive probabilities of disease progression events at the individual level, scaled up to the population level using multinomial distributions (stochastic simulations) or proportions of individuals undergoing disease class transitions (deterministic simulations) (see Appendix B of Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). Further, these values can be overridden when values more appropriate to a specific region are available, or values can be selected according to their likelihoods from a distribution of values when available from a suitable source (e.g., from an MCMC procedure, as discussed in Appendix C, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). Of course, incidence and mortality time series data, as well as response driver parameters, will be region specific and depend on policies implemented to help control local outbreaks.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Incidence and Mortality time series are loaded by selecting a CSV file (see the Choose File window on the left). These data along with Epidemic Parameters and Epidemic Drivers values can be loaded separately or default values (shown here) can be loaded, modified, and then saved for use later as a single .dat file. The Fitting interval value is inserted by the user and the Data size value is automatically computed from the length of Incidence and Mortality time series. Once all the parameter values have been set, the Opt Page button on the right can be selected to take the user to the NMB-DASA optimisation page. A forecasting simulation Finish time can be inserted or selected later on the Forecast Page. The yellow Enable Instructional Popups window can be checked to activate mouse-over popups, as illustrated here for the Contact Rate reduction factor</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Fig2_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>
                <p id="Par26">The disease induced mortality rate can also be obtained directly from epidemiological data and the average mortality rate over any period of time can be estimated from the number cases observed and the ultimate fate of those cases: recovery or death. During the course of an outbreak, in the context of COVID-19, however, the time between an individual being infected with SARS-CoV-2 and a definitive outcome can be several weeks. So this time lag has to be taken into account when estimating mortality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Further, during the course of an outbreak, provided the healthcare system is not overwhelmed, we might expect mortality rates to drop as hospitals learn how to take care of the more serious cases admitted for treatment and care.</p>
                <p id="Par27">Parameters that are difficult to explicitly identify from case-history data include the absolute contact rates as a function of behaviour (social distancing or not) and the probability of transmission as a function of the proximity, duration, and background environmental conditions (e.g., humidity, temperature, air movement, fomite characteristics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] during contact). Also difficult to obtain is the state of the population at the time that the first few cases are detected. The first cases are the first group of individuals identified in disease class I at the nominal start of modelling an outbreak, which for convenience we denote as time <inline-formula id="IEq84"><alternatives><tex-math id="M153">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$t=0$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M154"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq84.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. Of course, we anchor this point to some suitable calendar day to facilitate interpretation of results. The number of individuals assigned the value <italic>I</italic>(0) depends on the level of surveillance at time <italic>t</italic>. In a well-developed health care system, depending on the proportion of asymptomatic carriers and the severity of the disease, more than half the cases may easily go undetected during the first few weeks of an outbreak, though surveillance should improve during the course of the outbreak. In a poorly-developed healthcare system, the proportion of cases detected during the initial stage of an outbreak may be considerably lower.</p>
                <p id="Par28">Of course, only symptomatic cases will initially be detected: asymptomatic cases will require the implementation of some sort of testing regimen. Thus, at the start of an epidemic, the numbers of individuals in disease classes C (<italic>C</italic>(0)), L (<italic>L</italic>(0)) and A (<italic>A</italic>(0)) are unknown and, thus, need to be estimated. The latter two can be expressed in terms of the estimated value <italic>I</italic>(0) if the initial growth rate of the epidemic can be reasonably guessed at from past experience with similar epidemics, in which case <italic>L</italic>(0) and <italic>A</italic>(0) may computed from the estimate of <italic>I</italic>(0) (see Appendix B.2, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>) rather than having to be estimated as well. The value of <italic>C</italic>(0), however, also needs to be estimate since its relationship to <italic>I</italic>(0) depends on various other parameters, such as the thwart and succumb periods. Since these two periods are complementary rates out of the same disease class C, and (as a first cut) the net rate through C is more critical to estimate than the size of C itself, we can fix the thwart period at 1. In this case, the fit of the contact rate and succumb periods will then scale relative to the thwart period. The sensitivity of results to this first-cut assumption can later be tested or relaxed, as deemed appropriate.</p>
                <p id="Par29">The initial value <italic>V</italic>(0) for the number of individuals assumed to be immune to infection by SARS-CoV-2 at the start of the outbreak can be set to be 0, since this virus is thought to be novel for humans. Of course, it may emerge that some cross immunity exists for individuals that have previously been exposed to SARS-CoV-1 or other corona viruses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. In this case, initial immunity data can be used to estimate a value for <italic>V</italic>(0) or we can think of the population at risk, as discussed below, to be some appropriate fraction of its true size. In this case, a slightly higher estimate of the true contact rate will emerge from fitting the model to incidence data because contact rates are inversely proportional to the population size <italic>N</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) (see Eqs. A.17 in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>).</p>
                <p id="Par30">Initially, two of the drivers—surveillance and patient isolation rates—can be set at positive constant values, based on a crude expectation of the current level of efficiency of the healthcare infrastructure. For a developed country, we may want to set initial surveillance levels at, say, 0.5 (50%) and hospitalisation levels at, say, 0.35, or some other values that are more reflective of the severity or mildness of the disease. For countries with poor health infrastructure, or diseases milder than COVID-19, values of 0.1 for both these levels may be more suitable. These guesses can be changed later, as the forensic analysis of the structure of the outbreak proceeds, and the sensitivity of projected outcomes to these initial guesses are evaluated.</p>
                <p id="Par31">Another parameter that remains somewhat uncertain at the start of an outbreak is the size <italic>N</italic> of the population at risk. In an isolated, spatially homogeneous population (e.g., an island where all individuals randomly encounter others from different parts of the island—that is, the population is well mixed at, say, a weekly scale), <italic>N</italic> should be the size of the population. In large metropolitan areas where the boundaries separating the relatively well-mixed portion of the population compared to outlying areas, we may want to set the value of <italic>N</italic> to some nominal/effective value <inline-formula id="IEq85"><alternatives><tex-math id="M155">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$N_\text{eff}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M156"><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mtext>eff</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq85.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> that is, say, 1 million or even 10 million when the population size justifies this choice. Initially the actual choice is not critical, because the outbreak dynamics in standard SEIR models, including SCLAIV, is insensitive to the value of <inline-formula id="IEq86"><alternatives><tex-math id="M157">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$N_\text{eff}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M158"><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mtext>eff</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq86.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. As the outbreak progresses and the total number of infections approaches, say <inline-formula id="IEq87"><alternatives><tex-math id="M159">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$10\%$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M160"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq87.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> of <inline-formula id="IEq88"><alternatives><tex-math id="M161">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$N_\text{eff}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M162"><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mtext>eff</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq88.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, then our choice for this value becomes significant. The reason is that <inline-formula id="IEq89"><alternatives><tex-math id="M163">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$N_\text{eff}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M164"><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mtext>eff</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq89.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> determines how rapidly the exponential phase of the initial outbreak begins to lose steam as the decreasing proportion of susceptible individuals in the population begins to play a role in cresting the incidence curve. Thus for epidemics in which the total number of infections exceeds 10%, it may be useful to estimate the “effective population size” <inline-formula id="IEq90"><alternatives><tex-math id="M165">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$N_\text{eff}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M166"><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mtext>eff</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq90.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> when fitting the model output to incidence data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>].</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec5">
                <title>Fitting the model</title>
                <p id="Par32">NMB-DASA uses a maximum-likelihood estimation (MLE) method to fit selected parameters to the incidence and simultaneously or separately to the mortality data by selecting a value for Wt:Incidence/Deaths, as discussed below (also see Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). It also provides for parameter values obtained from Bayesian Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) methods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] generated elsewhere to be used in forecasting simulations (See Section C.3, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). We plan to include MCMC directly in future versions of NMB-DASA<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>An incomplete view (upper left corner) of the optimisation page of the NMB-DASA web app. The leftmost (purple) panel is where variables to be included in the optimisation are checked. The next (pink) panel to its right is where the details of the optimisation procedure are entered: in this case the Fit Range is 31 and Wt:Incidence/Deaths is zero, implying that only the incidence curve is being fit. In this pink panel we see the MLE took 267 iterations to converge, and the absolute log-likelihood error (369 after truncating beyond the decimal point; see Eq. C.2, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>) is provided in the Error window. The incidence and mortality time series and simulated solutions over the interval [0,35] are plotted in top part of the white panel. Below these are MLE and input values of the basic SCLAIV parameters used in the simulation, apart from the mortality rate (i.e., virulence: for this fit has been set to 0.001) that on a larger view of the Opt Page appears just to right of the Patient Isolation window. All switching functions are set to the Constant mode (red rather than green switch values), with indicated values in this case provided rather than fitted</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Fig3_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p>
                <p id="Par33">The following is an outline of the process we used to undertake a forensic analysis of the Israeli incidence and mortality rate data and, in part, the South African and English incidence and mortality rate data. In all cases, we fitted our model to a 7-day lagged moving average of the incidence data because of an obvious seven-day oscillation in new cases reported around the world [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] and, also, newly identified cases are likely associated with individuals actually transferring to the I class some days prior to this reporting event.</p>
                <p id="Par34">A step-wise procedure for running and fitting the SCLAIV model (also see the videos provided at the website (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>) is: <list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par35"><italic>Load Data.</italic> Load the incidence and mortality data using a CSV (comma-separated values) file in which the first row is an incidence data time series and the second row is a mortality time series of the same length as the first. Load the default set of epidemic and driver parameters. If any of the default parameters require modification, these can be overwritten by directly entering data into the appropriate window and then saved by selecting the SAVE SETTINGS button for direct loading next time around.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par36"><italic>Fit Initial Outbreak Phase.</italic> Fit those basic SCLAIV epidemic parameters that cannot be independently estimated by checking them off on the optimisation page (purple panel in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>), setting Wt:incidence/deaths to 1, Fit Range to some desired value, such as 14 or 30, and then pressing the Opt button (pink panel in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). These parameters are likely to be the contact rate kappa, the succumb period P_suc, the initial value C_0 for the contact class, and the initial value I_0 for the symptomatic infectious class. Note, as discussed above, the ratio P_suc/P_thw is more salient than either parameter on its own, so we have normalised P_thw=1. After running an optimisation, the MLE values obtained can be saved using the SAVE SETTINGS button. If desired, an MLE value for the mortality rate can be obtained by unchecking all the variables use in the previous fitting, checking vir_const, resetting Wt:incidence/deaths=0 and then pressing the Opt button again. We note that fitting incidence and mortality are not entirely independent processes, but they are nearly so while the proportion dying is just a few percent and the proportion of susceptibles remains greater than 90%. By selecting Wt:incidence/deaths in between 0 and 1 we can fit both simultaneously, but are then faced with obtaining different solutions for different values of the Wt:incidence/deaths setting on (0, 1).</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par37"><italic>Fit Social Distancing Phase.</italic> When using the model to project the outbreak pattern beyond the initial fit phase, a point will likely be reached where the simulated incidence time series is growing much more rapidly than the empirical time series. If the reverse occurs, then the <italic>Fit Initial Outbreak Phase</italic> step described above should be repeated using a shorter Fit Range value. The reason for this over estimation is either because the effects of social distancing are beginning to take affect, or the effective population size is considerably smaller than initially anticipated. If the latter case is suspected then <inline-formula id="IEq91"><alternatives><tex-math id="M167">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$N_\text{eff}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M168"><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mtext>eff</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq91.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> should be increased, or it can be replaced by an <inline-formula id="IEq92"><alternatives><tex-math id="M169">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$N_\text{eff}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M170"><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mtext>eff</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq92.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> parameter whose size is estimated as part of the MLE process, as discussed in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. At this point, one can proceed by unchecking all variables fitted in the <italic>Fit Initial outbreak Phase</italic> optimisation procedure, and then checking all the social relaxation driver variables to carry out a new MLE fitting procedure with the Fit Range parameter now set beyond its <italic>Fit Initial Outbreak Phase</italic> by several weeks, using the data as a rough guide to where the end of the social distancing phase appears to be occurring because incidence is beginning to decline less steeply or even rise (e.g., see Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par38"><italic>Fit Social Relaxation Phase.</italic> The model can now be used to project the outbreak pattern beyond the <italic>Fit Social Distancing Phase</italic>. If the outbreak has been successfully quelled then the fitting task is complete. In many cases, however, the outbreak may either not be dampened sufficiently fast (as in the case of the COVID-19 in England, see “<xref rid="Sec6" ref-type="sec">Results</xref>” section for details) or may even exhibit a second growth phase that is stronger than the first (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). In either case, the MLE values obtained in the <italic>Fit Initial Outbreak Phase</italic> and <italic>Fit Social Distancing Phase</italic> can be saved and a third round of MLE fitting executed. In this case we may choose to check only the social distancing driver parameters and optimise over a Fit Range that goes several weeks beyond the <italic>Fit Social Distancing Phase</italic>. Other approaches can be taken, discussed in the different case studies below.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par39"><italic>Scenario Projection and Counterfactual Assessments.</italic> We have considerable freedom to run counter-factuals and forecasts (see Appendix C.2, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>), depending on what values we give to the Fitting Interval and Finish Timing for simulation variables (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Forecasting using MCMC parameter estimates can also be undertaken (see Appendix C.3, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>), as illustrated in the Israel COVID-19 case study. The forecasting page of the web app is designed to permit the flexibility of working with two data sets and two time windows: the first is to simulate the model in deterministic mode on an interval <inline-formula id="IEq93"><alternatives><tex-math id="M171">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$[0,t_\text{fit}]$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M172"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mtext>fit</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq93.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and second to allow one (in deterministic mode) or repeated runs (in stochastic mode) on the interval <inline-formula id="IEq94"><alternatives><tex-math id="M173">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$[t_\text{fit},t_\text{fin}]$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M174"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mtext>fit</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mtext>fin</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq94.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. The latter can be either executed by incorporating demographic stochasticity alone, or it can include a file of parameter values obtained from an MCMC fit of the model to data.</p></list-item></list><fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>The daily incidence (new cases) time series (points connected by light brown lines) is plotted from March 1, 2020 to August, 18, 2020. The blue curve is a 7-day lagged moving average plotted to August 12 (which averages over data up to August 18: deaths on August 12, for example can only be identified and recorded as caused by COVID-19 on or after the actual day of death). The different phases of the outbreak, approximately indicated by broken range bars, are: 1. <italic>Initial outbreak phase</italic>, 2. <italic>Social distancing phase</italic>, 3. <italic>Social relaxation phase</italic>, 4. <italic>Second wave mitigation phase</italic></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Fig4_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec6">
              <title>Results</title>
              <p id="Par40">The Israeli, South African, and English COVID-19 illustrative studies presented here are of limited scope. Deeper studies typically involve teams of individuals including those familiar with any idiosyncrasies of the data. Thus our examples are meant to be purely illustrative of how NMB-DASA can be used rather than comprehensive analyses of the epidemics considered.</p>
              <sec id="Sec7">
                <title>COVID-19 in Israel</title>
                <p id="Par41">The first COVID-19 infections in Israel occurred in late February [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. A steady stream of cases only began to be recorded starting around March 1. On March 9, a 14-day home isolation was imposed on all individuals arriving from abroad. A national state of emergency was declared in the Israel on March 19 with the first recorded COVID-19 death of an Israeli citizen occurring on March 20 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>].</p>
                <p id="Par42">A plot of the COVID-19 incidence data from March 1 to August 18 (7-day lagged moving average to August 12) in Israel reveals a rising <italic>initial outbreak phase</italic> in March, followed by a steady drop during a <italic>social distancing phase</italic> to an average of fewer than 20 new cases per day during the second and third weeks of May (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). During the last week of May, incidence began to rise steadily again during a <italic>social relaxation phase</italic>. A <italic>second wave mitigation phase</italic> set in around mid-July, as the second wave was flattened in response to measures used to try and bring the epidemic under control [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p>
                <p id="Par43">We begin by first using MLE to fit our basic free set of SCLAIV parameters (i.e., values for the contact rate kappa, succumb period P_suc, and initial number of individuals in classes C (C_0) and I (I_0), which were not set <italic>a priori</italic> from literature data—see Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) to the first two weeks of the <italic>initial outbreak</italic> data in March 2020. The fit was tight, as shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> along with the four MLE values (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> obtained from the optimisation procedure and other relevant SCLAIV parameters used in model. A subsequent fit to the first month of data indicated that the effects of social distancing were already retarding the outbreak in the second half of March (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>), yielding a new set of four MLE values applicable to fitting the model over the first 31 days. This 31-day fit, however, was quite poor, so we decided to added a social distancing component to MLE fitting of the <italic>initial outbreak</italic> phase (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold> MLE of the basic SCLAIV parameters fitted to the first 14 days (March 1 to 14) of Israeli incidence data only (Wt:Incidence/Deaths=0). <bold>b</bold>. MLE values obtained from this fit. Note, the mortality simulation does not rise to a single individual since no COVID-19 deaths were recorded in Israel during the first two weeks of March. Compare this fit with the same fitting procedure applied to the whole of March, as depicted in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, where we see a rising daily death total in the second half of March</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Fig5_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig><fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p><bold>a, b</bold>. An MLE fit of the basic SCLAIV model &amp; 4 social distancing parameters (SocDist_steep fixed at 3) to the first 31 days of Israeli incidence data. <bold>c, d</bold>. An extension of the fit in <bold>a</bold> obtained by accepting the MLE parameters listed in <bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold> but fitting 4 social relaxation parameters ( SocRel_steep fixed at 3) to the first 100. Note the value SocRel_init=0 in <bold>d</bold> was not fixed, but represents a boundary constraint in the MLE solution</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Fig6_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p>
                <p id="Par44">We thus added a social distancing switching function to our MLE fit of incidence over the first 31 days to obtain Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a, which includes simulation of the model out to day 100. This simulation indicates that the 31-day MLE continues to fit incidence well to around day 80, but then fails to fit to day 100. To correct this, we could either: i.) fix the 8 MLE parameters obtained in our 31-day fit (kappa, I_0, C_0, P_suc in panel Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a and SocDist_on, SocDist_init, SocDist_fnl, SocDist_switch in panel Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>b), but now check the 4 social relaxation parameters SocRel_on, SocRel_init, SocRel_fnl, SocRel_switch in panel Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>d to obtain a new 4 parameter MLE fit over the first 100 days; or ii) we could simultaneously fit all 12 parameters to the first 100 days. We followed the former case to obtained the fit illustrated in Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>c and the 4 new MLE parameter values provided in Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>d. Again we note that SocRel_init=0 is part of a solution induced by the constraint SocRel_init<inline-formula id="IEq95"><alternatives><tex-math id="M175">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\ge 0$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M176"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq95.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold> Simultaneous MLE of 4 SCLAIV, 4 social-distancing and 4 social-relaxation parameters to the first 135 Israeli incidence time series points (i.e. Wt:Incidence/Deaths=0). <bold>b</bold> A better fit of the mortality data alone can be obtained by accepting the MLE values in <bold>a</bold>, setting Wt:Incidence/Deaths=1 and obtaining ML fit for the 3 virulence parameters (we fixed Vir_on=0 and Vir_steep=1) to the first 135 mortality time series points. Note that Vir_fnl=0 is a boundary constraint solution</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Fig7_HTML" id="MO8"/></fig></p>
                <p id="Par45">We also decided to see how well our MLE procedure would perform when fitting all 12 parameters simultaneously, but we did this in the context of all 135 days of incidence data. The result of this MLE undertaking is illustrated in Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>a. In both of the above fits to the first 100 and then 135 incidence data points, we set the disease-induced mortality rate to 0.001 (i.e., Vir_init=0.001). The fits of the mortality rate time series thereby obtained, appear reasonable for the initial phase of the outbreak, but fail beyond the third week of April (e.g., see middle graph in Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). We thus decided to fit a switching curve to the mortality data, by fixing all the values used to obtain the MLE fit depicted in Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>a, setting Wt:Incidence/Deaths to 1, and allowing the parameters Vir_init, Vir_fnl, and Vir_switch to vary in an MLE fit of the model to the mortality data. The resulting MLE fit is depicted in Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>b. We note that the values for Vir_onset and Vir_steep were <italic>a priori</italic> set at 0 and 1 respectively, since disease-induced mortality is always in effect. The remaining MLE parameter values for the virulence switching curve are listed in Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>b. Again we note that the MLE value Vir_fnl=1 represents a boundary solution. A plot of the three switching functions associated with the fits depicted in Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref> are provided in Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>.<fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Plots of the social-distancing switching (applied only to class <inline-formula id="IEq96"><alternatives><tex-math id="M177">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {S}_\text{r}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M178"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>S</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq96.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>), social-relaxation switching (applied only to class S), and the disease-induced natural mortality switching (applied only classes I and <inline-formula id="IEq97"><alternatives><tex-math id="M179">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {I}_\text{r}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M180"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>I</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq97.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) functions obtained from MLE fits of the relevant parameters to the first 100 days of Israeli incidence and mortality data (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>) are shown over the interval March 1 to August 18. The onset values for these three switching functions are days 4 (March 5), 74 (May 14), and 0 (March 1) respectively. The switching points (half way between initial and final values, although the switching time can precede the onset time, as discussed in Section A.3 and caption to Fig. A.2, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>) are on days 6 (March 7), 38 (April 8) and 4 (March 3) respectively. The range of initial to final values are indicated by the values that scale the vertical axes of the three curves in question</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Fig8_HTML" id="MO9"/></fig></p>
                <p id="Par46">Phase 4 of the Israeli COVID-19 outbreak, starting around early to mid-July, exhibited considerably more oscillations in daily incidence and less directionality in growth (phases 1 and 3) or decline (phase 2) associated with it (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>) than the first three phases. Thus we speculate that phase 4 represents a mixture of different intensities of social distancing and social relaxation at different times in different parts of Israel, as various categories of workers and groups of individuals change behaviour in response to social policies and individuals’ perceptions of risk. Thus, we decided to accept the MLE parameters up to day 125 (July 4), as fitted to the first 135 days of incidence and mortality data (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>) and to carryout MCMC fits of the incidence data from day 128 to 166 (as shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>) with respect to constant social distancing and relaxation rates, as described in Appendix C.3 ( Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). More precisely, we carried out an MCMC fit of SocDist_const and SocRel_const (cf. bottom row of sliders in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>) on the incidence data interval [125,166], with all other parameters fixed at the values associated with the fits depicted in Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>.<fig id="Fig9"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>A partial view of the <italic>Forecasting page</italic> show the Number of Runs to be performed, the Number of Days for the total simulations, the Forecast Onset day and the MCMC box checked with the first four rows of MCMC input data shown. The first part of the model projections of Israeli incidence and mortality per unit time are in red in the two left most graphics panels, along with the data plotted in blue. The green curves beyond the red are single stochastic simulations (since the Deter_Stoc switch is flipped to the Stoc). The two right side panels represent the mean plus/minus 2 standard deviations generated from 100 runs using the MCMC data and stochastic projection mode. The number of runs made is specified in the Number of Runs window</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Fig9_HTML" id="MO10"/></fig></p>
                <p id="Par47">The distribution of the parameters obtained from these MCMC fits are provided in Appendix C ( Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). The actual forecasts are illustrated in Fig. <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>. The plotted standard deviations are based on 100 runs. The mean values SocDist_const=0.1316 and SocRel_const=0.00487 obtained from the MCMC procedure respectively represent 103% and 27% of the values of the social-distancing and social-relaxation switching functions on day <inline-formula id="IEq98"><alternatives><tex-math id="M181">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$t=125$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M182"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>125</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq98.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>), which are: SocDist(125)=0.127 and SocRel(125)=0.018. The MCMC estimates of these two constants are highly correlated (the cross correlation is 0.984; Appendix C.3, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). Thus, essentially, it appears that a four-fold reduction in the social-relaxation levels at the beginning of July have confined incidence to the relatively high levels of 1100 to 1700 cases per day throughout September to November. It will require an additional five-fold reduction in the social-relaxation level of early July to bring the epidemic down the point where the number of new cases per day September to November is below 200 (see Fig. D.2 in Appendix D Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>, SOM, for deterministic projects that verify these ballpark figures).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec8">
                <title>COVID-19 in South Africa</title>
                <p id="Par48">The first case of COVID-19 was recorded in South Africa on March 5. A week later only 1 of the 17 recorded cases appeared to involve a local transmission event (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.voanews.com/science-health/coronavirus-outbreak/south-africa-sees-first-local-coronavirus-transmission">https://www.voanews.com/science-health/coronavirus-outbreak/south-africa-sees-first-local-coronavirus-transmission</ext-link>): most new cases during the first three weeks of March 2019 were associated with individuals returning from trips to Europe. The local outbreak only started to pick up the last week of March. This local importation effect is evident in the new cases plotted in Fig <xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>a (see region around the last week of March). Thus we decided to only start fitting the incidence data from Apri 1 onwards. As with the Israeli study, we fitted our model to a 7-day lagged moving averages (Fig <xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>a, b), rather than the raw data themselves.<fig id="Fig10"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold> The incidence (daily new cases; blue) data time series and a 7-day lagged moving average (brown) plotted for new cases of COVID-19 in South Africa from March 6 to Aug 8 (raw data to Aug 14), 2020. <bold>b</bold> As in <bold>a</bold> but plots for daily COVID-19 deaths rather than incidence. <bold>c</bold> Maximum-likelihood estimation (MLE) fits (red plot) of the 4 basic SCLAIV parameters (i.e., kappa, P_suc, I_0, C_0) to the 7-day lagged moving average incidence time series (blue) from April 1 to June 30 (91 points). <bold>d–f</bold> As in <bold>c</bold> but fitting over the interval April 1 to August 8 and, in addition to 4 basic SCLAIV parameters, progressively including: <bold>d</bold> 4 social distancing switching function parameters (SocDist_steep fixed at 3); <bold>e</bold> 3 surveillance switching function parameters (onset time, Surveil_on, fixed at 0; Surveil_steep, fixed at 2); and, <bold>f</bold> 4 social relaxation switching function parameters (SocRel_steep fixed at 3). <bold>g</bold> A combined MLE fit of the incidence (<bold>g1</bold>) and daily mortality (<bold>g2</bold>) time series from April 1 to Aug 8 of the 4 basic SCLAIV parameters plus social distancing, surveillance, social relaxation and switching function parameters, with the MLE forms of these latter four functions presented in plots <bold>g3</bold> See Fig. D.6 in Appendix D, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>, for switching parameter values. Incidence and mortality data source: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ourworldindata.org/coronavirus/country/south-africa?country=%7eZAF">https://ourworldindata.org/coronavirus/country/south-africa?country=~ZAF</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Fig10_HTML" id="MO11"/></fig></p>
                <p id="Par49">Using the step-wise approach described in Section 2.3 and illustrated more fully in the Israeli case study, we conducted a four basic SCLAIV parameter MLE fit of the incidence data from April 1 to June 30 (91 points) and projected 4 weeks beyond this to provide convincing visual evidence (Fig. <xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>c) that social distancing had started to play a key role in flattening the incidence curve some weeks before. We thus conducted a 4-SCLAIV plus 4 social-distancing parameters MLE fit of the first 130 incidence data points, obtaining the relatively poor fit depicted in (Fig. <xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>d). This fit dramatically improved when 3 surveillance parameters were added to the MLE optimisation (Fig. <xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>e). An additional improvement was obtained when including 4 social-relaxation parameters in the MLE optimisation (Fig. <xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>f). Although Fig. <xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>e looks like a better fit than Fig. <xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>f it is not in terms of MLE (the errors associated the fits depicted in Figs. <xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>e and f respectively are 15643 and 5453: see Figs. D.4 &amp; D.5 in SOM) because poorer fits in the early stages, when cases are few, are penalised more than poor fits in the later stages when cases are many. The reason for this is that the value of log-likelihood function (Eq. C.2 in Appendix C, SOM) is dependent on proportional rather than absolute deviations because computations are based on the Poisson probability of particular values arising. Also, although social relaxation switches on earlier than social distancing, this early onset has no effect until individuals begin to accumulate in the social distancing class <inline-formula id="IEq99"><alternatives><tex-math id="M183">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {S}_\text{r}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M184"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>S</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq99.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec9">
                <title>COVID-19 in England</title>
                <p id="Par50">The first two confirmed cases of COVID-19 in England were identified on January 29 in the city of York <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://metro.co.uk/2020/04/19/first-case-coronavirus-uk-COVID-19-diagnosis-12578061/">https://metro.co.uk/2020/04/19/first-case-coronavirus-uk-COVID-19-diagnosis-12578061/</ext-link>. During the month of March another 56 cases in England were recorded (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://coronavirus.data.gov.uk/">https://coronavirus.data.gov.uk/</ext-link>). Our analysis starts at this point in fitting our model to the 7-day lagged moving average of new case in England, starting on March 1 and ending on April 30 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>c, d &amp; e) or August 10 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>f, g).<fig id="Fig11"><label>Fig. 11</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold> The incidence (daily new cases; blue) data time series and a 7-day lagged moving average (brown) plotted for new cases of COVID-19 in England from Feb 19 to Aug 10 (raw data to Aug 16), 2020. <bold>b</bold> As in <bold>a</bold> but plots for daily COVID-19 deaths rather than incidence. <bold>c</bold> Maximum-likelihood estimation (MLE) fits (red plot) of the 4 basic SCLAIV parameters (i.e., kappa, P_suc, I_0, C_0) to the 7-day lagged moving average incidence time series (blue) from March 1 to April 30 (first 60 points). <bold>d, e</bold> As in <bold>c</bold> but in addition to 4 basic SCLAIV parameters, progressively including: <bold>d</bold> 4 social distancing and 3 surveillance switching function parameters (SocDist_steep, Surveil_steep, and Surveil_on fixed at 3, 2, and 0 respectively) and <bold>e</bold> 4 social relaxation switching function parameters (SocRel_steep fixed at 3). <bold>f</bold> As in <bold>e</bold>, but now fitting over the full 163 incidence points. <bold>f</bold>, <bold>g</bold> A combined MLE fit of the incidence (<bold>g1</bold>) and daily mortality (<bold>g2</bold>) time series from April 1 to Aug 10 of the 4 basic SCLAIV parameters plus social distancing, surveillance, social relaxation and switching function parameters, with the MLE forms of these latter four functions presented in plots <bold>g3</bold>. See Fig. D.11 in Appendix D, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>, for switching parameter values. Data source: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://coronavirus.data.gov.uk/">https://coronavirus.data.gov.uk/</ext-link></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Fig11_HTML" id="MO12"/></fig></p>
                <p id="Par51">Our first fit of our model to COVID-19 incidence in England over the period March 1 to April 30 involved MLEs of the 4-SCLAIV plus 4 social-distancing switching function parameters. This reasonably fit was notably improved (the absolute log-likelhood error value dropping from 3360 to 1812) by adding 3 surveillance switching function parameters (Fig. <xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>d). Further improvement was obtained (log-likelhood error value now dropping to 831) by adding 4 social-relaxation switching function parameters to the MLE fit. This 15-parameter MLE fit was then extended to the full 163 point time series (i.e., up to August 10) to obtain the fit depicted in Fig. <xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>f (for more details on Figs. <xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>c-f see Figures D.7-10, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). Rather than accepting this fit to incidence, we carried out simultaneous fit of incidence and mortality with the inclusion of the virulence switching function parameters and setting Wt:Incidence/Deaths=0.5. Specifically, we added 3 virulence switching parameters to the 15 used to fit the incidence alone in Fig. <xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>f to obtain the fit to incidence depicted in Fig. <xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>g1 and the fit to mortality depicted in Fig. <xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>g2. The forms of the switching curves obtained from this MLE fit are provided in Fig. <xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>g3 (see Fig. D.10, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>, for more details and parameter values).</p>
                <p id="Par52">The switching functions depicted in Fig. <xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>g3 suggest the following. First, surveillance started out around 0.3, but rapidly doubled during the first month (March) to the asymptotic value of 0.6. Social distancing appears to only have started in earnest around the end of March raising four-fold in value through April and May. Social relaxation also started in March (the actual rate has no effect until individuals start to accumulate in the risk reduction class <inline-formula id="IEq100"><alternatives><tex-math id="M185">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {S}_\text{r}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M186"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>S</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq100.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> through the action of social distancing), rising steadily in through May, June and July as a partial counter to the effects of the social distancing process. This social relaxation counter to social distancing remained below a quarter of the per-capita social distancing level (per-capita S for social distancing, per-capita <inline-formula id="IEq101"><alternatives><tex-math id="M187">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {S}_\text{r}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M188"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>S</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq101.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> for social relaxation) through most of this time, which allowed social distancing to dominate and keep the epidemic decline going throughout all of May and June. In July, however, the effect of social relaxation reversed this trend, and it remains to be seen which will dominate from mid August onwards as social behaviour adapts over time.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec10">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <sec id="Sec11">
                <title>Comparisons and insights</title>
                <p id="Par53">The three epidemics that we examined represents a range that includes: one of the most serious epidemics worldwide, which in late August appeared to be well passed its peak (South Africa); one of the most severe epidemics in Europe that now has been brought under control, but could well break out again if vigilance is lost (England); and a relatively large outbreak for a smaller country that exhibited a second wave considerably more severe than first, and that is now heading into a phase where the epidemic could well fester for the rest of 2020 (Israel). In all of these, our analyses uncovered putative periods of time when different driving forces were dominating: periods when social distancing provided the necessary driving force to flatten and even reverse the exponential growth phase, followed by periods when relaxation of social distancing threatened or allowed a second wave, an including periods of change in surveillance or treatment efficacy. Although statistical modelling is required to link values for these drivers to various activities, their quantification in the context of specific cases allows relative assessments to be made for each of those cases. Thus, we are able to make statements such as: the Israeli epidemic will continue to produce an average of around 1500 new case per day throughout August to November, unless the efficacy of social distancing measures rise to at least 3/4 of where they were throughout March.</p>
                <p id="Par54">With hindsight obtained during the final revision of this paper, our MCMC projections from July 7 to the end of November (Figs <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref> and <xref rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig">12</xref>) captured very well the dip and then slight rise in the trajectory of the Israeli incidence curve for the 7 week period from July 7 to the end of August. At the end of August, however, social distancing behaviour must have greatly relaxed because an exceptionally strong third wave broke out with incidence peaking at around 5800 per day at the end of September compared with 1600 cases per day around the second peak in mid-July (Fig. <xref rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig">12</xref>). The occurrence of such third peaks illustrates how predictions can go wrong when behavioural drivers are limited to on-off switching. Only multiple switching of behavioural drivers can account for the type of third peak behaviour observed in the Israeli epidemic. Predicting when these switches occur, however, requires that various socio-economic factors such as holiday periods and social distancing fatigue be taken into account.<fig id="Fig12"><label>Fig. 12</label><caption><p>The daily incidence in the Israeli epidemic is plotted (orange curve) from March 1 to November 30, 2020. The blue curve is the simulated output fitted to the incidence data over the period March 1 to July 7, with MCMC projections of the mean (continued blue curve) plus/minus 2 standard deviations (broken red curves) over the period July 9 to Nov 30 (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Fig12_HTML" id="MO13"/></fig></p>
                <p id="Par55">Our SCLAIV formulation can be extended to include drivers with multiple switches. More feasible from a parameter estimation point of view, though, is to fit our SCLAIV-response model to say a second or third wave of data, using a starting condition that corresponds to the state of the epidemic at the end of the first or second wave. The dynamics of the first, second and third waves can then be compared, thereby providing some additional insights into the way populations respond to the unfolding of local epidemics.</p>
                <p id="Par56">Most current dynamical systems models of epidemics (i.e., SEIR-based systems of difference or differential equation models) do not have the kinds of structures in place that facilitate analyses of behavioural drivers of the type included in our SCLAIV-response formulation. In particular, our SCLAIV-response model provides an opportunity to obtain insights that come from looking at the various fractions of individuals in various SCLAIV-response classes over time. In addition, we expect these fractions to be more robust than estimated values of the driver parameters themselves because of co-linearity issues associated with fitting models with many parameters to incidence and mortality data (e.g., in fitting the social distancing and social relaxation drivers, it is the net rate at which behavioural changes occur rather than the independent time-varying rates of the drivers themselves).</p>
                <p id="Par57">An examination of plots of the <italic>curve-flattening index</italic>
<inline-formula id="IEq102"><alternatives><tex-math id="M189">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$c_\text{flatten}(t)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M190"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mtext>flatten</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq102.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> introduced in the Methods section (Eq. <xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="">1</xref>) allows as to compare the intensity to which behavioural factors were operating to suppress the epidemic outbreaks in Israel, South African and England over the period March to July, 2020 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig13" ref-type="fig">13</xref>). These plots indicate that an earlier and stronger behavioural shutdown response occurred in Israel than in England or South Africa, while behavioural suppression gradually increased in South Africa compared with moderate steady decreases in Israel and England over the period in question. The curve flattening index in Israel was clearly released for some reason during September 2020 to allow incidence to rise so dramatically during September, which was a major holiday month that included celebrations of the Jewish New Year (which occurred on September 18–20).<fig id="Fig13"><label>Fig. 13</label><caption><p>The time courses of our curve flattening index for Israel, South Africa and England are plotted over the period March to July, 2020. This index is the proportion of susceptibles in disease class <bold>S</bold><inline-formula id="IEq103"><alternatives><tex-math id="M191">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$_\text{r}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M192"><mml:msub><mml:mrow/><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq103.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> over time (see Eq. <xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="">1</xref>) and, as such, is 0 if none of the susceptibles have taken measures to reduce the rate of SARS-CoV-2 transmission through social distancing, mask wearing or other suitable actions. On the other hand, this index is 1 when all individuals in the population have take precautions to reduce the risk of transmission by an order of magnitude (corresponding to the fact that we have set the Contact rate reduction parameter in the model to <inline-formula id="IEq104"><alternatives><tex-math id="M193">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\delta _\text{con}=0.1$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M194"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mtext>con</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq104.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>—see Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Fig13_HTML" id="MO14"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="Sec12">
                <title>Strengths and weaknesses</title>
                <p id="Par58">At the end of 2020, web apps available for aiding the kinds of analyses presented in this paper are limited. The most flexible of these is the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.covid19sim.org/">https://www.covid19sim.org/</ext-link>, developed by a consortium that includes the Massachusetts General Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Georgia Tech, and Boston Medical Center. The COVID-19 Simulator provides “... a tool designed to help policymakers decide how to respond to the novel coronavirus.” The tool can be used to explore the impact of social-distancing interventions by selecting one of four intensity levels applied at a selected time. The simulator does not allow the user to upload his or her own data and limits analyses to US National and State levels. Other web sites, such as <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.idmod.org/documentation">https://www.idmod.org/documentation</ext-link> (Institute of Diseas Modeling) EMOD or Covasim, or the platform <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.epimodel.org/index.html">https://www.epimodel.org/index.html</ext-link> require users to have some coding or epidemiological modelling experience.</p>
                <p id="Par59">Strengths of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://covid-webapp.numerusinc.com/">http://covid-webapp.numerusinc.com/</ext-link> web app are that it allows users to input their own data, fit model parameters to data using maximum-likelihood methods, and undertake scenario and forecasting studies with the ability to manipulate an array (8 in total; see Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) of policy-relevant drivers. Additionally, the South African, English and Israeli COVID-19 case studies provide clear exemplars on how the NMB-DASA Web App can be used to identify which drivers dominate during different phases of an epidemic. If other healthcare and social media infrastructural data (i.e., beyond incidence and mortality rate time series) can be used to independently specify or estimate surveillance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>], social distancing and relaxation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>], quarantining [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] and treatment advances, then further analyses can be undertaken to verify results. In particular, proportions of individuals in the immune class predicted by our model can be tested if appropriately collected serology data are available [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>].</p>
                <p id="Par60">Although our exemplar indicates that NMB-DASA can be used to perform analyses of disease outbreaks caused by directly transmissible pathogens for which incidence data alone are available, much deeper analyses can be undertaken. First, spatial structure can be taken into account [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Second, links between model output and data may be sought that pertain to individual and societal factors influencing transmission. This can be done by making statistical links between model parameters putative factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. This would require the dynamic analyses of the types demonstrated here augmented with statistical models that linked dynamic measures (such as new cases growth rates over initial and later phases of the outbreak) to key factors of interest.</p>
                <p id="Par62">Critics of our SCLAIV+D+response approach to modeling COVID-19 could say that: 1.) our model has too many parameters for fits to be credible; 2.) the focus is on point estimates to obtain fits of the model to incidence and mortality data, since MCMC fits are currently external to the app; 3.) many of these point estimates are either not well known or possibly not accurate; or, 4.) the results we obtain have not been adequately validated or even their robustness confirmed using sensitivity analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>] or other assessment techniques.</p>
                <p id="Par63">In addressing these criticisms, we note Einstein’s dictum that “Everything should be made as simple as possible, but not simpler” speaks to two ideas: the idea of Occam’s razor that the most simple of all formulations needed to capture a particular process should be used; and the idea that if a model is too simple it omits a key process altogether. SEIR models themselves conform to Occam’s razor in ignoring heterogeneities in the relative succeptibility and infectivity of individuals, and in invoking the assumption of a well-mixed population that obviates the need for considerations of spatial structure. Heterogeneity in infectivity is of importance when considering the questions of, say, the role of superspreaders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], susceptibility and morbidity with regard to age [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>], or policies related to particular subgroups in the population, such as opening schools [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Spatial structure is important, for example, when considering the impact of restricting travel [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>] on managing COVID-19 epidemics. Just as with any SEIR model, the web app can be used to focus on subgroups or spatial structure, although assumptions about links between these groups and the population at large will need to be made.</p>
                <p id="Par64">Second, since the purpose of our web app is to provide a tool for shedding light on the aggregated effects of several different behavioural and mitigating drivers as they ramp up or down over time, we need to include all drivers of interest in the context of making the model adequate to address the questions at hand [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. In addition, we cannot identify when these drivers may be ramping up or down if we do not characterise them as switching functions. This requires a proliferation of parameters, but these parameters are not all involved in fitting the model at various stages of the outbreak. This is the reason for trying to fit the basic SCLAIV parameters that cannot be independently obtained to the initial outbreak phase and then identifying other phases where the parameters of particular drivers can be estimated. It is also why it is useful (though not necessary) to be able to fit changes in virulence to the mortality data alone once fits to the incidence data have taken place.</p>
                <p id="Par65">Third, not all parameters need to be accurately known (though the more accurate the better), if some are to be specified and others fitted to the data. For example, the initial phases of an epidemic are characterised by its growth rate per unit serial interval time. This characterising value is represented by the quantity <inline-formula id="IEq105"><alternatives><tex-math id="M195">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$R_0$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M196"><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq105.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, which we defined in the introduction as the average number of individuals an infected individual can expect to infect at the initial stage of an outbreak. Depending on the complexity of the model, estimation of <inline-formula id="IEq106"><alternatives><tex-math id="M197">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$R_0$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M198"><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq106.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> involves contact rates and infectiousness (force of infection), periods of time spent in disease classes, and even disease-induced mortality rates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Thus, if one of these parameters is not accurately known, our experience has been [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] that the estimation process will compensate by adjusting the values of other parameters involved in the computation of <inline-formula id="IEq107"><alternatives><tex-math id="M199">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$R_0$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M200"><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq107.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. This compensatory process can be seen quite clearly in the context of the MCMC forecast undertaken for the fourth phase of the Israel outbreak, where we see that that correlation between the social distancing and social relaxation constants being estimated exceeds 98% (Fig. C.2, Appendix C, Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). Additionally, the question of when and where to carry out Bayesian MCMC rather than MLE model fitting of parameters is one that requires a much more extensive discussion than can be undertaken here. We will skirt around this by saying that MCMC is really important when it comes to using forecasts to mitigate risk—that is, when it is important to have a sense of how bad things might get. Maximum-likelihood estimation, however, is much easier and faster to implement and, because of its relative simplicity, may be more useful when trying to identify different phases of an outbreak and making comparative assessments on the efficacy of implementing particular mitigating drivers.</p>
                <p id="Par66">Fourth, we agree that sensitivity analyses are useful for evaluating the robustness of results and should be undertaken in studies that probe more deeply than presented here. Additionally, our SCLAIV model provides a number of auxiliary predictions, such as the proportion of individuals that are immune (i.e., the value of the variable <italic>V</italic>(<italic>t</italic>)/<italic>N</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) as it changes over time) that can be evaluated against serological data obtained through a statistically valid sampling method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Deeper in-country studies, involving local experts and a wide array of auxiliary data (i.e., beyond incidence and mortality rate time series) can thus also be used to either further support or refute results obtained.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="Sec13">
              <title>Conclusion</title>
              <p id="Par67">In summary, the NMB-DASA web app is based on a model that is both relevant and appropriate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>] for carrying out the types of forensic analyses on social and mitigating drivers of epidemics illustrated in our three COVID-19 case studies and, thereby, provides another tool in the epidemiologist tool box for managing outbreaks. Although additional statistical modelling is needed to relate disease-class structure aspects of our epidemic driver analyses, such as the proportion of susceptibles in the social distancing class <inline-formula id="IEq108"><alternatives><tex-math id="M201">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {S}_\text{r}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M202"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>S</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq108.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> compared with the non-social distancing class S, to other more difficult to come by measures of social behaviour, NMB-DASA provides a way to uncover disease-class structures that are critical to managing epidemics and mitigating the level of economic damage that has been wrought by the COVID-19 pandemic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. In the spirit of appropriate complexity modelling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], even though our S versus <inline-formula id="IEq109"><alternatives><tex-math id="M203">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {S}_\text{r}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M204"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>S</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq109.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> view is only a binary representation of what is, in reality, a spectrum of social distancing behaviour, it has considerable value in comparing social distancing behaviour at different points in time within the same epidemic or different epidemics at comparable points in time. Further, NMB-DASA allows other critical time-varying drivers to be identified, including surveillance that appears to be particularly salient in fitting our SCLAIV response model to the English incidence profile, and reductions in per-case mortality rates that occur in all three of our illustrative studies.</p>
              <p id="Par68">COVID-19 itself is not an anomaly, but one event in series of expected future events that have a past history in SARS, MERS, Ebola, not to mention avian influenza and other highly contagious emerging infectious diseases of zoonotic origin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. Our current experience with COVID-19 will help facilitate our response to these future outbreaks and potential pandemics. The availability of computational tools, such as <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://covid-webapp.numerusinc.com/">http://covid-webapp.numerusinc.com/</ext-link>, will enable policy makers and healthcare administrators to be caught less flat-footed at the start of the next outbreak than has been the case for the COVID-19 pandemic.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
              <title>Supplementary Information</title>
              <sec id="Sec22">
                <p>
                  <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1">
                    <media xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_MOESM1_ESM.pdf">
                      <caption>
                        <p><bold>Additional file 1: </bold>A Additional file is provided containing: Appendix A, details of a continuous-time version of our SCLAIV model; Appendix B, our discrete-time implementation of this model; Appendix C, parameter estimation and simulation procedures, including details of our MCMC computation; and Appendix D, additional case-study figures.</p>
                      </caption>
                    </media>
                  </supplementary-material>
                  <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2">
                    <media xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_MOESM2_ESM.zip">
                      <caption>
                        <p><bold>Additional file 2:</bold> Three training videos are available with links provided by selecting the instructional material button at the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://covid-webapp.numerusinc.com/">http://covid-webapp.numerusinc.com/</ext-link> Home page. Direct links to these videos are: Training video 1, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iK4VSdiMOC4">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iK4VSdiMOC4</ext-link>; Training video 2, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZBdwZaknyj4&amp;t=604s">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZBdwZaknyj4&amp;t=604s</ext-link>; Traning video 3, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NtwcCGDog_o">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NtwcCGDog_o</ext-link>.</p>
                      </caption>
                    </media>
                  </supplementary-material>
                </p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <glossary>
              <title>Abbreviations</title>
              <def-list>
                <def-item>
                  <term>
                    <inline-formula id="IEq1">
                      <alternatives>
                        <tex-math id="M205">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$c_{{\text{flattening}}}(t)$$\end{document}</tex-math>
                        <mml:math id="M206">
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:msub>
                              <mml:mi>c</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mtext>flattening</mml:mtext>
                            </mml:msub>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mi>t</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:math>
                        <inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq1.gif"/>
                      </alternatives>
                    </inline-formula>
                  </term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par5">Time-dependent curve flattening index</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>COVID-19</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par6">Corona viral disease, 2019</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>CSV</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par7">Comma-separated values</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>IDM</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par8">Institute of Disease Modeling</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>MCMC</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par9">Markov chain Monte Carlo</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>MLE</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par10">Maximum-likelihood estimation</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>NMB-DASA</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par11">Numerus Model Builder Data and Simulation Analysis</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>Pc-adc</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par12">Per-capita applicable-disease-class</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>SM</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par13">Supplementary Material</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>SARS-CoV-2</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par14">Severe acute respiratory syndrome covid virus 2</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>SCLAIV+D</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par15">Susceptible, Contact, Latent, Asymptomatic infectious, Infectious, Vaccinated, Dead disease classes</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term><inline-formula id="IEq2"><alternatives><tex-math id="M207">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {S}_\text{r}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M208"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>S</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq2.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq3"><alternatives><tex-math id="M209">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {C}_\text{r}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M210"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq3.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq4"><alternatives><tex-math id="M211">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {L}_\text{r}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M212"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>L</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq4.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq5"><alternatives><tex-math id="M213">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {A}_\text{r}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M214"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>A</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq5.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq6"><alternatives><tex-math id="M215">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {I}_\text{r}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M216"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>I</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq6.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>, <inline-formula id="IEq7"><alternatives><tex-math id="M217">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\hbox {V}_\text{r}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M218"><mml:msub><mml:mtext>V</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:msub></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq7.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>:</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par16">Susceptible, Contact, Latent, Asymptomatic infectious, Infectious, Vaccinated response classes, with actual numbers in each class at time <italic>t</italic> being the italicised version, viz. <italic>S</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) and <inline-formula id="IEq8"><alternatives><tex-math id="M219">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$S_\text{r}(t)$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M220"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mtext>r</mml:mtext></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="12967_2021_2736_Article_IEq8.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> etc.</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>SEIR</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par17">Susceptible, Exposed, Infectious, Recovered</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
              </def-list>
            </glossary>
            <fn-group>
              <fn>
                <p>Wayne M Getz and Richard Salter Co-first authors</p>
              </fn>
              <fn>
                <p>
                  <bold>Publisher's Note</bold>
                </p>
                <p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <sec>
              <title>Supplementary Information</title>
              <p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1186/s12967-021-02736-2.</p>
            </sec>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgements</title>
              <p>Ludovica Luisa Vissat thanks Michalis Michaelides and Sally Paganin for providing useful guidance for the MCMC procedure.</p>
            </ack>
            <notes notes-type="author-contribution">
              <title>Authors’ contributions</title>
              <p>WMG, conceived the study, formulated the model and wrote the manuscript. Richard Salter developed the web site and the Numerus Modeling Builder software platform. RS and LLV were responsible for the MCMC simulations and the material on this in the Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>. NH scrapped data from the web. All authors read and edited the final version of the paper. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="funding-information">
              <title>Funding</title>
              <p>This research was funded by NSF Grant 2032264.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="data-availability">
              <title>Availability of data and materials</title>
              <p>Data for the Israeli outbreak are available at the NMB-DASA website and the authors can be contact if other data are needed.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes id="FPar2">
              <title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
              <p id="Par76">Not applicable.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes id="FPar3">
              <title>Consent for publication</title>
              <p id="Par77">All authors have read the ms and agree to its publication in BMC Translational Medicine.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes id="FPar4" notes-type="COI-statement">
              <title>Competing interests</title>
              <p id="Par78">Wayne M. Getz and Richard Salter are two of three owners of Numerus Inc., which is responsible for developing and maintaining the Numerus Model Builder software platform.</p>
            </notes>
            <ref-list id="Bib1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="CR1">
                <label>1.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zhang J, Litvinova M, Liang Y, Wang Y, Wang W, Zhao S, Wu Q, Merler S, Viboud C, Vespignani A, et al. Changes in contact patterns shape the dynamics of the covid-19 outbreak in china. Science. 2020.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR2">
                <label>2.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wilder-Smith</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Freedman</surname>
                      <given-names>DO</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Isolation, quarantine, social distancing and community containment: pivotal role for old-style public health measures in the novel coronavirus (2019-ncov) outbreak</article-title>
                  <source>J Travel Med</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>27</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>020</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jtm/taaa020</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR3">
                <label>3.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bi Q, Wu Y, Mei S, Ye C, Zou X, Zhang Z, Liu X, Wei L, Truelove SA, Zhang T, et al. Epidemiology and transmission of covid-19 in 391 cases and 1286 of their close contacts in shenzhen, china: a retrospective cohort study. The Lancet Infectious Diseases. 2020.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR4">
                <label>4.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tang B, Xia F, Tang S, Bragazzi NL, Li Q, Sun X, Liang J, Xiao Y, Wu J. The effectiveness of quarantine and isolation determine the trend of the covid-19 epidemics in the final phase of the current outbreak in china. International Journal of Infectious Diseases. 2020.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR5">
                <label>5.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Park SW, Cornforth DM, Dushoff J, Weitz JS. The time scale of asymptomatic transmission affects estimates of epidemic potential in the covid-19 outbreak. Epidemics. 2020;100392.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR6">
                <label>6.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Furukawa NW, Brooks JT, Sobel J. Evidence supporting transmission of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 while presymptomatic or asymptomatic. Emerging infectious diseases. 2020;26(7).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR7">
                <label>7.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ferguson N, Laydon D, Nedjati Gilani G, Imai N, Ainslie K, Baguelin M, Bhatia S, Boonyasiri A, Cucunuba Perez Z, Cuomo-Dannenburg G, et al. Report 9: Impact of non-pharmaceutical interventions (npis) to reduce covid19 mortality and healthcare demand. Technology and Medicine: Imperial College of Science; 2020.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR8">
                <label>8.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pei</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Song</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shaman</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Substantial undocumented infection facilitates the rapid dissemination of novel coronavirus (sars-cov-2)</article-title>
                  <source>Science</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>368</volume>
                  <issue>6490</issue>
                  <fpage>489</fpage>
                  <lpage>493</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abb3221</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32179701</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR9">
                <label>9.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Eikenberry SE, Mancuso M, Iboi E, Phan T, Eikenberry K, Kuang Y, Kostelich E, Gumel AB To mask or not to mask: Modeling the potential for face mask use by the general public to curtail the covid-19 pandemic. Infectious Disease Modelling. 2020.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR10">
                <label>10.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lauer</surname>
                      <given-names>SA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Grantz</surname>
                      <given-names>KH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bi</surname>
                      <given-names>Q</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jones</surname>
                      <given-names>FK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zheng</surname>
                      <given-names>Q</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Meredith</surname>
                      <given-names>HR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Azman</surname>
                      <given-names>AS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reich</surname>
                      <given-names>NG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lessler</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The incubation period of coronavirus disease 2019 (covid-19) from publicly reported confirmed cases: estimation and application</article-title>
                  <source>Annals Internal Med</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>172</volume>
                  <issue>9</issue>
                  <fpage>577</fpage>
                  <lpage>582</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/M20-0504</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR11">
                <label>11.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Linton</surname>
                      <given-names>NM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kobayashi</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hayashi</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Akhmetzhanov</surname>
                      <given-names>AR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jung</surname>
                      <given-names>S-M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yuan</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kinoshita</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nishiura</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Incubation period and other epidemiological characteristics of 2019 novel coronavirus infections with right truncation: a statistical analysis of publicly available case data</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Med</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>538</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm9020538</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR12">
                <label>12.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bar-On YM, Sender R, Flamholz AI, Phillips R, Milo R A quantitative compendium of covid-19 epidemiology. arXiv preprint <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.01283">arXiv:2006.01283</ext-link> 2020.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR13">
                <label>13.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hethcote HW The basic epidemiology models: models, expressions for r0, parameter estimation, and applications. In: Mathematical Understanding of Infectious Disease Dynamics, pp. 1–61. World Scientific, 2009.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR14">
                <label>14.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Van den Driessche</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Watmough</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Reproduction numbers and sub-threshold endemic equilibria for compartmental models of disease transmission</article-title>
                  <source>Mathematical Biosci</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>180</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <lpage>48</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0025-5564(02)00108-6</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR15">
                <label>15.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sette A, Crotty S. Pre-existing immunity to sars-cov-2: the knowns and unknowns. Nature Reviews Immunology. 2020;1–2.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR16">
                <label>16.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Getz</surname>
                      <given-names>WM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Salter</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Muellerklein</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yoon</surname>
                      <given-names>HS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tallam</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Modeling epidemics: A primer and numerus model builder implementation</article-title>
                  <source>Epidemics</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>25</volume>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <lpage>19</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.epidem.2018.06.001</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30017895</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR17">
                <label>17.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hamra</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>MacLehose</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Richardson</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Markov chain monte carlo: an introduction for epidemiologists</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Epidemiol</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>627</fpage>
                  <lpage>634</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dyt043</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23569196</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR18">
                <label>18.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Roberts</surname>
                      <given-names>GO</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rosenthal</surname>
                      <given-names>JS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>General state space markov chains and mcmc algorithms</article-title>
                  <source>Probability Surveys</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>1</volume>
                  <fpage>20</fpage>
                  <lpage>71</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1214/154957804100000024</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR19">
                <label>19.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ricon-Becker I, Tarrasch R, Blinder P, Ben-Eliyahu S A seven-day cycle in covid-19 infection and mortality rates: Are inter-generational social interactions on the weekends killing susceptible people? medRxiv 2020.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR20">
                <label>20.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rossman</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Keshet</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shilo</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gavrieli</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bauman</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cohen</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shelly</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Balicer</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Geiger</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dor</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A framework for identifying regional outbreak and spread of covid-19 from one-minute population-wide surveys</article-title>
                  <source>Nature Med</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <fpage>634</fpage>
                  <lpage>638</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-020-0857-9</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32273611</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR21">
                <label>21.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Last M The first wave of covid-19 in israel-initial analysis of publicly available data. medRxiv 2020.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR22">
                <label>22.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bodas</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Peleg</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Self-isolation compliance in the covid-19 era influenced by compensation: Findings from a recent survey in israel: Public attitudes toward the covid-19 outbreak and self-isolation: a cross sectional study of the adult population of israel</article-title>
                  <source>Health Affairs</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>39</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>936</fpage>
                  <lpage>941</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1377/hlthaff.2020.00382</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32271627</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR23">
                <label>23.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yue</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Clapham</surname>
                      <given-names>HE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cook</surname>
                      <given-names>AR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Estimating the size of a covid-19 epidemic from surveillance systems</article-title>
                  <source>Epidemiology</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>31</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>567</fpage>
                  <lpage>569</lpage>
                  <?supplied-pmid 32324625?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32324625</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR24">
                <label>24.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Silverman JD, Hupert N, Washburne AD. Using influenza surveillance networks to estimate state-specific prevalence of sars-cov-2 in the united states. Science translational medicine. 2020;12(554).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR25">
                <label>25.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yasaka</surname>
                      <given-names>TM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lehrich</surname>
                      <given-names>BM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sahyouni</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Peer-to-peer contact tracing: development of a privacy-preserving smartphone app</article-title>
                  <source>JMIR mHealth uHealth</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <fpage>18936</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/18936</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR26">
                <label>26.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bastos ML, Tavaziva G, Abidi SK, Campbell JR, Haraoui L-P, Johnston JC, Lan Z, Law S, MacLean E, Trajman A, et al. Diagnostic accuracy of serological tests for covid-19: systematic review and meta-analysis. bmj 2020;370.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR27">
                <label>27.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huang</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ding</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Spatial-temporal distribution of covid-19 in china and its prediction: A data-driven modeling analysis</article-title>
                  <source>J Infect Developing Countries</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <issue>03</issue>
                  <fpage>246</fpage>
                  <lpage>253</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3855/jidc.12585</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR28">
                <label>28.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kramer</surname>
                      <given-names>AM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pulliam</surname>
                      <given-names>JT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alexander</surname>
                      <given-names>LW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Park</surname>
                      <given-names>AW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rohani</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Drake</surname>
                      <given-names>JM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Spatial spread of the west africa ebola epidemic</article-title>
                  <source>Open Sci</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>3</volume>
                  <issue>8</issue>
                  <fpage>160294</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR29">
                <label>29.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Getz</surname>
                      <given-names>WM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Salter</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mgbara</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Adequacy of seir models when epidemics have spatial structure: Ebola in sierra leone</article-title>
                  <source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>374</volume>
                  <issue>1775</issue>
                  <fpage>20180282</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2018.0282</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR30">
                <label>30.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Williamson EJ, Walker AJ, Bhaskaran K, Bacon S, Bates C, Morton CE, Curtis HJ, Mehrkar A, Evans D, Inglesby P, et al. Opensafely: factors associated with covid-19 death in 17 million patients. Nature. 2020;1–11.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR31">
                <label>31.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lakshmi Priyadarsini</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Suresh</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Factors influencing the epidemiological characteristics of pandemic covid 19: A tism approach</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Healthcare Management</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>89</fpage>
                  <lpage>98</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/20479700.2020.1755804</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR32">
                <label>32.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Saltelli A, Tarantola S, Campolongo F, Ratto M Sensitivity Analysis in Practice: a Guide to Assessing Scientific Models vol. 1. Wiley Online Library, 2004.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR33">
                <label>33.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lloyd-Smith</surname>
                      <given-names>JO</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schreiber</surname>
                      <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kopp</surname>
                      <given-names>PE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Getz</surname>
                      <given-names>WM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Superspreading and the effect of individual variation on disease emergence</article-title>
                  <source>Nature</source>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <volume>438</volume>
                  <issue>7066</issue>
                  <fpage>355</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature04153</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16292310</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR34">
                <label>34.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dowd</surname>
                      <given-names>JB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Andriano</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brazel</surname>
                      <given-names>DM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rotondi</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Block</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ding</surname>
                      <given-names>X</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mills</surname>
                      <given-names>MC</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Demographic science aids in understanding the spread and fatality rates of covid-19</article-title>
                  <source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>117</volume>
                  <issue>18</issue>
                  <fpage>9696</fpage>
                  <lpage>9698</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2004911117</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR35">
                <label>35.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Viner RM, Russell SJ, Croker H, Packer J, Ward J, Stansfield C, Mytton O, Bonell C, Booy R School closure and management practices during coronavirus outbreaks including covid-19: a rapid systematic review. The Lancet Child &amp; Adolescent Health 2020.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR36">
                <label>36.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chinazzi</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davis</surname>
                      <given-names>JT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ajelli</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gioannini</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Litvinova</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Merler</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>y Piontti</surname>
                      <given-names>AP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mu</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rossi</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sun</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effect of travel restrictions on the spread of the 2019 novel coronavirus (covid-19) outbreak</article-title>
                  <source>Science</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>368</volume>
                  <issue>6489</issue>
                  <fpage>395</fpage>
                  <lpage>400</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aba9757</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32144116</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR37">
                <label>37.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Getz</surname>
                      <given-names>WM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Marshall</surname>
                      <given-names>CR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Carlson</surname>
                      <given-names>CJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Giuggioli</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ryan</surname>
                      <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Romañach</surname>
                      <given-names>SS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Boettiger</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chamberlain</surname>
                      <given-names>SD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Larsen</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>D’Odorico</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Making ecological models adequate</article-title>
                  <source>Ecology Lett</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>21</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>153</fpage>
                  <lpage>166</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ele.12893</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR38">
                <label>38.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Heesterbeek</surname>
                      <given-names>JAP</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A brief history of r 0 and a recipe for its calculation</article-title>
                  <source>Acta Biotheoretica</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>50</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <lpage>204</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1016599411804</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12211331</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR39">
                <label>39.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pollán M, Pérez-Gómez B, Pastor-Barriuso R, Oteo J, Hernán MA, Pérez-Olmeda M, Sanmartín JL, Fernández-García A, Cruz I, de Larrea NF, et al. Prevalence of sars-cov-2 in spain (ene-covid): a nationwide, population-based seroepidemiological study. The Lancet. 2020.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR40">
                <label>40.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Larsen</surname>
                      <given-names>LG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eppinga</surname>
                      <given-names>MB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Passalacqua</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Getz</surname>
                      <given-names>WM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rose</surname>
                      <given-names>KA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liang</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Appropriate complexity landscape modeling</article-title>
                  <source>Earth Sci Rev</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>160</volume>
                  <fpage>111</fpage>
                  <lpage>130</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.earscirev.2016.06.016</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR41">
                <label>41.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nicola M, Alsafi Z, Sohrabi C, Kerwan A, Al-Jabir A, Iosifidis C, Agha M, Agha R. The socio-economic implications of the coronavirus and covid-19 pandemic: a review. International Journal of Surgery. 2020.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR42">
                <label>42.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jones</surname>
                      <given-names>KE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Patel</surname>
                      <given-names>NG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Levy</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Storeygard</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Balk</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gittleman</surname>
                      <given-names>JL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Daszak</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Global trends in emerging infectious diseases</article-title>
                  <source>Nature</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>451</volume>
                  <issue>7181</issue>
                  <fpage>990</fpage>
                  <lpage>993</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature06536</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18288193</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR43">
                <label>43.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Evans TS, Shi Z, Boots M, Liu W, Olival KJ, Xiao X, Vandewoude S, Brown H, Chen J-L, Civitello DJ, et al. Synergistic china-us ecological research is essential for global emerging infectious disease preparedness. EcoHealth. 2020;1–14.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR44">
                <label>44.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Reperant LA, Osterhaus AD Aids, avian flu, sars, mers, ebola, zik... what next? Vaccine 35. 2017;(35), 4470–4474.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR45">
                <label>45.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tian</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>C-H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kraemer</surname>
                      <given-names>MU</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cai</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xu</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>Q</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An investigation of transmission control measures during the first 50 days of the covid-19 epidemic in china</article-title>
                  <source>Science</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>368</volume>
                  <issue>6491</issue>
                  <fpage>638</fpage>
                  <lpage>642</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abb6105</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32234804</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR46">
                <label>46.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>McKinley</surname>
                      <given-names>TJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ross</surname>
                      <given-names>JV</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Deardon</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cook</surname>
                      <given-names>AR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Simulation-based bayesian inference for epidemic models</article-title>
                  <source>Computational Statistics Data Analysis</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>71</volume>
                  <fpage>434</fpage>
                  <lpage>447</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.csda.2012.12.012</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR47">
                <label>47.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dehning J, Zierenberg J, Spitzner FP, Wibral M, Neto JP, Wilczek M, Priesemann V. Inferring change points in the spread of covid-19 reveals the effectiveness of interventions. Science. 2020.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR48">
                <label>48.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kissler</surname>
                      <given-names>SM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tedijanto</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goldstein</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Grad</surname>
                      <given-names>YH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lipsitch</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Projecting the transmission dynamics of sars-cov-2 through the postpandemic period</article-title>
                  <source>Science</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>368</volume>
                  <issue>6493</issue>
                  <fpage>860</fpage>
                  <lpage>868</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abb5793</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32291278</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
