<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-03-11T01:01:58Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7094103" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7094103</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-03-25</datestamp>
        <setSpec>pheelsevier</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Theor Biol</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Theor Biol</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Journal of Theoretical Biology</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0022-5193</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1095-8541</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Elsevier Ltd.</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC7094103</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7094103</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">7094103</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31228488</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pii">S0022-5193(19)30255-3</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtbi.2019.06.020</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>A model for epidemic dynamics in a community with visitor subpopulation</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0001">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Dansu</surname>
                    <given-names>Emmanuel J.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="cor0001" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0002">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Seno</surname>
                    <given-names>Hiromi</given-names>
                  </name>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="aff0001">Research Center for Pure and Applied Mathematics, Graduate School of Information Sciences, Tohoku University, Aramaki-Aza-Aoba 6-3-09, Aoba-ku, Sendai 980-8579, Japan</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor0001"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author.</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>20</day>
                <month>6</month>
                <year>2019</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.-->
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <day>7</day>
                <month>10</month>
                <year>2019</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>20</day>
                <month>6</month>
                <year>2019</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>478</volume>
              <fpage>115</fpage>
              <lpage>127</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>5</day>
                  <month>2</month>
                  <year>2019</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>16</day>
                  <month>6</month>
                  <year>2019</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>19</day>
                  <month>6</month>
                  <year>2019</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2019 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2019</copyright-year>
                <copyright-holder>Elsevier Ltd</copyright-holder>
                <license>
                  <license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="absh001">
                <title>Highlights</title>
                <p>
                  <list list-type="simple" id="lst0003">
                    <list-item id="lstitem0001">
                      <label>•</label>
                      <p id="p0001">With a model consisting of SIR and SIS models, we affirm claims in previous works.</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item id="lstitem0002">
                      <label>•</label>
                      <p id="p0002">We derive different basic reproduction numbers looking at varying perspectives.</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item id="lstitem0003">
                      <label>•</label>
                      <p id="p0003">We discuss the biological meanings of these basic reproduction numbers.</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item id="lstitem0004">
                      <label>•</label>
                      <p id="p0004">All the basic reproduction numbers coincide with respect to the critical condition.</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item id="lstitem0005">
                      <label>•</label>
                      <p id="p0005">Relevant public health policies are proposed based on our findings.</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                </p>
              </abstract>
              <abstract id="abs0001">
                <p>With a five dimensional system of ordinary differential equations based on the SIR and SIS models, we consider the dynamics of epidemics in a community which consists of residents and short-stay visitors. Taking different viewpoints to consider public health policies to control the disease, we derive different basic reproduction numbers and clarify their common/different mathematical natures so as to understand their meanings in the dynamics of the epidemic. From our analyses, the short-stay visitor subpopulation could become significant in determining the fate of diseases in the community. Furthermore, our arguments demonstrate that it is necessary to choose one variant of basic reproduction number in order to formulate appropriate public health policies.</p>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group id="keys0001">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>Epidemic dynamics</kwd>
                <kwd>Mathematical model</kwd>
                <kwd>Ordinary differential equations</kwd>
                <kwd>Basic reproduction number</kwd>
                <kwd>Public health</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="sec0001">
              <label>1</label>
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p id="p0006">As the world becomes more of a global village with advances in technology and easier accessibility to different places, it is very crucial to consider side effects like the spread of diseases. The history of man is replete with stories of epidemics invading groups of people, sometimes resulting in mortality. In the long run, such diseases can disappear and recur in the future or become less deadly due to people getting immune. Some notable epidemics in history include the “Spanish” flu (1918–1919) as well as the Black Deaths (1346–1350) which invaded Europe from Asia and recurred for three decades afterwards before getting eliminated (<xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">Brauer, 2017</xref>).</p>
              <p id="p0007">It is a well established fact that ‘globetrotters’ contribute significantly to the global movement of microbes as they serve as a crucial sentinel population. The displacement of people due to social and political unrest as well as the natural migration of disease vectors to new areas also contribute to the worldwide spread of diseases (<xref rid="bib0042" ref-type="bibr">Wilson, 2010</xref>, <xref rid="bib0041" ref-type="bibr">WHO, 2018</xref>).</p>
              <p id="p0008">Infectious diseases do not respect border restrictions as their spread is magnified by rapid urbanization, globalization of trade and travels as well as unpredictable climate change and complexities in societal behavior (<xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">MacIntyre et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bib0038" ref-type="bibr">Walters et al., 2018</xref>). All of these factors have practically removed the barriers which prevent epidemic transmission among humans and between humans and animals (<xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">Farrar et al., 2016</xref>).</p>
              <p id="p0009">In the work presented by <xref rid="bib0027" ref-type="bibr">Parikh et al. (2013)</xref>, a synthetic population model of the Washington DC metro area was extended to include leisure and business travelers classified as transients. The final size of the epidemic among residents was found to be remarkably higher when transients were included in the simulation of a flu-like disease outbreak. According to <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">Chowell et al. (2016)</xref>, it is crucial to formulate reliable models that embody the basic transmission characteristics of specific pathogens and social scenarios. They further stated that improved models are required to capture the variation in early growth dynamics of real epidemics in order to gain better understanding of the dynamics as they reviewed trends in modeling and classifying early epidemic progression.</p>
              <p id="p0010">In considering the emerging diseases of wildlife, <xref rid="bib0034" ref-type="bibr">Tompkins et al. (2015)</xref> show that the key drivers of such diseases are agents from domestic sources and human-assisted exposure to infectious agents from wild populations. Talking about swine fever otherwise known as hog cholera, wild boar populations are known to serve as reservoir for the disease thereby constituting a great challenge for domestic pig farmers, veterinarians and other stakeholders (<xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">Mur, Sánchez-Vizcaíno, Fernández-Carrión, Jurado, Rolesu, Feliziani, Laddomada, Martínez-López, 2018</xref>, <xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">Postel, Austermann-Busch, Petrov, Moennig, Becher, 2018</xref>). It then becomes a daunting public health challenge to prevent contacts between wild boar and local pig populations.</p>
              <p id="p0011">Epidemiologists are always concerned about the outbreak of diseases and increasing global travels can easily increase their worries. For instance, as of March 2015, Japan was confirmed to be totally free of measles. However, that status changed when a new wave of measles infections was reportedly started by a tourist in Okinawa Prefecture in March 2018 (<xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Mizumoto, Kobayashi, Chowell, 2018</xref>, <xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Diseases, 2018</xref>). The threat of measles is a serious one because it has about the highest basic reproduction number <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0</sub> among the most commonly known infectious diseases (<xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">van den Driessche, 2017</xref>). It has been established that <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0</sub> is a very vital threshold parameter that theoretically determines whether a disease is eliminated or becomes endemic after it is introduced into a given population. In fact, it is widely believed to be one of the most important contributions of mathematics to the field of epidemiology (<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Diekmann, Heesterbeek, Roberts, 2010</xref>, <xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">Heffernan, Smith, Wahl, 2005</xref>, <xref rid="bib0036" ref-type="bibr">van den Driessche, Watmough, 2002</xref>). <xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">Heffernan et al. (2005)</xref> gave a concise summary of prevalent approaches for formulating <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0</sub> from deterministic models as well as relevant data. They also looked closely at the use of <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0</sub> in evaluating diseases like severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) and avian influenza as well as some livestock and vector-borne diseases. <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">van den Driessche (2017)</xref> applied the theoretical concepts of <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0</sub> to various disease models, namely the West Nile virus in birds, anthrax in animals, cholera and Zika in humans.</p>
              <p id="p0012">Basically, <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0</sub> is concerned with the initial trend of infective populations in ideal situations where very small number of infective individuals appear and are always surrounded by susceptible individuals. Before such infectives lose their infectivity, the density of susceptibles is assumed to be unchanged. In such a biological context, the basic reproduction number is defined as the expected number of new cases of an infection caused by an infected individual, in a population consisting of susceptible contacts only.</p>
              <p id="p0013">Following this biological definition, a mathematical theory is used to derive the basic reproduction number as the spectral radius of a specific matrix which is called the ”next generation matrix” (NGM) for a system of ordinary differential equations governing epidemic dynamics (see <xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">Cushing, Diekmann, 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Diekmann, Heesterbeek, Britton, 2013</xref> for a complete reference, or see <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">van den Driessche, 2017</xref> for a recent review). In the frequently referred paper by <xref rid="bib0036" ref-type="bibr">van den Driessche and Watmough (2002)</xref>, very helpful results were obtained for disease control having investigated the actual definition of <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0</sub> based on a compartmental system of ordinary differential equations. <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Diekmann et al. (2010)</xref> highlighted the NGM as the foundation for the mathematical definition of <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0</sub>. As such, their work attempted to demystify issues surrounding the formulation of NGMs since <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0</sub>s are basically defined as the spectral radii of such matrices. We should recognize that, as described above, the basic reproduction number is defined both biologically/conceptually and mathematically as the <italic>supremum</italic> for the expected number of secondary cases in epidemic dynamics, whereas it is clear that the index <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0</sub> could be important and useful to characterize the threat of infectious diseases.</p>
              <p id="p0014">In this paper, we emphasize the role of <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0</sub> from some specific viewpoints in theoretical discussions. We examine <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0</sub> focused on (i) transmission of disease within and to the resident population and (ii) transmission of disease within and to the short-stay visitor population. Such residents and visitors may be considered to be either humans or animals as a variety of situations can be considered. The <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0</sub> focused on residents can be considered as the most standard case as it may be a bit difficult to really estimate the impact of short-stay visitors in the spread of diseases. The <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0</sub> focused on short-stay visitors is very important when the residents are considered as some vectors in the community which can easily spread diseases to visitors. That way, we can make inferences by combining different <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0</sub>s. Besides we shall demonstrate that <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0</sub> only deals with the initial behavior of infections because the overall behavior is governed by the model under consideration.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0002">
              <label>2</label>
              <title>Assumptions, modeling, and model</title>
              <p id="p0015">We consider a community consisting of residents and short-stay visitors. Our focus is on the dynamics of epidemics over a short period of time such that the total population size of the community is taken to be constant, ignoring any change due to birth and death within the period of interest. Also, the resident and visitor populations are respectively constant. We assume that all immigrating visitors are susceptible and likely to be infected during their stay in the community. In addition, infected visitors can carry on their normal activities during their stay thus still appearing susceptible until they leave the community.</p>
              <p id="p0016">Following the stated assumptions, we consider the following model governing the epidemic dynamics:<disp-formula id="eq0001"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si48.svg"><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>where the variables <italic>x<sub>r</sub>, y<sub>r</sub>, z<sub>r</sub>, x<sub>v</sub></italic>, and <italic>y<sub>v</sub></italic> are the <italic>susceptible resident</italic>, the <italic>infective resident</italic>, the <italic>recovered resident</italic>, the <italic>susceptible visitor</italic>, and the <italic>infective visitor</italic> population sizes respectively in the community at time <italic>t</italic>. The infection coefficients <italic>β<sub>rr</sub>, β<sub>vr</sub>, β<sub>rv</sub></italic> and <italic>β<sub>vv</sub></italic> are positive constants. They represent transmissions from infective to susceptible individuals, respectively <italic>from resident to resident, from resident to visitor, from visitor to resident</italic>, and <italic>from visitor to visitor</italic>as shown in <xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>
.<fig id="fig0001"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>The scheme of the model for the epidemic dynamics of a community with short-stay visitor subpopulation.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0001">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig></p>
              <p id="p0017">Based on the simplest modeling assumption, the interactions among individuals within the community follow the concept of complete (perfect) mixing. Therefore, the disease transmission is given by mass-action terms like in the case of the classical Kermack–Mckendrick epidemic dynamics model (for example, see <xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Diekmann, Heesterbeek, Britton, 2013</xref>, <xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">Keeling, Rohani, 2008</xref>, <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">Martcheva, 2015</xref>). <italic>ρ</italic> is the recovery rate of the <italic>resident</italic> population. <italic>M</italic> is the flux (velocity) of visitor immigration, while <italic>E</italic> is the flux of visitor emigration.</p>
              <p id="p0018">To complete the model, we take the above-mentioned assumptions into account such that<disp-formula id="ueq0001"><mml:math id="M2" altimg="si49.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where the total <italic>resident</italic> population size <italic>N<sub>r</sub></italic> and the total <italic>visitor</italic> population size <italic>N<sub>v</sub></italic> are constant independent of time. Hence, from the equations for the <italic>x<sub>v</sub>, y<sub>v</sub></italic> compartments of the model, we get<disp-formula id="ueq0002"><mml:math id="M3" altimg="si50.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>With these relations from the assumptions of constant subpopulation sizes, we can get the following closed three-dimensional system in terms of (<italic>x<sub>r</sub>, y<sub>r</sub>, y<sub>v</sub></italic>):<disp-formula id="eq0002"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M4" altimg="si51.svg"><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0003">
              <label>3</label>
              <title>The dynamics without cross infection</title>
              <sec id="sec0004">
                <label>3.1</label>
                <title>The resident subpopulation</title>
                <p id="p0019">If there is no cross infection such that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M5" altimg="si52.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M6" altimg="si53.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in the system <xref rid="eq0001" ref-type="disp-formula">(1)</xref>, the epidemic dynamics with respect to the resident subpopulation follows the classical Kermack–Mckendrick SIR model (see <xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Diekmann, Heesterbeek, Britton, 2013</xref>, <xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">Keeling, Rohani, 2008</xref>, <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">Martcheva, 2015</xref> or any other textbooks of mathematical biology/epidemiology). Going by the well-known nature of the SIR model, we see that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M7" altimg="si54.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> with some <inline-formula><mml:math id="M8" altimg="si55.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> as <italic>t</italic> → ∞ for the initial condition given by <inline-formula><mml:math id="M9" altimg="si56.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> with <italic>y</italic>
<sub><italic>r</italic>0</sub> &gt; 0. The final size of the epidemic, that is, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M10" altimg="si57.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> ( &gt; 0) is implicitly determined by<disp-formula id="eq0003"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M11" altimg="si58.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mi>ln</mml:mi><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
                <p id="p0020">The basic reproduction number can be defined by<disp-formula id="eq0004"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="M12" altimg="si59.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>which is expressed by the product of the expected duration of infectivity of each infective resident 1/<italic>ρ</italic>, the resident-resident transmission coefficient <italic>β<sub>rr</sub></italic>, and the resident subpopulation size <italic>N<sub>r</sub></italic>. When <inline-formula><mml:math id="M13" altimg="si60.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the infective population size <italic>y<sub>r</sub></italic> decreases monotonically towards 0. When <inline-formula><mml:math id="M14" altimg="si61.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the temporal variation of <italic>y<sub>r</sub></italic> shows a peak signifying an outbreak after a period of increase from a sufficiently small initial value <inline-formula><mml:math id="M15" altimg="si62.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0005">
                <label>3.2</label>
                <title>The visitor subpopulation</title>
                <p id="p0021">The visitor population without cross infection mathematically corresponds with the classical Kermack–Mckendrick SIS model. Now, let us consider such an initial condition that 0 &lt; <italic>y<sub>v</sub></italic>(0) ≪ 1 and <italic>x<sub>v</sub></italic>(0) ≈ <italic>N<sub>v</sub></italic>. Then, for <italic>dy<sub>v</sub></italic>/<italic>dt</italic> in <xref rid="eq0002" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref>,<disp-formula id="ueq0003"><mml:math id="M16" altimg="si63.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>Thus, when the right hand side is positive, that is, if <inline-formula><mml:math id="M17" altimg="si64.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the infective population size <italic>y<sub>v</sub></italic> increases in an initial period. So we can obtain the basic reproduction number<disp-formula id="eq0005"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="M18" altimg="si65.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>which appears as the product of the expected duration of each visitor’s stay in the community <italic>N<sub>v</sub></italic>/<italic>M</italic>, the visitor-visitor transmission coefficient <italic>β<sub>vv</sub></italic>, and the visitor subpopulation size <italic>N<sub>v</sub></italic>. If <inline-formula><mml:math id="M19" altimg="si66.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the infective population size decreases in an initial period. Furthermore, from <xref rid="eq0002" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref>, we can get<disp-formula id="eq0006"><label>(6)</label><mml:math id="M20" altimg="si67.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">{</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>such that if <inline-formula><mml:math id="M21" altimg="si68.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<italic>dy<sub>v</sub></italic>/<italic>dt</italic> &lt; 0 for any <italic>t</italic> &gt; 0. So, <italic>y<sub>v</sub></italic> is monotonically decreasing if <inline-formula><mml:math id="M22" altimg="si69.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> such that <italic>y<sub>v</sub></italic> → 0 as <italic>t</italic> → ∞. Otherwise, if <inline-formula><mml:math id="M23" altimg="si70.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M24" altimg="si71.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> as <italic>t</italic> → ∞.</p>
                <p id="p0022">When <inline-formula><mml:math id="M25" altimg="si68.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the disease is eventually eliminated from the visitor population due to the outflow of infective visitors which outweighs the inflow of susceptible visitors. In contrast, when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M26" altimg="si70.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the disease becomes endemic, that is, the disease remains at any given time after its invasion in the population. In other words, the recruitment of infective visitors from the inflow of susceptible visitors compensates for the outflow of infective visitors.</p>
                <p id="p0023">Since the disease is endemic in the visitor subpopulation when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M27" altimg="si70.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> it eventually disperses throughout the resident subpopulation when there is cross infection from visitors to residents, that is, when <italic>β<sub>rv</sub></italic> &gt; 0. Even if <inline-formula><mml:math id="M28" altimg="si60.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> cross infections with <italic>β<sub>vr</sub></italic> &gt; 0 and <italic>β<sub>rv</sub></italic> &gt; 0 cause disease outbreak within the resident subpopulation when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M29" altimg="si72.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. In other words, when there are cross infections, disease outbreak necessarily occurs within the resident subpopulation as far as <inline-formula><mml:math id="M30" altimg="si72.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Consequently, if <inline-formula><mml:math id="M31" altimg="si73.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> or <inline-formula><mml:math id="M32" altimg="si70.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> disease outbreak occurs in the resident subpopulation in the presence of cross infections, that is, when <italic>β<sub>vr</sub></italic> &gt; 0 and <italic>β<sub>rv</sub></italic> &gt; 0. Hereafter, with the effect of cross infection, we shall focus on the case when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M33" altimg="si74.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M34" altimg="si75.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0006">
              <label>4</label>
              <title>Equilibrium states</title>
              <p id="p0024">There is no oscillatory solution for the system <xref rid="eq0002" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref>. It is easily seen that <italic>y<sub>r</sub></italic> and <italic>y<sub>v</sub></italic> are positive and finite at any finite time <italic>t</italic> for any <italic>y<sub>r</sub></italic>(0) &gt; 0 and <italic>y<sub>v</sub></italic>(0) &gt; 0. Since <italic>dx<sub>r</sub></italic>/<italic>dt</italic> &lt; 0 for any positive <italic>x<sub>r</sub>, y<sub>r</sub></italic>, and <italic>y<sub>v</sub>, x<sub>r</sub></italic> is monotonically decreasing in time though it cannot become negative because it is bounded below by zero. Thus <italic>x<sub>r</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>) &gt; 0 for any <italic>t</italic> &gt; 0 and any <italic>x<sub>r</sub></italic>(0) &gt; 0. If <italic>y<sub>r</sub></italic>(0) &gt; 0 and <italic>y<sub>v</sub></italic>(0) &gt; 0, indeed we have<disp-formula id="ueq0004"><mml:math id="M35" altimg="si76.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>and<disp-formula id="ueq0005"><mml:math id="M36" altimg="si77.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>exp</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∫</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>So, <italic>x<sub>r</sub></italic> must always converge to a non-negative value. Hence, it can be easily proven that both of <italic>y<sub>r</sub></italic> and <italic>y<sub>v</sub></italic> also converge to non-negative values. Therefore, (<italic>x<sub>r</sub>, y<sub>r</sub>, y<sub>v</sub></italic>) always attains some kind of equilibrium state, which excludes the possibility of oscillatory solutions.</p>
              <p id="p0025">From the equations in <xref rid="eq0002" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref>, we can obtain the following result:<statement id="enun0001"><label>Lemma 4.1</label><p id="p0026"><italic>For the system</italic><xref rid="eq0002" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref><italic>, there are possible equilibria</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="M37" altimg="si78.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>for</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="M38" altimg="si79.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>and</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="M39" altimg="si80.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>. The latter equilibrium exists when and only when</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="M40" altimg="si81.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>.</italic></p></statement>
</p>
              <p id="p0027">Next, by the arguments given in <xref rid="sec0015" ref-type="sec">Appendix A</xref>, we can get the following result about feasible equilibrium values for <xref rid="eq0002" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref>:<statement id="enun0002"><label>Theorem 4.2</label><p id="p0028"><italic>For the system</italic><xref rid="eq0002" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref><italic>,</italic><list list-type="simple" id="lst0001"><list-item id="lstitem0006"><label>1.</label><p id="p0029"><italic>y<sub>r</sub></italic> → 0 <italic>as t</italic> → ∞<italic>;</italic>
</p></list-item><list-item id="lstitem0007"><label>2.</label><p id="p0030"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M41" altimg="si82.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>with</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="M42" altimg="si79.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>as t</italic> → ∞ <italic>if</italic>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M43" altimg="si69.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<italic>;</italic>
</p></list-item><list-item id="lstitem0008"><label>3.</label><p id="p0031"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M44" altimg="si83.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>as t</italic> → ∞ <italic>if</italic>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M45" altimg="si81.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<italic>when β<sub>rv</sub></italic> &gt; 0<italic>.</italic>
</p></list-item></list></p></statement>
</p>
              <p id="p0032">As shown in <xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>
(b), if <inline-formula><mml:math id="M46" altimg="si70.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> all residents would have experienced the infection in the end while there is always a portion of infective visitors, this gives rise to an endemic situation. On the other hand, as we see in <xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>(a), if <inline-formula><mml:math id="M47" altimg="si66.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> there is a portion of susceptible residents who would not have experienced the infection in the end. Also, the visitor population would have no infected individuals in the end. Here, the disease disappears from the community in the long run. It should be noted that the value of the basic reproduction number <inline-formula><mml:math id="M48" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> clearly determines the epidemic size for the resident subpopulation.<fig id="fig0002"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Numerical examples of temporal variation of system <xref rid="eq0002" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref>. (a) <inline-formula><mml:math id="M49" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.75</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.50</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.05</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>32.73</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>; (b) <inline-formula><mml:math id="M50" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.75</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.50</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.08</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>56.69</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Commonly, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M51" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>100000.00</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>100.00</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.14</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>20.00</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M52" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>99990.0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>10.0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M53" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M54" altimg="si6.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0002">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2_lrg"/></fig></p>
              <p id="p0033">For the system <xref rid="eq0002" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref> with cross infections, we could not obtain any equation(s) like <xref rid="eq0003" ref-type="disp-formula">(3)</xref> to determine the final size of the epidemic. However, we can get the following analytical estimation going by the proof shown in <xref rid="sec0016" ref-type="sec">Appendix B</xref>:<statement id="enun0003"><label>Theorem 4.3</label><p id="p0034"><italic>As for the state</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="M55" altimg="si78.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>feasible for the system</italic><xref rid="eq0002" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref><italic>when</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="M56" altimg="si68.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>the value</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="M57" altimg="si7.svg"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>necessarily satisfies</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="M58" altimg="si84.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">upper</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>defined by</italic><disp-formula id="eq0007"><label>(7)</label><mml:math id="M59" altimg="si85.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">upper</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><italic>The value x<sub>r</sub> cannot approach any value beyond</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="M60" altimg="si86.svg"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">upper</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>from any initial state with y<sub>r</sub></italic>(0) &gt; 0 <italic>or y<sub>v</sub></italic>(0) &gt; 0<italic>.</italic>
</p></statement>
</p>
              <p id="p0035">This result can be confirmed by the numerical calculations shown in <xref rid="fig0003" ref-type="fig">Figs. 3</xref>
and <xref rid="fig0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>
.<fig id="fig0003"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>The dependence of the final size of susceptible resident population <inline-formula><mml:math id="M61" altimg="si7.svg"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula> on the initial size of infective resident population <italic>y<sub>r</sub></italic>(0) and on <italic>β<sub>rr</sub></italic>. (a) <inline-formula><mml:math id="M62" altimg="si8.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.0</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M63" altimg="si9.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>10.0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M64" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>; (b) <inline-formula><mml:math id="M65" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>99990.0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>10.0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The horizontal axis in (b) shows the value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M66" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> which is a function of <italic>β<sub>rr</sub></italic> as given by <xref rid="eq0004" ref-type="disp-formula">(4)</xref>. Commonly, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M67" altimg="si12.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>100000.0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M68" altimg="si13.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>100.0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M69" altimg="si14.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M70" altimg="si15.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M71" altimg="si16.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.6</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M72" altimg="si17.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.0</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M73" altimg="si18.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>4.0</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M74" altimg="si19.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.8</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M75" altimg="si20.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.08</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M76" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>200.0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0003">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig0004"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>The dependence of the final size of susceptible resident population <inline-formula><mml:math id="M77" altimg="si7.svg"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula> on <italic>β<sub>vv</sub></italic> and on <italic>M</italic>. (a) <inline-formula><mml:math id="M78" altimg="si8.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.0</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M79" altimg="si22.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>10.0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>; (b) <inline-formula><mml:math id="M80" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>3.0</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M81" altimg="si24.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.50</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>; (c) <inline-formula><mml:math id="M82" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.5</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M83" altimg="si26.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.75</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The horizontal axes show the values of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M84" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> which is a function of <italic>β<sub>vv</sub></italic> for the upper figures with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M85" altimg="si28.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and that of <italic>M</italic> for the lower ones with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M86" altimg="si29.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>4.0</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> as given by <xref rid="eq0005" ref-type="disp-formula">(5)</xref>. Commonly, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M87" altimg="si12.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>100000.0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M88" altimg="si13.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>100.0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M89" altimg="si14.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M90" altimg="si16.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.6</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M91" altimg="si17.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.0</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M92" altimg="si20.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.08</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M93" altimg="si30.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>200.0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M94" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>99990.0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>10.0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0004">Fig. 4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4_lrg"/></fig></p>
              <p id="p0036">Although the critical value <inline-formula><mml:math id="M95" altimg="si86.svg"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">upper</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula> given in <xref rid="enun0003" ref-type="statement">Theorem 4.3</xref> is independent of the initial condition of the system <xref rid="eq0002" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref>, the numerical result given in <xref rid="fig0003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>(a) explicitly indicates that the final size <inline-formula><mml:math id="M96" altimg="si7.svg"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula> itself depends on the initial condition. This is similar to a characteristic of the standard Kermack–McKendrick SIR model. Also, the numerical results given in <xref rid="fig0004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> indicates that the final size <inline-formula><mml:math id="M97" altimg="si7.svg"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula> is significantly affected by interactions with the visitor subpopulation as mathematically implied by <xref rid="enun0002" ref-type="statement">Theorem 4.2</xref>.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0007">
              <label>5</label>
              <title>The basic reproduction numbers</title>
              <p id="p0037">We discuss in this section how the different basic reproduction numbers can be mathematically derived for the model <xref rid="eq0002" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref>. Subsequently, going by their meanings from the perspective of modeling, we examine how they are different and what nature they have in common (for such possibly different formulas for basic reproduction number, see the arguments in <xref rid="bib0004" ref-type="bibr">Brauer, Castillo-Chavez, Mubayi, Towers, 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">Cushing, Diekmann, 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">van den Driessche, 2017</xref>).</p>
              <sec id="sec0008">
                <label>5.1</label>
                <title>The basic reproduction numbers in terms of each subpopulation</title>
                <p id="p0038">At first, let us consider a public health policy geared towards controlling the disease among residents. Then, it is necessary to evaluate the basic reproduction number which is defined as the index about the possibility of the disease spread within the resident population. As shown in <xref rid="sec0017" ref-type="sec">Appendix C</xref>, making use of the NGM with the theory given by <xref rid="bib0036" ref-type="bibr">van den Driessche and Watmough (2002)</xref>, <xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">van den Driessche et al. (2008)</xref>, we can derive the following basic reproduction number for the model <xref rid="eq0002" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref> when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M98" altimg="si75.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>:<disp-formula id="eq0008"><label>(8)</label><mml:math id="M99" altimg="si87.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi mathvariant="script">B</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>with<disp-formula id="ueq0006"><mml:math id="M100" altimg="si88.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">B</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M101" altimg="si89.svg"><mml:mi mathvariant="script">B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> expresses the ratio of the infectivity between residents and visitors (<italic>inter-subpopulation infection</italic>) to the infectivity within subpopulations (<italic>intra-subpopulation infection</italic>). Larger <inline-formula><mml:math id="M102" altimg="si89.svg"><mml:mi mathvariant="script">B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> means that infections between subpopulations are more significant than those within them. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M103" altimg="si90.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> can be regarded as the expected number of infective residents that a single infective visitor can produce, assuming that every contact to the resident is always to the susceptible. It appears as the product of the expected duration of each visitor’s stay in the community <italic>N<sub>v</sub></italic>/<italic>M</italic>, the visitor-resident transmission coefficient <italic>β<sub>rv</sub></italic>, and the resident subpopulation size <italic>N<sub>r</sub></italic>. Conversely, the expected number of infective visitors that a single infective resident can produce, assuming every contact to the visitor is always to the susceptible, is <inline-formula><mml:math id="M104" altimg="si91.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> which is expressed by the product of the expected duration of the infectivity of each infective resident 1/<italic>ρ</italic>, the resident-visitor transmission coefficient <italic>β<sub>vr</sub></italic>, and the visitor subpopulation size <italic>N<sub>v</sub></italic>.</p>
                <p id="p0039">The basic reproduction number <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub> can be translated based on its conceptual definition as similarly argued in (<xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">Cushing and Diekmann, 2016</xref>): The formula <xref rid="eq0008" ref-type="disp-formula">(8)</xref> can be rewritten as<disp-formula id="ueq0007"><mml:math id="M105" altimg="si92.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>∞</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mtext>for</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="4.pt"/><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>As illustrated in <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>
, the first term <inline-formula><mml:math id="M106" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> means the expected number of secondary infective residents produced by the initial single infective resident, which may be regarded as the secondary cases arising from <italic>direct</italic> infection. In contrast, the second term adds the expected number of secondary infective residents produced by the infective visitors who can be regarded to have the source of their infection traced back only along the line of infective visitors to the initial single infective resident. From the biological definitions of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M107" altimg="si93.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M108" altimg="si94.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M109" altimg="si95.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the initial single infective resident is expected to produce <inline-formula><mml:math id="M110" altimg="si91.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> infective visitors, and subsequently each of these infective visitors is expected to produce <inline-formula><mml:math id="M111" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> infective visitors. Looking at the furtherance of the infection process only within the visitor subpopulation caused by the initial single infective resident, the simple addition of those new infective visitors produced by the cascade of infections results in <inline-formula><mml:math id="M112" altimg="si96.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mo>⋯</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Then since <inline-formula><mml:math id="M113" altimg="si90.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is the expected number of infective residents produced by a single infective visitor, we see that the product of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M114" altimg="si90.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and this sum can be consequently regarded as the expected number of secondary infective residents produced by the infective visitors who can have the root of their infection traced back to the initial single infective resident.<fig id="fig0005"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Decomposition of the basic reproduction numbers <italic>R</italic><sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub> and <italic>R</italic><sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub> defined by <xref rid="eq0008" ref-type="disp-formula">(8)</xref> and <xref rid="eq0009" ref-type="disp-formula">(9)</xref>.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0005">Fig. 5</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr5_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="p0040">We remark that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M115" altimg="si97.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mi>∞</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> as <inline-formula><mml:math id="M116" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> increases towards 1. This could be regarded as reasonable because we have clarified in the previous sections that the whole resident subpopulation is necessarily infected if <inline-formula><mml:math id="M117" altimg="si72.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Indeed, applying this translation about the meaning of the formula <xref rid="eq0008" ref-type="disp-formula">(8)</xref> for the case when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M118" altimg="si98.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the basic reproduction number would be divergent due to the divergence of the sum <inline-formula><mml:math id="M119" altimg="si96.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mo>⋯</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. It should be remarked that such divergence of the basic reproduction number does not mean that the actual basic reproduction number would be divergent. It simply means that the <italic>supremum</italic> for the expected number of secondary cases in the epidemic dynamics does not exist, so that the situation could be regarded as highly threatening as the disease spreads in the resident subpopulation. This is the same for the situation with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M120" altimg="si72.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> as mentioned above.</p>
                <p id="p0041">In contrast, when we consider a public health policy for controlling the disease among visitors, it is necessary to evaluate the basic reproduction number <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub> which is defined as the index about the possibility of the disease spread in the visitor population. The process for deriving <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub> is similar to that of <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub> (<xref rid="sec0017" ref-type="sec">Appendix C</xref>):<disp-formula id="eq0009"><label>(9)</label><mml:math id="M121" altimg="si99.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi mathvariant="script">B</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="newline">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>∞</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mtext>for</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="4.pt"/><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
                <p id="p0042">A similar translation is applicable for <xref rid="eq0009" ref-type="disp-formula">(9)</xref> like the one for <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub> (see <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>). We remark again that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M122" altimg="si100.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mi>∞</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> as <inline-formula><mml:math id="M123" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> increases towards 1, which can be interpreted as a consequence due to the divergence of the sum <inline-formula><mml:math id="M124" altimg="si101.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mo>⋯</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for <italic>R<sub>rr</sub></italic> ≥ 1. This scenario is different from the previous one because the infective residents eventually disappear in the end for <italic>R<sub>rr</sub></italic> &gt; 1 after every resident is infected and recovers. However, we need to recall that the basic reproduction number is defined as the expected number of secondary cases in the conceptually supremum case for the subsequent infections. Thus, this result can be understood as the case when the basic reproduction number of the resident subpopulation corresponding to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M125" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is kept beyond 1. As such, the visitor subpopulation is regarded as always being exposed to infective residents by cross infection (which corresponds to the divergence of the above-mentioned sum). This situation could indicate that the threat of disease spread in the visitor subpopulation is enormous.</p>
                <p id="p0043">Note that the basic reproduction numbers <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub> and <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub> may be specifically called ‘type reproduction numbers’ as in the terminology of (<xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">Heesterbeek, Roberts, 2007</xref>, <xref rid="bib0029" ref-type="bibr">Roberts, Heesterbeek, 2003</xref>) because we are interested only in the total number of expected secondary infections in each subpopulation originating from an infective individual within the same subpopulation (also see <xref rid="bib0019" ref-type="bibr">Lewis, Shuai, van den Driessche, 2019</xref>, <xref rid="bib0032" ref-type="bibr">Smith, McKenzie, Snow, Hay, 2007</xref>, <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">van den Driessche, 2017</xref>, <xref rid="bib0043" ref-type="bibr">Yakob, Clements, 2013</xref>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0009">
                <label>5.2</label>
                <title>Comparison of the basic reproduction numbers</title>
                <p id="p0044">The basic reproduction numbers <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub> and <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub> are basically different but have a common critical nature shown in the following theorem:<statement id="enun0004"><label>Theorem 5.1</label><p id="p0045"><italic>The condition R</italic><sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub> &lt; 1 <italic>holds if and only if R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub> &lt; 1<italic>.</italic>
</p></statement>
</p>
                <p id="p0046">Therefore the condition <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub> &gt; 1 holds if and only if <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub> &gt; 1. This theorem can be easily proven by the definitions of <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub> and <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub> given by <xref rid="eq0008" ref-type="disp-formula">(8)</xref> and <xref rid="eq0009" ref-type="disp-formula">(9)</xref>. As a special case, we can consider the critical condition <inline-formula><mml:math id="M126" altimg="si102.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M127" altimg="si103.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> which lead to the following corollary:<statement id="enun0005"><label>Corollary 5.1.1</label><p id="p0047"><italic>There is a set of values</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="M128" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>and</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="M129" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>each less than 1, say</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="M130" altimg="si104.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>such that</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="M131" altimg="si102.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>and</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="M132" altimg="si105.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>. The set is defined by</italic><disp-formula id="ueq0008"><mml:math id="M133" altimg="si106.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">B</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.33em"/><mml:mspace width="4.pt"/><mml:mtext>for</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="4.pt"/><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="4.pt"/><mml:mtext>and</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="4.pt"/><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p></statement>
</p>
                <p id="p0048">The dependence of <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub> and <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub> on <inline-formula><mml:math id="M134" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M135" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is shown in <xref rid="fig0006" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>
. It is quite clear from the figure that even if <inline-formula><mml:math id="M136" altimg="si74.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M137" altimg="si66.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> as far as there is cross infection, the basic reproduction number for each subpopulation can become greater than unity simultaneously. Furthermore, <xref rid="fig0006" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> explicitly shows that as the effect of cross infection becomes stronger (i.e., for larger <inline-formula><mml:math id="M138" altimg="si89.svg"><mml:mi mathvariant="script">B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>), the basic reproduction numbers are more likely to become greater than unity.<fig id="fig0006"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Classification of the region <inline-formula><mml:math id="M139" altimg="si31.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in terms of the values of <italic>R</italic><sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub> and <italic>R</italic><sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub>. (a) <inline-formula><mml:math id="M140" altimg="si32.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">B</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>; (b) <inline-formula><mml:math id="M141" altimg="si33.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">B</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>; (c) <inline-formula><mml:math id="M142" altimg="si34.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">B</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The boundary corresponds to the set of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M143" altimg="si35.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> defined in <xref rid="enun0005" ref-type="statement">Corollary 5.1.1</xref> with <xref rid="enun0004" ref-type="statement">Theorem 5.1</xref>.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0006">Fig. 6</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr6_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="p0049">Now, as derived in <xref rid="sec0017" ref-type="sec">Appendix C</xref>, we can consider an additional basic reproduction number given by<disp-formula id="eq0010"><label>(10)</label><mml:math id="M144" altimg="si107.svg"><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>Although this basic reproduction number <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>c</italic></sub> may be the one formally derived by the NGM for the system <xref rid="eq0002" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref>, the formula <xref rid="eq0010" ref-type="disp-formula">(10)</xref> could not be translated by the conceptual definition of basic reproduction number as we did for <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub> and <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub>. Hence, in this paper we use <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>c</italic></sub> only as a reference index for the other basic reproduction numbers.</p>
                <p id="p0050">As numerically shown in <xref rid="fig0007" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>
, although the three basic reproduction numbers <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub>, <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub>, and <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>c</italic></sub> have different values from each other, the critical condition is identical.<statement id="enun0006"><label>Theorem 5.2</label><p id="p0051"><italic>The condition R</italic><sub>0∣<italic>c</italic></sub> &lt; 1 <italic>holds if and only if R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub> &lt; 1 <italic>(i.e., R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub> &lt; 1<italic>) when</italic>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M145" altimg="si74.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<italic>and</italic>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M146" altimg="si75.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<italic>.</italic>
</p></statement>
<fig id="fig0007"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Differences in the values of <italic>R</italic><sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub>, <italic>R</italic><sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub> and <italic>R</italic><sub>0∣<italic>c</italic></sub> given by <xref rid="eq0008" ref-type="disp-formula">(8)</xref>, <xref rid="eq0009" ref-type="disp-formula">(9)</xref> and <xref rid="eq0010" ref-type="disp-formula">(10)</xref> with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M147" altimg="si36.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">B</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. (a) <inline-formula><mml:math id="M148" altimg="si37.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>; (b) <inline-formula><mml:math id="M149" altimg="si38.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The three curves intersect when they take the value of unity.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0007">Fig. 7</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr7_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="p0052">As mentioned in (<xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">Cushing and Diekmann, 2016</xref>) and other literature, independent of the formula of the basic reproduction number, the critical condition that it is equal to unity is mathematically identical as long as it is well-defined.<statement id="enun0007"><label>Corollary 5.2.1</label><p id="p0053"><italic>The condition</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="M150" altimg="si108.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>is mathematically equivalent to the condition</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="M151" altimg="si102.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>(</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="M152" altimg="si105.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>).</italic></p></statement>
</p>
                <p id="p0054">Moreover, we can find the following mathematical result about their order (<xref rid="sec0018" ref-type="sec">Appendix D</xref>):<statement id="enun0008"><label>Corollary 5.2.2</label><p id="p0055"><italic>When R</italic><sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub> &lt; 1 <italic>and R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub> &lt; 1, <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>c</italic></sub> &gt; <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub>
<italic>and R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>c</italic></sub> &gt; <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub>
<italic>. When R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub> &gt; 1 <italic>or R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub> &gt; 1, <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>c</italic></sub> &lt; <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub>
<italic>and R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>c</italic></sub> &lt; <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub>
<italic>.</italic>
</p></statement>
</p>
                <p id="p0056">It is clearly undetermined which is the larger between <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub> and <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub> because from <xref rid="eq0008" ref-type="disp-formula">(8)</xref> and <xref rid="eq0009" ref-type="disp-formula">(9)</xref>, they are symmetric in terms of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M153" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M154" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>. Their relative values therefore depend on the values of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M155" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M156" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>. In contrast, the above corollary shows that <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>c</italic></sub> is necessarily larger than <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub> and <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub> when <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub> &lt; 1 and <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub> &lt; 1, where either <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub> or <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub> is less than unity if and only if the other is less than unity as we see in <xref rid="enun0004" ref-type="statement">Theorem 5.1</xref>. When <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub> &gt; 1 or <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub> &gt; 1, <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>c</italic></sub> is necessarily smaller than <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub> and <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub>.</p>
                <p id="p0057">From the standpoint that the basic reproduction numbers <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub> and <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub> are more practical compared to <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>c</italic></sub>, we can remark that <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>c</italic></sub>, which would be frequently/conventionally used as the mathematically derived basic reproduction number, appears to overestimate the basic reproduction number for each subpopulation when it is smaller than unity while underestimating it when it is larger than unity.</p>
                <p id="p0058">When a disease is imported into the community by tourists or other short term visitors, <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub> can be reasonably measured in a bid to protect the residents. Actually, the features of the residents could be identified more easily than those of the visitors. In contrast, <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub> could be important and have to be practically evaluated from the standpoint of a specific kind of visitor subpopulation. For instance, when the visitors are prone to a particular kind of disease to which the residents in the community are characteristically immune though they can facilitate its spread. Furthermore, since the basic reproduction number <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>c</italic></sub> corresponds to the expected number of secondary cases summed up for both resident and visitor subpopulations, it would be an unsatisfactory overestimation for discussing the prevention, the intervention, or the containment of the spread of a transmissible disease in the kind of community we consider. Moreover, <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>c</italic></sub> is quite tricky to estimate given the contrasting peculiarities of the two subpopulations: the attributes of residents are relatively easier to measure compared to those of visitors who are only around in the community for a short period.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0010">
              <label>6</label>
              <title>Concluding remarks</title>
              <p id="p0059">It is obvious that some kind of control measures need to be put in place to mitigate the effects of disease transmission in a community with visitor population. The most obvious measure might be to control the visitor population size, <italic>N<sub>v</sub></italic>. However, it would be equally effective to control the flux, that is, the inflow and outflow, <italic>M</italic> and <italic>E</italic>. A sufficiently large <italic>M</italic> (and <italic>E</italic>) means the duration of stay <italic>N<sub>v</sub></italic>/<italic>M</italic> ≪ 1 so as to make <inline-formula><mml:math id="M157" altimg="si109.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo>≪</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> which guarantees the suppression of disease spread. For the purpose of clarity, a large <italic>M</italic> implies large visitor movements. As stated earlier, reducing the visitor population size will be very effective although it is in general quite difficult to achieve within a country except in conserved areas. For transnational human movements, visa application processes can be tightened but in a world of growing globalization, that might be counterproductive.</p>
              <p id="p0060">The dynamics of swine fever, which is endemic and of major concern in the global hog business, is a very good example which corresponds to our model since there is the possibility of cross infection within and between domestic pig and wild boar populations such that we have <italic>β<sub>rr</sub></italic> &gt; 0, <italic>β<sub>vr</sub></italic> &gt; 0, <italic>β<sub>rv</sub></italic> &gt; 0 and <italic>β<sub>vv</sub></italic> &gt; 0. It is established that the disease is transmitted both directly as stated earlier and indirectly (through polluted carcasses, food waste, or vehicles and equipment). For pig farm holders, the value of the basic reproduction number <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub> is very critical. To make sure it is kept as low as possible, the following are very crucial: vaccination (though there are still knowledge gaps) and control measures like proscription of swill feeding, isolation of pigs before introduction into stock, culling and thorough disinfection of all hogs on affected farms, proper disposal of carcasses, homogenized strict import approach for live pigs and pork, management of wild boars and prevention of contacts between local pigs and wild boars (<xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">Mur, Sánchez-Vizcaíno, Fernández-Carrión, Jurado, Rolesu, Feliziani, Laddomada, Martínez-López, 2018</xref>, <xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">Postel, Austermann-Busch, Petrov, Moennig, Becher, 2018</xref>, <xref rid="bib0031" ref-type="bibr">Sánchez-Cordón, Montoya, Reis, Dixon, 2018</xref>).</p>
              <p id="p0061">For the model we considered, the basic reproduction number can be viewed from different perspectives depending on the focus of public health policy makers. Any mathematical variant of the basic reproduction number, namely <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0|<italic>r</italic></sub> and <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0|<italic>v</italic></sub>, can be said to be the supremum of the expected number of secondary infections which keeps changing with the effects of new infections.</p>
              <sec id="sec0011">
                <label>6.1</label>
                <title>Effects of cross infection</title>
                <p id="p0062">From the results obtained in the previous sections, we can say that even when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M158" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M159" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> are small, there could be disease outbreak in the subpopulations given sufficiently high cross infections. This implies that even without outbreak in isolation, when the subpopulations have contacts with each other, there is always a likelihood of outbreak. Such a case is numerically demonstrated by <xref rid="fig0008" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>
for our model <xref rid="eq0002" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref>. Due to the small values of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M160" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M161" altimg="si94.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> it is likely that the infective population size decreases in an initial period within the subpopulation where the initial infective appears. However, since the basic reproduction number can go beyond unity when there is cross infection, an outbreak of disease appears after a time lag. This kind of time lag in the temporal variation later leading to disease outbreak would likely cause delays in policy/social/sanitary measures against disease invasion in the community.<fig id="fig0008"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Numerical examples of the temporal variation of the system <xref rid="eq0002" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref>. (a) <inline-formula><mml:math id="M162" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>99990.0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>10.0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>; (b) <inline-formula><mml:math id="M163" altimg="si39.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>100000.0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Commonly, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M164" altimg="si40.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">B</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M165" altimg="si41.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.4</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M166" altimg="si42.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M167" altimg="si43.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>16.90</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M168" altimg="si44.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.02</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M169" altimg="si45.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.200</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M170" altimg="si46.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.167</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M171" altimg="si47.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.084</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0008">Fig. 8</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr8_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="p0063">To measure the contribution of cross infection on the basic reproduction number for each subpopulation, we may use the following indices:<disp-formula id="ueq0009"><mml:math id="M172" altimg="si110.svg"><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:msub><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mtext>for</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="4.pt"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:msub><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mtext>for</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="4.pt"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>It can be easily found that if <inline-formula><mml:math id="M173" altimg="si111.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> then <italic>ξ<sub>r</sub></italic> &gt; <italic>ξ<sub>v</sub></italic>. This means that the effect of cross infection on the resident subpopulation is more serious as the isolated visitor subpopulation has the larger basic reproduction number for the disease. Conversely, we can say that the effect of cross infection on the visitor subpopulation is more serious when the isolated resident subpopulation has the larger basic reproduction number for the disease. Intuitively, these results are very much acceptable.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0012">
                <label>6.2</label>
                <title>Application for malaria</title>
                <p id="p0064">Malaria is a disease of global relevance as it has been a key concern in almost 100 countries of the world. Interestingly, it is preventable but its control has proven to be something which requires serious attention as drug-resistant strains of the plasmodium species, the cause of malaria, have been known to emerge. Ineffective vaccination programmes have also been known to result to more fatal outbreaks of this disease transmitted by the female Anopheles mosquitoes to humans after being infected when they bite infective humans (<xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">Cowman et al., 2016</xref>).</p>
                <p id="p0065">In order to apply our model for malaria, humans can be viewed as residents while mosquitoes can be regarded as visitors. The recruitment of mosquitoes can be seen as their influx into the visitor subpopulation while the effective elimination of mosquitoes by the use of insecticides or through other means can be taken as leading to their outflux from the visitor subpopulation. Notably, for malaria, there are generally no direct human-human and mosquito-mosquito transmissions, so intra-subpopulation infections do not exist, that is, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M174" altimg="si112.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Then, we have<disp-formula id="eq0011"><label>(11)</label><mml:math id="M175" altimg="si113.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>Managing <italic>β<sub>vr</sub></italic> and <italic>β<sub>rv</sub></italic> implies taking some measures to control mosquitoes as they both have direct effects in the outbreak of malaria. <italic>N<sub>r</sub></italic> and <italic>N<sub>v</sub></italic> also have direct effect, but more attention should be paid to the latter because of its square order contribution on the basic reproduction numbers. If we can control the mosquito density <italic>N<sub>v</sub></italic> so that <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub> &lt; 1, the outbreak of malaria could be successfully suppressed. This argument could be extended to other vector-borne diseases like Dengue fever, Lyme disease, West Nile fever, etc.</p>
                <p id="p0066">Taking a different standpoint where we consider mosquitoes as residents and humans as visitors, for example, the case of some explorers in a mosquito infested environment, the expected duration of stay <italic>N<sub>v</sub></italic>/<italic>M</italic> appears very crucial. A sufficiently short duration of stay could help manage the epidemic effectively. Also, an enough low contact rate with the mosquito population would be very vital. This can be achieved by control measures like the use of insecticide-treated nets (ITN) and mosquito repellents. Another control measure might be the use of vaccination by the visitors to make them immune to being infected.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0013">
                <label>6.3</label>
                <title>Application for avian influenza</title>
                <p id="p0067"><xref rid="bib0017" ref-type="bibr">Horimoto et al. (2005)</xref> predicted that a new influenza pandemic would occur following outbreaks of the H5 and H7 subtypes of avian influenza A in birds and humans. Infection in humans was known to occur through very close contact with birds which had been infected while bird to bird infections were obviously easier. Using the concept of the basic reproduction number, <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al. (2015)</xref> investigated the dynamics of a bird-to-human transmission model with regards to human psychology vis-à-vis avian influenza. Their outcome shows that if there is an outbreak, “the saturation effect within avian population and the psychological effect in human population cannot change the stability of equilibria but can affect the number of infected humans”. <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Liu and Fang (2015)</xref> formulated a two-host dynamic model for H7N9 virus infection in both bird and human populations. Critical transmission parameters were computed using nationwide surveillance data of infections in mainland China. The analysis of their model shows that the long term prevention of human H7N9 infections is necessitated by culling infected birds.</p>
                <p id="p0068">From the perspective of our model, we take humans as residents and birds as short-stay visitors such that <italic>β<sub>rr</sub></italic> ≈ 0, <italic>β<sub>vr</sub></italic> ≈ 0, <italic>β<sub>rv</sub></italic> &gt; 0 and <italic>β<sub>vv</sub></italic> &gt; 0 since human-to-bird influenza transmissions are almost impossible and human-to-human infections are quite rare. So, we have <inline-formula><mml:math id="M176" altimg="si114.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">B</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M177" altimg="si115.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Otherwise, taking domesticated birds as residents and wild birds as short-stay visitors, we have <italic>β<sub>rr</sub></italic> &gt; 0, <italic>β<sub>vr</sub></italic> ≈ 0, <italic>β<sub>rv</sub></italic> &gt; 0, and <italic>β<sub>vv</sub></italic> &gt; 0. In this case, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M178" altimg="si114.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">B</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M179" altimg="si116.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                <p id="p0069">Just like in the case of malaria, one effective control measure for avian influenza would be to ensure that infected birds are kept away as much as possible since <inline-formula><mml:math id="M180" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> depends on the square value of the bird population density. For wild birds that migrate seasonally to a local community, measures can be taken to keep them off. For poultry and other possible local hosts of avian influenza, screening or culling as established by (<xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Liu and Fang, 2015</xref>) can help in preventing the disease outbreak in the local community.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0014">
                <label>6.4</label>
                <title>Relationship with metapopulation dynamics</title>
                <p id="p0070">In the past couple of decades, most papers related to theoretical/mathematical studies of the global spread of transmissible diseases were focused on the mobility of humans over various populations or patches (see <xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr">Arino, van den Driessche, 2006</xref>, <xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">Colizza, Vespignani, 2008</xref>, <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Gong, Small, 2018</xref>, <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Saito, Nishiura, Higuchi, 2018</xref>, <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Soriano-Paños, Lotero, Arenas, Gómez-Gardeñes, 2018</xref>, <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">Wang, Wu, 2018</xref> and references therein). Frequently, such movements correspond to migration as opposed to temporary visits for a finite period as we consider in our case, or to human transportation on a large spatial scale during relatively long trips. Our scenario of short visits does not fully capture the metapopulation framework in most of those previous works but the interaction between the resident and visitor subpopulations has some semblance of metapopulation behavior. Indeed, the two subpopulations may be regarded as patches between which diseases can spread. This may be said to display some metapopulation dynamics in the context of modern trends in social networks (<xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Hackl, Dubernet, 2019</xref>, <xref rid="bib0039" ref-type="bibr">Wang, Wang, Wu, 2018</xref>) while metapopulation dynamics have been generally based on a spatially heterogeneous structure of population distribution (<xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr">Arino, van den Driessche, 2006</xref>, <xref rid="bib0002" ref-type="bibr">Ball, Britton, House, Isham, Mollison, Pellis, Scalia Tomba, 2015</xref>, <xref rid="bib0026" ref-type="bibr">North, Godfray, 2017</xref>).</p>
                <p id="p0071">In this paper, we have considered a community under epidemic interaction with short-term visitors. We do not explicitly consider metapopulation dynamics although the visitors in our model can be regarded as the epidemic agents in terms of interaction between “patches” in a metapopulation. In this sense, the analysis of our model can be regarded as being about the likelihood of the spread of a transmissible disease in a community which corresponds to a patch. It is necessary to discuss such a likelihood over a metapopulation especially when an transnational or global-scale outbreak is concerned, whereas even in such a case, each local community in the metapopulation must consider the likelihood of spread within the community in order to prevent or contain it as mentioned in the last part of <xref rid="sec0009" ref-type="sec">Section 5.2</xref>. This paper could be regarded as a mathematical modeling work devoted to such a problem.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list id="bib001">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="bib0001">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0001">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Arino</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>van den Driessche</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Disease spread in metapopulations</article-title>
                  <source>Fields Inst. Commun.</source>
                  <volume>48</volume>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>13</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0002">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0002">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ball</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Britton</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>House</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Isham</surname>
                      <given-names>V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mollison</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pellis</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Scalia Tomba</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Seven challenges for metapopulation models of epidemics, including households models</article-title>
                  <source>Epidemics</source>
                  <volume>10</volume>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <fpage>63</fpage>
                  <lpage>67</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25843386</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0003">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0003">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brauer</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Mathematical epidemiology: past, present, and future</article-title>
                  <source>Infect. Dis. Modell.</source>
                  <volume>2</volume>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <lpage>127</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0004">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0004">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brauer</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Castillo-Chavez</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mubayi</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Towers</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Some models for epidemics of vector-transmitted diseases</article-title>
                  <source>Infect. Dis. Modell.</source>
                  <volume>1</volume>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <fpage>79</fpage>
                  <lpage>87</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0005">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0005">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chowell</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sattenspiel</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bansal</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Viboud</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Mathematical models to characterize early epidemic growth: a review</article-title>
                  <source>Phys. Life Rev.</source>
                  <volume>18</volume>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <fpage>66</fpage>
                  <lpage>97</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27451336</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0006">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0006">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Colizza</surname>
                      <given-names>V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vespignani</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Epidemic modeling in metapopulation systems with heterogeneous coupling pattern: theory and simulations</article-title>
                  <source>J. Theor. Biol.</source>
                  <volume>251</volume>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <fpage>450</fpage>
                  <lpage>467</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18222487</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0007">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0007">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cowman</surname>
                      <given-names>A.F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Healer</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Marapana</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Marsh</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Malaria: biology and disease</article-title>
                  <source>Cell</source>
                  <volume>167</volume>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <fpage>610</fpage>
                  <lpage>624</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27768886</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0008">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0008">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cushing</surname>
                      <given-names>J.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Diekmann</surname>
                      <given-names>O.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The many guises of <italic>r</italic><sub>0</sub> (a didactic note)</article-title>
                  <source>J. Theor. Biol.</source>
                  <volume>404</volume>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <fpage>295</fpage>
                  <lpage>302</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27320680</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0009">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0009">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Diekmann</surname>
                      <given-names>O.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Heesterbeek</surname>
                      <given-names>J.A.P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Britton</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Mathematical tools for understanding infectious disease dynamics</chapter-title>
                  <source>Princeton Series in Theoretical and Computational Biology</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <publisher-name>Princeton University Press, Princeton</publisher-name>
                  <fpage>520pp</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0010">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0010">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Diekmann</surname>
                      <given-names>O.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Heesterbeek</surname>
                      <given-names>J.A.P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Roberts</surname>
                      <given-names>M.G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The construction of next-generation matrices for compartmental epidemic models</article-title>
                  <source>R. Soc. Interface</source>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <fpage>873</fpage>
                  <lpage>885</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19892718</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0011">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0011">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Diseases</surname>
                      <given-names>N.I.o.I.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Measles situation update, epidemiologic week 1–20, 2018 (as of 23 may 2018)</chapter-title>
                  <source>Infectious Diseases Weekly Report (IDWR), Infectious Disease Surveillance Center, National Institute of Infectious Diseases, Japan</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0012">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0012">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Farrar</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cristin</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Basu</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Global Disease Outbreaks</chapter-title>
                  <year>2016</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0013">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0013">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gong</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Small</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Epidemic spreading on metapopulation networks including migration and demographics</article-title>
                  <source>Chaos</source>
                  <volume>28</volume>
                  <issue>8</issue>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <fpage>083102</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.5021167</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30180639</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0014">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0014">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hackl</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dubernet</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Epidemic spreading in urban areas using agent-based transportation models</article-title>
                  <source>Future Internet</source>
                  <volume>11</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>14</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3929/ethz-b-000337854</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <note>
                  <p>92</p>
                </note>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0015">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0015">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Heesterbeek</surname>
                      <given-names>J.A.P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Roberts</surname>
                      <given-names>M.G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The type-reproduction number <italic>t</italic> in models for infectious disease control</article-title>
                  <source>Math. Biosci.</source>
                  <volume>206</volume>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <lpage>10</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16529777</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0016">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0016">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Heffernan</surname>
                      <given-names>J.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Smith</surname>
                      <given-names>R.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wahl</surname>
                      <given-names>L.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Perspectives on the basic reproductive ratio</article-title>
                  <source>R. Soc. Interface</source>
                  <volume>2</volume>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <fpage>281</fpage>
                  <lpage>293</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16849186</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0017">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0017">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Horimoto</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kawaoka</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Influenza</surname>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Lessons from past pandemics, warnings from current incidents</article-title>
                  <source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</source>
                  <volume>3</volume>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <fpage>591</fpage>
                  <lpage>600</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16064053</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0018">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0018">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Keeling</surname>
                      <given-names>M.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rohani</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Modeling Infectious Diseases in Humans and Animals</chapter-title>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0019">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0019">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lewis</surname>
                      <given-names>M.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shuai</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>van den Driessche</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A general theory for target reproduction numbers with applications to ecology and epidemiology</article-title>
                  <source>J. Math. Biol.</source>
                  <volume>78</volume>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <fpage>2317</fpage>
                  <lpage>2339</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30854577</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0020">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0020">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pang</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ruan</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Global dynamics of avian influenza epidemic models with psychological effect</article-title>
                  <source>Comput. Math. Methods Med.</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <fpage>12pp</fpage>
                </element-citation>
                <note>
                  <p>Article ID 913726</p>
                </note>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0021">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0021">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fang</surname>
                      <given-names>C.T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A modeling study of human infections with avian influenza a H7N9 virus in Mainland China</article-title>
                  <source>Int. J. Infect. Dis.</source>
                  <volume>41</volume>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <fpage>73</fpage>
                  <lpage>78</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26585941</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0022">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0022">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>MacIntyre</surname>
                      <given-names>C.R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Karki</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sheikh</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zwar</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Heywood</surname>
                      <given-names>A.E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The role of travel in measles outbreaks in Australia–an enhanced surveillance study</article-title>
                  <source>Vaccine</source>
                  <volume>34</volume>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <fpage>4386</fpage>
                  <lpage>4391</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27449078</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0023">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0023">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Martcheva</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>An Introduction to Mathematical Epidemiology</chapter-title>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
                  <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0024">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0024">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mizumoto</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kobayashi</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chowell</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Transmission potential of modified measles during an outbreak, Japan, March–May 2018</article-title>
                  <source>Euro Surveill.</source>
                  <volume>23</volume>
                  <issue>24</issue>
                  <year>2018</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0025">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0025">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mur</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sánchez-Vizcaíno</surname>
                      <given-names>J.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fernández-Carrión</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jurado</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rolesu</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Feliziani</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Laddomada</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Martínez-López</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Understanding african swine fever infection dynamics in sardinia using a spatially explicit transmission model in domestic pig farms</article-title>
                  <source>Transbound. Emerg. Dis.</source>
                  <volume>65</volume>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <fpage>123</fpage>
                  <lpage>134</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28296281</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0026">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0026">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>North</surname>
                      <given-names>A.R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Godfray</surname>
                      <given-names>H.C.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The dynamics of disease in a metapopulation: the role of dispersal range</article-title>
                  <source>J. Theor. Biol.</source>
                  <volume>418</volume>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <lpage>65</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28130098</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0027">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0027">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Parikh</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Youssef</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Swarup</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eubank</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Modeling the effect of Transient Populations on Epidemics in Washington DC</chapter-title>
                  <year>2013</year>
                </element-citation>
                <note>
                  <p>Article 3152</p>
                </note>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0028">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0028">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Postel</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Austermann-Busch</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Petrov</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Moennig</surname>
                      <given-names>V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Becher</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Epidemiology, diagnosis and control of classical swine fever: recent developments and future challenges</article-title>
                  <source>Transbound. Emerg. Dis.</source>
                  <volume>65</volume>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <fpage>248</fpage>
                  <lpage>261</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0029">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0029">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Roberts</surname>
                      <given-names>M.G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Heesterbeek</surname>
                      <given-names>J.A.P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A new method for estimating the effort required to control an infectious disease</article-title>
                  <source>Proc. R. Soc. London B</source>
                  <volume>270</volume>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <fpage>1359</fpage>
                  <lpage>1364</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0030">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0030">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Saito</surname>
                      <given-names>M.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nishiura</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Higuchi</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Reconstructing the transmission dynamics of rubella in japan, 2012–2013</article-title>
                  <source>PLoS ONE</source>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <fpage>e0205889</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0205889</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30332469</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0031">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0031">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sánchez-Cordón</surname>
                      <given-names>P.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Montoya</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reis</surname>
                      <given-names>A.L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dixon</surname>
                      <given-names>L.K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>African swine fever: a re-emerging viral disease threatening the global pig industry</article-title>
                  <source>Vet. J.</source>
                  <volume>233</volume>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <fpage>41</fpage>
                  <lpage>48</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29486878</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0032">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0032">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Smith</surname>
                      <given-names>D.L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McKenzie</surname>
                      <given-names>F.E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Snow</surname>
                      <given-names>R.W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hay</surname>
                      <given-names>S.I.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Revisiting the basic reproductive number for malaria and its implications for malaria control</article-title>
                  <source>PLoS Biol.</source>
                  <volume>5</volume>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <fpage>e42</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17311470</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0033">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0033">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Soriano-Paños</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lotero</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Arenas</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gómez-Gardeñes</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Spreading processes in multiplex metapopulations containing different mobility networks</article-title>
                  <source>Phys. Rev. X</source>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <fpage>031039</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevX.8.031039</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0034">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0034">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tompkins</surname>
                      <given-names>D.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Carver</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jones</surname>
                      <given-names>M.E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Krkošek</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Skerratt</surname>
                      <given-names>L.F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Emerging infectious diseases of wildlife: a critical perspective</article-title>
                  <source>Trends Parasitol.</source>
                  <volume>31</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <lpage>159</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25709109</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0035">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0035">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>van den Driessche</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Reproduction numbers of infectious disease models</article-title>
                  <source>Infect. Dis. Modell.</source>
                  <volume>2</volume>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <fpage>288</fpage>
                  <lpage>303</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0036">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0036">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>van den Driessche</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Watmough</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Reproduction numbers and sub-threshold endemic equilibria for compartmental models of disease transmission</article-title>
                  <source>Math. Biosci.</source>
                  <volume>180</volume>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <lpage>48</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12387915</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0037">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0037">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>van den Driessche</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Watmough</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brauer</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Further notes on the basic reproduction number</chapter-title>
                  <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brauer</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>van den Driessche</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Mathematical Epidemiology (Lecture Notes in Mathematics)</source>
                  <volume>vol. 1945</volume>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
                  <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>
                  <fpage>159</fpage>
                  <lpage>178</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0038">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0038">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Walters</surname>
                      <given-names>C.E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Meslé</surname>
                      <given-names>M.M.I.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hall</surname>
                      <given-names>I.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Modelling the global spread of diseases: a review of current practice and capability</article-title>
                  <source>Epidemics</source>
                  <volume>25</volume>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>8</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29853411</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0039">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0039">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Inferring metapopulation propagation network for intra-city epidemic control and prevention. in: KDD 2018: 24th ACM SIGKDD international conference on knowledge discovery &amp; data mining</chapter-title>
                  <source>August 19–23, 2018, London, United Kingdom ACM, New York, NY, USA</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <fpage>830</fpage>
                  <lpage>838</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1145/3219819.3219865</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0040">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0040">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>J.T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Characterizing the dynamics underlying global spread of epidemics</article-title>
                  <source>Nat. Commun.</source>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <fpage>218</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-017-02344-z</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29335536</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0041">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0041">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>WHO</surname>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Managing Epidemics: Key Facts about Major Deadly Diseases</chapter-title>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>
                  <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0042">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0042">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wilson</surname>
                      <given-names>M.E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Global travel and emerging infections</chapter-title>
                  <source>Infectious Disease Movement in a Borderless World: Workshop Summary</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <fpage>90</fpage>
                  <lpage>104</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0043">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0043">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yakob</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Clements</surname>
                      <given-names>A.C.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A mathematical model of Chikungunya dynamics and control: the major epidemic on Réunion Island</article-title>
                  <source>PLoS ONE</source>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <fpage>e57448</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23554860</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
            <sec id="sec0015">
              <label>Appendix A</label>
              <title>Proof for Theorem 4.2</title>
              <p id="p0074"><list list-type="simple" id="lst0002"><list-item id="lstitem0009"><label>1.</label><p id="p0075">Suppose that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M181" altimg="si117.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Then, if <inline-formula><mml:math id="M182" altimg="si118.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> we have<disp-formula id="ueq0010"><mml:math id="M183" altimg="si119.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mtext>for</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="4.pt"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>≫</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>This is contradictory to the precondition for <italic>x<sub>r</sub></italic> to converge to a positive value. Therefore, <italic>x<sub>r</sub></italic> → 0 as <italic>t</italic> → ∞. Then we have <inline-formula><mml:math id="M184" altimg="si120.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for <italic>t</italic> ≫ 1. Since this is contradictory again, we conclude that <italic>y<sub>r</sub></italic> → 0.</p></list-item><list-item id="lstitem0010"><label>2.</label><p id="p0076">Since <italic>y<sub>r</sub></italic> → 0 as <italic>t</italic> → ∞, we have<disp-formula id="eq0012"><label>(A.1)</label><mml:math id="M185" altimg="si121.svg"><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mtext>for</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="4.pt"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>≫</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mtext>when</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="4.pt"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mtext>for</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="4.pt"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>≫</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mtext>with</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="4.pt"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p><p id="p0077">From these results, we can easily find that, if <inline-formula><mml:math id="M186" altimg="si122.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> with <italic>β<sub>vv</sub></italic> &gt; 0, that is, if <inline-formula><mml:math id="M187" altimg="si68.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> then <italic>dy<sub>v</sub></italic>/<italic>dt</italic> &lt; 0 for <italic>t</italic> ≫ 1 so that <italic>y<sub>v</sub></italic> → 0 as <italic>t</italic> → ∞. Also, <italic>y<sub>v</sub></italic> → 0 as <italic>t</italic> → ∞ when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M188" altimg="si123.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p><p id="p0078">These arguments show that, when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M189" altimg="si68.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> all infective visitors end up leaving the community such that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M190" altimg="si124.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M191" altimg="si79.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> as <italic>t</italic> → ∞.</p></list-item><list-item id="lstitem0011"><label>3.</label><p id="p0079">If <inline-formula><mml:math id="M192" altimg="si125.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> with <italic>β<sub>vv</sub></italic> &gt; 0, that is, if <inline-formula><mml:math id="M193" altimg="si68.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> then <xref rid="eq0012" ref-type="disp-formula">(A.1)</xref> corresponds to a logistic equation. This implies that<disp-formula id="ueq0011"><mml:math id="M194" altimg="si126.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mtext>as</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="4.pt"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mi>∞</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>Thus, for <italic>y<sub>r</sub></italic> → 0 as <italic>t</italic> → ∞, we have<disp-formula id="ueq0012"><mml:math id="M195" altimg="si127.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mtext>for</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="4.pt"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>≫</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p><p id="p0080">Hence, when <italic>β<sub>rv</sub></italic> &gt; 0, we see that <italic>x<sub>r</sub></italic> → 0 as <italic>t</italic> → ∞. These arguments prove that<disp-formula id="ueq0013"><mml:math id="M196" altimg="si128.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mtext>as</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="4.pt"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mi>∞</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p></list-item></list>This result can also be supported by the local stability analysis. We can easily get the following Jacobian matrix for the system <xref rid="eq0002" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref> about the equilibrium point <inline-formula><mml:math id="M197" altimg="si129.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> :<disp-formula id="eq0013"><label>(A.2)</label><mml:math id="M198" altimg="si130.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>which has eigenvalues <inline-formula><mml:math id="M199" altimg="si131.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M200" altimg="si132.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M201" altimg="si133.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. This establishes that, if <inline-formula><mml:math id="M202" altimg="si70.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the equilibrium point <inline-formula><mml:math id="M203" altimg="si134.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> exists locally asymptotically stable. In the same way, making use of the eigenvalue analysis about the Jacobian matrix for the linearization of <xref rid="eq0002" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref>, it can also be proven that the equilibrium point (0,0,0) is unstable if <inline-formula><mml:math id="M204" altimg="si72.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0016">
              <label>Appendix B</label>
              <title>Proof for Theorem 4.3</title>
              <p id="p0081">Now, let us consider the case that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M205" altimg="si68.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M206" altimg="si82.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M207" altimg="si55.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> as <italic>t</italic> → ∞, being proved by <xref rid="enun0002" ref-type="statement">Theorem 4.2</xref>. We can derive the following Jacobian matrix about the point <inline-formula><mml:math id="M208" altimg="si135.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M209" altimg="si55.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>:<disp-formula id="eq0014"><label>(B.1)</label><mml:math id="M210" altimg="si136.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>which can be evaluated using the bottom right 2 × 2 matrix<disp-formula id="eq0015"><label>(B.2)</label><mml:math id="M211" altimg="si137.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">J</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>whose characteristic equation is given by<disp-formula id="eq0016"><label>(B.3)</label><mml:math id="M212" altimg="si138.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>tr</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">J</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>det</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">J</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where<disp-formula id="ueq0014"><mml:math id="M213" altimg="si139.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tr</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">J</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>and<disp-formula id="ueq0015"><mml:math id="M214" altimg="si140.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>det</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">J</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">B</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>with<disp-formula id="ueq0016"><mml:math id="M215" altimg="si141.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">B</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>This <inline-formula><mml:math id="M216" altimg="si89.svg"><mml:mi mathvariant="script">B</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> expresses the ratio of the infectivity between residents and visitors (<italic>inter-subcommunity infection</italic>) to the infectivity within subcommunities (<italic>intra-subcommunity infection</italic>).</p>
              <p id="p0082">From the theory of local stability, the point <inline-formula><mml:math id="M217" altimg="si78.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is unfeasible if <inline-formula><mml:math id="M218" altimg="si142.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tr</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">J</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> or <inline-formula><mml:math id="M219" altimg="si143.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>det</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">J</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The condition <inline-formula><mml:math id="M220" altimg="si142.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tr</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">J</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> gives<disp-formula id="eq0017"><label>(B.4)</label><mml:math id="M221" altimg="si144.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>For <inline-formula><mml:math id="M222" altimg="si145.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>det</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">J</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> we have<disp-formula id="eq0018"><label>(B.5)</label><mml:math id="M223" altimg="si146.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">B</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>Since the right side of <xref rid="eq0017" ref-type="disp-formula">(B.4)</xref> is greater than that of <xref rid="eq0018" ref-type="disp-formula">(B.5)</xref>, we can conclude that if <xref rid="eq0017" ref-type="disp-formula">(B.4)</xref> is satisfied, then <inline-formula><mml:math id="M224" altimg="si78.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M225" altimg="si55.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is unfeasible. So we define the critical value <inline-formula><mml:math id="M226" altimg="si86.svg"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">upper</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula> by the right side of <xref rid="eq0017" ref-type="disp-formula">(B.4)</xref>, that is, by <xref rid="eq0007" ref-type="disp-formula">(7)</xref>. Consequently from these arguments, the point <inline-formula><mml:math id="M227" altimg="si147.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M228" altimg="si148.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">upper</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is unfeasible. Thus, the feasible equilibrium state <inline-formula><mml:math id="M229" altimg="si78.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M230" altimg="si55.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> must satisfy <inline-formula><mml:math id="M231" altimg="si84.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">upper</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0017">
              <label>Appendix C</label>
              <title>Derivation of <italic>R</italic><sub>0|<italic>r</italic></sub>, <italic>R</italic><sub>0|<italic>v</italic></sub>, and <italic>R</italic><sub>0|<italic>c</italic></sub></title>
              <p id="p0083">In order to obtain the basic reproduction number <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub> which is the index of the possibility of the disease spread within the resident subpopulation, following the theory given by (<xref rid="bib0036" ref-type="bibr">van den Driessche, Watmough, 2002</xref>, <xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">van den Driessche, Watmough, Brauer, 2008</xref>), we arrange <xref rid="eq0002" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref> at first as follows:<disp-formula id="eq0019"><label>(C.1)</label><mml:math id="M232" altimg="si149.svg"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>then decompose it into the recruitment terms of new infections <italic>for the resident</italic> and the other terms as follows:<disp-formula id="eq0020"><label>(C.2)</label><mml:math id="M233" altimg="si150.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">X</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">F</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M234" altimg="si151.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">X</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>T</mml:mtext></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. <bold><italic>F</italic></bold> represents the recruitment rate of new infections, and <bold><italic>V</italic></bold> represents the other factors related to the epidemic dynamics, so that<disp-formula id="eq0021"><label>(C.3)</label><mml:math id="M235" altimg="si152.svg"><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">F</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="2.em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">V</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
              <p id="p0084">Next, we have the Jacobian matrices of <bold><italic>F</italic></bold> and <bold><italic>V</italic></bold> about <bold><italic>X</italic></bold>:<disp-formula id="ueq0017"><mml:math id="M236" altimg="si153.svg"><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">F</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">V</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>At the disease-free equilibrium <bold><italic>X</italic></bold>
<sub>0</sub> ≔ (0  0  <italic>N<sub>r</sub></italic>)<sup>T</sup>, they become<disp-formula id="ueq0018"><mml:math id="M237" altimg="si154.svg"><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">F</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>Taking the top left hand corner 2 × 2 matrices in each of the two matrices, we have<disp-formula id="ueq0019"><mml:math id="M238" altimg="si155.svg"><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">F</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="2.em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">V</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
              <p id="p0085">Then, the next generation matrix (NGM) is obtained by<disp-formula id="eq0022"><label>(C.4)</label><mml:math id="M239" altimg="si156.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">K</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">FV</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>The basic reproduction number <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub> is given by the maximum absolute value of the eigenvalues of <xref rid="eq0022" ref-type="disp-formula">(C.4)</xref>, that is,<disp-formula id="ueq0020"><mml:math id="M240" altimg="si157.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>max</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">}</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>Therefore we get the following basic reproduction number for the model <xref rid="eq0002" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref>:<disp-formula id="eq0023"><label>(C.5)</label><mml:math id="M241" altimg="si158.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi mathvariant="script">B</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>Since we consider only the case that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M242" altimg="si66.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> we obtain <xref rid="eq0008" ref-type="disp-formula">(8)</xref> as <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub>.</p>
              <p id="p0086">To derive <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub>, we should change the decomposition of <xref rid="eq0019" ref-type="disp-formula">(C.1)</xref> because we now consider the basic reproduction number which is the index of the possibility of the disease spread within the visitor subpopulation. The decomposition into <bold><italic>F</italic></bold> and <bold><italic>V</italic></bold> should be such that the recruitment terms of new infections <italic>for the visitor</italic> and the other terms are as follows, differently from <xref rid="eq0021" ref-type="disp-formula">(C.3)</xref>:<disp-formula id="ueq0021"><mml:math id="M243" altimg="si159.svg"><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">F</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="2.em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">V</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>In the way same with that for <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub>, the NGM <inline-formula><mml:math id="M244" altimg="si160.svg"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">K</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is obtained as<disp-formula id="eq0024"><label>(C.6)</label><mml:math id="M245" altimg="si161.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">K</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>Therefore, the basic reproductive number <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub> given by the maximum absolute value of the eigenvalues of <xref rid="eq0024" ref-type="disp-formula">(C.6)</xref> is expressed as follows:<disp-formula id="ueq0022"><mml:math id="M246" altimg="si162.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mi mathvariant="script">B</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>Since we consider only the case that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M247" altimg="si163.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> we obtain <xref rid="eq0009" ref-type="disp-formula">(9)</xref> as <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub>.</p>
              <p id="p0087">In order to derive the basic reproduction number for the whole community <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>c</italic></sub>, we should change the decomposition of <xref rid="eq0019" ref-type="disp-formula">(C.1)</xref>, because the decomposition into <bold><italic>F</italic></bold> and <bold><italic>V</italic></bold> should be such that the recruitment terms of new infections come <italic>from both residents and visitors</italic>, differently from those for <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub> and <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub>:<disp-formula id="ueq0023"><mml:math id="M248" altimg="si164.svg"><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">F</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="2.em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">V</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>Then the NGM <inline-formula><mml:math id="M249" altimg="si160.svg"><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">K</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is now obtained as<disp-formula id="eq0025"><label>(C.7)</label><mml:math id="M250" altimg="si165.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">K</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>Since the characteristic equation of the matrix <xref rid="eq0025" ref-type="disp-formula">(C.7)</xref> can be expressed as<disp-formula id="eq0026"><label>(C.8)</label><mml:math id="M251" altimg="si166.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>we can easily find that the basic reproductive number <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>c</italic></sub> given by the maximum absolute value of the eigenvalues of <xref rid="eq0025" ref-type="disp-formula">(C.7)</xref> becomes <xref rid="eq0010" ref-type="disp-formula">(10)</xref>:<disp-formula id="ueq0024"><mml:math id="M252" altimg="si167.svg"><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>max</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>±</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0018">
              <label>Appendix D</label>
              <title>Proofs for Theorem 4.3, Corollaries <xref rid="enun0007" ref-type="statement">5.2.1</xref> and <xref rid="enun0008" ref-type="statement">5.2.2</xref></title>
              <p id="p0088">For <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>c</italic></sub> &lt; 1, it is necessary and sufficient that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M253" altimg="si168.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tr</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">K</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <italic>f</italic>(1) &gt; 0 for the characteristic equation of the NGM <inline-formula><mml:math id="M254" altimg="si169.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">K</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> given by <xref rid="eq0026" ref-type="disp-formula">(C.8)</xref>. Since we are considering the case that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M255" altimg="si74.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M256" altimg="si66.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> we can easily find that necessarily <inline-formula><mml:math id="M257" altimg="si170.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>tr</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-script">K</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Next, we can find that the condition <italic>f</italic>(1) &gt; 0 is equivalent to <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub> &lt; 1. Therefore, it is shown that <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>c</italic></sub> &lt; 1 if <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub> &lt; 1. The converse is also true. Then the proof of <xref rid="enun0006" ref-type="statement">Theorem 5.2</xref> is established, and <xref rid="enun0007" ref-type="statement">Corollary 5.2.1</xref> also follows. Going by <xref rid="enun0004" ref-type="statement">Theorem 5.1</xref>, the theorem and the corollary hold also for <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub>.</p>
              <p id="p0089">To prove <xref rid="enun0008" ref-type="statement">Corollary 5.2.2</xref>, we show from the characteristic equation <xref rid="eq0026" ref-type="disp-formula">(C.8)</xref> that <italic>f</italic>(<italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub>) &lt; 0. If so, it is guaranteed that <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>c</italic></sub> &gt; <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub>. Indeed, since <inline-formula><mml:math id="M258" altimg="si171.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> from <xref rid="eq0008" ref-type="disp-formula">(8)</xref>, we can find that<disp-formula id="ueq0025"><mml:math id="M259" altimg="si172.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">B</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>Since <inline-formula><mml:math id="M260" altimg="si173.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">B</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> it is necessarily satisfied that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M261" altimg="si174.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> that is, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M262" altimg="si175.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>∣</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. So, given <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub> &lt; 1, we have <italic>f</italic>(<italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub>) &lt; 0 so that <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>c</italic></sub> &gt; <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>r</italic></sub>. Going by <xref rid="enun0006" ref-type="statement">Theorem 5.2</xref>, it is also established that <italic>R</italic>
<sub>0∣<italic>v</italic></sub> &lt; 1. This completes the proof.</p>
            </sec>
            <ack id="ack0001">
              <title>Acknowledgment</title>
              <p id="p0073">The author HS was supported in part by <funding-source id="gs00001"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100001691</institution-id><institution>JSPS</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> KAKENHI Grant Number 18K03407.</p>
            </ack>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
