<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-03-11T00:57:37Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7902324" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7902324</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-02-24</datestamp>
        <setSpec>phebmjpg</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur J Hosp Pharm</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur J Hosp Pharm</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">ejhpharm</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ejhp</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>European Journal of Hospital Pharmacy</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">2047-9956</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2047-9964</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>BMJ Publishing Group</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>BMA House, Tavistock Square, London, WC1H 9JR</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC7902324</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7902324</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">7902324</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33619027</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ejhpharm-2020-002633</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/ejhpharm-2020-002633</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Research</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll">
                  <subject>2474</subject>
                  <subject>2341</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>The European COVID-19 drugs calculation tool: an aid for the estimation of the drugs needed during the SARS-CoV 2 pandemic</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib id="author-74295684" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4383-3726</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Leonardi Vinci</surname>
                    <given-names>Daniele</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-84348365" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Meccio</surname>
                    <given-names>Adriano</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-43892087" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Provenzani</surname>
                    <given-names>Alessio</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-74612980" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Faggiano</surname>
                    <given-names>Maria Ernestina</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-52895395" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Miljković</surname>
                    <given-names>Nenad</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-67424896" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Makridaki</surname>
                    <given-names>Despina</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-63992873" contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Horák</surname>
                    <given-names>Petr</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff7">7</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib id="author-32010498" contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8496-9908</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Polidori</surname>
                    <given-names>Piera</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="department">School of Specialization in Hospital Pharmacy</institution>, <institution>University of Palermo</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Palermo</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Sicilia</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="department">Chemical Engineering</institution>, <institution>University of Palermo</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Palermo</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Sicilia</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution content-type="department">Clinical Pharmacy</institution>, <institution>ISMETT</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Palermo</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution content-type="department">Pharmacy</institution>, <institution>AOU Policlinico</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Bari</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Puglia</addr-line>, <country>Italy</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><institution content-type="department">Hospital Pharmacy</institution>, <institution>Institute of Orthopaedic Surgery "Banjica"</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Belgrade</addr-line>, <country>Serbia</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><institution>Pharmacy Services, "Sismanoglio- Amalia Fleming", General Hospital of Attica</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Athens</addr-line>, <country>Greece</country></aff>
              <aff id="aff7"><label>7</label><institution content-type="department">Hospital Pharmacy</institution>, <institution>Motol University Hospital</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Praha</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Praha</addr-line>, <country>Czech Republic</country></aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp><label>Correspondence to</label> Dr Daniele Leonardi Vinci, School of Specialization in Hospital Pharmacy, University of Palermo, Palermo 90131, Italy; <email>daniele.leo93@gmail.com</email></corresp>
                <fn fn-type="other" id="fn6">
                  <p>EAHP Statement 2: Selection, Procurement and Distribution.</p>
                </fn>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <month>2</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>22</day>
                <month>2</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <elocation-id>ejhpharm-2020-002633</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>05</day>
                  <month>12</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>19</day>
                  <month>1</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>02</day>
                  <month>2</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© European Association of Hospital Pharmacists 2021. No commercial re-use. See rights and permissions. Published by BMJ.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
                <ali:free_to_read start_date="2021-02-22" end_date="2022-02-22"/>
                <license license-type="covid-19-tdm">
                  <license-p>This article is made freely available for use in accordance with BMJ’s website terms and conditions for the duration of the covid-19 pandemic or until otherwise determined by BMJ. You may use, download and print the article for any lawful, non-commercial purpose (including text and data mining) provided that all copyright notices and trade marks are retained.</license-p>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="covid-19-tdm">https://bmj.com/coronavirus/usage</ali:license_ref>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="ejhpharm-2020-002633.pdf"/>
              <abstract>
                <sec>
                  <title>Objective</title>
                  <p>To create an informatics supportive tool, which can assist healthcare professionals in estimating potential requirements for essential drug supplies to respond to the current SARS-CoV-2 pandemic based on epidemiological forecasting.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods</title>
                  <p>The tool was based on a Susceptible-Infected-Removed (SIR) epidemiological model in which the population is divided into three compartments and transmission parameters are specified to define the rate at which people move between stages. Appropriate data entry was guaranteed by the creation of structured guided paths. The drugs needed for the forecasted patients were estimated according to a list of critical care drugs compiled by consulting previous published scientific works, national and international guidelines. For each drug, an estimation was made of the percentage average ICU uptake for each therapeutic group and active principle.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>The tool consists of a Microsoft Excel template that is based on the initial epidemiological situation, the non-pharmaceutical interventions applied, the risk of hospitalisation based on the population age distribution, and the hospital beds available. The tool provides a forecast of which patients with COVID-19 will need to be treated in a hospital setting. The number of patients is used to estimate the drugs needed based on the average daily dose and the treatment length of each drug. The possibility of editing the type of distribution (exponential or linear) of the number of patients at the beginning of the analysis, the percentage adherence with non-pharmaceutical interventions and their delayed effect, and all the key epidemiological parameters make the estimation tailorable to different clinical contexts and needs.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusions</title>
                  <p>This model might be an effective supporting tool that could be easily implemented within the workflow of health professionals. All the information reported in this paper could be useful in developing new strategies to tackle the COVID-19 pandemic.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>public health</kwd>
                <kwd>critical care</kwd>
                <kwd>COVID-19</kwd>
                <kwd>practice guideline</kwd>
                <kwd>health care rationing</kwd>
                <kwd>health care economics and organizations</kwd>
                <kwd>Medical Informatics</kwd>
                <kwd>CLINICAL MEDICINE</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>access-type</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>free</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro" id="s1">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>The COVID-19 pandemic has proved to be a global health threat, with approximately 100 million people infected and more than 2 million deaths worldwide.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> The pandemic trend is influenced by multiple factors and each nation has adopted specific strategies to impede its spread. National health services have, therefore, been unprecedentedly challenged to assure adequate patient care, despite a constantly escalating demand for supportive drugs. This complex situation requires appropriate planning that is deeply affected by many aspects, such as the long-term unpredictability of the pandemic evolution, the disruption and vulnerability of the supply chains,<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> and the timeliness required by the decision-making process. All these aspects can generate misleading estimations, which can deeply impact the efficiency of the assistance provided by healthcare facilities, resulting in either a lack of therapies or placing further pressure on already constrained drugs and the supply chain. For this reason, health professionals should use adequate tools that can support the calculation of therapeutic needs, especially for those patients that require intensive care. With this regard, modelling of the pandemic appears to be crucial. As reported in a previous work,<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> every country, province or hospital should carry out proper pandemic modelling based on the epidemiological features and adapted to the local population in terms of number of people and age distribution in order to tailor and optimise the estimates to their specific situation.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s2">
              <title>Aim of the study</title>
              <p>We decide to create an informatics supportive tool, the European COVID-19 Drugs Calculation Tool (ECDCT). This tool is capable of assisting pharmacists, local healthcare institutions, governments, partners and other stakeholder to easily estimate potential requirements for essential drug supplies to respond to the current COVID-19 pandemic based on epidemiological forecasting.</p>
              <p>We also wanted to share our methodological approach with other colleagues, so that our work might help to develop future strategies for the management of drug supplies during a pandemic emergency.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="materials" id="s3">
              <title>Materials and methods</title>
              <p>The ECDCT was developed using Microsoft Excel software and was structured as a user-friendly interactive application that allows users, through a series of guided paths, to enter data about the current epidemiological situation in various countries and geographical areas. Based on the data provided, the tool will output a drug needs estimation derived from an epidemiological forecasting model.</p>
              <sec id="s3-1">
                <title>Forecasting model</title>
                <p>Epidemiological forecasting was based on a susceptible-infected-removed (SIR) model,<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> which describes the transmission dynamics as the flow over time of individuals of a given population (N) through three mutually exclusive population compartments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">figure 1</xref>):</p>
                <list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Susceptible (S): healthy individuals at risk of becoming infected.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Infected (I): individuals who have already been infected by the virus and can transmit it to susceptible individuals.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>Removed (R): individuals who recovered from the virus and are assumed to be immune, or those who have died.</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
                <fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Figure 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Schematic visualisation of susceptible-infected-removed (SIR) compartments. The total population (N) is given by the sum of S+I+R compartments. At the early stage of an unprecedented pandemic, S can be approximated to N.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="ejhpharm-2020-002633f01"/>
                </fig>
                <p>Given the short timespans involved, it is assumed that the total population does not change significantly during the forecasted period as the births and deaths unrelated to the infection can be neglected and the number of deaths from the virus is small compared with the living population. Moreover, no immigration and emigration phenomena were considered, since movements between countries are restricted during outbreaks. We also assumed that the population is well mixed and every person interacts with one another. Finally, we assumed that all infected people are infectious and are spreading the disease among the susceptible population, and that people who are immune will not become susceptible again.</p>
                <p>Defining s=S/N, i=I/N, r=R/N as the fraction of the population in each compartment, the rates of change of the three populations are governed by the following system of ordinary differential equations:</p>
                <p>
                  <disp-formula id="E1">
                    <label>(1)</label>
                    <mml:math id="eqn1">
                      <mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0">
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mfrac>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi>
                            </mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:mfrac>
                          <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:mstyle>
                    </mml:math>
                  </disp-formula>
                </p>
                <p>
                  <disp-formula id="E2">
                    <label>(2)</label>
                    <mml:math id="eqn2">
                      <mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0">
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mfrac>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi>
                              </mml:mrow>
                            </mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:mfrac>
                          <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>ν</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:mstyle>
                    </mml:math>
                  </disp-formula>
                </p>
                <p>
                  <disp-formula id="E3">
                    <label>(3)</label>
                    <mml:math id="eqn3">
                      <mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0">
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mfrac>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mrow>
                                  <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi>
                                </mml:mrow>
                              </mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi>
                              </mml:mrow>
                            </mml:mfrac>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>ν</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:mstyle>
                    </mml:math>
                  </disp-formula>
                </p>
                <p>where β represents the rate of spread of infection by an infected person per day when they interact with the susceptible population, and ν is the rate of removal that governs the number of removed people. As β and ν can be difficult to obtain by the average user, we calculate the expected infected individuals based on the basic reproduction number (R<sub>0</sub>), which can be calculated as:</p>
                <p>
                  <disp-formula id="E4">
                    <label>(4)</label>
                    <mml:math id="eqn4">
                      <mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0">
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                            <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mi>τ</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo>
                            <mml:msup>
                              <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">c</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                            </mml:msup>
                            <mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:mstyle>
                    </mml:math>
                  </disp-formula>
                </p>
                <p>where τ=infection/contact, c=contact/time, d=time/infection. Since β and ν can be respectively defined as β = τ c and d = ν −1, we calculated β as:</p>
                <p>
                  <disp-formula id="E5">
                    <label>(5)</label>
                    <mml:math id="eqn5">
                      <mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0">
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mfrac>
                              <mml:msub>
                                <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mrow>
                                  <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                                </mml:mrow>
                              </mml:msub>
                              <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi>
                            </mml:mfrac>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:mstyle>
                    </mml:math>
                  </disp-formula>
                </p>
                <p>We augmented our SIR model by including the effects of Non-Pharmaceutical Interventions (NPIs), a series of public health containment measures, on the R effective (R<sub>t</sub>) value, as reported by the Covidactnow Response Simulator,<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> and by correcting the number of infected people according to the testing capacity, as shown by the WHO COVID-19 Essential Supplies Forecasting Tool.<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Finally, we set the default tuning values of the ECDCT based on what reported in the scientific literature,<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6–13</xref> as illustrated in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>.</p>
                <table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 1</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>List of assumptions made to tune the susceptible-infected-removed (SIR) model</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Assumptions group</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specific parameter</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Value</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Additional notes</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">References</td>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="3" colspan="1">R<sub>0</sub></td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">C</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12,5</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average rate of contact between susceptible and infected<break/>individuals</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="3" colspan="1">
                          <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">τ</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,68%</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Probability of infection given contact between a susceptible and infected individual</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Duration of infectiousness</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Hospitalisation details</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of stay of<break/>hospitalised non-ICU patients</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="3" colspan="1">
                          <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7 8</xref>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of stay of hospitalised ICU patients</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of stay in ICU</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="7" colspan="1">Clinical features</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% of ventilated ICU patients</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70%</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
                          <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% of intubated ICU patients</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50%</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% of shock ICU patients</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35%</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average days until hospitalisation</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% of mild and moderate cases</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80%</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hospitalisation rate</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inferred</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depending on the population’s age group and the corresponding risk of hospitalisation according to Imperial College data</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">
                          <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% hospitalised in ICU</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inferred</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Depending on the population’s age group and the corresponding risk of critical care need according to Imperial College data</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Testing</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% mild/moderate cases detected by test</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10%</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage of infected individuals with mild or moderate symptoms that will be detected by testing</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6 12</xref>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="18" colspan="1">Non-pharmaceutical interventions</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min R<sub>t</sub> with 100% mask compliance</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum R<sub>t</sub> value achieved with all the population wearing masks</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="17" colspan="1">
                          <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mask spread reduction</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% reduction of infectious spread by those infected wearing masks</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mask protection level</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% protection of those susceptible wearing masks</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min R<sub>t</sub> with complete shelter in place</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum R<sub>t</sub> value achieved with all the population sheltering in place</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Susceptible shelter in place efficacy</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of susceptible who will actually shelter in place</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Infected shelter in place efficacy</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of infected who will actually shelter in place</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Closure NPI min R<sub>t</sub></td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum R<sub>t</sub> value achieved with the closure of all the activities, not taking into account masks and sheltering in place</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Schools and universities (R<sub>t</sub> impact)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,2</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="10" colspan="1">Maximum contribution provided by the closure of each specific activity (100% compliance) on the Rt value</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Large events (Rt impact)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bars/restaurants (Rt impact)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Offices and factories (Rt impact)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">House of worship (Rt impact)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Personal care (Rt impact)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-essential retail (Rt impact)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Essential retail (Rt impact)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Entertainment (Rt impact)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outdoor recreation (Rt impact)</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lag time before NPIs impact the Rt (days), suggested values 14–21</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Delay between the date of NPI implementation and the date of their observable maximum impact on the Rt value</td>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>
                        </td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                  <table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="T1_FN1">
                      <p>NPI, non-pharmaceutical intervention; R<sub>t</sub>, R effective.</p>
                    </fn>
                  </table-wrap-foot>
                </table-wrap>
                <p>Although many more complex epidemiological models exist, we adopted the SIR because:</p>
                <list list-type="bullet">
                  <list-item>
                    <p>it is easier for users with limited epidemiological competences as it requires fewer variables, easily obtained through official sources;</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>it allows removal of many of the complexities associated with the real-time evolution of the virus’ spread, while still providing a good estimation, both quantitatively and qualitatively<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>;</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>our forecasting needs did not require a highly accurate model on a short-time period, but one that could capture the fundamental human-to-human transmission dynamics of the pandemic, as the final aim of the ECDCT is estimation of drugs needs throughout the whole COVID-19 surge;</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item>
                    <p>it is widely adopted in the scientific literature<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14 15</xref> and other similar forecasting tools,<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6 7</xref> although with some ad-hoc variations.</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3-2">
                <title>Drugs selection</title>
                <p>The drugs included in the ECDCT were selected by reviewing published scientific works, national and international guidelines,<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3 6 16–21</xref> and adjusted according to local practices.</p>
                <p>As the treatment guidelines for patients with non-critical disease, at the time of writing, are still not exhaustively defined and most of the drugs are used when needed and depending on the patient’s clinical features, such as the need for oxygen supplementation, it is hard to accurately quantify the demand for drugs in this patient population. For this reason, we provide specific drugs need estimations only for patients requiring critical care (ICU).</p>
                <p>The calculation method adopted was informed by a previously published scientific work<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> considering the patient and treatment characteristics assumptions, such as the percentage uptake of a drug group, treatment duration for each drug, drug dosages and percentage usage within a drug group.</p>
                <p>The dosages entered were chosen on the basis of the most likely daily dosages according to what is reported in the scientific literature. When there was uncertainty or in the case of emergency medications for which the dosage ranges can vary widely (eg, naloxone, flumazenil), the Lexicomp maximum dosages were used as reference.</p>
                <p>Some of the assumptions made for the drugs needed that are influenced by local practices and availability of drugs (dosages, duration of treatments for specific indications, and others) have been designed to be modifiable by the users in order to better adapt the estimation to their different clinical needs.</p>
                <sec id="s3-2-1">
                  <title>Additional data sources</title>
                  <p>To aid the ECDCT compiling process, we included data about the population and the number of hospital beds by country, extrapolated by the World Bank.<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22 23</xref> Moreover, the number of people was stratified by age groups based on the age distribution by income, with data extrapolated from the United Nations,<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> and the specific income group of each country. These values were used to infer the percentage of patients with symptoms who would require hospitalisation and critical care in the population considered, based on the standard percentages reported by Imperial College.<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results" id="s4">
              <title>Results</title>
              <p>The final version of the ECDCT consists of an Excel template in which it is possible, through a guided and structured user form, to enter all the epidemiological data required to perform the forecasting, such as population selection, R<sub>0</sub> value, initial epidemiological situation, NPIs and availability of hospital beds. In particular, the population considered can be either chosen from a specific country or manually entered. For the R<sub>0</sub> value, it is possible to enter the whole value, or to specify the single epidemiological parameters described in equation 4.</p>
              <p>Information about the initial epidemiological situation refers to the total number of patients who tested positive for COVID-19 and those who were admitted to hospital and were logged on the day of the analysis. Because some of the forecasted values (eg, patients admitted to hospital) depend on the epidemiological situation of the previous few days, we achieved better modelling of the early stages of the analysis by including the epidemiological data relating to either 14 days prior to, or the day of the start of the pandemic (when the first cases occurred), if it happened less than 14 days earlier. This last option is especially useful in case there is a resurgence of the SARS-CoV2 infection after a period of no new detected cases. We considered a maximum threshold of 14 days because it corresponds to the average duration of the infection, with an incubating period of 4 days,<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> a contagious period of 5 days<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> and a convalescence period of 5 days.<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> This epidemiological information is used to automatically distribute the number of cases occurring in the aforementioned interval according to an exponential or linear growth, based on the user’s preferences. As reported by Cooper and colleagues,<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> at the beginning of the epidemic, when R<sub>t</sub> &gt;1 and S ≈ 1, the rate of infection obtained through a SIR model can be described by an exponential increase, and thus equation 2 can be approximated to:</p>
              <p>
                <disp-formula id="E6">
                  <label>(6)</label>
                  <mml:math id="eqn6">
                    <mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0">
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mfrac>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi>
                            </mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:mfrac>
                          <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mi>ν</mml:mi>
                            </mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mstyle>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              </p>
              <p>
                <disp-formula id="E7">
                  <label>(7)</label>
                  <mml:math id="eqn7">
                    <mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0">
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                            <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:msup>
                            <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mi>β</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mo>−</mml:mo>
                                <mml:mi>ν</mml:mi>
                              </mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:msup>
                          <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mstyle>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              </p>
              <p>which can be rewritten as</p>
              <p>
                <disp-formula id="E8">
                  <label>(8)</label>
                  <mml:math id="eqn8">
                    <mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0">
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                            <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:msup>
                            <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
                          </mml:msup>
                          <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mstyle>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              </p>
              <p>In ECDCT, because the number of people with infection at the beginning and at the end of the interval considered are known, we inferred λ as:</p>
              <p>
                <disp-formula id="E9">
                  <label>(9)</label>
                  <mml:math id="eqn9">
                    <mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0">
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:msub>
                            <mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:msub>
                          <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">l</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mo>[</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                                <mml:msub>
                                  <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi>
                                  <mml:mrow>
                                    <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi>
                                  </mml:mrow>
                                </mml:msub>
                                <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                              </mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
                              </mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                                <mml:msub>
                                  <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi>
                                  <mml:mrow>
                                    <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                                  </mml:mrow>
                                </mml:msub>
                                <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                              </mml:mrow>
                            </mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mo>]</mml:mo>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mo>/</mml:mo>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:msub>
                            <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:msub>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mstyle>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              </p>
              <p>Where t<sub>0</sub> and t<sub>d</sub> are, respectively, the beginning and the end of the interval.</p>
              <p>Finally, we fitted the exponential growth of the infected population as:</p>
              <p>
                <disp-formula id="E10">
                  <label>(10)</label>
                  <mml:math id="eqn10">
                    <mml:mstyle displaystyle="true" scriptlevel="0">
                      <mml:mrow>
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                          <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                            <mml:msub>
                              <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                              </mml:mrow>
                            </mml:msub>
                            <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                          </mml:mrow>
                          <mml:msubsup>
                            <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">f</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi>
                            </mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>λ</mml:mi>
                          </mml:msubsup>
                          <mml:mi mathvariant="normal">t</mml:mi>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:mrow>
                    </mml:mstyle>
                  </mml:math>
                </disp-formula>
              </p>
              <p>The linear growth uniformly distributes the number of cases occurring in the interval considered, and can be used when the exponential growth is not reliable, such as in extremely short timespans or in the mid-late stage of the pandemic surge.</p>
              <p>The tool also includes a set of NPIs, such as the closure of activities, the use of masks and the sheltering in place of the population. Concerning the type of closure, the users are allowed to choose between a default set of activity closures or assigning each of them individually. As reported in other works,<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5 26</xref> we included a factor (that we called percentage of closure and adherence), which represents the percentage of compliance with the public health measures on a scale from 0 (no intervention) to 1 (maximum measure’s compliance). We also included an additional parameter relating to the lag time before the NPIs’ full impact on R<sub>t</sub>, which is the delay between the date of NPIs’ implementation and the date of their observable maximum impact on the R<sub>t</sub> value. In fact, as has been previously reported in another work,<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> there are a series of factors (eg, virus incubation and delay in lab testing) that generate a delayed detection of the NPIs’ effect. Therefore, the evaluation of the NPIs’ effect may require an observational period of 2–3 weeks.<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref> During this time frame, the R<sub>t</sub> reduction is step-wisely achieved by subtracting an increasing percentage of the total NPI effect, calculated as follows:</p>
              <p>NPI reduction on R<sub>t</sub> * (number of days that have passed since the NPI implementation date / the total number of lag days).</p>
              <p>Hospital beds were inferred for each country by considering the average number of beds/1000 inhabitants and adjusted by the country’s total population. When calculating critical care bed numbers, or when data were missing, we used the average number of beds/1000 inhabitants for the appropriate country’s income group, as reported by the Imperial College.<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></p>
              <p>If the forecasting is performed based on a manually entered population, the ECDCT allows one to specify the number of beds available, and whether those beds are used to assist the whole population or just a percentage of it. Using the latter option, drug estimation will be performed only for the specified percentage of the total number forecasted to be infected, which could be useful for single hospitals that are likely to assist only a fraction of all patients who will need hospitalisation within the area considered.</p>
              <p>Hospital bed availability is a key parameter in our calculation because it is used to set the maximum amount of drugs needed since the total number of hospital beds corresponds to the maximum number of patients that will be therapeutically assisted (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">figure 2</xref>).</p>
              <fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Figure 2</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>Comparison between the predicted hospital bed demand and the real hospitalisation capacity simulated using the European COVID-19 drugs calculation tool (ECDCT). For this simulation, the following values were used: population=59 132 073, R<sub>0</sub>=2.35, total number of cases=1 400 000, active cases=700 000, patients in hospital=35 000, new cases=23 000, total number of cases 14 days previously=600 000, new cases 14 days previously=20 000, total hospital beds available=201 049, percentage of mild/moderate cases detected by test=33%. No NPIs (non-pharmaceutical implementation) was considered.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ejhpharm-2020-002633f02"/>
              </fig>
              <p>The ECDCT also includes a series of editable epidemiological parameters that are useful to finely tune the tool, as reported in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>. Among them, the percentage of patients with mild to moderate severity of symptoms that are detected by tests is of particular note because it is used to calculate the number of patients admitted to hospital. According to scientific evidence, the percentage of undocumented infections (not tested) at the beginning of the outbreak ranged between 82% and 90%.<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> Because patients with severe to critical symptoms are the least likely to remain undetected, we decided to consider the percentage of undocumented infections as relating exclusively to patients with mild to moderate symptoms. Therefore, the default percentage of mild to moderate cases detected by test is set equal to 10%,<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> but it will be updated according to the latest scientific evidence.</p>
              <p>To improve data visualisation about the epidemiological progression and hospital bed availability, we introduced a summary dashboard where the information is displayed through both charts and tables.</p>
              <p>Finally, the estimation of drugs based on the number of patients obtained with the SIR model is performed considering the list of drugs selected. This list includes 51 drugs belonging to 19 therapeutic groups (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SP1">online supplemental table</xref>). For each drug we specify the active principle, the daily dose, the pharmaceutical form, the percentage uptake of the drug group, the percentage usage within a drug group and the treatment duration for each drug. In case of therapeutically equivalent alternatives, the users are allowed to select their preferred choice. As reported by Hogg and colleagues,<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> the total amount of drug is calculated as follows: the adjusted amount of a specific drug used=daily dose * % of use in ICU (according to therapeutic group) * % of use in ICU (according to each active principle) * average treatment length (days). This adjusted amount is then multiplied by the total number of patients in the timeframe considered.</p>
              <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SP1">
                <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/ejhpharm-2020-002633.supp1</object-id>
                <label>Supplementary data</label>
                <p>
                  <inline-supplementary-material id="SS1" xlink:href="ejhpharm-2020-002633supp001.pdf" mime-subtype="pdf" mimetype="application" content-type="local-data"/>
                </p>
              </supplementary-material>
              <p>In our tool, the value obtained is then divided by a specific dosage available on the market (editable by the users) to calculate the total amount of unit doses required. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">figure 3</xref> an example of drug estimation output is reported.</p>
              <fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Figure 3</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>A representative example of the drug estimation output. The drugs amount displayed in the ICU table refers to 5015 patients in ICU, as reported in the ′sum of new ICU patients′ field above the timeline.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="ejhpharm-2020-002633f03"/>
              </fig>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion" id="s5">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>As previously stated, predictive models for epidemics are fundamental to understand the course of the epidemic and to plan effective strategies.<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> In particular, as outlined in a previously published paper,<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> some of the features of a forecasting model should be:</p>
              <list list-type="bullet">
                <list-item>
                  <p>pragmatic and focusing only on the relevant question for surge capacity;</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>taking into account the most relevant data such as R<sub>0</sub> of the virus, the expected or observed rate of hospitalisation, need for ICU, need for mechanical ventilation, ICU length of stay;</p>
                </list-item>
                <list-item>
                  <p>incorporating the impact of installing social distancing measures in society and their delayed impact on case detection.</p>
                </list-item>
              </list>
              <p>In the ECDCT, we sought to implement all these features to create a tool that could represent a useful aid to estimate potential requirements for essential drug supplies to respond to the current COVID-19 pandemic.</p>
              <p>The main goal of our work was to find a compromise between the creation of an accessible and user-friendly interface and an adequate capacity to capture the fundamental dynamics of the pandemic and thus capable of performing reliable drugs estimation. This aim has informed every developmental decision, such as the choice of basing our epidemiological forecasting on a SIR model, and the adoption of a well defined drugs calculation methodology, which can be easily personalised according to the users’ needs, through a series of editable parameters.</p>
              <p>However, it should be considered that the reference values used to tune our model, as with every other model, are often the result of data of questionable quality and homogeneity. As suggested by Casella,<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> there can be remarkable differences between countries’ standards and capacity for swab testing, data lost due to clerical errors, and the NPIs′ effectiveness that is still quite uncertain.</p>
              <p>Particularly, the NPIs′ effectiveness, in order to be statistically significant, is evaluated by grouping together countries with very different social habits and interpretations of the same measure (eg, lockdown) in the same dataset. Additionally, it should be noted that the impact of NPIs can differ according to a country’s income group.<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></p>
              <p>Another critical aspect to consider is the fast evolution of available data, which require constant updating of the relevant parameters to ensure that the forecasting always mirrors the current epidemiological and clinical situation. This is particularly true for the lab testing capacity, which has increased since the beginning of the pandemic,<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> and the list of drugs included because the therapeutic guidelines and protocols for patients with SARS-CoV-2 have extensively changed over time.<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s6">
              <title>Conclusion</title>
              <p>Despite its intrinsic limitations, we believe that the ECDCT can still be an effective aid for the health professionals’ workflow. Moreover, all the information reported in this paper can represent a useful aid to guide our colleagues in the development of their own methods and tools to tackle the COVID-19 pandemic. The evaluation of the possible benefits derived from the introduction of ECDCT in daily drug management will be an interesting subject for future works.</p>
              <boxed-text id="BX1" position="float" orientation="portrait">
                <caption>
                  <title>What this paper adds</title>
                </caption>
                <sec>
                  <title>What is already known on this subject</title>
                  <list list-type="bullet">
                    <list-item>
                      <p>the COVID-19 pandemic represents a global health emergency that has exacerbated pharmaceutical demand</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>the emergency aspect of the pandemic makes it necessary to estimate pharmaceutical needs in a short time</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>considering that it is a new virus, it is not possible to use historical consumption data as a reference</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>What this study adds</title>
                  <list list-type="bullet">
                    <list-item>
                      <p>the description of an informatics tool that allows users to make a timely estimate of pharmaceutical needs</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <p>a drugs forecasting method based on an epidemiological model that can be customised to different settings, needs or other future pandemics</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                </sec>
              </boxed-text>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <fn-group>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Contributors:</bold> DLV and AM developed the tool and wrote the manuscript. PP and AP contributed in the bibliographic research and writing of the manuscript. MEF, NM, DM and PH revised the manuscript.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Funding:</bold> The authors have not declared a specific grant for this research from any funding agency in the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
                <p><bold>Competing interests:</bold> None declared.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Patient consent for publication:</bold> Not required.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Data availability statement:</bold> All data relevant to the study are included in the article or uploaded as supplementary information. No patients data included.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn fn-type="other">
                <p><bold>Supplemental material:</bold> This content has been supplied by the author(s). It has not been vetted by BMJ Publishing Group Limited (BMJ) and may not have been peer-reviewed. Any opinions or recommendations discussed are solely those of the author(s) and are not endorsed by BMJ. BMJ disclaims all liability and responsibility arising from any reliance placed on the content. Where the content includes any translated material, BMJ does not warrant the accuracy and reliability of the translations (including but not limited to local regulations, clinical guidelines, terminology, drug names and drug dosages), and is not responsible for any error and/or omissions arising from translation and adaptation or otherwise.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="R1">
                <label>1</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>An interactive web-based dashboard to track COVID-19 in real time</article-title>. <source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>533</fpage>–<lpage>4</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(20)30120-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/32087114?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32087114</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R2">
                <label>2</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Leonardi Vinci</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Polidori</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Polidori</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>The healthcare and pharmaceutical vulnerability emerging from the new coronavirus outbreak</article-title>. <source>Eur J Hosp Pharm</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>129</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/ejhpharm-2020-002278</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/32419930?></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R3">
                <label>3</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hota</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fried</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burry</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Preparing your intensive care unit for the second wave of H1N1 and future surges</article-title>. <source>Crit Care Med</source><year>2010</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>e110</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/CCM.0b013e3181c66940</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19935417?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19935417</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R4">
                <label>4</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></string-name></person-group><source>Notes on R0</source>. <volume>323</volume><publisher-loc>California</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Department of Anthropological Sciences</publisher-name>, <year>2007</year>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>19</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R5">
                <label>5</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Covidactnow</collab></person-group><article-title>COVID response simulator</article-title>. Available: <uri xlink:href="https://covidactnow.org/resources">https://covidactnow.org/resources</uri> [Accessed <comment>Nov 2020</comment>].</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R6">
                <label>6</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>WHO</collab></person-group><article-title>COVID-19 essential supplies forecasting tool</article-title>, <year>2020</year> Available: <uri xlink:href="https://www.who.int/publications/m/item/covid-19-essential-supplies-forecasting-tool">https://www.who.int/publications/m/item/covid-19-essential-supplies-forecasting-tool</uri> [Accessed <comment>Nov 2020</comment>].</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R7">
                <label>7</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Adhikari</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Greening</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>COVID19Surge: a manual to assist state and local public health officials and hospital administrators in estimating the impact of a novel coronavirus pandemic on hospital surge capacity (beta test version). centers for disease control and prevention, U.S. department of health and human services</article-title><year>2020</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R8">
                <label>8</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Eubank</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eckstrand</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Commentary on Ferguson, et al., "Impact of Non-pharmaceutical Interventions (NPIs) to Reduce COVID-19 Mortality and Healthcare Demand"</article-title>. <source>Bull Math Biol</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>82</volume>:<elocation-id>52</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11538-020-00726-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/32270376?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32270376</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R9">
                <label>9</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arabi</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alhazzani</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Managing ICU surge during the COVID-19 crisis: rapid guidelines</article-title>. <source>Intensive Care Med</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>1303</fpage>–<lpage>25</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00134-020-06092-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/32514598?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32514598</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R10">
                <label>10</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Management of critically ill patients with COVID-19 in ICU: statement from front-line intensive care experts in Wuhan, China</article-title>. <source>Ann Intensive Care</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<elocation-id>73</elocation-id>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13613-020-00689-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/32506258?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32506258</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R11">
                <label>11</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>W-J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ni</surname><given-names>Z-Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Clinical characteristics of coronavirus disease 2019 in China</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>382</volume>:<fpage>1708</fpage>–<lpage>20</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2002032</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/32109013?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32109013</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R12">
                <label>12</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Substantial undocumented infection facilitates the rapid dissemination of novel coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2)</article-title>. <source>Science</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>368</volume>:<fpage>489</fpage>–<lpage>93</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abb3221</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/32179701?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32179701</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R13">
                <label>13</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Flaxman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Estimating the number of infections and the impact of non-pharmaceutical interventions on COVID-19 in 11 European countries</article-title>. <source>Imperial College London, Tech Rep</source><year>2020</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R14">
                <label>14</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mondal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Antonopoulos</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>A Sir model assumption for the spread of COVID-19 in different communities</article-title>. <source>Chaos Solitons Fractals</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>139</volume>:<fpage>110057</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chaos.2020.110057</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/32834610?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32834610</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R15">
                <label>15</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Anand</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sabarinath</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Geetha</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Predicting the Spread of COVID-19 Using $$SIR$$ Model Augmented to Incorporate Quarantine and Testing</article-title>. <source>Trans Indian Natl Acad Eng</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>141</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s41403-020-00151-5</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R16">
                <label>16</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>COVID-19 Treatment Guidelines Panel</collab></person-group><article-title>Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) treatment guidelines. National Institutes of health</article-title>. Available: <uri xlink:href="https://www.covid19treatmentguidelines.nih.gov/">https://www.covid19treatmentguidelines.nih.gov/</uri> [Accessed <comment>Nov 2020</comment>].</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R17">
                <label>17</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hogg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huey</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Informing critical care drug requirements in response to the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>. <source>Eur J Hosp Pharm</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>263</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/ejhpharm-2020-002368</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/32661105?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32661105</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R18">
                <label>18</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Veklury product informations</collab></person-group><article-title>EMEA/H/C/005622</article-title><year>2020</year>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R19">
                <label>19</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Anticoagulant treatment is associated with decreased mortality in severe coronavirus disease 2019 patients with coagulopathy</article-title>. <source>J Thromb Haemost</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>1094</fpage>–<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jth.14817</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/32220112?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32220112</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R20">
                <label>20</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Renew</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ratzlaff</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hernandez-Torres</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Neuromuscular blockade management in the critically ill patient</article-title>. <source>J Intensive Care</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40560-020-00455-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/32483489?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32483489</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R21">
                <label>21</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>N-N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Postonogova</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Intravenous lidocaine to prevent postoperative airway complications in adults: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Br J Anaesth</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>124</volume>:<fpage>314</fpage>–<lpage>23</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bja.2019.11.033</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/32000978?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32000978</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R22">
                <label>22</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="web"><article-title>The world bank, hospital beds (per 1,000 people)</article-title>. Available: <uri xlink:href="https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SH.MED.BEDS.ZS">https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SH.MED.BEDS.ZS</uri> [Accessed <comment>Nov 2020</comment>].</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R23">
                <label>23</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="web"><article-title>The world bank, population total</article-title>. Available: <uri xlink:href="https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SP.POP.TOTL">https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SP.POP.TOTL</uri> [Accessed <comment>Nov 2020</comment>].</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R24">
                <label>24</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>United Nations</collab></person-group><article-title>Population by age group both sexes</article-title>. Available: <uri xlink:href="https://population.un.org/wpp/DataQuery/">https://population.un.org/wpp/DataQuery/</uri> [Accessed <comment>Nov 2020</comment>].</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R25">
                <label>25</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Peak</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kahn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grad</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Individual quarantine versus active monitoring of contacts for the mitigation of COVID-19: a modelling study</article-title>. <source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>1025</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(20)30361-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/32445710?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32445710</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R26">
                <label>26</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Casella</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Can the COVID-19 epidemic be controlled on the basis of daily test reports?</article-title><source>IEEE Control Systems Letters</source>, <year>2021</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>1079</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/LCSYS.2020.3009912</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R27">
                <label>27</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Giordano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Blanchini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bruno</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>Modelling the COVID-19 epidemic and implementation of population-wide interventions in Italy</article-title>. <source>Nat Med</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>26</volume>:<fpage>855</fpage>–<lpage>60</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-020-0883-7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/32322102?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32322102</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R28">
                <label>28</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>PGT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Whittaker</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>The impact of COVID-19 and strategies for mitigation and suppression in low- and middle-income countries</article-title>. <source>Science</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>369</volume>:<fpage>413</fpage>–<lpage>22</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abc0035</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/32532802?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32532802</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R29">
                <label>29</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hasell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mathieu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beltekian</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group><article-title>A cross-country database of COVID-19 testing</article-title>. <source>Sci Data</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>345</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41597-020-00688-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/33033256?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33033256</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="R30">
                <label>30</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Provenzani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Polidori</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group><article-title>Covid-19 and drug therapy, what we learned</article-title>. <source>Int J Clin Pharm</source><year>2020</year>;<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>833</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11096-020-01049-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/32382873?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32382873</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
