<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-03-11T00:54:36Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7897405" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7897405</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-02-22</datestamp>
        <setSpec>pheelsevier</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Value Health</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Value Health</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Value in Health</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">1098-3015</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1524-4733</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>ISPOR-The Professional Society for Health Economics and Outcomes Research. Published by Elsevier Inc.</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC7897405</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7897405</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">7897405</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33933229</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pii">S1098-3015(21)00033-4</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jval.2020.12.009</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Themed Section: COVID-19</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Disease Burden Attributable to the First Wave of COVID-19 in China and the Effect of Timing on the Cost-Effectiveness of Movement Restriction Policies</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Zhao</surname>
                    <given-names>Jidi</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Jin</surname>
                    <given-names>Huajie</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Li</surname>
                    <given-names>Xun</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Jia</surname>
                    <given-names>Jianguo</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Zhang</surname>
                    <given-names>Chao</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Zhao</surname>
                    <given-names>Huijuan</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ma</surname>
                    <given-names>Wuren</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au8">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Wang</surname>
                    <given-names>Zhuozhu</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">5</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au9">
                  <name>
                    <surname>He</surname>
                    <given-names>Yi</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">6</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au10">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Lee</surname>
                    <given-names>Jimmy</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">7</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au15">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Zhang</surname>
                    <given-names>Donglan</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff8" ref-type="aff">8</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au11">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Yin</surname>
                    <given-names>Bo</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff9" ref-type="aff">9</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au12">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Zheng</surname>
                    <given-names>Weiwei</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff10" ref-type="aff">10</xref>
                  <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">∗</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au13">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Wang</surname>
                    <given-names>Haiyin</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff11" ref-type="aff">11</xref>
                  <xref rid="cor2" ref-type="corresp">∗∗</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au14">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Pennington</surname>
                    <given-names>Mark</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Public Administration, College of Economics and Management, East China Normal University, Shanghai, China</aff>
                <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>King’s Health Economics, Health Service and Population Research Department, Institute of Psychiatry, Psychology, and Neuroscience at King’s College London, London, UK</aff>
                <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Environmental Health, School of Public Health, Fudan University, Shanghai, China</aff>
                <aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>Development Institute, Tongji University, Shanghai, China</aff>
                <aff id="aff5"><label>5</label>Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, Zhejiang, China</aff>
                <aff id="aff6"><label>6</label>Curtin University of Technology, (WA) Australia, Bentley WA, Australia</aff>
                <aff id="aff7"><label>7</label>University of California, Los Angeles, Los Angeles, CA, USA</aff>
                <aff id="aff8"><label>8</label>Department of Health Policy and Management, College of Public Health, University of Georgia, Athens, GA, USA</aff>
                <aff id="aff9"><label>9</label>Huashan Hospital, Fudan University, Shanghai, China</aff>
                <aff id="aff10"><label>10</label>Department of Environmental Health, School of Public Health, Fudan University, Shanghai, China</aff>
                <aff id="aff11"><label>11</label>Health Technology Assessment Research Department, Shanghai Health Development Research Centre, Shanghai, China</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label><bold>Correspondence:</bold> Weiwei Zheng, No. 130 Dongan Road, Shanghai 200032, China.</corresp>
                <corresp id="cor2"><label>∗∗</label>or Haiyin Wang, No. 181 Xinbei Road, Shanghai 201199, China.</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>21</day>
                <month>2</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.-->
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <month>5</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>21</day>
                <month>2</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>24</volume>
              <issue>5</issue>
              <fpage>615</fpage>
              <lpage>624</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>13</day>
                  <month>12</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2021 ISPOR-The Professional Society for Health Economics and Outcomes Research. Published by Elsevier Inc.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
                <copyright-holder>ISPOR–The Professional Society for Health Economics and Outcomes Research</copyright-holder>
                <license>
                  <license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="abs0010">
                <sec>
                  <title>Objectives</title>
                  <p>Movement restriction policies (MRPs) are effective in preventing/delaying COVID-19 transmission but are associated with high societal cost. This study aims to estimate the health burden of the first wave of COVID-19 in China and the cost-effectiveness of early versus late implementation of MRPs to inform preparation for future waves.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods</title>
                  <p>The SEIR (susceptible, exposed, infectious, and recovered) modeling framework was adapted to simulate the health and cost outcomes of initiating MRPs at different times: rapid implementation (January 23, the real-world scenario), delayed by 1 week, delayed by 2 weeks, and delayed by 4 weeks. The end point was set as the day when newly confirmed cases reached zero. Two costing perspectives were adopted: healthcare and societal. Input data were obtained from official statistics and published literature. The primary outcomes were disability-adjusted life-years, cost, and net monetary benefit. Costs were reported in both Chinese renminbi (RMB) and US dollars (USD) at 2019 values.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>The first wave of COVID-19 in China resulted in 38 348 disability adjusted life-years lost (95% CI 19 417-64 130) and 2639 billion RMB losses (95% CI 1347-4688). The rapid implementation strategy dominated all other delayed strategies. This conclusion was robust to all scenarios tested. At a willingness-to-pay threshold of 70 892 RMB (the national annual GDP per capita) per disability-adjusted life-year saved, the probability for the rapid implementation to be the optimal strategy was 96%.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusions</title>
                  <p>Early implementation of MRPs in response to COVID-19 reduced both the health burden and societal cost and thus should be used for future waves of COVID-19.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group id="kwrds0010">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>COVID-19</kwd>
                <kwd>cost-effectiveness analysis</kwd>
                <kwd>DALY</kwd>
                <kwd>disease burden</kwd>
                <kwd>movement restriction policies</kwd>
                <kwd>timing</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="sec1">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p id="p0025">Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2), also known as coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19), is an infectious disease that causes fever, cough, shortness of breath, pneumonia, and lung infections and results in high morbidity and mortality. Although many countries, such as China, Korea, Japan, and Singapore, have passed the peak of the first wave of the COVID-19 epidemic, recent epidemic data<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> and studies<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> have shown that a second wave of COVID-19 is likely to occur. Studies of the first wave showed that movement restriction policies (MRPs)—such as quarantine/isolation for suspected or confirmed cases and travel restrictions for the entire population of the country—are effective in preventing/delaying COVID-19 transition.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> However, MRPs could potentially result in huge productivity losses.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> Whether it is cost-effective to start MRPs early, when there are fewer cases and deaths, is a difficult question for decision makers.</p>
              <p id="p0030">Across countries, the period between the detection of the first case and the implementation of MRPs has varied. <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>
shows the timing of initial and national MRPs adopted by the governments of 6 countries to suppress COVID-19 transmission, starting from the official reporting of the first case in that country (data sources for <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> are reported in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix 1</xref> in Supplemental Materials found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.12.009" id="intref0010">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.12.009</ext-link>). The first MRP in China (movement restrictions in Wuhan, Hubei) started on January 23, 2020 (day 4), when the number of daily new cases and new deaths was 259 and 8, respectively. In the United Kingdom, movement restrictions were first imposed on March 23, 2020 (day 49), when the number of daily new cases and new deaths were 967 and 74, respectively. The effect of timing on the cost-effectiveness of MRPs is unknown. To help decision makers to identify the optimal timing of MRPs for future waves of COVID-19, this modeling study examines the health burden attributable to the first wave of COVID-19 in China and the cost-effectiveness of rapid versus delayed enforcement of MRPs by simulating the potential consequences of MRPs implemented at different time.<fig id="fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The period between the first public release of COVID-19 epidemic data and the implementation of MRPs in different countries. (A) Number of daily new cases of COVID-19 by country. (B) Number of daily new deaths of COVID-19 by country. Day 1 was defined as the first day of public release of COVID-19 epidemic data for each country. The dates of initial movement restrictions and movement restrictions were obtained from government reports and published news and are reported in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix 1</xref> in Supplemental Materials found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.12.009" id="intref0160">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.12.009</ext-link>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig></p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec2">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <p id="p0035">This study was reported according to the Consensus on Health Economics Evaluation Report Standards recommendations for reporting health economic evaluations.<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> This study did not access individual patient data. Hence, ethical approval and patient-informed consents were not required.</p>
              <sec id="sec2.1">
                <title>Population</title>
                <p id="p0040">The population of interest was all residents in China. This study focused on the first wave of COVID-19 outbreak. All imported cases from abroad were excluded. At the time of this study, imported cases constituted only 0.01% of all confirmed cases. Therefore, this exclusion is unlikely to impact on the results.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2.2">
                <title>Competing Strategies</title>
                <p id="p0045">Four competing strategies were compared. Strategy A represents the real-word scenario in China, where the first MRP started on January 23, 2020 and ended on March 25, 2020, when there were no more newly confirmed cases identified in mainland China. Strategies B, C, and D represent a 1-week, 2-week, and 4-week delay in the imposition of MRPs, respectively. For strategies B-D, MRPs end on the day when national newly confirmed cases reach zero.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2.3">
                <title>Perspective and Outcomes</title>
                <p id="p0050">Two costing perspectives were adopted: healthcare and societal. From the healthcare perspective, the cost components included identification, diagnosis, treatment, and follow-up of COVID-19. From the societal perspective, the cost components included direct healthcare costs (as described above), direct non-healthcare costs (quarantine for close contacts and suspected cases), and productivity losses. All costs were expressed in renminbi (RMB; 2019 value) and converted to US dollars (USD) using the Organization of Economic Cooperation and Development annual exchange rate for 2019 (1 USD = 6.91 RMB).<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>
</p>
                <p id="p0055">The primary outcomes were disability adjusted life-years (DALYs), cost, and net monetary benefit (NMB). DALY is a measure of overall health burden, expressed as the number of “healthy” years lost due to ill health, disability, or early death. The DALYs for a disease were calculated as the sum of the years of life lost (YLL) due to premature mortality in the population, and the years lost due to disability (YLD) for people living with the consequences/sequelae of the disease. DALY losses were discounted at a rate of 3%.<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> NMB is a summary statistic that represents the net value of an intervention in monetary terms after consideration of the cost. Health gains are valued according to the threshold willingness-to-pay (WTP) to avert a DALY. NMB is then calculated as (-DALY ∗ WTP threshold) – Cost. Incremental NMB measures the difference in NMB between alternative strategies. Secondary outcomes included the accumulated number of confirmed cases, quarantined/isolated people, and deaths.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2.4">
                <title>Model Structure</title>
                <p id="p0060">The transmission of COVID-19 in Hubei province and the other parts of China was simulated using a dynamic simulation model. The outputs of the model include the number of people infected, the number of people under quarantine, and fatalities. The SEIR framework, which models the flows of people between 4 states—susceptible (S), exposed (E), infectious (I), and recovered (R)—has been widely used in infectious disease modeling.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> The original SEIR framework assumes that individuals in the “exposed” (latent) state—those individuals who have been infected but are currently asymptomatic—are not infectious. However, asymptomatic individuals infected with SARS-CoV-2 are infectious.<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> In addition, the original SEIR framework does not explicitly consider the impact of large-scale quarantine on close contacts of suspected or confirmed cases and individuals with recent traveling history, or the impact of the lockdown of cities in Hubei province. Therefore, the original SEIR framework was adapted for this study to model the infectiousness of asymptomatic individuals in the latent period and the impact of quarantine and city lockdown. System dynamic modeling was chosen to implement the adapted SEIR framework because it can capture complex feedback loops within a system and investigate how the system evolves over time under various scenarios.</p>
                <p id="p0065">To capture the initial spread of COVID-19 in Hubei province, prior to transmission to other parts of China, two submodels were built within our model (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>
): submodel A simulates disease transmission in Hubei province, whereas submodel B simulates disease transmission in other parts of China. Patients who are not quarantined or isolated can move between submodel A and B, to simulate the disease transmission resulting from population movement between Hubei provinces and other parts of China. Within each submodel, there are 2 modules: one represents individuals who are quarantined or isolated (yellow boxes in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>), and another represents individuals who are not quarantined or isolated (gray boxes in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). It was assumed that disease transmission can happen only within individuals who are not under quarantine; that is, only “susceptible” individuals not under quarantine may contact the disease, after being in contact with “exposed” or “infectious” individuals who are not under quarantine. Not all “susceptible” individuals in contact with “exposed” or “infectious” individuals will be infected. Those “susceptible” individuals who become infected but are currently asymptomatic enter the “exposed” state and are infectious. After the latent period, these “exposed” individuals become symptomatic and more infectious and move to the “infectious” state. According to the Chinese clinical guidelines for COVID-19,<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> all confirmed cases are admitted to the hospital regardless of the severity of their illness. Therefore, the model assumed that all identified “infectious” individuals (ie, those who are already under quarantine/isolation) move to the “hospital” state. Unidentified “infectious” individuals (ie, those who are not under quarantine/isolation) may remain unidentified and achieve recovery with little medical intervention or be admitted to hospital if their symptoms worsen. All “infectious” individuals are at risk of death. Identified and unidentified “infectious” individuals surviving COVID-19 enter the “recovered” phase after the infectious period is over. “Recovered” individuals are assumed to acquire long-term immunity to COVID-19. The detailed definition of each health state, and the parameters and the mathematical equations for simulating population flow among different health states, are described in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix 2.1-2.3</xref> in Supplemental Materials found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.12.009" id="intref0015">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.12.009</ext-link>. A detailed description of the types of MRPs simulated in the model is reported in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix 2.4</xref> in Supplemental Materials found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.12.009" id="intref0020">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.12.009</ext-link>. A list of all key assumptions of the model are reported in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix 2.5</xref> in Supplemental Materials found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.12.009" id="intref0025">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.12.009</ext-link>.<fig id="fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Epidemiological model structure. Susceptible = susceptible individuals who have not contracted a COVID-19 infection; Exposed = individuals who have been exposed but are currently asymptomatic, infectious; Infectious = infected individuals who have developed a symptomatic infection, infectious; Hospital = diagnosed infected individuals treated in the hospital; Recovered = infected individuals recovered from COVID-19.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2_lrg"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2.5">
                <title>Input Data</title>
                <p id="p0070">The epidemiological data, such as the number of newly confirmed cases, cumulative confirmed cases, cases under quarantine/isolation, deaths, and recovered cases, were obtained from the COVID-19 statistics data published by the National Health Commission and the Health Commission of Hubei province<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> and used to calibrate some parameters and validate our model (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>
). According to a recent observational study of 44 672 confirmed cases, 80.2% of confirmed cases were nonsevere cases, 13.6% were severe cases, and 6.2% were critical cases.<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> The migration data between Hubei province and other parts of China were obtained from the Baidu Migration website, which reports the number of people moving between Hubei province and other parts of China during the Spring Festival travel period 2019-2020 (see <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix 3</xref> in Supplemental Materials found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.12.009" id="intref0030">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.12.009</ext-link>). The total Chinese population was obtained from government statistics.<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> There is a lack of data on disability weights associated with COVID-19 infection. Based on expert opinion, the clinical respiratory symptoms of COVID-19 are comparable to chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) at different severity levels.<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref> Therefore, the disability weight of mild/moderate COPD (0.17) was used as a proxy for nonsevere COVID-19, while the disability weight of severe COPD (0.53) was used as a proxy for severe/critical COVID-19. The duration of illness was assumed to be 14 days and 42 days for moderate and critical cases, respectively. Gender-specific Chinese population life expectancies were obtained from the WHO life table.<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref> YLLs were calculated as loss of life expectancy at the age of death and weighted by the gender ratio (male 51% vs 49% female).<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> Resource use and unit costs were obtained from a recent cost-of-illness study conducted by Jin et al,<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> which estimated the healthcare and societal cost of COVID-19 in mainland China, based on government reports, clinical guidelines, and other published literature. The input data for cost-effectiveness analysis are summarized in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> and reported in detail in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix 4.1</xref> in Supplemental Materials found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.12.009" id="intref0035">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.12.009</ext-link>.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Summary of key input data.<xref rid="tbl1fnlowast" ref-type="table-fn">∗</xref></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Data</th><th>Base case value</th><th>Source</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="3"><bold>1. COVID-19</bold> <bold>epidemic in China</bold></td></tr><tr><td> 1.1 Total number of COVID-19 cases</td><td>83 650 (95% CI, 73 510-97 330)</td><td>[<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td> 1.2 Total COVID-19 deaths</td><td>3345 (95% CI, 3007-3905)</td><td>[<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><bold>2. Direct costs</bold></td></tr><tr><td> 2.1 Direct healthcare cost</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td> 2.1.1 Proportion of mild/moderate, severe, and critical case (%)</td><td>81.5%; 13.8%; 4.7%</td><td>[<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td> 2.1.2 Length of hospital stay for patients with mild/moderate, severe, and critical COVID-19 (day)</td><td>14; 21; 42</td><td>[<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td> 2.1.3 Average cost for close contact diagnosed as COVID-19 negative (RMB)</td><td>532</td><td>[<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Data</th><th>Base case value</th><th>Source</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td> 2.1.4 Average cost for suspected cases diagnosed as COVID-19 negative (RMB)</td><td align="char">1002</td><td>[<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td> 2.1.5  Average cost for confirmed case - nonsevere, severe, critical (RMB)</td><td>5601; 52 951; 151 344</td><td>[<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td> 2.2 Direct non-healthcare cost</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td> 2.2.1 Weighted quarantine cost for suspected cases diagnosed as COVID-19 negative (RMB)</td><td align="char">1170</td><td>[<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td> 2.2.2 Weighted quarantine cost for suspected cases diagnosed as COVID-19 positive (RMB)</td><td align="char">481</td><td>[<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td> 2.2.3 Weighted quarantine cost for all suspected cases (RMB)</td><td align="char">757</td><td>[<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Categories of data</th><th>Data value</th><th>Source</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td> 2.3 Total cost on risk allowance for medical staff (100 million RMB)</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td> 2.3.1 Number of front-line healthcare staff</td><td align="char">42 600</td><td>[<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td> 2.3.2 Daily allowance (RMB)</td><td align="char">300</td><td>[<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><bold>3. Indirect costs</bold></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td> 3.1 Productivity loss</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td> 3.1.1 National average salary per working day (RMB)</td><td align="char">272</td><td>[<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td> 3.1.2 Working time lost - people not considered to have had COVID-19 (day)</td><td align="char">23</td><td>[<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td> 3.1.3 Working time lost - close contact (day)</td><td align="char">28</td><td>[<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td> 3.1.4 Working time lost - suspected case (day)</td><td align="char">24</td><td>[<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Categories of data</th><th>Data value</th><th>Source</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td> 3.1.5 Working time lost - confirmed case - nonsevere, severe, critical, dead (day)</td><td>37; 41; 42; 44</td><td>[<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td> 3.2 National return to work index</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td> 3.2.1 March 3, 2020（%）</td><td align="char">57.42</td><td>[<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td> 3.2.2 March 10, 2020（%）</td><td align="char">64.15</td><td>[<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td> 3.2.3 March 17, 2020（%）</td><td align="char">69.95</td><td>[<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td> 3.2.4 March 24, 2020（%）</td><td align="char">74.82</td><td>[<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td><bold>4. DALY</bold></td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td> 4.1 Disability weight of mild/moderate COVID-19</td><td align="char">0.01</td><td>[<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td> 4.2 Duration of mild/moderate COVID-19 (year)</td><td align="char">0.04</td><td>[<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Categories of data</th><th>Data value</th><th>Source</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td> 4.3 Disability weight of severe/critical COVID-19</td><td>0.53</td><td>[<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td> 4.4 Duration of severe/critical COVID-19 (year)</td><td>0.12</td><td>[<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td> 4.5 Disability weight of sequela</td><td>0.17</td><td>[<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td> 4.6 Sequelae duration (year)</td><td>0.25</td><td>[<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl1fnlowast"><label>∗</label><p id="ntpara0015">A complete list of all input data with ranges and distributions are reported in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix 4.1</xref> in Supplemental Materials found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.12.009" id="intref0165">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.12.009</ext-link>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2.6">
                <title>Model Verification and Validation</title>
                <p id="p0075">Extensive model verification and validation activities were undertaken, including white-box tests (scrutinizing the programming code), black-box tests (testing the behavior of the model), and comparing results with real-world data. The model outputs under strategy A (“current practice”) were compared against the historical data published by the National Health Commission and the Health Commission of Hubei province.<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref> The comparison results (see <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix 5</xref> in Supplemental Materials found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.12.009" id="intref0040">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.12.009</ext-link>) indicate our model accurately simulated the trend of disease transition in Hubei province and other parts of China. On March 25, 2020, the differences between simulated outputs and historical data are very minor: 3.59% for cumulative number of confirmed cases, 1.92% for total number of cases under quarantine/isolation, and 1.76% for total number of deaths.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2.7">
                <title>Cost-Effectiveness Analysis</title>
                <p id="p0080">Based on the outputs of the system dynamic model (ie, the number of people infected, the number of people under quarantine, and fatalities), as well as published epidemiological data,<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> disutility data, and costing data,<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> the total DALY losses and costs were calculated for each strategy. In line with WHO recommendations,<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> the monetary value of a DALY was set at the national annual GDP per capita (70 892 RMB).<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> The strategy with the highest NMB was considered the most cost-effective.</p>
                <p id="p0085">Extensive sensitivity analyses were undertaken to test the robustness of the results to different sets of assumptions and different input data, including: (1) 1-way sensitivity analysis to assess the impact of uncertainty around the value of a single or multiple parameter(s); and (2) probabilistic sensitivity analysis, which examines the impact of joint uncertainty of multiple parameters simultaneously. A summary of all parameters tested in sensitivity analysis, and methods of conducting probabilistic sensitivity analysis are reported in the Section 4.1 and 4.2, respectively, of the <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix 1</xref> in Supplemental Materials found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.12.009" id="intref0045">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.12.009</ext-link>.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec3">
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="sec3.1">
                <title>Number of Cases</title>
                <p id="p0090">The simulated daily disease transmission outcomes (number of quarantined/isolated people, confirmed cases, and deaths) under different strategies are illustrated in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix 6</xref> in Supplemental Materials found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.12.009" id="intref0050">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.12.009</ext-link>. Under strategies B, C, and D, the dates when there were no more newly confirmed cases were April 25, May 10, and May 30, 2020, respectively. The total numbers of cases and fatalities are reported in the <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix</xref>, Section 6. One-week delay (strategy B) results in 0.463 million confirmed cases (95% confidence interval (CI) 0.25-1.16), 7.98 million cases under quarantine/isolation (95% CI 4.67-20.56), and 0.012 million deaths (95% CI 0.01-0.03); 2-week delay (strategy C) results in 2.34 million confirmed cases (95% CI 1.09-6.61), 64.76 million cases under quarantine/isolation (95% CI 32.78-193.6), and 0.04 million deaths (95% CI 0.02-0.09); and 4-week delay (strategy D) results in 37.74 million confirmed cases (95% CI 15.92-104.70), 1.68 billion cases under quarantine/isolation (95% CI 703.2 million to 5.08 billion), and 0.29 million deaths (95% CI 0.14, 0.64).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec3.2">
                <title>DALYs</title>
                <p id="p0095">The DALYs accrued for each strategy are reported in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>
. Strategy A (“current practice”) results in 38 348 DALYs (95% CI 19 523-64 310), of which 822 were caused by YLD (95% CI 387-2259) and 32 575 was caused by YLL (95% CI 18 338-63 242). Compared to strategy A, a 1-week delay (strategy B) results in 101 437 more DALYs, a 2-week delay (strategy C) results in 393 877 more DALYs, and a 4-week delay (strategy D) results in 3 711 721 more DALYs.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The burden of COVID-19 in China in real-world and different simulation scenarios.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Age</th><th rowspan="2">Cases</th><th rowspan="2">Deaths</th><th rowspan="2">YLDs</th><th>YLLs<hr/></th><th><hr/></th><th>DALYs<hr/></th><th><hr/></th></tr><tr><th>Undiscounted</th><th>Discounted</th><th>Undiscounted</th><th>Discounted</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="8"><bold>Real-world</bold></td></tr><tr><td>0~</td><td align="char">753</td><td align="char">0</td><td align="char">0</td><td align="char">0</td><td>-</td><td align="char">0</td><td align="char">0</td></tr><tr><td>10~</td><td align="char">1004</td><td align="char">3</td><td align="char">0</td><td align="char">208</td><td align="char">97</td><td align="char">209</td><td align="char">97</td></tr><tr><td>20~</td><td align="char">6776</td><td align="char">23</td><td align="char">2</td><td align="char">1231</td><td align="char">634</td><td align="char">1233</td><td align="char">636</td></tr><tr><td>30~</td><td align="char">14 221</td><td align="char">60</td><td align="char">338</td><td align="char">2584</td><td align="char">1486</td><td align="char">2921</td><td align="char">1823</td></tr><tr><td>40~</td><td align="char">16 061</td><td align="char">124</td><td align="char">172</td><td align="char">4129</td><td align="char">2664</td><td align="char">4301</td><td align="char">2836</td></tr><tr><td>50~</td><td align="char">18 738</td><td align="char">425</td><td align="char">228</td><td align="char">10 266</td><td align="char">7445</td><td align="char">10 494</td><td align="char">7673</td></tr><tr><td>60~</td><td align="char">16 061</td><td align="char">1010</td><td align="char">338</td><td align="char">16 033</td><td align="char">12 987</td><td align="char">16 371</td><td align="char">13 326</td></tr><tr><td>70~</td><td align="char">7361</td><td align="char">1020</td><td align="char">58</td><td align="char">9622</td><td align="char">8522</td><td align="char">9680</td><td align="char">8580</td></tr><tr><td>80~</td><td align="char">2677</td><td align="char">679</td><td align="char">1</td><td align="char">3593</td><td align="char">3376</td><td align="char">3594</td><td align="char">3376</td></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td align="char">83 650</td><td align="char">3345</td><td align="char">1137</td><td align="char">47 666</td><td align="char">37 211</td><td align="char">48 803</td><td align="char">38 348</td></tr><tr><td colspan="8"><bold>Scenario A: delay 1 week</bold></td></tr><tr><td>0~</td><td align="char">4167</td><td align="char">0</td><td align="char">1</td><td>-</td><td align="char">0</td><td align="char">1</td><td align="char">1</td></tr><tr><td>10~</td><td align="char">5556</td><td align="char">12</td><td align="char">2</td><td align="char">748</td><td align="char">347</td><td align="char">749</td><td align="char">348</td></tr><tr><td>20~</td><td align="char">37 503</td><td align="char">84</td><td align="char">12</td><td align="char">4415</td><td align="char">2274</td><td align="char">4427</td><td align="char">2286</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Age</th><th rowspan="2">Cases</th><th rowspan="2">Deaths</th><th rowspan="2">YLDs</th><th>YLLs<hr/></th><th><hr/></th><th>DALYs<hr/></th><th><hr/></th></tr><tr><th>Undiscounted</th><th>Discounted</th><th>Undiscounted</th><th>Discounted</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>30~</td><td align="char">78 710</td><td align="char">216</td><td align="char">1869</td><td align="char">9269</td><td align="char">5330</td><td align="char">11 138</td><td align="char">7199</td></tr><tr><td>40~</td><td align="char">88 896</td><td align="char">444</td><td align="char">950</td><td align="char">14 813</td><td align="char">9558</td><td align="char">15 763</td><td align="char">10 508</td></tr><tr><td>50~</td><td align="char">103 712</td><td align="char">1524</td><td align="char">1262</td><td align="char">36 828</td><td align="char">26 710</td><td align="char">38 090</td><td align="char">27 972</td></tr><tr><td>60~</td><td align="char">88 896</td><td align="char">3624</td><td align="char">1872</td><td align="char">57 517</td><td align="char">46 591</td><td align="char">59 389</td><td align="char">48 464</td></tr><tr><td>70~</td><td align="char">40 744</td><td align="char">3660</td><td align="char">320</td><td align="char">34 518</td><td align="char">30 572</td><td align="char">34 839</td><td align="char">30 892</td></tr><tr><td>80~</td><td align="char">14 816</td><td align="char">2436</td><td align="char">5</td><td align="char">12 890</td><td align="char">12 109</td><td align="char">12 894</td><td align="char">12 114</td></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td align="char">463 000</td><td align="char">12 000</td><td align="char">6293</td><td align="char">170 998</td><td align="char">133 491</td><td align="char">177 291</td><td align="char">139 784</td></tr><tr><td colspan="8"><bold>Scenario B: delay 2 weeks</bold></td></tr><tr><td>0~</td><td align="char">21 024</td><td align="char">0</td><td align="char">7</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td align="char">7</td><td align="char">7</td></tr><tr><td>10~</td><td align="char">28 032</td><td align="char">36</td><td align="char">9</td><td align="char">2243</td><td align="char">1040</td><td align="char">2252</td><td align="char">1049</td></tr><tr><td>20~</td><td align="char">189 216</td><td align="char">252</td><td align="char">59</td><td align="char">13 245</td><td align="char">6822</td><td align="char">13 304</td><td align="char">6881</td></tr><tr><td>30~</td><td align="char">397 120</td><td align="char">648</td><td align="char">9431</td><td align="char">27 806</td><td align="char">15 990</td><td align="char">37 237</td><td align="char">25 421</td></tr><tr><td>40~</td><td align="char">448 512</td><td align="char">1332</td><td align="char">4794</td><td align="char">44 439</td><td align="char">28 674</td><td align="char">49 232</td><td align="char">33 467</td></tr><tr><td>50~</td><td align="char">523 264</td><td align="char">4572</td><td align="char">6368</td><td align="char">110 484</td><td align="char">80 129</td><td align="char">116 852</td><td align="char">86 497</td></tr><tr><td>60~</td><td align="char">448 512</td><td align="char">10 872</td><td align="char">9447</td><td align="char">172 551</td><td align="char">139 774</td><td align="char">181 998</td><td align="char">149 220</td></tr><tr><td>70~</td><td align="char">205 568</td><td align="char">10 980</td><td align="char">1615</td><td align="char">103 555</td><td align="char">91 716</td><td align="char">105 170</td><td align="char">93 331</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Age</th><th rowspan="2">Cases</th><th rowspan="2">Deaths</th><th rowspan="2">YLDs</th><th>YLLs<hr/></th><th><hr/></th><th>DALYs<hr/></th><th><hr/></th></tr><tr><th><bold>Undiscounted</bold></th><th><bold>Discounted</bold></th><th><bold>Undiscounted</bold></th><th><bold>Discounted</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>80~</td><td align="char">74 752</td><td align="char">7308</td><td align="char">23</td><td align="char">38 669</td><td align="char">36 328</td><td align="char">38 693</td><td align="char">36 352</td></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td align="char">2 336 000</td><td align="char">36 000</td><td align="char">31 752</td><td align="char">512 993</td><td align="char">400 473</td><td align="char">544 745</td><td align="char">432 225</td></tr><tr><td colspan="8"><bold>Scenario C: delay 4 weeks</bold></td></tr><tr><td>0~</td><td align="char">339 615</td><td align="char">0</td><td align="char">106</td><td>-</td><td align="char">0</td><td align="char">106</td><td align="char">106</td></tr><tr><td>10~</td><td align="char">452 820</td><td align="char">291</td><td align="char">142</td><td align="char">18 132</td><td align="char">8407</td><td align="char">18 273</td><td align="char">8549</td></tr><tr><td>20~</td><td align="char">3 056 535</td><td align="char">2037</td><td align="char">955</td><td align="char">107 064</td><td align="char">55 146</td><td align="char">108 019</td><td align="char">56 102</td></tr><tr><td>30~</td><td align="char">6 414 950</td><td align="char">5238</td><td align="char">152 341</td><td align="char">224 768</td><td align="char">129 253</td><td align="char">377 109</td><td align="char">281 594</td></tr><tr><td>40~</td><td align="char">7 245 120</td><td align="char">10 767</td><td align="char">77 433</td><td align="char">359 214</td><td align="char">231 778</td><td align="char">436 647</td><td align="char">309 211</td></tr><tr><td>50~</td><td align="char">8 452 640</td><td align="char">36 957</td><td align="char">102 866</td><td align="char">893 080</td><td align="char">647 707</td><td align="char">995 946</td><td align="char">750 574</td></tr><tr><td>60~</td><td align="char">7 245 120</td><td align="char">87 882</td><td align="char">152 601</td><td align="char">1 394 789</td><td align="char">1 129 837</td><td align="char">1 547 389</td><td align="char">1 282 438</td></tr><tr><td>70~</td><td align="char">3 320 680</td><td align="char">88 755</td><td align="char">26 094</td><td align="char">837 071</td><td align="char">741 370</td><td align="char">863 165</td><td align="char">767 464</td></tr><tr><td>80~</td><td align="char">1 207 520</td><td align="char">59 073</td><td align="char">377</td><td align="char">312 576</td><td align="char">293 655</td><td align="char">312 953</td><td align="char">294 033</td></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td align="char">37 735 000</td><td align="char">291 000</td><td align="char">512 916</td><td align="char">4 146 693</td><td align="char">3 237 153</td><td align="char">4 659 608</td><td align="char">3 750 069</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>DALY indicates disability-adjusted life-year; YLD, years lived with disability; YLL, years of life lost due to premature mortality.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec3.3">
                <title>Cost-Effectiveness Results</title>
                <p id="p0100">Compared to strategy A (“current practice”), the incremental societal costs of strategy B, C, and D were 1920 (95% CI 928-4841), 3682 (95% CI 1635-5792), and 20 327 (95% CI 11 677-39 674) billion RMB, respectively (278, 533, and 2942 billion USD). Strategy A (“current practice”) dominates all other strategies, from both a healthcare perspective and societal perspective (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>
). The proportion of societal costs attributable to healthcare in strategies A, B, C, and D were 0.14%, 0.62%, 3.23%, and 18.25%, respectively. Productivity losses were 99.86%, 99.38%, 96.77%, and 81.75%, respectively.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Cost and effectiveness results different strategies.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>No delay RMB (USD)</th><th>1-week delay RMB (USD)</th><th>2-week delay RMB (USD)</th><th>4-week delay RMB (USD)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Total cost (billion)</td><td align="char">2638 (343)</td><td align="char">4559 (660)</td><td align="char">6320 (915)</td><td align="char">22 966 (3324)</td></tr><tr><td> Direct cost (billion)</td><td align="char">3.6 (0.5)</td><td align="char">28 (4.1)</td><td align="char">204 (29.5)</td><td align="char">4191 (606.5)</td></tr><tr><td> Indirect cost (billion)</td><td align="char">2635 (381)</td><td align="char">4531 (656)</td><td align="char">6117 (885)</td><td align="char">18 775 (2717)</td></tr><tr><td>DALY (person-year)</td><td>38 348</td><td>139 784</td><td>432 225</td><td>3 750 069</td></tr><tr><td>Net monetary benefit (billion)</td><td align="char">−2636 (−381)</td><td align="char">−4549 (−658)</td><td align="char">−6289 (−910)</td><td align="char">−22 699 (−3285)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
                <p id="p0105">Results were robust to 1-way sensitivity analyses (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>
and <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix Table S9</xref> in Supplemental Materials found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.12.009" id="intref0055">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.12.009</ext-link>). From a healthcare perspective, results were most sensitive to inpatient cost per critical case, number of working days for front-line healthcare staff, and number of front-line healthcare staff. From a societal perspective, results were most sensitive to employed people not considered to have had COVID-19, national average salary per working day, and working time lost for people not considered to have had COVID-19. At a willingness-to-pay of 70 892 RMB per DALY averted, the probability that strategy A is more cost-effective compared to strategy B, C, and D is 96%，99%, 100%, respectively. The detailed results of sensitivity analyses are presented in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix 7</xref> in Supplemental Materials found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.12.009" id="intref0060">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.12.009</ext-link>.<fig id="fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>One-way sensitivity analysis results and cost-effectiveness planes. (A) One-way sensitivity analysis results from the healthcare perspective, “One-week delay” versus “No delay”; (B) One-way sensitivity analysis results from the societal perspective, “One-week delay” versus “No delay.” Net monetary benefit = -DALY losses ∗ Chinese GDP – Cost. Each variable tested is reported in the diagram in the following format: Variable name: Base case value [Minimum value – Maximum value].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3_lrg"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec4">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p id="p0110">To our knowledge, this is the first study that assessed the health burden of COVID-19 in China. This study found that the first wave of COVID-19 in China resulted in 38 348 DALYs lost (95% CI 19 523-64 310) and a cost of 278 billion USD. The average discounted DALY loss was estimated to be 0.46 per patient with COVID-19. Patients aged 50-70 years old accounted for 58.9% of the DALY loss, reflecting higher mortality rates in older patients. The DALY loss estimated by this study allows comparison with studies of other infectious diseases<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> and can inform future cost-effectiveness analyses.</p>
              <p id="p0115">This is also the first study that explored the effect of timing on the cost-effectiveness of MRPs. Delay in initiating MRPs leads to exponential growth in DALY loss and societal cost: a 4-week delay resulted in 3.7 million more DALYs and 2942 billion USD additional societal cost, compared to no delay. Unsurprisingly, a later start time of MRPs results in many more infected cases, because those infected will increase the chance of infection for susceptible individuals. This in turn has an impact on the duration of the COVID-19 outbreak: under strategy A, it took only 62 days for the national newly confirmed cases to reach zero, whereas for strategy D, it took more than 100 days. The increased duration of MRPs resulted in greater productivity losses for strategies with longer delays. These findings are intuitive. However, our results quantified the impact of delay in imposition of MRPs. The results of this study can help decision makers to identify the optimal timing of implementing MRPs for future waves of COVID-19 within limited resources.</p>
              <sec id="sec4.1">
                <title>Comparison With Published Literature</title>
                <p id="p0120">SEIR models have been widely used by a number of studies to forecast the future trends of COVID-19<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> or to assess the effectiveness of interventions for preventing COVID-19.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Lai et al<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> used an SEIR model to examine the impact of timing on the effectiveness of MRPs and found that delays of 1, 2, or 3 weeks would have led to a 3-fold, 7-fold, or 18-fold increase in the number of cases. We found a delay of 1 or 2 weeks led to a 5.5-fold or a 27.9-fold increase in cases, respectively. The difference probably reflects an assumption that asymptomatic individuals are not infectious in Lai’s model. Yang et al<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> also examined the impact of delayed MRPs using an SEIR model and found that a delay of 5 days led to a 3-fold increase in cases. They estimated a 67-fold increase in cases in the absence of MRPs. An SEIR model of Wuhan found that staggered lifting of MRPs in May 2020 reduced the number of cases in mid-2020 by 92% compared to a scenario assuming no MRPs.<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> One study assessed the cost impact of early implementation of quarantine during the 2003 severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) outbreak in Hong Kong.<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> They found that within a fixed budget and for a controllable outbreak, early implementation of quarantine achieved the best results.</p>
                <p id="p0125">Our rapid review did not identify any studies that assessed the COVID-19 associated DALY values. The global health burden of premature mortality due to the Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV) has been estimated; the average years of life lost were 8.3 and 7.7 for males and females, respectively.<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> These findings are lower than our estimate of the YLL loss for COVID-19 (14 undiscounted YLL per death). The global years of life lost for patients with MERS-CoV has been estimated at 14 520, which is a quarter of our estimated DALY loss (38 348 DALYs). While mortality from MERS-CoV was higher, the number of COVID-19 cases in China (83 650) is much larger than the number of patients infected with MERS-CoV (1789). The health burden caused by human coronavirus (HCoV) NL63 in hospitalized patients in the UK has been reported.<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> The estimated DALY per 1000 hospitalized patients ranged from 0.3 for patients 16-64 years old to 1.7 for patients under 5 years old. The modest losses reflect much lower morbidity and mortality caused by HCoVs compared to SARS-CoV-2.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec4.2">
                <title>Implications for Clinical Practice and Future Research</title>
                <p id="p0130">Our findings support the findings of recent research that early MRPs are more cost-effective than delayed MRPs.<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref> The imposition of MRPs poses ethical dilemmas regarding the restriction of civil liberties<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref> alongside concerns on the impact on the economy. Understandably, governments have been reluctant to take these steps. Quantifying the impact on costs and health of postponement of MRPs reduces uncertainty and supports decision making. Consensus is emerging regarding the appropriate response to emerging epidemics informed by cost-effectiveness analysis. Contact tracing and case isolation are highly cost-effective, along with the use of protective equipment by healthcare staff.<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref> MRPs are far more expensive and only likely to be considered where mortality is high and contact tracing has failed to control an outbreak. MRPs were implemented early in the cycle of the epidemic in China and appear to have been successful in controlling the epidemic. Other countries have been slower to implement MRPs and are only now beginning to ease restrictions. Comparative analysis is required, but experiences to date in different countries support the argument for early implementation of MRPs.<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref>
</p>
                <p id="p0135">Although there has been overwhelming support for MRPs among the medical community, significant dissension remains on the justification for implementing MRPs, with some commentators questioning whether the benefits of MRPs in saving lives from COVID-19 outweigh the cost.<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref> A recent review concluded MRPs are cost-effective where the case fatality rate is above 1% and the disease is highly infectious.<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> A recent US study concluded that the lives saved by introducing MRPs, when valued at $10 000 000 each, outweighed the economic cost over the next 30 years.<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref> Results were sensitive to the value of one life saved, and it seems unlikely that other governments would routinely place such a high value on a life saved. However, available evidence supports the use of aggressive testing and contract tracing, alongside the imposition of MRPs to increase effectiveness and reduce costs.<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref> Those findings highlight the value of maintaining testing facilities in preparation for future epidemics. Nevertheless, the relative cost-effectiveness of different public health measures under scenarios of epidemics with varying infectiousness and mortality requires further research.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec4.3">
                <title>Strengths and Limitations</title>
                <p id="p0140">There are several strengths of this study. Our analysis extended previous work in 2 important ways. While previous models<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> estimated the number of COVID-19 cases and deaths, our analysis also estimated the number of people quarantined during the implementation of MRPs. Our model adapted the original SEIR framework by separating individuals who are currently under or not under quarantine, allowing the number of people under quarantine under different strategies to be estimated and the cost implications captured. This is important since the cost of quarantine accounts for 20% of the direct cost of COVID-19 in China.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> Furthermore, many previous SEIR models<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> assumed that asymptomatic exposed individuals are not infectious, which is not the case for individuals infected with SARS-CoV-2. In our analysis, the infectiousness of asymptomatic exposed individuals was modeled. Second, by using system dynamic modeling, populated with the real-world population migration data and number of confirmed cases and deaths, this study was able to estimate not only the number of COVID-19 cases and fatalities, but also the number of close contacts/suspected cases under quarantine/isolation. Third, our analysis drew on detailed data on the costs of COVID-19 and the migration patterns of Chinese residents during the Chinese New Year holidays. Fourth, our model was probabilistic, allowing consideration of the joint impact of sampling uncertainty in the parameters and facilitating the reporting of cost-effectiveness acceptability curves. This approach to capture parameter uncertainty is recommended by the UK’s National Institute for health and Care Excellence.<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref>
</p>
                <p id="p0145">There are several limitations of this study. First, the study period is less than a year. Therefore, the long-term health and cost impacts of COVID-19, such as the impact of canceled or delayed routine treatment for people with chronic conditions (eg, cancer, diabetes, cardiovascular diseases), were not captured. Therefore, our estimates are likely to underestimate the true DALY loss and economic burden of COVID-19. Second, there was a lack of data on the age distribution of all confirmed cases and deaths in China, as well as the proportion of patients who were nonsevere, severe, and critical in each age group. These data were estimated based on published cohort studies. Third, during the study period there was a lack of data on the sequelae of COVID-19. Therefore, the disutility caused by any potential sequelae were not considered. Fourth, while the cost data for this study were obtained from a recent, detailed cost-of-illness study, some cost components were not included, such as productivity losses for carers of suspected/confirmed cases and patients’ out-of-pocket payments for travel and over-the-counter medicines.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> Fifth, the system dynamic model did not explicitly address the differences in age, sex, and severity among the confirmed cases due to a lack of such data. Sixth, it has been suggested the differential equations that underpin the SEIR model may underestimate the reproductive rate R<sub>0</sub>.<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref> Finally, while we estimated the uncertainty associated with parameters derived from calibration and propagated this through our probabilistic analysis, we did not apply a fully probabilistic approach to the estimation of parameter values from calibration and their subsequent propagation through our analysis. Consequently, we may have underestimated the impact of uncertainty arising from the calibration process.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec5">
              <title>Conclusion</title>
              <p id="p0150">The health burden of COVID-19 in China over the period of January to March 2020 far exceeded the previous MERS-CoV outbreak. Relatively rapid introduction of MRPs greatly reduced the health burden and the overall cost. When faced with an outbreak of a disease that may be highly infectious and associated with raised mortality, early implementation of MRPs is advisable. Future pandemic responses will need to weigh the cost of early implementation of MRPs against the potential cost of delay. Our analysis provides important evidence on the cost of delay to the economy and population health to inform such decisions.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list id="cebib0010">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="bib1">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref1">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>Worldometers</collab>
                    <collab>World Population</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.worldometers.info/" id="intref0070">https://www.worldometers.info/</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib2">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leung</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>J.T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leung</surname>
                      <given-names>G.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>First-wave COVID-19 transmissibility and severity in China outside Hubei after control measures, and second-wave scenario planning: a modelling impact assessment</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet</source>
                  <volume>395</volume>
                  <issue>10233</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1382</fpage>
                  <lpage>1393</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32277878</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib3">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lai</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ruktanonchai</surname>
                      <given-names>N.W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhou</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of non-pharmaceutical interventions to contain COVID-19 in China</article-title>
                  <source>Nature</source>
                  <volume>585</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>410</fpage>
                  <lpage>413</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-020-2293-x</pub-id>
                  <comment>In this issue</comment>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32365354</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib4">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Prem</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Russell</surname>
                      <given-names>T.W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effect of control strategies to reduce social mixing on outcomes of the COVID-19 epidemic in Wuhan, China: a modelling study</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet Public Health</source>
                  <volume>5</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>e261</fpage>
                  <lpage>e270</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32220655</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib5">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hou</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhou</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effectiveness of quarantine of Wuhan city against the corona virus disease 2019 (COVID-19): a well-mixed SEIR model analysis</article-title>
                  <source>J Med Virol</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib6">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zeng</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Modified SEIR and AI prediction of the epidemics trend of COVID-19 in China under public health interventions</article-title>
                  <source>J Thoracic Dis</source>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>165</fpage>
                  <lpage>174</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib7">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jin</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Economic burden of COVID-19, China, January–March, 2021: a cost-of-illness study</article-title>
                  <source>Bulletin of the World Health Organization</source>
                  <volume>99</volume>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <fpage>112</fpage>
                  <lpage>124</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2471/BLT.20.267112</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33551505</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib8">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Husereau</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Drummond</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Petrou</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Consolidated Health Economic Evaluation Reporting Standards (CHEERS) statement</article-title>
                  <source>PharmacoEconomics</source>
                  <volume>31</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <fpage>361</fpage>
                  <lpage>367</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23529207</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib9">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref9">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>Organization of Economic Cooperation and Development</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Exchange rates</article-title>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://data.oecd.org/conversion/exchange-rates.htm" id="intref0075">https://data.oecd.org/conversion/exchange-rates.htm</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref10">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>Department of Health Statistics and Information Systems WHO</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>WHO methods and data sources for global burden of disease estimates 2013</article-title>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/healthinfo/statistics/GlobalDALYmethods_2000_2011.pdf" id="intref0080">https://www.who.int/healthinfo/statistics/GlobalDALYmethods_2000_2011.pdf</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>J.T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leung</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leung</surname>
                      <given-names>G.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Nowcasting and forecasting the potential domestic and international spread of the 2019-nCoV outbreak originating in Wuhan, China: a modelling study</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet</source>
                  <volume>395</volume>
                  <issue>10225</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>689</fpage>
                  <lpage>697</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32014114</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Emery</surname>
                      <given-names>J.C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Russel</surname>
                      <given-names>T.W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The contribution of asymptomatic SARS-CoV-2 infections to transmission on the Diamond Princess cruise ship</article-title>
                  <source>Elife</source>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <issue>e58699</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.58699</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref13">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>The National Health Commission of the People’s Republic of China</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Guidance on infection prevention and control for COVID-19 (7th edition)</article-title>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gov.cn/zhengce/zhengceku/2020-03/04/5486705/files/ae61004f930d47598711a0d4cbf874a9.pdf" id="intref0085">http://www.gov.cn/zhengce/zhengceku/2020-03/04/5486705/files/ae61004f930d47598711a0d4cbf874a9.pdf</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref14">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>First Affiliated Hospital of Zhejiang University School of Medicine</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Handbook of COVID-19 prevention and treatment</article-title>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://covid-19.alibabacloud.com/" id="intref0090">https://covid-19.alibabacloud.com/</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref15">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>The National Health Commission of the People’s Republic of China</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Latest statistics on COVID-19</article-title>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nhc.gov.cn/xcs/yqtb/list_gzbd.shtml" id="intref0095">http://www.nhc.gov.cn/xcs/yqtb/list_gzbd.shtml</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib16">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref16">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>Health Commission of Hubei Province</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>COVID-19 bulletin (in Chinese)</article-title>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wjw.hubei.gov.cn/bmdt/ztzl/fkxxgzbdgrfyyq/xxfb/" id="intref0100">http://wjw.hubei.gov.cn/bmdt/ztzl/fkxxgzbdgrfyyq/xxfb/</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib17">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>Epidemiology Working Group for NCIP Epidemic Response</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The epidemiological characteristics of an outbreak of 2019 novel coronavirus disease (COVID-19) in China</article-title>
                  <source>Chin J Epidemiol</source>
                  <volume>41</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <lpage>151</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib18">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref18">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>National Bureau of Statistics of China</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>China Statistical Yearbook 2019</article-title>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.stats.gov.cn/tjsj/ndsj/2019/indexch.htm" id="intref0105">http://www.stats.gov.cn/tjsj/ndsj/2019/indexch.htm</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib19">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref19">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>Hubei Statistics Bureau</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Hubei National Economic and Social Development Statistical Bulletin (2019) (in Chinese)</article-title>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tjj.hubei.gov.cn/tjsj/tjgb/ndtjgb/qstjgb/202003/t20200323_2188487" id="intref0110">http://tjj.hubei.gov.cn/tjsj/tjgb/ndtjgb/qstjgb/202003/t20200323_2188487</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib20">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref20">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>Global Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Gold COVID-19 guidance</article-title>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://goldcopd.org/gold-COVID-19-guidance/" id="intref0115">https://goldcopd.org/gold-COVID-19-guidance/</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib21">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref21">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>World Health Organisation</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>WHO methods and data sources for the global burden of disease estimates 2000-2015</article-title>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/healthinfo/global_burden_disease/GlobalDALYmethods_2000_2015.pdf?ua=1" id="intref0120">https://www.who.int/healthinfo/global_burden_disease/GlobalDALYmethods_2000_2015.pdf?ua=1</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib22">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bertram</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lauer</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Joncheere</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cost-effectiveness thresholds: pros and cons</article-title>
                  <source>Bull World Health Org</source>
                  <volume>94</volume>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <fpage>925</fpage>
                  <lpage>930</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27994285</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib23">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kyu</surname>
                      <given-names>H.H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abate</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abate</surname>
                      <given-names>K.H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Global, regional, and national disability-adjusted life-years (DALYs) for 359 diseases and injuries and healthy life expectancy (HALE) for 195 countries and territories, 1990-2017: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2017</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet</source>
                  <volume>392</volume>
                  <issue>10159</issue>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <fpage>1859</fpage>
                  <lpage>1922</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30415748</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib24">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mubayi</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zaleta</surname>
                      <given-names>C.K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Martcheva</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Castillo-Chavez</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A cost-based comparison of quarantine strategies for new emerging diseases</article-title>
                  <source>Math Biosci Eng</source>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <fpage>687</fpage>
                  <lpage>717</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20578793</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib25">
                <label>25</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Salamatbakhsh</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mobaraki</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sadeghimohammadi</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ahmadzadeh</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The global burden of premature mortality due to the Middle East respiratory syndrome (MERS) using standard expected years of life lost, 2012 to 2019</article-title>
                  <source>BMC Public Health</source>
                  <volume>19</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <fpage>1523</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31727042</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib26">
                <label>26</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gaunt</surname>
                      <given-names>E.R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Harvala</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McIntyre</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Templeton</surname>
                      <given-names>K.E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Simmonds</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Disease burden of the most commonly detected respiratory viruses in hospitalized patients calculated using the disability adjusted life year (DALY) model</article-title>
                  <source>J Clin Virol</source>
                  <volume>52</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
                  <lpage>221</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21880543</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib27">
                <label>27</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Juneau</surname>
                      <given-names>C.-E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pueyo</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bell</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gee</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Potvin</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evidence-based, cost-effective interventions to suppress the COVID-19 pandemic: a rapid systematic review</article-title>
                  <source>medRxiv</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2020.04.20.20054726</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib28">
                <label>28</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fidler</surname>
                      <given-names>D.P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gostin</surname>
                      <given-names>L.O.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Markel</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Through the quarantine looking glass: drug-resistant tuberculosis and public health governance, law, and ethics</article-title>
                  <source>J Law Med Ethics</source>
                  <volume>35</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <comment>616-628, 512</comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib29">
                <label>29</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Scally</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jacobson</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abbasi</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The UK’s public health response to covid-19</article-title>
                  <source>BMJ</source>
                  <volume>369</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>m1932</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.m1932</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32414712</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib30">
                <label>30</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref30">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Teacher</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The costs and benefits of coronavirus policies need to be weighed</article-title>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://iea.org.uk/the-costs-and-benefits-of-coronavirus-policies-need-to-be-weighed/" id="intref0125">https://iea.org.uk/the-costs-and-benefits-of-coronavirus-policies-need-to-be-weighed/</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib31">
                <label>31</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thunström</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Newbold</surname>
                      <given-names>S.C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Finnoff</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ashworth</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shogren</surname>
                      <given-names>J.F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The benefits and costs of using social distancing to flatten the curve for COVID-19</article-title>
                  <source>J Benefit Cost Anal</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>27</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib32">
                <label>32</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref35">Piguillem F, Shi L. 2020. "Optimal COVID-19 Quarantine and Testing Policies", EIEF Working Papers Series 2004, Einaudi Institute for Economics and Finance (EIEF), revised Apr 2020.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib33">
                <label>33</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref33">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>The National Institute for Health and Care Excellence</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Guide to the methods of technology appraisal</article-title>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nice.org.uk/process/pmg9/chapter/foreword" id="intref0130">https://www.nice.org.uk/process/pmg9/chapter/foreword</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib34">
                <label>34</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sref35b">Fodor Z, Katz SD, Kovacs TG. Why integral equations should be used instead of differential equations to describe the dynamics of epidemics? 2020. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2004.07208" id="intref0175t">https://arxiv.org/abs/2004.07208</ext-link>. Accessed February 16, 2021.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib35">
                <label>35</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref35a">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>China government website</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Press conference of the joint prevention and control mechanism of the State Council</article-title>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gov.cn/xinwen/gwylflkjz11/index.htm" id="intref0135">http://www.gov.cn/xinwen/gwylflkjz11/index.htm</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib36">
                <label>36</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref36">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>Ministry of Finance of the People’s Republic of China</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Financial support for novel coronavirus pneumonia prevention and control policy measures Q &amp; A</article-title>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mof.gov.cn/zhengwuxinxi/caizhengxinwen/202003/t20200320_3486097.htm" id="intref0140">http://www.mof.gov.cn/zhengwuxinxi/caizhengxinwen/202003/t20200320_3486097.htm</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib37">
                <label>37</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref37">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baidu</surname>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Mobile population and migration data</article-title>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://qianxi.baidu.com/" id="intref0145">http://qianxi.baidu.com/</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib38">
                <label>38</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref38">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>China Network news</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Experts: COVID-19 cases usually have pulmonary fibrosis in the short term without sequelae</article-title>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://news.china.com/socialgd/10000169/20200319/37940558.html" id="intref0150">https://news.china.com/socialgd/10000169/20200319/37940558.html</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
            <sec id="appsec1" sec-type="supplementary-material">
              <title>Supplemental Material</title>
              <p id="p0250">
                <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1">
                  <caption>
                    <title>Supplementary Material</title>
                  </caption>
                  <media xlink:href="mmc1.docx"/>
                </supplementary-material>
              </p>
            </sec>
            <ack id="ack0010">
              <p id="p0175"><bold>Author Contributions</bold>: <italic>Concept and design</italic>: J. Zhao, Zheng, H. Wang</p>
              <p id="p0180"><italic>Acquisition of data</italic>: J. Zhao, Li, Jia, Zhang, H. Zhao, Ma, Z. Wang, He, Lee, Yin, H. Wang</p>
              <p id="p0185"><italic>Analysis and interpretation of data</italic>: J. Zhao, Jin, Li, Jia, Zhang, H. Zhao, Ma, Z. Wang, He, Lee, Yin, H. Wang</p>
              <p id="p0190"><italic>Drafting of the manuscript</italic>: J. Zhao, Jin, Li, Zheng, H. Wang</p>
              <p id="p0195"><italic>Critical revision of the paper for important intellectual content</italic>: Jin, Pennington</p>
              <p id="p0200"><italic>Statistical analysis</italic>: J. Zhao, Jia, Z. Wang, He, Lee, Yin, H. Wang</p>
              <p id="p0205"><italic>Obtaining</italic><italic>funding</italic>: Zheng, H. Wang</p>
              <p id="p0210"><italic>Administrative, technical, or logistic</italic><italic>support</italic>: Pennington</p>
              <p id="p0215"><italic>Supervision</italic>: Zheng</p>
              <p id="p0220"><italic>Other</italic> (conducting literature review): Zhang, H. Zhao</p>
              <p id="p0225"><italic>Other</italic> (reviewing draft)<italic>:</italic> Pennington</p>
              <p id="p0230"><bold>Conflict of Interest Disclosures:</bold> Dr Pennington reported receiving personal fees from Merck outside the submitted work. No other disclosures were reported.</p>
              <p id="p0235"><bold>Funding/Support:</bold> This work was supported by <funding-source id="gs1">National Social Science Foundation</funding-source> of China (No. 18BGL235), <funding-source id="gs2">Shanghai Municipal Commission of Health and the Family Foundation for Young Talents</funding-source> (2017YQ023), and <funding-source id="gs3">Fourth Round of Shanghai Three-Year Action Plan on Public Health Discipline</funding-source> and <funding-source id="gs4">Talent Program: Evidence-Based Public Health and Health Economics</funding-source> (No. 15GWZK0901).</p>
              <p id="p0240"><bold>Role of the</bold><bold>Funder/Sponsor:</bold> The funder had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, management, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript; and decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</p>
              <p id="p0245"><bold>Acknowledgment:</bold> The authors thank Xiao Li, MSc (University of Antwerp, Antwerp, Belgium), who provided valued advice on <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> and DALY calculation.</p>
            </ack>
            <fn-group>
              <fn id="d35e1843">
                <p id="ntpara0010">Jidi Zhao, Huajie Jin, and Xun Li contributed equally to this work.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="appsec2" fn-type="supplementary-material">
                <p id="p0255">Supplementary data associated with this article can be found in the online version at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.12.009" id="intref0065">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.12.009</ext-link>.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
