<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-03-11T00:59:40Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7738757" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7738757</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-01-03</datestamp>
        <setSpec>elsevierwt</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Vaccine</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Vaccine</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Vaccine</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0264-410X</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1873-2518</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Elsevier Science</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC7738757</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7738757</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">7738757</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33303180</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pii">S0264-410X(20)31150-6</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2020.09.008</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Modeling the cost-effectiveness of maternal acellular pertussis immunization (aP) in different socioeconomic settings: A dynamic transmission model of pertussis in three Brazilian states</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au005">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Luz</surname>
                    <given-names>Paula M.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <email>paula.luz@ini.fiocruz.br</email>
                  <xref rid="af005" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
                  <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au010">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Struchiner</surname>
                    <given-names>Claudio J.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="af010" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au015">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kim</surname>
                    <given-names>Sun-Young</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="af020" ref-type="aff">d</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au020">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Minamisava</surname>
                    <given-names>Ruth</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="af025" ref-type="aff">e</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au025">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Andrade</surname>
                    <given-names>Ana Lucia S.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="af015" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au030">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Sanderson</surname>
                    <given-names>Colin</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="af030" ref-type="aff">f</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au035">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Russell</surname>
                    <given-names>Louise B.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="af035" ref-type="aff">g</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au040">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Toscano</surname>
                    <given-names>Cristiana M.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="af015" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="af005"><label>a</label>Instituto Nacional de Infectologia Evandro Chagas, Fundação Oswaldo Cruz, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil</aff>
                <aff id="af010"><label>b</label>Escola de Matemática Aplicada, Fundação Getúlio Vargas, Praia de Botafogo, 190, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil</aff>
                <aff id="af015"><label>c</label>Instituto de Patologia Tropical e Saúde Pública, Universidade Federal de Goiás, Goiania, Goiás, Brazil</aff>
                <aff id="af020"><label>d</label>Seoul National University, Department of Healthcare Management and Policy, SNU Graduate School of Public Health, 1 Gwanak-ro, Gwanak-gu, Seoul 08826, South Korea</aff>
                <aff id="af025"><label>e</label>Faculdade de Enfermagem, Universidade Federal de Goiás, Goiania, Goias, Brazil</aff>
                <aff id="af030"><label>f</label>London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, Department of Health Services Research and Policy, 15-17 Tavistock Place, London WC1H 9SH, United Kingdom</aff>
                <aff id="af035"><label>g</label>University of Pennsylvania, Department of Medical Ethics and Health Policy, 423 Guardian Drive, Philadelphia PA 19104, USA</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author at: Instituto Nacional de Infectologia Evandro Chagas, Fundação Oswaldo Cruz, Avenida Brasil 4365, Manguinhos, CEP 22461 Rio de Janeiro, Brazil. <email>paula.luz@ini.fiocruz.br</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>03</day>
                <month>1</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="ppub">.-->
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <day>03</day>
                <month>1</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>39</volume>
              <issue>1</issue>
              <fpage>125</fpage>
              <lpage>136</lpage>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2020 The Author(s)</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2020</copyright-year>
                <license license-type="CC BY" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                  <license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="ab005">
                <sec>
                  <title>Objectives</title>
                  <p>Using dynamic transmission models we evaluated the health and cost outcomes of adding acellular pertussis (aP) vaccination of pregnant women to infant vaccination in three Brazilian states that represent different socioeconomic conditions. The primary objective was to determine whether the same model structure could be used to represent pertussis disease dynamics in differing socioeconomic conditions.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods</title>
                  <p>We tested three model structures (SIR, SIRS, SIRSIs) to represent population-level transmission in three socio-demographically distinct Brazilian states: São Paulo, Paraná and Bahia. Two strategies were evaluated: infant wP vaccination alone versus maternal aP immunization plus infant wP vaccination. Model projections for 2014–2029 include outpatient and inpatient pertussis cases, pertussis deaths, years of life lost, disability-adjusted life-years (DALYs) lost, and costs (in 2014 USD) of maternal aP vaccination, infant vaccination, and pertussis medical treatment. Incremental cost per DALY averted is presented from the perspective of the Brazilian National Health System.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>Based on goodness-of-fit statistics, the SIRSIs model fit best, although it had only a modest improvement in statistical quantitative assessments relative to the SIRS model. For all three Brazilian states, maternal aP immunization led to higher costs but also saved infant lives and averted DALYs. The 2014 USD cost/DALY averted was $3068 in Sao Paulo, $2962 in Parana, and $2022 in Bahia. These results were robust in sensitivity analyses with the incremental cost-effectiveness ratios exceeding per capita gross regional product only when the probability that a pertussis case is reported was assumed higher than base case implying more overt cases and deaths and therefore more medical costs.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusions</title>
                  <p>The same model structure fit all three states best, supporting the idea that the disease behaves similarly across different socioeconomic conditions. We also found that immunization of pregnant women with aP is cost-effective in diverse Brazilian states.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group id="kg005">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>Pertussis</kwd>
                <kwd>Maternal immunization</kwd>
                <kwd>Dynamic transmission models</kwd>
                <kwd>Cost-effectiveness analysis</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="s0005">
              <label>1</label>
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p id="p0005">Currently, pertussis is endemic in all countries causing 16 million cases and ∼195,000 child deaths annually <xref rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, with epidemic cycles occurring every 2–5 years <xref rid="b0010" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. Childhood immunization has led to longer intervals between pertussis outbreaks which indicates increased herd immunity <xref rid="b0015" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. Also, a shift in the age distribution of pertussis towards older age groups (adolescents and young adults) has been reported in recent years in high-income countries <xref rid="b0025" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. Recently, however, many countries have reported a resurgence in pertussis cases and deaths, particularly among infants too young to receive their own vaccinations <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="b0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>.</p>
              <p id="p0010">Single-dose maternal acellular pertussis (aP) immunization during pregnancy, which confers immunity on the infant through transplacental antibody transfer and reduces infants’ exposure to infection by protecting their mothers, could efficiently prevent disease and death in infants. Countries’ existing maternal immunization programs, which already provide tetanus toxoid, offer a feasible platform to provide maternal aP immunization, although at additional cost. To date, economic analysis of maternal aP immunization have shown it to be a cost-effective strategy in high-income countries <xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="b0050" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>.</p>
              <p id="p0015">Brazil introduced pertussis wP vaccine into its routine childhood immunization program in 1973. Currently, the schedule includes a 3 dose-primary series of pentavalent vaccine including diphtheria, tetanus, whole-cell pertussis, <italic>Haemophilus influenzae</italic> type b, and Hepatitis B (DTwP-Hib-HB) recommended at 2, 4 and 6 months of age, followed by two booster doses with DTwP at 15 months and 4 years of age. In the National Health System, aP vaccines are available, free of charge, only for children at high risk of adverse reactions to the wP vaccine (preterm infants, children with severe neurological or cardiac conditions and those who have previously had severe adverse events following whole-cell pertussis immunization) <xref rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. Additionally, aP vaccines are available in private immunization clinics. In November 2014, for pregnant women, the Brazilian Ministry of Health replaced diphtheria-tetanus vaccine with a single dose vaccine of tetanus-diphtheria-acellular pertussis vaccine <xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref> purchased through the Pan American Health Organization Revolving Fund.</p>
              <p id="p0020">We tested three structures for dynamic transmission models to explore the cost-effectiveness of maternal immunization in different socioeconomic conditions. Because Brazil has state-specific demographic and surveillance data we tested these model structures against data for three Brazilian states that represent a range of socioeconomic conditions (Sao Paulo, Parana, and Bahia). These conditions are illustrative of upper to lower-middle income settings. Since many low- and middle-income countries (LMICs) do not have enough data, of sufficient quality, to allow the development of a country-specific dynamic transmission model, the aim of our analysis was to determine whether a single model structure could fit three diverse states, and thus might represent disease dynamics in other countries with similar socioeconomic conditions. Additionally, we used the models to project the health outcomes, costs and cost-effectiveness of introducing maternal aP immunization in these three states.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s0010">
              <label>2</label>
              <title>Methods</title>
              <sec id="s0015">
                <label>2.1</label>
                <title>Model structures and parameters</title>
                <p id="p0025">We developed three population-level age-structured compartmental models of pertussis transmission dynamics. Each model is described by a system of differential equations with up to five compartments to describe disease natural history and four to describe childhood and maternal vaccination. Each of the compartments is subdivided into 13 age compartments (0–1 month, 2–3, 4–5, 6–8, 9–11, 12–23 months, 2–4, 5–9, 10–14, 15–19, 20–49, 50–79, 80+ years), which were parameterized with state population size, birth rate and age-specific death rates.</p>
                <p id="p0030">The epidemiologic models are extensions of the classic Susceptible-Infectious-Recovered (SIR) model that includes vaccine compartments describing routine infant vaccination in addition to, depending on model structure, two types of infection: primary (I) and secondary (Is). Susceptible individuals (S) of all ages can acquire infection from contact with an infectious person (I or Is). Time spent infected corresponds to the infectious period, during which transmission may occur according to age-specific force of infection. When infected individuals recover from primary infection (I), they initially have immunity against pertussis (R) but immunity may wane, depending on the model structure.</p>
                <p id="p0035">To identify the model structure that best fits the data for each state, three structures with different assumptions about immunity waning and repeat infections were tested. Our approach reflects uncertainty surrounding the epidemiology of pertussis <xref rid="b0065" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. The SIR model assumes lifelong immunity and consequently no secondary infections occur. The SIRS model assumes that immunity wanes and that secondary infections are as infectious and symptomatic (and therefore reported to the same extent) as primary infections. The SIRSI model also assumes that immunity wanes but, compared to primary infections, secondary infections are as infectious but less symptomatic and therefore less likely to be reported. That is, the SIR model assumes lifelong immunity while the SIRS and the SIRSI models assume immunity wanes and that individuals become susceptible to repeat primary infections (model SIRS) or secondary infections (Is, model SIRSI).</p>
                <p id="p0040">Routine infant whole-cell pertussis (wP) vaccination occurs at 2–3, 4–5, 6–8, 9–11, 12–23 months depending on the observed probability of receiving each of the primary childhood doses. These probabilities determine the fraction of infants that moves from the susceptible (S) or the maternal immunization (Vm, see below) compartments to the vaccinated compartments (V1: first dose, V2: second dose, V3: third dose). Infants vaccinated against pertussis may be protected by vaccination (V1p) or not protected (V1n) depending on the primary vaccine failure probability (vf). From vaccine protected compartments (V1p, V2p, V3p), upon waning, they may become susceptible to infection (move to S). Immunity from both routine vaccination (V) and maternal immunization (Mv) wane at different rates.</p>
                <p id="p0045">Maternal immunization is modeled by assigning a fraction of newborns, based on vaccine coverage, into a maternally immune compartment (Vm) which is further subdivided into a protected (Vmp) and not protected (Vmn) depending on vaccine effectiveness. When maternal immunity wanes, those initially protected become susceptible to pertussis infection (S). All “not protected” compartments are as susceptible as S. All “protected” compartments are immune, with different waning immunity rates.</p>
                <p id="p0050">Force of infection was defined for each age group according to effective contact rates and number of infected people. We modeled the contact between age-compartments based on a contact matrix that describes the average number of contacts per day that each individual is likely to have with another individual. Since an empirically-derived matrix is not yet available for Brazil, we adapted one for a middle-income country, Poland <xref rid="b0075" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, to the Brazilian scenario by adjusting the published matrix by the ratio of average household size (Poland::Brazil) and subsequently to each state (Brazil::State). The Polish matrix was chosen based on a qualitative assessment of the similarities of the contact patterns in the two countries. For use in the model, the original matrix, which used 5-year age groups, was condensed/expanded as necessary to map to the 13 age groups in the present study. Additionally, the matrix was corrected for reciprocity - that is, following prior studies, it was adjusted so that the off-diagonal elements were symmetric and the contact rate was the same for any two age-groups regardless of which group initiated contact <xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>.</p>
                <p id="p0055">The model includes parameters to quantify duration and degree of infectiousness; duration of natural, vaccine, and maternally acquired immunity; efficacy and coverage of infant and maternal vaccines; and the likelihood that whole-cell or acellular vaccine will fail to protect. Parameter values, ranges and sources are described in <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, a more thorough description is given in the Technical Appendix, Section #8.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0005"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Model parameters: symbol, description, sources, and base case values (range).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Symbol</th><th>Description</th><th>Definitions and sources</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Demography</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Births</td><td>Births</td><td># of births/day, state data from the Brazilian National Institute of Geography and Statistics. See Technical Appendix, Section #1.</td></tr><tr><td>d</td><td>Ageing</td><td>1/duration of age group. For example, for the age group 10–14 years, duration is 5 years. Defined for age group i = 1–12, there is no ageing parameter for the last age group.</td></tr><tr><td>m</td><td>Mortality</td><td>Mortality rate from all causes, state-specific population data from the National Institute of Geography and Statistics and all-cause mortality data from the National Mortality System. See Technical Appendix, Section #1. Defined for age group i = 1–13.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Natural history</td><td/></tr><tr><td>fi</td><td>Force of infection</td><td>Time-dependent parameter based on age-specific contact rates and the pool of infectious individuals at any given time. Defined for age group i = 1–13.</td></tr><tr><td>c<sub>i,j</sub></td><td>Contact rate between age group i (i = 1–13) and age group j (j = 1–13)</td><td>Polish POLYMOD matrix <xref rid="b0075" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref> adjusted for average state-specific household size. See Methods and Technical Appendix, Section #1.</td></tr><tr><td>pi</td><td>Transmission probability per contact</td><td>Initial values for each state based on <xref rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref> and then adjusted during model fitting, see Technical Appendix, Section #1. Defined for age group i = 1–13.</td></tr><tr><td>g</td><td>1/infectious period</td><td>1/25 days (21–28). Initial values based on <xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref> and then adjusted during model fitting. See Technical Appendix, Section #1 and #6.</td></tr><tr><td>wi</td><td>Waning of infection induced immunity</td><td>25 years (10–50). Derived during model fitting, see Technical Appendix, Section #1 and #6.</td></tr><tr><td>mpi</td><td>Pertussis-specific mortality</td><td>Mortality rate from pertussis, state-specific population data from the National Institute of Geography and Statistics and pertussis-specific mortality data from National Mortality System. See Technical Appendix, Section #2. Defined for age group i = 1–5.</td></tr><tr><td>r</td><td>Reporting probability for symptomatic cases</td><td>State-specific likelihood that an infection will be symptomatic/reported. Derived during model fitting, see Technical Appendix, Section #1 and #6. The reporting probability for secondary infections, applicable to model structure SIRSI, was assumed to be 1/10 of that of the primary infection.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Vaccine coverage</td><td/></tr><tr><td>vc1</td><td>Vaccine coverage wP, 1st dose</td><td>Probability of being vaccinated, estimated from the National Survey of Vaccine Coverage in State Capitals in Brazil in 2007. See Technical Appendix for details, Section #3.</td></tr><tr><td>vc2</td><td>Vaccine coverage wP, 2nd dose</td><td>Probability of being vaccinated, estimated from the National Survey of Vaccine Coverage in State Capitals in Brazil in 2007. See Technical Appendix for details, Section #3.</td></tr><tr><td>vc3</td><td>Vaccine coverage wP, 3rd dose</td><td>Probability of being vaccinated, estimated from the National Survey of Vaccine Coverage in State Capitals in Brazil in 2007. See Technical Appendix for details, Section #3.</td></tr><tr><td>vcm</td><td>Vaccine coverage aP, maternal</td><td>State-specific data from the Brazilian National Immunization Program, Section #3.</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Vaccine effectiveness</td><td/></tr><tr><td>ve1</td><td>Effectiveness wP, 1st dose</td><td>0.68 (95%CI: 0.456–0.811) <xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref></td></tr><tr><td>ve2</td><td>Effectiveness wP, 2nd dose</td><td>0.92 (95% CI: 0.847–0.957) <xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref></td></tr><tr><td>ve3</td><td>Effectiveness wP, 3rd dose</td><td>0.99 (95% CI: 0.989–1.000) <xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref></td></tr><tr><td>vem</td><td>Effectiveness aP, maternal</td><td>0.91 (95% CI:0.82–0.95) <xref rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Primary vaccine failure</td><td/></tr><tr><td>vfw</td><td>Proportion of vaccine failure, wP</td><td>0.1 (0–0.15) <xref rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref></td></tr><tr><td>vfa</td><td>Proportion of vaccine failure, aP</td><td>0.1 (0–0.15) <xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Immunity waning</td><td/></tr><tr><td>w1</td><td>Waning immunity of wP 1st dose</td><td>14.5 years (range 5–30 years). Derived during model fitting, see Technical Appendix, Section #1 and #6.</td></tr><tr><td>w2</td><td>Waning immunity of wP 2nd dose</td><td>14.5 years (range 5–30 years). Derived during model fitting, see Technical Appendix, Section #1 and #6.</td></tr><tr><td>w3</td><td>Waning immunity of wP 3rd dose</td><td>14.5 years (range 5–30 years). Derived during model fitting, see Technical Appendix, Section #1 and #6.</td></tr><tr><td>wm</td><td>Waning immunity of aP, infant<xref rid="tblfn1" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td>3 months (range 2–4 months) <xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn1"><label>*</label><p id="np005">Waning of immunity in the infant; waning of immunity in the pregnant woman is not modeled. State-specific means that data or parameters are specific to each of the Brazilian states modelled in the present analysis: São Paulo, Paraná and Bahia.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s0020">
                <label>2.2</label>
                <title>Data</title>
                <p id="p0060">We modeled maternal aP immunization in three states: (a) São Paulo in Southeast Brazil, (b) Paraná in the South, and (c) Bahia in the Northeast. São Paulo is the most populous, the most developed, ranking 2nd in the country (out of 27) on the human development index and has the highest per capita income (<xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) <xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. The gross regional product per capita (the equivalent of the gross domestic product for the regions of a country) mirrors the previous statistics and, in 2014, was 17,881 USD in São Paulo, 13,310 USD in Paraná and 6273 USD in Bahia <xref rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. Infant vaccine coverage was lowest in Bahia in the two nationally representative surveys (<xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) <xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, <xref rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0010"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Summary of the characteristics of the states.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>Sao Paulo</th><th>Parana</th><th>Bahia</th><th>Source</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Population (millions, 2018)</td><td>45</td><td>11</td><td>15</td><td><xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref></td></tr><tr><td>Per capita income (monthly, Reais, 2017)</td><td>1712</td><td>1472</td><td>862</td><td><xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref></td></tr><tr><td>Employment (ind. ≥ 16 years of age, 2017)</td><td>72%</td><td>68%</td><td>40%</td><td><xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref></td></tr><tr><td>Human development index (HDI, 2010)</td><td>0.783</td><td>0.749</td><td>0.660</td><td><xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref></td></tr><tr><td>Relative HDI ranking (out of 27)</td><td>2nd</td><td>6th</td><td>22nd</td><td><xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref></td></tr><tr><td>Gross regional product per capita (USD)</td><td>17,881</td><td>13,310</td><td>6273</td><td><xref rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref></td></tr><tr><td>Vaccination</td><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>1991 birth cohort, assessed 1996, by region</td><td>72.9<xref rid="tblfn2" ref-type="table-fn">#</xref></td><td>87.1<xref rid="tblfn2" ref-type="table-fn">#</xref></td><td>60.7<xref rid="tblfn2" ref-type="table-fn">#</xref></td><td><xref rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref></td></tr><tr><td>2005 birth cohort, assessed 2007, by state capital</td><td>83.0<xref rid="tblfn3" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td>97.7<xref rid="tblfn3" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td>78.7<xref rid="tblfn3" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></td><td><xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn2"><label>#</label><p id="np010">Percent of children surveyed who within 12–23 months of age had received all childhood immunizations included in the national immunization program.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn3"><label>*</label><p id="np015">Percent of children surveyed who by 18 months of age had received all childhood immunizations included in the national immunization program.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s0025">
                <label>2.3</label>
                <title>Pertussis epidemiology</title>
                <p id="p0065">In Brazil, notification of pertussis is compulsory, and the clinical, epidemiologic and laboratory criteria used for case classification are standardized and periodically revised by the national public health surveillance system <xref rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. We undertook a comprehensive review of available demographic, epidemiologic, and mortality data for the three states (see the Technical Appendix, Section #2). Mandatory notification of pertussis cases has been in place since 1973 (in electronic format since 1998) and notified cases are available through the Brazilian National Notifiable Surveillance System (SINAN) <xref rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. Suspected cases are defined based on symptoms while confirmation of suspected cases can be based on clinical, laboratory, or epidemiological criteria <xref rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. We considered all confirmed cases, irrespective of confirmation criteria, and defined outpatient cases as all confirmed cases in the surveillance information system except for those indicated as requiring hospitalization. Hospitalized cases were obtained from the Brazilian Hospitalization Information System (SIH, Sistema de Informações Hospitalares do SUS) and were defined as all individuals hospitalized within SUS in which the main cause of hospitalization was reported as being pertussis. Since these represent only hospitalizations occurring within the public health system, we adjusted the number of hospitalizations by public health system (SUS) coverage in each state to estimate all hospitalizations. Deaths from pertussis were obtained from the Brazilian Mortality Information System (SIM, Sistema de Informação de Mortalidade).</p>
                <p id="p0070">Infant vaccination against pertussis was initiated in the 1970s with notable national increase in coverage after 1973 leading to a significant reduction in incidence during the 1990s. More recently, a significant increase in pertussis incidence has been observed in Brazil with the highest rates in infants younger than 6 months <xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref> and evidence of pertussis infection among adolescents and adults <xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. Evidence from nationwide studies show an increase in pertussis incidence as early as 2007 and peaking in 2010–2014 <xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="b0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, <xref rid="b0145" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. Some authors have suggested that it could be associated with decreased vaccination coverage in some parts of the country and with a switch from DTwPHib to DTwPHib-HBV in 2012 <xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, <xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, <xref rid="b0150" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>. A more recent study from São Paulo State, in the Southeast of Brazil, described similar findings with increase in cases in all age groups in 2011–2014 with a sharp decrease in 2015 <xref rid="b0155" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. As pointed out by others, the challenges to interpreting these trends include the recent introduction of new and more sensitive molecular diagnostic methods, including PCR in 2009, enhanced sensitivity of the surveillance system with selected hospital-based sentinel sites for severe pertussis surveillance, enhanced disease awareness as a result of the recent epidemic, and decrease in infant vaccination coverage over the years <xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, <xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, <xref rid="b0150" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, <xref rid="b0155" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>.</p>
                <p id="p0075">As mentioned in the Introduction, the diphtheria-tetanus vaccine was replaced with tetanus-diphtheria-acellular pertussis vaccine (Tdap) for pregnant women in 2014 <xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. The rationale for this strategy is to protect the infant too young to be vaccinated with transplacental antibody transfer from mother to infant, as well as to protect the mother and potentially reduce household transmission.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s0030">
                <label>2.4</label>
                <title>Costs</title>
                <p id="p0080">Details of the cost data are provided in the Technical Appendix (Section #4). Briefly, in the present, we included direct medical costs pertaining to pertussis disease and the costs of the vaccines. Costs of pertussis outpatient cases were estimated based on standardized guidelines for pertussis case management and included diagnostic exams, medical visits, and medications. Costs of inpatient pertussis cases, stratified by age sub-group and by patient outcome (survive/death) were derived from reimbursements paid for all pertussis hospitalizations in 2014 in the hospitals of the Brazilian National Public Health system (SUS), which covers 75% of the Brazilian population.</p>
                <p id="p0085">Brazil began maternal aP immunization in 2014 using a single dose vaccine of multivalent formulation (adolescent/adult TdaP) purchased through the Pan American Health Organization Revolving Fund. To the base price per dose (USD 8.9), freight and insurance charges (3%) and a service charge (4.25%) were added, bringing the total to USD 9.55. An additional 5% wastage rate, as recommended by WHO and varied between 0 and 15% in sensitivity analyses, was added (total cost USD 10). Delivery costs were not separately estimated for maternal aP immunization since Td is being replaced by TdaP, as such it is assumed that there is no incremental cost of delivering TdaP.</p>
                <p id="p0090">For infant wP vaccines, we used the 2014 listed dose price for the single dose pentavalent vaccine DTwPHib-HBV liquid formulation, which is purchased through the Pan American Health Organization Revolving Fund. To the base price per dose, freight and insurance charges (3%) and a service charge (4.25%) were added, totaling USD 2.71. An additional 5% wastage rate, as recommended by WHO and varied between 0 and 15% in sensitivity analyses, brings the cost for each vaccine dose to USD 2.84. The cost of delivering a dose of vaccine for any individual was obtained from a primary study conducted in 2013 in Brazil which estimated the cost of the immunization program in the country <xref rid="b0160" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s0035">
                <label>2.5</label>
                <title>Model fitting</title>
                <p id="p0095">An important step towards documenting the credibility and usefulness of a model is the process of model fitting. This involves exploring the different model structures as well as different parameter values which are varied within a priori plausible bounds to identify combinations that provide a better fit between model predicted time series and observed data. Parameters whose values were highly uncertain, even after consulting the available evidence, were derived during model fitting; these included: reporting probability for symptomatic cases, a multiplier that scales the probability of infection per contact, waning of immunity from infection, and duration of infection.</p>
                <p id="p0100">As calibration targets, we initially used monthly age-specific observed data from official sources for each Brazilian state for the period 2000–2016 and subsequently aggregated the data into one annual time series of cases for each age group (&lt;1, 1–9, and 10+ years of age) to ease computational burden. These calibration targets were fitted to model predicted age-specific time series of infections which were grouped into the corresponding age groups: &lt;1 year, 1–9 years and 10+ years of age, for each Brazilian state (São Paulo, Paraná, Bahia). Further details on the calibration targets and model predictions as provided in the Technical Appendix, Section #6.</p>
                <p id="p0105">To assess goodness of fit, we used graphical displays and multiple goodness-of-fit (GOF) statistics including the mean absolute error (MAE), which measures the average magnitude of the errors in a set of predictions; the root mean square error (RMSE), which gives the standard deviation of the prediction error; the normalized root mean square error (NRMSE), given in percentage; and the ratio of the RMSE to the standard deviation of the observations (RSR). For all these measures, the lower the value, the better the fit.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s0040">
                <label>2.6</label>
                <title>Interventions, primary outcome and analysis</title>
                <p id="p0110">The strategies modeled were 1) routine childhood pertussis wP vaccination only and 2) routine childhood wP vaccination plus aP maternal immunization. The impact of each strategy was simulated over a time horizon of 16 years, from 2014 when maternal aP immunization was introduced in Brazil to the end of 2029. We assumed the perspective of the Brazilian National Health system that accounts for direct medical costs for vaccination and disease treatment. Health, cost and cost-effectiveness outcomes were discounted at 3%, and the costs were expressed in 2014 US dollars.</p>
                <p id="p0115">For the cost-effectiveness analysis, our primary outcome was cost per disability-adjusted life year (DALY) averted. The number of DALYs was calculated as the sum of the number of years of life lost due to premature death and the number of years lost due to disability in the case of outpatient/inpatient cases using published methods <xref rid="b0165" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. These calculations used the disability weights for pertussis obtained from the Global Burden of Disease study <xref rid="b0170" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref> and average Brazilian life-expectancy, 81.75 years, as recommended in recent Burden of Disease studies from Brazil <xref rid="b0175" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. Further details are given in the Technical Appendix, Section #5.</p>
                <p id="p0120">The incremental cost-effectiveness ratio (ICER) of maternal aP was calculated by dividing the difference in cost between the two strategies, in 2014 US dollars, by the difference in DALYs which yields the cost/DALY. The decision to adopt a new intervention can be evaluated by comparing cost/DALY to estimates of societal willingness-to-pay for additional health gains. For comparison with prior studies, we defined an intervention as cost-effective if its cost/DALY averted is less than the state’s per capita Gross Regional Product <xref rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>.</p>
                <p id="p0125">One-way sensitivity analysis was assessed for a range of parameters including vaccine effectiveness, waning of immunity from infection, childhood vaccines and maternal vaccine, likelihood that the vaccine will fail, duration of infection, reporting probability for symptomatic cases, disability weight, discount rate, and costs (outpatient, inpatient, vaccine administration costs, maternal vaccine cost). Probabilistic sensitivity analyses were not performed as per current recommendations for dynamic transmission models <xref rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s0045">
              <label>3</label>
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="s0050">
                <label>3.1</label>
                <title>Model structure</title>
                <p id="p0130"><xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>, <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>, <xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> show, by state, the monthly number of outpatient and inpatient cases and deaths by aggregated age groups (&lt;1, 1–9, and 10+ years of age). Numbers of outpatient and inpatient cases and deaths were very low before 2010 and increased sharply between 2010 and 2014, as other epidemiologic studies from several regions in Brazil have shown <xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="b0145" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, <xref rid="b0155" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. Inpatient cases exceeded outpatient cases in those &lt;1 year of age likely due to the higher probability of severe disease in this age group.<fig id="f0005"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Age-specific (&lt;1 year, 1–9 years and 10+ years of age) monthly pertussis deaths (solid), inpatient cases (dotted) and outpatient cases (dashed) from Brazilian official sources in São Paulo, 2000–2016.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig><fig id="f0010"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Age-specific (&lt;1 year, 1–9 years and 10+ years of age) monthly pertussis deaths (solid), inpatient cases (dotted) and outpatient cases (dashed) from Brazilian official sources in Paraná, 2000–2016.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig><fig id="f0015"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Age-specific (&lt;1 year, 1–9 years and 10+ years of age) monthly pertussis deaths (solid), inpatient cases (dotted) and outpatient cases (dashed) from Brazilian official sources in Bahia, 2000–2016.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></p>
                <p id="p0135">Inspection of the graphical displays (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>, <xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, <xref rid="f0030" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>) show that models fitted reasonably well to the observed data though all models miss the 2014 peak by a substantial amount (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>, <xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, <xref rid="f0030" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>): the SIR produced the worst fit and the SIRS and the SIRSIs models fit best with small improvement in the fit statistics (<xref rid="t0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Among states, we see that the model for Paraná has the lowest NRMSE meaning that it had the best fit when compared to São Paulo and Bahia.<fig id="f0020"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Comparison between the observed data (circles) and model projected outcomes by model structure SIR (solid), SIRS (dotted) and SIRSIs (dashed) in São Paulo, 2000–2016.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig><fig id="f0025"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Comparison between the observed data (circles) and model projected outcomes by model structure SIR (solid), SIRS (dotted) and SIRSIs (dashed) in Paraná, 2000–2016.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr5"/></fig><fig id="f0030"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Comparison between the observed data (circles) and model projected outcomes by model structure SIR (solid), SIRS (dotted) and SIRSIs (dashed) in Bahia, 2000–2016.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr6"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="t0015"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Model goodness-of-fit statistics by model type and state: mean absolute error (MAE), root mean square error (RMSE), normalized root mean square error (NRMSE), and the ratio of the RMSE between the predictions and actual observation to the standard deviation of the observations (RSR).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>MAE</th><th>RMSE</th><th>NRMSE (%)</th><th>RSR</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>São Paulo</td><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>SIR</td><td>141.7</td><td>239.5</td><td>65.4</td><td>0.65</td></tr><tr><td>SIRS</td><td>129.9</td><td>221.6</td><td>60.5</td><td>0.60</td></tr><tr><td>SIRSIs</td><td>121.5</td><td>221.5</td><td>57.8</td><td>0.58</td></tr><tr><td>Paraná</td><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>SIR</td><td>20.5</td><td>35.9</td><td>45.3</td><td>0.45</td></tr><tr><td>SIRS</td><td>20.6</td><td>33.6</td><td>42.4</td><td>0.42</td></tr><tr><td>SIRSIs</td><td>19.8</td><td>32.3</td><td>40.7</td><td>0.41</td></tr><tr><td>Bahia</td><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>SIR</td><td>25.2</td><td>47.9</td><td>61.5</td><td>0.62</td></tr><tr><td>SIRS</td><td>22.6</td><td>44.2</td><td>56.8</td><td>0.57</td></tr><tr><td>SIRSIs</td><td>21.0</td><td>42.3</td><td>54.3</td><td>0.54</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
                <p id="p0140">Parameter values derived during model fitting included: reporting probability for symptomatic cases (São Paulo 3.4%, Paraná 2.5%, Bahia 1.4%), the multiplier that scales probability of infection (∼10×, not state-specific), waning of immunity from infection (∼25 years, not state-specific) and duration of infection (25 days, not state-specific).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s0055">
                <label>3.2</label>
                <title>Cost-effectiveness of aP immunization in the 3 states</title>
                <p id="p0145">The incremental cost-effectiveness of maternal aP immunization was USD 3068, 2962 and 2022 per DALY averted in São Paulo, Paraná and Bahia, respectively (<xref rid="t0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). The following sections detail the results for each state and the impact of parameter uncertainty on the results.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0020"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Impact of maternal aP on outpatient and inpatient cases, deaths, years of life lost, disability adjusted life-years and costs in São Paulo, Paraná, and Bahia, 2014–2029.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th colspan="2">São Paulo<hr/></th><th colspan="2">Paraná<hr/></th><th colspan="2">Bahia<hr/></th></tr><tr><th/><th>No aP</th><th>With aP</th><th>No aP</th><th>With aP</th><th>No aP</th><th>With aP</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Outpatient cases</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>&lt;1 year</td><td>15,237</td><td>3,547</td><td>3,756</td><td>1,877</td><td>2,902</td><td>1,242</td></tr><tr><td>1–9 years</td><td>46,957</td><td>25,066</td><td>9,702</td><td>7,877</td><td>7,014</td><td>5,540</td></tr><tr><td>10+ years</td><td>106,626</td><td>52,466</td><td>20,816</td><td>15,316</td><td>14,473</td><td>10,182</td></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>168,820</td><td>81,078</td><td>34,273</td><td>25,069</td><td>24,389</td><td>16,966</td></tr><tr><td>Outpatient cases averted (N)</td><td/><td>87,742</td><td/><td>9,204</td><td/><td>7,423</td></tr><tr><td>Outpatient cases averted (%)</td><td/><td>52.0</td><td/><td>26.9</td><td/><td>30.4</td></tr><tr><td>Inpatient cases</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>&lt;1 year</td><td>22,856</td><td>5319</td><td>5629</td><td>2814</td><td>4359</td><td>1865</td></tr><tr><td>1–9 years</td><td>22,088</td><td>8810</td><td>5507</td><td>4043</td><td>3944</td><td>2707</td></tr><tr><td>10+ years</td><td>2452</td><td>1125</td><td>489</td><td>351</td><td>339</td><td>229</td></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>47,399</td><td>15,250</td><td>11,626</td><td>7208</td><td>8643</td><td>4802</td></tr><tr><td>Inpatient cases averted (N)</td><td/><td>32,148</td><td/><td>4418</td><td/><td>3841</td></tr><tr><td>Inpatient cases averted (%)</td><td/><td>67.8</td><td/><td>38.0</td><td/><td>44</td></tr><tr><td>Deaths</td><td>301</td><td>70</td><td>138</td><td>66</td><td>201</td><td>85</td></tr><tr><td>Deaths averted (N)</td><td/><td>232</td><td/><td>72</td><td/><td>116</td></tr><tr><td>Years of life lost (YLL)</td><td>24,288</td><td>5651</td><td>10,861</td><td>5,428</td><td>16,391</td><td>7011</td></tr><tr><td>YLL averted (N)</td><td/><td>18,637</td><td/><td>5433</td><td/><td>9380</td></tr><tr><td>YLL averted (%)</td><td/><td>76.7</td><td/><td>50.0</td><td/><td>57.2</td></tr><tr><td>DALYs</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>&lt;1 year</td><td>24,363</td><td>5668</td><td>10,881</td><td>5,439</td><td>16,405</td><td>7,017</td></tr><tr><td>1–9 years</td><td>138</td><td>66</td><td>25</td><td>25</td><td>25</td><td>13</td></tr><tr><td>10+ years</td><td>213</td><td>104</td><td>38</td><td>26</td><td>25</td><td>22</td></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>24,712</td><td>5840</td><td>10,950</td><td>5493</td><td>16,453</td><td>7055</td></tr><tr><td>DALYs averted (N)</td><td/><td>18,872</td><td/><td>5458</td><td/><td>9399</td></tr><tr><td>DALYs averted (%)</td><td/><td>76.4</td><td/><td>49.8</td><td/><td>57.1</td></tr><tr><td>Costs (USD millions)</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Medical treatment</td><td>25.7</td><td>8.3</td><td>6.3</td><td>3.8</td><td>4.7</td><td>2.6</td></tr><tr><td>Vaccine</td><td>164.5</td><td>239.8</td><td>66.6</td><td>85.2</td><td>40.4</td><td>61.5</td></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>190.3</td><td>248.2</td><td>72.9</td><td>89.0</td><td>45.1</td><td>64.1</td></tr><tr><td>Incremental costs</td><td/><td>57.9</td><td/><td>16.2</td><td/><td>19.0</td></tr><tr><td>Cost (2014 USD) per DALY averted</td><td/><td>3068</td><td/><td>2962</td><td/><td>2022</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s0060">
                <label>3.3</label>
                <title>São Paulo</title>
                <p id="p0150">Maternal vaccination has an impact on all health outcomes, particularly deaths. With maternal vaccination, outpatient and inpatient cases decreased to 81,078 and 15,250 (52% of outpatient and 68% of inpatient cases were averted). Deaths in infants &lt;1 year of age dropped to 70 and years of life lost due to pertussis dropped to 5651. Overall, 77% of the DALYs expected to be lost to pertussis were averted by maternal vaccination. Total costs were higher with maternal vaccination than for routine infant wP vaccination alone, with vaccine costs increasing by ∼USD 75 million while medical costs decreased to 8.3 million. In total, incremental costs of maternal vaccination amounted to USD 57.9 million.</p>
                <p id="p0155">One-way sensitivity analyses showed that, in order, reporting probability for symptomatic cases, infection duration, aP vaccine cost and infant wP vaccine coverage were the most influential parameters. None of these parameters, however, led to cost-effectiveness ratios that exceeded São Paulo’s gross regional product per capita (17,881 USD in 2014).</p>
                <p id="p0160">Reporting probability for symptomatic cases, a highly uncertain parameter, was varied within the range estimated in the model fitting process. A higher reporting probability (10.4%) implied a much higher burden of cases and deaths yielding significantly higher medical costs. In this scenario, aP becomes more cost-effective, at 392 USD/DALY averted. In contrast, when reporting probability was lower (1.2%), reported cases, deaths, and medical costs decreased substantially. In this scenario, vaccine costs represent a higher fraction of total costs and the cost of maternal immunization increases to USD 10,731 USD/DALY averted.</p>
                <p id="p0165">The impact of infection duration is similar in that when the infectious period is longer, more cases/deaths are expected, leading to a lower cost/DALY averted (when infection lasts 28 days, rather than 25 as in the base case, USD 2319/DALY). When the infectious period is shorter (21 days), there are fewer cases/deaths and lower medical costs, with the result that maternal immunization costs USD 9823/DALY. At a higher vaccine cost (15 USD) maternal immunization costs USD 4620/DALY (50% higher than base case) while at lower cost (5 USD) it costs USD 1773/DALY (half of base case).</p>
                <p id="p0170">Increasing infant wP vaccine coverage to levels reported in 1996 in São Paulo, which were higher than those in 2007 makes maternal immunization less attractive (USD 4719/DALY averted). Similarly, when infant vaccination is assumed more effective (for example, when wP vaccine failure is assumed to be zero), maternal immunization becomes less attractive (USD 4350/DALY averted).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s0065">
                <label>3.4</label>
                <title>Paraná</title>
                <p id="p0175">With maternal vaccination, 27% of outpatient and 38% of inpatient cases were averted. Deaths in infants &lt;1 year of age dropped to 66 and years of life lost due to pertussis dropped by 50%. Overall, 50% of the DALYs expected to be lost to pertussis were averted by maternal vaccination. Total costs were higher due to vaccine costs. Paraná’s gross regional product in 2014 was 13,310 USD making maternal immunization in Paraná a cost-effective strategy, costing USD 2962 per DALY averted.</p>
                <p id="p0180">The same parameters that were most influential in São Paulo were also the most influential in Paraná. The reporting probability for symptomatic cases was the only parameter that led to significant changes with maternal immunization becoming more attractive when reporting probability was higher than base case (7.9%, USD 621/DALY averted) and not attractive when the reporting probability was lower than base case (0.4%, USD 18,604/DALY averted).</p>
                <p id="p0185">Increasing infant wP vaccine coverage to levels reported in 1996 in Paraná, which were higher than those in 2007 makes maternal immunization less attractive (USD 11,483/DALY averted). Compared to São Paulo and Bahia, the influence of infant wP vaccine coverage on the cost-effectiveness ratio was most striking for Paraná, a state where vaccine coverage has remained high over the years.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s0070">
                <label>3.5</label>
                <title>Bahia</title>
                <p id="p0190">Bahia was the state with the lowest estimated vaccination coverage and highest infant case-fatality. Nonetheless the results for the cost-effectiveness of maternal aP immunization were very similar to those in São Paulo and Paraná. In Bahia, the cost/DALY of maternal aP immunization was estimated at a third of Bahia’s gross regional product per capita (USD 6273 in 2014).</p>
                <p id="p0195">Again, the reporting probability for symptomatic cases was the most influential parameter, with maternal immunization costing USD 15,335/DALY averted when reporting probability was lower than base case (0.2%) and USD 395/DALY when reporting probability was higher than base case (5.2%). One-way sensitivity analyses again showed that, in order, infection duration, aP vaccine cost and wP vaccine coverage were also influential parameters though not to the point of making maternal vaccination not cost-effective.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s0075">
              <label>4</label>
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p id="p0200">We developed and tested three dynamic transmission model structures (SIR, SIRS, SIRSI) parameterized to represent three distinct lower-middle and upper-middle income settings and used the best fitting model structure to project the cost-effectiveness of maternal aP immunization. We found that the same model structure fit all three settings, despite their different demographic and socio-economic conditions. The SIR model structure showed the poorest fit to the data suggesting that to adequately capture pertussis dynamics it is important to allow for waning immunity and repeat infections, as previous studies have suggested <xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. The difference in fit between the two models that incorporate waning (SIRS and SIRSIs) was minimal. That the same model structure provides the best fit to all three states best supports the idea that the disease behaves similarly across different socioeconomic conditions and that it may apply to other lower- and middle-income settings. Thus this analysis provides support for our use of an SIRSIs model fitted to Brazilian disease data, with appropriate changes in key parameter values, to evaluate the cost-effectiveness of maternal immunization <xref rid="b0185" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>.</p>
              <p id="p0205">In dynamic models, the rate at which susceptible individuals become infected depends on the number of infectious individuals in the population at any given time <xref rid="b0190" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. This force of infection is crucial to the evaluation of vaccine programs because vaccination not only reduces the incidence of disease in those immunized, by direct protection, but also indirectly protects nonvaccinated individuals against infection <xref rid="b0190" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. This indirect protection is often referred to as herd immunity <xref rid="b0195" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>, <xref rid="b0200" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>, <xref rid="b0205" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>. In the simplest case, disease incidence should be reduced by a factor that is proportional to the product of vaccine coverage and vaccine efficacy <xref rid="b0200" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. However, a more realistic analysis, as Fine and colleagues suggests, should consider “(1) the distribution of vaccines and of disease risk in communities; (2) the nature of the immunity induced by the vaccine; as well as (3) the indirect protection of nonimmune persons by the presence of immune persons” <xref rid="b0200" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. Consideration of these factors implies that pertussis dynamics varies significantly over time and space.</p>
              <p id="p0210">Our models were developed following current recommendations for model conceptualization and validation. Recent literature has recommended that models aiming to assess the effect of vaccination should not apply the simulated vaccine program at birth nor at the end of the “vaccine schedule” (such as the end of the primary course) <xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. Accordingly, we have modeled vaccination by dose and age, incorporating both doses given at the recommended ages and those given later. This approach allowed for greater granularity in modeling vaccine coverage rates. Moreover, authors have suggested that models that fail to include fluctuations in vaccine coverage over time may not capture cohort effects, particularly when natural infection leads to long lasting immunity <xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. Our approach was to assume vaccine coverage changed over time as reported in nationally representative surveys of vaccine coverage in addition to published literature <xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, <xref rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, <xref rid="b0210" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>, <xref rid="b0215" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>, <xref rid="b0220" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>. As for more generic characteristics, as suggested <xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="b0225" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, our models incorporate multiple age groups, assume age-specific contact rates, and use multiple sources of local data for parametrization and model fitting.</p>
              <p id="p0215">In agreement with other modeling and economic studies of pertussis resurgence and alternative vaccination strategies <xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, <xref rid="b0230" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>, we found the reporting probability to be the most influential parameter. An analysis from the United States found that differences in the reporting probability (or reporting rate as it is usually denominated) implied a change in the decision whether or not to adopt maternal vaccination <xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. In a study from Australia, the reporting rate was the second most important parameter influencing the cost-effectiveness of maternal immunization <xref rid="b0235" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>. When authors assumed that a higher fraction of cases was reported, maternal aP was more cost-effective. The reporting rate represents the fraction of infections that require medical attention and thus incur costs. There are many layers involved in the relationship between an infection and a reported case including probability of developing of symptoms, probability of seeking care, physician awareness and willingness to notify, testing likelihood and accuracy of the methodology, and notification infrastructure. As a result, one should use local data to estimate this parameter and/or explore its impact in sensitivity analysis as reporting rates from a particular study or population are not applicable to other settings <xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>.</p>
              <p id="p0220">For the three different settings here explored, we used model fitting processes to estimate the reporting probability for symptomatic cases that best fitted the observed data. Our estimates indicated that the reporting probability varied by state, lowest in Bahia and highest in São Paulo, which might reflect the fact that São Paulo was one of the first states to institute molecular diagnostic methods and, in general, has more referral centers and resources <xref rid="b0155" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. With the estimated reporting probabilities, maternal aP immunization was found to be a cost-effective strategy. A higher reporting probability than assumed in base case makes maternal aP immunization more cost-effective because the added costs of the vaccine are offset by the savings in treatment costs. In contrast, a lower reporting probability compared to base case leads to maternal aP immunization being less attractive. Epidemiologic studies of pertussis disease burden suggest that cases are significantly underreported even in high-income settings <xref rid="b0240" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>, <xref rid="b0245" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>, <xref rid="b0250" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>, <xref rid="b0255" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref> and thus that lower estimates for the reporting probability are more realistic.</p>
              <p id="p0225">We also found that higher infant wP vaccine coverage made maternal aP immunization a less attractive strategy. The reasoning for this finding is that as fewer notified cases occur, due to high infant vaccine coverage, there is less disease burden to be averted by maternal immunization. However, current infant wP vaccine coverage levels have not significantly decreased transmission, leading to an increased disease burden in recent years, in particular among infants &lt;1 year who are most likely to be symptomatic, require hospitalization, and die <xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="b0155" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, <xref rid="b0160" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. Given currently observed pertussis incidence and infant coverage, maternal aP immunization would be a cost-effective strategy if the cost-effectiveness benchmark is each state’s GDP per capita, or even half of GDP per capita. Our results and conclusions are similar to those for Brazil as a whole <xref rid="b0185" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. Specifically, if infant wP vaccine coverage remains low, maternal aP immunization is cost-effective. At higher infant vaccine coverage rates (such as reported in 1996) the cost/DALY averted of maternal aP immunization is higher as there is less disease to be averted. In our analysis, the impact of higher infant vaccine coverage was most striking for Paraná, the state with highest coverage <xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. These findings evidence the contribution of herd immunity to the non-linear behavior of the dynamic model system <xref rid="b0195" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>.</p>
              <p id="p0230">Relatedly, in an accompanying paper <xref rid="b0260" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>, we compare maternal aP immunization cost-effectiveness results using a dynamic and a static model and highlight when the static model is likely sufficient for informing public health decisions. Results show that if infant vaccine coverage is low, then maternal immunization is cost-effective irrespective of model type. In contrast, when infant vaccine coverage is extremely high, then the dynamic transmission model is capable of showing how maternal immunization might not be cost-effective while the static model continues to suggest the strategy would be cost-effective. The rationale for implementing maternal aP immunization is direct protection of the newborns (0–2 months) through the maternal antibodies. As such, one could argue that having a maternal aP immunization in addition to infant vaccination could be valuable in settings where infant vaccine coverage cannot be expected to be maintained at a consistently high level over space and time. That is, if infant vaccine coverage is expected to vary, then maternal immunization acts as a backup, for safety, preventing infection among those who are most vulnerable to severe disease and death. For the present analysis, we reviewed available data on infant vaccine coverage for Brazil and its states and municipalities and found significant heterogeneity in space and time <xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, <xref rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, <xref rid="b0215" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>, <xref rid="b0220" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>, a scenario likely experienced in other low and middle income countries <xref rid="b0265" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>, <xref rid="b0270" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>.</p>
              <p id="p0235">We note a few important considerations on the concept of a “threshold proportion of immune persons that, if reached, could eliminate infection” (for a more complete assessment please refer to <xref rid="b0200" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>). The herd immunity threshold is “an epidemiologic attribute with which to characterize particular infections” for which rough estimates have been generated <xref rid="b0200" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. In reality, however, heterogeneities in population demography, social structure, and contact rates (within and between age groups), the degree and duration of immunity elicited by pathogen and vaccine, as well as the stochastic nature of epidemic processes play a role in determining the level of vaccination required to eliminate disease in a particular time and place <xref rid="b0200" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. Though our levels of vaccine coverage were relatively high, for Paraná in particular, results show that it is likely far from decreasing incidence to the point of elimination. Moreover, studies have shown a significant reduction in vaccine coverage, to levels clearly below any threshold, at the municipal level (83% of Brazilian municipalities reporting DTP coverage of 95% in 2006 but only 55% in 2012) <xref rid="b0145" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>. Incomplete vaccine coverage has been suggested as the reason for pertussis resurgence in Massachusetts as well <xref rid="b0275" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>.</p>
              <p id="p0240">Our study has several strengths and limitations that should be acknowledged. One strength was the use of local data to inform model fitting and parameter values. However, as observed in other settings <xref rid="b0240" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>, <xref rid="b0245" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>, <xref rid="b0250" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>, notified pertussis cases represent only a fraction of disease incidence which has influenced our fitting of the reporting probability parameter. In particular with regards to the 2014 increase in the number of reported cases, uncertainty about parameter values and model structure are among possible explanations for the under-fitting of the observed data. Of note is that, overall, all models under-fit the observed data for the age group &lt;1 year meaning that maternal aP immunization cost-effectiveness ratios may well represent conservative estimates. Perhaps other modeling strategies, such as stochastic or individual-based models, could better address the weakness of the current work though these would add their own challenges such as high dimension of the parameter space, program coding complexity, increased computer processing time, and subsequent parameter non-identifiability. A limitation is that vaccine coverage rates used to inform the model were available for only a few time points and that heterogeneities in coverage <xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, <xref rid="b0220" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref> were neglected. Moreover, for some parameters, such as the contact matrix, we had no local or Brazilian data and thus had to use data from countries with similar characteristics. The computational burden of fitting three different models to scarce observed data also limited the range of uncertainties that could be explored in sensitivity analyses. One example pertains to the reporting probability which was not age-specific and, for the SIRSI model that requires a reporting probability for secondary infections, an a priori assumption was made that its value be one-tenth of the reporting probability for primary infections. These assumptions, in turn, led to an age-dependent reporting probability effect in the SRISI model as it considers secondary infections that occur later in life. In addition, some aspects of pertussis natural history and the impact of vaccines, such as boosting or blunting of immunity from maternal antibodies, were not considered. Importantly, and following the recommendations highlighted in three reviews of economic analyses of pertussis vaccination strategies <xref rid="b0230" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>, <xref rid="b0280" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>, <xref rid="b0285" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>, limited understanding of important aspects of pertussis epidemiology suggests caution when extrapolating our results. More studies are needed to better inform the relationship between infection and case notification, the duration of immunity conferred by infection and vaccines, and how boosting of immunity may result from silent infections. Finally, though we did explore different model structures, we relied on an objective comparison of the goodness of fit of the three models, choosing the one with the best fit. The chosen model (SIRSIs) however, is less parsimonious than the SIRS model.</p>
              <p id="p0245">Nonetheless, dynamic transmission models are useful for projecting potential health outcomes and generating evidence for policy recommendations. We have shown that the SIRSIs model structure fit best the pertussis epidemiology of three settings that represent diverse socio-demographic conditions. It is thus reasonable to suggest that the same structure can represent disease transmission in a range of lower- and middle-income settings <xref rid="b0185" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. Our results also highlight the implications of the under-reporting of diseases which may lead to an underestimation of the value of reducing disease burden.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s0080">
              <title>Authors contributions</title>
              <p id="p0250">PML, CMT, SK, and LBR conceived the study, interpreted the results and wrote the paper. PML and CJS performed the analyses. SK, RM, ALA, CS, LBR and CMT collected the data and contributed to the analyses. CJS, SK, RM, ALA, and CS reviewed the manuscript.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s0085">
              <title>Funding</title>
              <p id="p0255"><funding-source id="gp005"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100000865</institution-id><institution>Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> Grant OPP1124529.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="COI-statement">
              <title>Declaration of Competing Interest</title>
              <p id="p0260">The authors declare the following financial interests/personal relationships which may be considered as potential competing interests: Dr. Andrade has received lecture fees and travel grants from GlaxoSmithKline and Pfizer. Dr. Minamisava has received travel grants from GlaxoSmithKline. All other authors have no conflicts of interest.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list id="bi005">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="b0005">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0005">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Black</surname>
                      <given-names>R.E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Global, regional, and national causes of child mortality in 2008: a systematic analysis</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet</source>
                  <volume>375</volume>
                  <issue>9730</issue>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <fpage>1969</fpage>
                  <lpage>1987</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20466419</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0010">
                <label>2</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0010">Plotkin SA, Orenstein WA, Offit PA. Vaccines. Sixth edition. ed. Philadelphia, Pa.: Elsevier Saunders; 2013. xix, p. 1550.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0015">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0015">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Broutin</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Impact of vaccination and birth rate on the epidemiology of pertussis: a comparative study in 64 countries</article-title>
                  <source>Proc Biol Sci</source>
                  <volume>277</volume>
                  <issue>1698</issue>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <fpage>3239</fpage>
                  <lpage>3245</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20534609</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0020">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0020">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Guimaraes</surname>
                      <given-names>L.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Carneiro</surname>
                      <given-names>E.L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Carvalho-Costa</surname>
                      <given-names>F.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Increasing incidence of pertussis in Brazil: a retrospective study using surveillance data</article-title>
                  <source>BMC Infect Dis</source>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <fpage>442</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26498058</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0025">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0025">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rohani</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Drake</surname>
                      <given-names>J.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The decline and resurgence of pertussis in the US</article-title>
                  <source>Epidemics</source>
                  <volume>3</volume>
                  <issue>3–4</issue>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <fpage>183</fpage>
                  <lpage>188</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22094341</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0030">
                <label>6</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0030">SAGE. WHO SAGE pertussis working group. Background paper. April 2014. Available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/immunization/sage/meetings/2014/april/1_Pertussis_background_FINAL4_web.pdf" id="ir010">https://www.who.int/immunization/sage/meetings/2014/april/1_Pertussis_background_FINAL4_web.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed March 6 2019; 2014.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0035">
                <label>7</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0035">Bagattini AM, et al. The data used to build the models: Pertussis morbidity and mortality burden considering various Brazilian data sources. Vaccine, Submitted.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0040">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0040">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Atkins</surname>
                      <given-names>K.E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cost-effectiveness of pertussis vaccination during pregnancy in the United States</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Epidemiol</source>
                  <volume>183</volume>
                  <issue>12</issue>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <fpage>1159</fpage>
                  <lpage>1170</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27188951</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0045">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0045">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>van Hoek</surname>
                      <given-names>A.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cost-effectiveness and programmatic benefits of maternal vaccination against pertussis in England</article-title>
                  <source>J Infect</source>
                  <volume>73</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <fpage>28</fpage>
                  <lpage>37</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27108802</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0050">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0050">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hoshi</surname>
                      <given-names>S.L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cost-effectiveness analysis of pertussis vaccination during pregnancy in Japan</article-title>
                  <source>Vaccine</source>
                  <volume>36</volume>
                  <issue>34</issue>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <fpage>5133</fpage>
                  <lpage>5140</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30041878</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0055">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0055">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brasil</surname>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Guia de Vigilância em Saúde. Secretaria de Vigilância em Saúde. Coordenação Geral de Desenvolvimento da Epidemiologia. Ministério da Saúde</article-title>
                  <source>Brasília.</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0060">
                <label>12</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0060">Brasil. Informe Técnico para Implantação da Vacina Adsorvida Difteria, Tétano e Coqueluche (Pertussis Acelular) tipo adulto - dTpa. Secretaria de Vigilância em Saúde. Departamento de Vigilância Epidemiológica. Ministério da Saúde. Brasília. Available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://portalarquivos2.saude.gov.br/images/pdf/2015/junho/26/Informe-T--cnico-dTpa-2014.pdf" id="ir015">http://portalarquivos2.saude.gov.br/images/pdf/2015/junho/26/Informe-T--cnico-dTpa-2014.pdf</ext-link>; 2014.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0065">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0065">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Blackwood</surname>
                      <given-names>J.C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Deciphering the impacts of vaccination and immunity on pertussis epidemiology in Thailand</article-title>
                  <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
                  <volume>110</volume>
                  <issue>23</issue>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <fpage>9595</fpage>
                  <lpage>9600</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23690587</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0070">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0070">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Campbell</surname>
                      <given-names>P.T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McCaw</surname>
                      <given-names>J.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McVernon</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Pertussis models to inform vaccine policy</article-title>
                  <source>Hum Vaccin Immunother</source>
                  <volume>11</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <fpage>669</fpage>
                  <lpage>678</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25714499</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0075">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0075">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mossong</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Social contacts and mixing patterns relevant to the spread of infectious diseases</article-title>
                  <source>PLoS Med</source>
                  <volume>5</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e74</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0080">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0080">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bento</surname>
                      <given-names>A.I.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rohani</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Forecasting epidemiological consequences of maternal immunization</article-title>
                  <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
                  <volume>63</volume>
                  <issue>suppl 4</issue>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <fpage>S205</fpage>
                  <lpage>S212</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27838674</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0085">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0085">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Choi</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Investigating the pertussis resurgence in England and Wales, and options for future control</article-title>
                  <source>BMC Med</source>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <fpage>121</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27580649</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0090">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0090">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fulton</surname>
                      <given-names>T.R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Protective effect of contemporary pertussis vaccines: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>
                  <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
                  <volume>62</volume>
                  <issue>9</issue>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <fpage>1100</fpage>
                  <lpage>1110</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26908803</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0095">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0095">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Juretzko</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effectiveness of acellular pertussis vaccine assessed by hospital-based active surveillance in Germany</article-title>
                  <source>Clin Infect Dis</source>
                  <volume>35</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <fpage>162</fpage>
                  <lpage>167</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12087522</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0100">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0100">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Amirthalingam</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effectiveness of maternal pertussis vaccination in England: an observational study</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet</source>
                  <volume>384</volume>
                  <issue>9953</issue>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <fpage>1521</fpage>
                  <lpage>1528</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25037990</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0105">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0105">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Magpantay</surname>
                      <given-names>F.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Pertussis immunity and epidemiology: mode and duration of vaccine-induced immunity</article-title>
                  <source>Parasitology</source>
                  <volume>143</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <fpage>835</fpage>
                  <lpage>849</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26337864</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0110">
                <label>22</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0110">IBGE. Cidades e Estados. Instituto Brasileiro de Geografia e Estatística [National Institute of Geography and Statistics]. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ibge.gov.br/cidades-e-estados.html" id="ir020">https://www.ibge.gov.br/cidades-e-estados.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0115">
                <label>23</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0115">IMF. International Monetary Fund. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.imf.org" id="ir025">www.imf.org</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0120">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0120">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Barata</surname>
                      <given-names>R.B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Socioeconomic inequalities and vaccination coverage: results of an immunisation coverage survey in 27 Brazilian capitals, 2007–2008</article-title>
                  <source>J Epidemiol Community Health</source>
                  <volume>66</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <fpage>934</fpage>
                  <lpage>941</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22268129</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0125">
                <label>25</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0125">Brasil. Pesquisa Nacional Sobre Demografia e Saúde 1996. Sociedade Civil Bem-Estar Familiar no Brasil, BEMFAM, Programa de Pesquisas de Demografia e Saúde (DHS) Macro International Inc. Available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://dhsprogram.com/pubs/pdf/fr77/fr77.pdf" id="ir030">https://dhsprogram.com/pubs/pdf/fr77/fr77.pdf</ext-link>; 1997.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0130">
                <label>26</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0130">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pimentel</surname>
                      <given-names>A.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Pertussis may be the cause of prolonged cough in adolescents and adults in the interepidemic period</article-title>
                  <source>Braz J Infect Dis</source>
                  <volume>19</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <fpage>43</fpage>
                  <lpage>46</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25452019</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0135">
                <label>27</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0135">Brasil. Boletim Epidemiológico. Situação Epidemiológica da Coqueluche. Volume 47. Secretaria de Vigilância em Saúde. Ministério da Saúde. Brasília; 2015.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0140">
                <label>28</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0140">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Torres</surname>
                      <given-names>R.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Resurgence of pertussis at the age of vaccination: clinical, epidemiological, and molecular aspects</article-title>
                  <source>J Pediatr (Rio J)</source>
                  <volume>91</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <fpage>333</fpage>
                  <lpage>338</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25623040</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0145">
                <label>29</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0145">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Falleiros Arlant</surname>
                      <given-names>L.H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Pertussis in Latin America: epidemiology and control strategies</article-title>
                  <source>Expert Rev Anti Infect Ther</source>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <fpage>1265</fpage>
                  <lpage>1275</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25139010</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0150">
                <label>30</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0150">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Willemann</surname>
                      <given-names>M.C.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Pertussis and number of doses of vaccine administered: a case-control study</article-title>
                  <source>Epidemiologia e Serviço de Saúde</source>
                  <volume>23</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <fpage>207</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0155">
                <label>31</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0155">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fernandes</surname>
                      <given-names>E.G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Challenges of interpreting epidemiologic surveillance pertussis data with changing diagnostic and immunization practices: the case of the state of Sao Paulo, Brazil</article-title>
                  <source>BMC Infect Dis</source>
                  <volume>18</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <fpage>126</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29534683</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0160">
                <label>32</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0160">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rivera-Rodriguez</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Toscano</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Resch</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Improved calibration estimators for the total cost of health programs and application to immunization in Brazil</article-title>
                  <source>PLoS ONE</source>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0212401</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0165">
                <label>33</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0165">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Murray</surname>
                      <given-names>C.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lopez</surname>
                      <given-names>A.D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Measuring the global burden of disease</article-title>
                  <source>N Engl J Med</source>
                  <volume>369</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <fpage>448</fpage>
                  <lpage>457</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23902484</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0170">
                <label>34</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0170">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Salomon</surname>
                      <given-names>J.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Disability weights for the Global Burden of Disease 2013 study</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet Glob Health</source>
                  <volume>3</volume>
                  <issue>11</issue>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <fpage>e712</fpage>
                  <lpage>e723</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26475018</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0175">
                <label>35</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0175">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leite Ida</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Burden of disease in Brazil and its regions, 2008</article-title>
                  <source>Cad Saude Publica</source>
                  <volume>31</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <fpage>1551</fpage>
                  <lpage>1564</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26248109</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0180">
                <label>36</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0180">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pitman</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Dynamic transmission modeling: a report of the ISPOR-SMDM Modeling Good Research Practices Task Force Working Group-5</article-title>
                  <source>Med Decis Making</source>
                  <volume>32</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <fpage>712</fpage>
                  <lpage>721</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22990086</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0185">
                <label>37</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0185">Kim S, et al. Cost-effectiveness of maternal pertussis immunization: Implications of a dynamic transmission model for low- and middle-income countries. Vaccine 2021;39(1):147–57.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0190">
                <label>38</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0190">Anderson RM, May RM. Infectious diseases of humans: dynamics and control. Oxford science publications. Oxford; New York: Oxford University Press. viii; 1991. p. 757.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0195">
                <label>39</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0195">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brisson</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Edmunds</surname>
                      <given-names>W.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Economic evaluation of vaccination programs: the impact of herd-immunity</article-title>
                  <source>Med Decis Making</source>
                  <volume>23</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <fpage>76</fpage>
                  <lpage>82</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12583457</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0200">
                <label>40</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0200">Fine PEM, et al., Chapter 77. Community protection. In: Plotkin SA, et al., editors. Vaccines. Elsevier; 2018. p. 1512–31.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0205">
                <label>41</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0205">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fine</surname>
                      <given-names>P.E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Herd immunity: history, theory, practice</article-title>
                  <source>Epidemiol Rev</source>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>1993</year>
                  <fpage>265</fpage>
                  <lpage>302</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8174658</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0210">
                <label>42</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0210">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Barata</surname>
                      <given-names>R.B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Immunization coverage survey: empirical assessment of the cluster sampling method proposed by the World Health Organization</article-title>
                  <source>Rev Panam Salud Publica</source>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <fpage>184</fpage>
                  <lpage>190</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15826398</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0215">
                <label>43</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0215">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>de Moraes Jde</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Vaccination coverage in the first year of life in 4 cities of the state of Sao Paulo, Brazil</article-title>
                  <source>Rev Panam Salud Publica</source>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <fpage>332</fpage>
                  <lpage>341</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11190970</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0220">
                <label>44</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0220">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Queiroz</surname>
                      <given-names>L.L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Coverage of the basic immunization schedule in the first year of life in State capitals in Northeast Brazil</article-title>
                  <source>Cad Saude Publica</source>
                  <volume>29</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <fpage>294</fpage>
                  <lpage>302</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23459815</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0225">
                <label>45</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0225">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>De Angelis</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Four key challenges in infectious disease modelling using data from multiple sources</article-title>
                  <source>Epidemics</source>
                  <volume>10</volume>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <lpage>87</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25843390</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0230">
                <label>46</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0230">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fernandes</surname>
                      <given-names>E.G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Economic evaluation of adolescents and adults' pertussis vaccination: a systematic review of current strategies</article-title>
                  <source>Hum Vaccin Immunother</source>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <fpage>14</fpage>
                  <lpage>27</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30118618</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0235">
                <label>47</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0235">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Van Bellinghen</surname>
                      <given-names>L.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Is adding maternal vaccination to prevent whooping cough cost-effective in Australia?</article-title>
                  <source>Hum Vaccin Immunother</source>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <issue>9</issue>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <fpage>2263</fpage>
                  <lpage>2273</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29771574</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0240">
                <label>48</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0240">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Crowcroft</surname>
                      <given-names>N.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Deaths from pertussis are underestimated in England</article-title>
                  <source>Arch Dis Child</source>
                  <volume>86</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <fpage>336</fpage>
                  <lpage>338</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11970924</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0245">
                <label>49</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0245">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Crowcroft</surname>
                      <given-names>N.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Under-reporting of pertussis in Ontario: A Canadian Immunization Research Network (CIRN) study using capture-recapture</article-title>
                  <source>PLoS ONE</source>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0195984</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0250">
                <label>50</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0250">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>van der Maas</surname>
                      <given-names>N.A.T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Severe underestimation of pertussis related hospitalizations and deaths in the Netherlands: a capture-recapture analysis</article-title>
                  <source>Vaccine</source>
                  <volume>35</volume>
                  <issue>33</issue>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <fpage>4162</fpage>
                  <lpage>4166</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28651837</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0255">
                <label>51</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0255">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>de Melker</surname>
                      <given-names>H.E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The incidence of Bordetella pertussis infections estimated in the population from a combination of serological surveys</article-title>
                  <source>J Infect</source>
                  <volume>53</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <fpage>106</fpage>
                  <lpage>113</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16352342</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0260">
                <label>52</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0260">Russell LB, et al. Comparison of static and dynamic models of maternal immunization to prevent infant pertussis in Brazil. Submitted to Special Issue; 2019.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0265">
                <label>53</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0265">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mosser</surname>
                      <given-names>J.F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Mapping diphtheria-pertussis-tetanus vaccine coverage in Africa, 2000–2016: a spatial and temporal modelling study</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet</source>
                  <volume>393</volume>
                  <issue>10183</issue>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <fpage>1843</fpage>
                  <lpage>1855</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30961907</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0270">
                <label>54</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0270">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Peck</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Global routine vaccination coverage, 2018</article-title>
                  <source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source>
                  <volume>68</volume>
                  <issue>42</issue>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <fpage>937</fpage>
                  <lpage>942</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31647786</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0275">
                <label>55</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0275">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Domenech de Celles</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The impact of past vaccination coverage and immunity on pertussis resurgence</article-title>
                  <source>Sci Transl Med</source>
                  <volume>10</volume>
                  <issue>434</issue>
                  <year>2018</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0280">
                <label>56</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0280">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rivero-Santana</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effectiveness and cost-effectiveness of different immunization strategies against whooping cough to reduce child morbidity and mortality</article-title>
                  <source>Health Policy</source>
                  <volume>115</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <fpage>82</fpage>
                  <lpage>91</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24444703</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0285">
                <label>57</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0285">Kim S, et al. Dynamic transmission models of pertussis vaccination and modeling implications for low- and middle-income countries: a systematic review. Vaccine, Submitted.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
            <sec id="s0095" sec-type="supplementary-material">
              <label>Appendix A</label>
              <title>Supplementary material</title>
              <p id="p0270">The following are the Supplementary data to this article:<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="m0010"><caption><title>Supplementary data 1</title></caption><media xlink:href="mmc1.docx"/></supplementary-material></p>
              <p id="p0275">
                <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="m0005">
                  <caption>
                    <title>Supplementary data 2</title>
                  </caption>
                  <media xlink:href="mmc2.docx"/>
                </supplementary-material>
              </p>
            </sec>
            <fn-group>
              <fn id="s0090" fn-type="supplementary-material">
                <label>Appendix A</label>
                <p id="p0265">Supplementary data to this article can be found online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vaccine.2020.09.008" id="ir005">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.vaccine.2020.09.008</ext-link>.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
