<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-03-11T00:57:37Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7759445" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7759445</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-12-28</datestamp>
        <setSpec>pheelsevier</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Results Phys</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Results Phys</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Results in Physics</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2211-3797</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>The Author(s). Published by Elsevier B.V.</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC7759445</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7759445</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">7759445</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33391984</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2211-3797(20)32160-4</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rinp.2020.103746</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">103746</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>A modified <italic>SEIR</italic> model to predict the COVID-19 outbreak in Spain and Italy: Simulating control scenarios and multi-scale epidemics</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au005">
                  <name>
                    <surname>López</surname>
                    <given-names>Leonardo</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au010">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Rodó</surname>
                    <given-names>Xavier</given-names>
                  </name>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="af005">Barcelona Institute for Global Health, Barcelona, Spain</aff>
                <aff id="af010">ICREA and Barcelona Institute for Global Health, Barcelona, Spain</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author.</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>25</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2020</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.-->
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <month>2</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>25</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2020</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>21</volume>
              <fpage>103746</fpage>
              <lpage>103746</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>4</day>
                  <month>9</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>15</day>
                  <month>12</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>16</day>
                  <month>12</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2020 The Author(s)</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2020</copyright-year>
                <license>
                  <license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="ab005">
                <p>After the spread of the SARS-CoV-2 epidemic out of China, evolution in the pandemic worldwide shows dramatic differences among countries. In Europe, the situation of Italy first and later Spain has generated great concen, and despite other countries show better prospects, large uncertainties yet remain on the future evolution and the efficacy of containment, mitigation, or attack strategies. This Manuscript was originally written in the last days of March as a way to report on the first current wave of the pandemic. The results were updated several times for March and also for the month of July. Here we applied a modified <italic>SEIR</italic> compartmental model accounting for the spread of infection during the latent period, in which we also incorporate effects of varying proportions of containment. We fit data to reported infected populations at the beginning of the first peak of the pandemic to account for the uncertainties in case reporting and study the scenario projections for the individual regions (CCAA). The aim of this model it’s to evaluate the confinement rate at the first stages of the epidemic outbreak in order to assess the scenarios that minimize the incidence but also the mortality. Results indicate that with data for March 23, the epidemics follow an evolution similar to the isolation of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si472.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> percent of the population, and if there were no effects of intervention actions it might reach a maximum of over <inline-formula><mml:math id="M2" altimg="si473.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.4</mml:mn><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> infected around April 27. The effect on the epidemics of the ongoing partial confinement measures is yet unknown (an update of results with data until March 31st is included), but increasing the isolation around ten times more could drastically reduce the peak to over <inline-formula><mml:math id="M3" altimg="si474.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> cases by early April, while each day of delay in taking this hard containment scenario represents a 90 percent increase of the infected population at the peak. Dynamics at the sub aggregated levels of CCAA show epidemics at the different levels of progression with the most worrying situation in Madrid and Catalonia. Increasing alpha values up to 10 times, in addition to a drastic reduction in clinical cases, would also more than a half the number of deaths. Updates for March 31st simulations indicate a substantial reduction in burden is underway. A similar approach conducted for Italy pre-and post-intervention also begins to suggest a substantial reduction in both infected and deaths has been achieved, showing the efficacy of drastic social distancing interventions. By last we show the real evolution of the pandemic up to the end of May and the beginning of July in order to calculate the real confinement rate from data to compare with the scenarios formulated at March.</p>
              </abstract>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="s0005">
              <label>1</label>
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p id="p0005">Epidemiological reports for the current situation of COVID-19 out of China indicate Europe was one of the centers of the pandemic in the month of May, and that nearly 200 countries/regions worldwide have reported cases <xref rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. Particularly in Italy and Spain, a large outbreak of SARS-CoV-2 infection occurred in the month of March 2020. Given the lack of previous exposure to this virus, future predictions of both the levels of virus spread in the global naive population and the acquired herd immunity cannot be properly anticipated. Data on the last similar pandemic one century ago remains limited for obvious reasons, despite aftermath reports exist <xref rid="b0010" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. Policymakers in the most affected countries face a difficult situation when trying to balance between draconian public health actions and keeping the economy alive, as the impact on the health of severe economic measures is also well-known <xref rid="b0015" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. The fact that the 1918 Spanish flu pandemic had a second deadly epidemic wave, presumably caused by mutations in the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M4" altimg="si475.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> viral strain <xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, has also stimulated a vivid debate on whether actions to take now should take into account this uncertain future. Under this scenario, optimal action on the COVID-19 pandemic is hard to fathom. And more so, the extent of pre-symptomatic and asymptomatic infections is not narrowly constrained (e.g. up to 86 percent<xref rid="b0025" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>). In China, regions as well as local governments, including Hubei, tightened preventive measures to curb the spreading of COVID-19 since Jan. 2020 <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. Many cities in Hubei province were locked down and many measures were implemented, such as tracing close contacts, quarantining infected cases, promoting social consensus on self-protection (e.g. wearing a face mask in the public area, minimum social distances). However, in other areas, the extent and efficacy of the so-called confinement or self-isolation are doubtful, and Facebook data on mobile location and movement showed yet massive people displacements under semi-confinement measures. At a time when the success of large-scale social distancing interventions is critical, access to accurate information to ascertain mobility is lacking <xref rid="b0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. Similarly, credible serology tests that could show whether someone has had the infection and recovered are not yet massively deployed, thereby assessment of SARS-CoV-2 prevalence in the population is not established <xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>.</p>
              <p id="p0010">We followed the approach of Peng et al. <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref> and implemented a modified SEIR model that accounts for the spread of infection during the latent period. This novel capacity to significantly spread during the latent period is a distinctive feature of the current SARS-CoV-2 epidemic if compared to SARS in 2003. Therefore, many classical models such as SIR<xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="b0050" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, SEIR <xref rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref> and SEIJR <xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref> are not appropriate to describe the outbreak of SARS-CoV-2 in China and elsewhere. Thanks to new data on the average latent period and average time of treatment, this time delay process can be successfully incorporated in a novel dynamical system framework to describe these unique dynamics. It has been discussed that at times of ongoing epidemics, and due to errors and under-reporting, accumulated numbers of diagnosed cases and even the number of deaths might reflect more reliably the extent of epidemic progression than the daily reported new cases. Alternately, and as in Chen 2020 <xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref> and Peng et al. <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref> we also employ the accumulated numbers in time as variables, as it was done also for modeling MERS-CoV in the recent past <xref rid="b0065" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. According with some studies <xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref> many of the first cases in China (before January 1, 2020), were linked to the Huanan Seafood Wholesale Market, as compared with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M5" altimg="si476.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>8.6</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> of the subsequent cases. The mean incubation period was <inline-formula><mml:math id="M6" altimg="si477.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>5.2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> days, with the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M7" altimg="si478.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>95</mml:mn><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">th</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> percentile of the distribution at <inline-formula><mml:math id="M8" altimg="si479.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12.5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> days. In its early stages, the epidemic doubled in size every <inline-formula><mml:math id="M9" altimg="si480.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>7.4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> days. With a mean serial interval of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M10" altimg="si481.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>7.5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> days, the basic reproductive number was estimated to be <inline-formula><mml:math id="M11" altimg="si482.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2.2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. On the basis of this information, there is evidence that human-to–human transmission has occurred among close contacts since the middle of December 2019. Isolating key segments of populations (e.g. vulnerable populations, workers providing essential services, or territory with too fast-growing incidences) to protect them from an uncontrolled epidemic progression, is under vivid discussion as the real extent of viral spread in the population is not well known. Both the limited diagnostic capacity and the lack of clear strategies and mechanisms to quarantine infectious individuals, stand as two of the main limitations to control disease spread. Countries such as South Korea <xref rid="b0075" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref> and Taiwan <xref rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref> rapidly deployed aggressive contact tracing and quarantine systems <xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, understanding that early deployment of resources to try to control initial seeding foci, often not only balances public health criteria but also economics. Given the differences in public health strategies and the varying capacity of the national health systems in each country to tackle the extent of the infection in the population, the growing proportions of undiagnosed infected that eventually show up, are seen to exert elevated stress on the already saturated health’s system capacities. It is therefore relevant to accurately evaluate the effects of the social distancing actions imposed by governments, such as the individual or territory isolation and interruption of labor activity and/or intra and inter-urban transportation. Such strong provisions of isolation for suspected cases and infection due to contact with undiagnosed individuals are also taken into account in our modeling approach. This same SEIR model has been utilized to compare the effects of the lock-down of Hubei province on the transmission dynamics in Wuhan and Beijing <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. Many works have been done to evaluate different aspects of COVID-19 dynamics. In Mohammad et al. <xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref> authors use a dynamical model based on the fractional derivative of nonlinear equations that describe the outbreak of COVID-19 according to the available infection data in the press. They simulate the available total cases reported and based on the data they use to show graphical illustrations of the numerical solutions of all parameters of the model being handled under different situations. The results of the model contribute to the ongoing research to reduce the spreading of the virus and infection cases but the complexity of the model can be very high.</p>
              <p id="p0015">The model formulated by Khan and Atangana <xref rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref> describes a mathematical model for CVID-19 putting the eye in the details of interaction among the bats and unknown hosts, then among the peoples and the reservoir of the infection (seafood market). In this work, the seafood market is considered the main source of infection. They assume the purchasing of items from the seafood market can infect either asymptomatically or symptomatically. They consider the available infection cases for January <inline-formula><mml:math id="M12" altimg="si483.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>21</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2020</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, till January <inline-formula><mml:math id="M13" altimg="si484.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>28</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2020</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. This model is centered on the very early stages of the pandemic and tries to solve the source of this worldwide infectious disease. This model is based on a previous work by Singh et al. <xref rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref> where the authors analyze the epidemiological model to describe computer viruses with an arbitrary order derivative having a non-singular kernel.</p>
              <p id="p0020">Gao et al. <xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref> investigate to find the optimal values of a mathematical model that reproduces the transfer of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M14" altimg="si485.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2019</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">-</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">nCoV</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> from the reservoir to people. This model, named Bats-Hosts-Reservoir-People coronavirus (BHRPC) model, is based on bats as essential animal reservoirs. They simulate the spreading under the optimal parameters. Whereas the obtained results show the effectiveness of the theoretical method considered for the governing system, the results also present much shed light on the dynamic behavior of the Bats-Hosts-Reservoir-People transmission network coronavirus model. As in the previous case, in this paper authors concentrate on the virus spillover from the animal reservoir more than on the human to human transmission of the virus.</p>
              <p id="p0025">Since the beginning of the pandemic, many efforts have been made by the scientific community to assess the possible impact of the pandemic to analyze strategies to mitigate its effect on the population <xref rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. In this sense, several approaches have been proposed. From machine learning techniques to understand the spreading and improve the forecasting of the infection <xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, to classic modeling approaches <xref rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, <xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref> based on differential equations as previously mentioned. All of these efforts are not in vain since different model configurations tackle/approach different aspects of the same problem. different aspects of the same problem.</p>
              <p id="p0030">In this work, we present a simple and easy-to-implement mathematical model that allows us to easily evaluate the best population confinement strategy during the initial stages of an outbreak. This allows us to know the impact that this strategy has on the final size of the outbreak and number of deaths. To do this, we focus on the first COVID-19 wave that spanned from early February to mid-July in Europe. We only use the data from the first wave of the pandemic due to there is a high discrepancy in the way this data was reported after July. For Spain, this problem is notable, mainly for the recovered cases but also for the reported cases.</p>
              <p id="p0035">The manuscript is organized as follows: in Section <xref rid="s0010" ref-type="sec">2</xref>, we describe the dynamic model and datasets used to simulate the evolution of the outbreak of SARS-CoV-2 in Spain and its administrative regions (CCAA), as well as in Italy, we also describe the methods used for the model optimization and the main parameters. The effect on the epidemic curves of the efficacy of the different intervention measures aggregated for Spain is presented in Section <xref rid="s0020" ref-type="sec">3.1</xref>. Section <xref rid="s0025" ref-type="sec">3.2</xref> provides estimates of the future number of diagnosed people, fatalities, and recovered individuals for each CCAA prediction as of March 23 and the main active foci in Section <xref rid="s0035" ref-type="sec">3.3</xref>. Section <xref rid="s0040" ref-type="sec">3.4</xref> addresses model uncertainties and limitations of our study, and we add results for Italy pre- and post-interventions in Section <xref rid="s0045" ref-type="sec">3.5</xref>. We also discuss the efficacy of possible actions in each case and territory in terms of health burden and report and provide an update of the situation up to March 31 and May 30 for Spain and for the case of Italy we provide a first actualization of the model for March 31 and a second, covering until July 4.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s0010">
              <label>2</label>
              <title>Model and data description</title>
              <p id="p0040">We used a generalized <italic>SEIR</italic> modeling framework similar to Peng et al. <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, which enables the testing of control interventions <xref rid="b9000" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. Compared with statistical methods mathematical modeling based on dynamical equations can often provide essential information on the epidemic dynamics. This is particularly true when basic epidemiological parameters are unknown or largely uncertain and more mechanistic understanding is needed, such as for the current COVID-19 disease. The population is assumed constant due to the rapid disease spread, i.e. the births and natural death have the same value. The recovery rate and death rate are time-dependant. The model also assumes that susceptible individuals (<italic>S</italic>) are contagious upon coming into contact with infected (<italic>I</italic>) individuals not detected. It is assumed, however, that the infected are all quarantined (<italic>Q</italic>) and that they do not have contact with susceptible individuals. In turn, the susceptible population can be protected by confinement by moving to the protected population compartment (<italic>C</italic>). This assumption on <italic>Q</italic> means that hospital infections are not considered under this framework, therefore resulting in a potential underestimation of the real contagion extent. However, we chose this option in an attempt to be conservative and our results should be interpreted as the current best-case scenario. It is assumed also that the protected population does not have contact with the infected individuals and therefore cannot be infected. The COVID-19 dynamics is modeled by the following equations system:<disp-formula id="e0005"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M15" altimg="si486.svg"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dS</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dt</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dE</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dt</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dI</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dt</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dQ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dt</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dR</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dt</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dD</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dt</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dC</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dt</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M16" altimg="si487.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the susceptible population, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M17" altimg="si488.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the confined susceptible population, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M18" altimg="si489.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the exposed population, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M19" altimg="si490.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the infectious population, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M20" altimg="si491.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the population under Quarantine (infected reported cases), <inline-formula><mml:math id="M21" altimg="si492.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the recovered population and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M22" altimg="si493.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the dead population by the virus.</p>
              <p id="p0045">The main parameters of the model are the protection rate (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M23" altimg="si494.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), the infection rate (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M24" altimg="si495.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), the incubation rate (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M25" altimg="si496.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), the quarantine rate (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M26" altimg="si497.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), the natural death and birth rate(<inline-formula><mml:math id="M27" altimg="si498.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M28" altimg="si499.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>80</mml:mn><mml:mspace height="0.8ex" width="0.35em"/><mml:mo>*</mml:mo><mml:mspace height="0.8ex" width="0.35em"/><mml:mn>365</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), the recovery rate (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M29" altimg="si500.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), the mortality rate by the virus (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M30" altimg="si501.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) and finally, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M31" altimg="si502.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the length of the protection by confinement (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M32" altimg="si503.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>30</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) The <inline-formula><mml:math id="M33" altimg="si504.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> parameters represent the rate of people being protected from infected populations at time <italic>t</italic> and it is used to model the different actions of control of the epidemic by isolation of a healthy population.</p>
              <p id="p0050">The parameters <inline-formula><mml:math id="M34" altimg="si505.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M35" altimg="si506.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are time-dependent following the approach of <xref rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref> and for simplicity are modeled as shown next in Eq. <xref rid="e0010" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref>
<disp-formula id="e0010"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M36" altimg="si507.svg"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">exp</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">exp</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M37" altimg="si508.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M38" altimg="si509.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are the fitted coefficients. The model parameters and their meaning are summarized in <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>
.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0005"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Main model parameters description.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Parameter</th><th>Description</th><th/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M39" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td>Protection rate</td><td/></tr><tr><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M40" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td>Infection rate</td><td/></tr><tr><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M41" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td>Incubation rate</td><td/></tr><tr><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M42" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td>Quarantine rate</td><td/></tr><tr><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M43" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td>Recovery rate</td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>k</italic></td><td>Mortality rate by the virus</td><td/></tr><tr><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M44" altimg="si6.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td>Natural death and birth rate</td><td/></tr><tr><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M45" altimg="si7.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td>Length of the protection</td><td/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
              <p id="p0055">The data for fitting the model to Spain was obtained from public data sources <xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, <xref rid="b0145" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref> and correspond to the reported cases, recovery cases, and deaths. Data is available for the entire country as well as for individual CCAA. Data for Italy is retrieved from the World Health Organization <xref rid="b0150" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>.</p>
              <p id="p0060">The model was fitted in a non-linear approach by calculating the normalized least-squares error of the model approximation and the infected reported cases. The optimization algorithm used was trust-region-reflective with a maximum number of iterations of 500 and a step size of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M46" altimg="si510.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>6.4</mml:mn><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">-</mml:mo><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The error for the model fitted for all Spain was <inline-formula><mml:math id="M47" altimg="si511.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">-</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mn>0.6</mml:mn><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">-</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M48" altimg="si512.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ci</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>95</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>).The fitted parameters are summarized in <xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>
.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0010"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Model fitted parameters for the 17 AA CC in Spain and for all Spain up to March 21.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Comunity</th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M49" altimg="si8.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M50" altimg="si9.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M51" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M52" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M53" altimg="si12.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M54" altimg="si13.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M55" altimg="si14.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M56" altimg="si15.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Andalucía</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M57" altimg="si16.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>015</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M58" altimg="si17.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>073</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M59" altimg="si18.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>776</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M60" altimg="si19.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>610</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M61" altimg="si20.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>062</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M62" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>017</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M63" altimg="si22.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>171</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M64" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>970</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Aragón</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M65" altimg="si24.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M66" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>118</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M67" altimg="si26.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>262</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M68" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>458</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M69" altimg="si28.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>013</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M70" altimg="si29.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>007</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M71" altimg="si30.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>014</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M72" altimg="si31.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>064</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Asturias</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M73" altimg="si32.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>001</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M74" altimg="si33.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>438</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M75" altimg="si34.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>264</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M76" altimg="si35.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>623</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M77" altimg="si36.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>023</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M78" altimg="si37.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>076</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M79" altimg="si38.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>017</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M80" altimg="si39.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>709</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Illes Balears</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M81" altimg="si40.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.025</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M82" altimg="si41.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.022</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M83" altimg="si42.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.256</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M84" altimg="si43.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.101</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M85" altimg="si44.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.042</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M86" altimg="si45.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.019</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M87" altimg="si46.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.020</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M88" altimg="si47.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.082</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Canarias</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M89" altimg="si48.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>007</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M90" altimg="si49.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>257</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M91" altimg="si50.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>182</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M92" altimg="si51.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>335</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M93" altimg="si52.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>035</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M94" altimg="si53.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>030</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M95" altimg="si54.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>005</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M96" altimg="si55.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>002</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Cantabria</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M97" altimg="si56.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.016</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M98" altimg="si57.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.086</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M99" altimg="si58.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.217</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M100" altimg="si59.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.010</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M101" altimg="si60.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.014</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M102" altimg="si61.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.607</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M103" altimg="si62.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.004</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M104" altimg="si63.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.012</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Castilla-La Mancha</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M105" altimg="si64.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M106" altimg="si65.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>339</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M107" altimg="si66.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>571</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M108" altimg="si67.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>750</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M109" altimg="si68.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>027</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M110" altimg="si69.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>044</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M111" altimg="si70.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>015</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M112" altimg="si71.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Castilla y León</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M113" altimg="si72.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>015</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M114" altimg="si73.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>124</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M115" altimg="si74.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>575</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M116" altimg="si75.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>467</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M117" altimg="si76.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>059</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M118" altimg="si77.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>027</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M119" altimg="si78.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>045</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M120" altimg="si79.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>219</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Catalunya</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M121" altimg="si80.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>015</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M122" altimg="si81.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>359</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M123" altimg="si82.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>138</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M124" altimg="si83.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>760</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M125" altimg="si84.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>159</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M126" altimg="si85.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>006</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M127" altimg="si86.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>651</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M128" altimg="si87.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>859</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>C. Valenciana</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M129" altimg="si88.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>015</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M130" altimg="si89.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>155</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M131" altimg="si90.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>862</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M132" altimg="si91.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>674</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M133" altimg="si92.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>090</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M134" altimg="si93.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>007</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M135" altimg="si94.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>447</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M136" altimg="si95.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>267</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Extremadura</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M137" altimg="si96.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.025</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M138" altimg="si97.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.017</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M139" altimg="si98.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.272</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M140" altimg="si99.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.203</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M141" altimg="si100.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.026</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M142" altimg="si101.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.013</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M143" altimg="si102.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.028</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M144" altimg="si103.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.080</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Galicia</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M145" altimg="si104.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.021</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M146" altimg="si105.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.835</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M147" altimg="si106.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.915</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M148" altimg="si107.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.892</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M149" altimg="si108.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.076</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M150" altimg="si109.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.004</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M151" altimg="si110.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.003</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M152" altimg="si111.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Madrid</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M153" altimg="si112.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>015</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M154" altimg="si113.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>227</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M155" altimg="si114.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>939</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M156" altimg="si115.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>613</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M157" altimg="si116.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>274</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M158" altimg="si117.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>011</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M159" altimg="si118.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>016</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M160" altimg="si119.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Murcia</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M161" altimg="si120.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.025</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M162" altimg="si121.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.871</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M163" altimg="si122.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.908</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M164" altimg="si123.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.090</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M165" altimg="si124.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.019</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M166" altimg="si125.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.006</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M167" altimg="si126.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.001</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M168" altimg="si127.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.037</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Navarra</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M169" altimg="si128.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>002</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M170" altimg="si129.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>012</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M171" altimg="si130.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>681</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M172" altimg="si131.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>686</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M173" altimg="si132.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>048</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M174" altimg="si133.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>002</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M175" altimg="si134.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>003</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M176" altimg="si135.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Euskadi</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M177" altimg="si136.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M178" altimg="si137.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>081</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M179" altimg="si138.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>564</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M180" altimg="si139.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>626</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M181" altimg="si140.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>137</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M182" altimg="si141.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>010</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M183" altimg="si142.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>015</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M184" altimg="si143.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>048</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>La Rioja</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M185" altimg="si144.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M186" altimg="si145.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>745</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M187" altimg="si146.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>241</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M188" altimg="si147.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>269</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M189" altimg="si148.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>016</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M190" altimg="si149.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>029</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M191" altimg="si150.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>003</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M192" altimg="si151.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>005</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td colspan="9"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td>Spain</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M193" altimg="si152.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>015</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M194" altimg="si153.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>288</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M195" altimg="si154.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>870</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M196" altimg="si155.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>585</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M197" altimg="si156.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>057</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M198" altimg="si157.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>026</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M199" altimg="si158.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>070</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M200" altimg="si159.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>144</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
              <p id="p0065">The ordinary differential equation (ODE) system was solved by using a nonlinear data-fitting approach that minimizes a least-squares error function, by using the lsqcurvefit function of the Matlab optimization toolbox. The problem to minimize is shown in<disp-formula id="e0015"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M201" altimg="si513.svg"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">min</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="‖" open="‖"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">data</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">data</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">min</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover></mml:mstyle><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">data</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ata</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>where given an input data, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M202" altimg="si514.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">data</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>(<inline-formula><mml:math id="M203" altimg="si515.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <italic>D</italic>), provided by the integration of the ODE system <xref rid="e0005" ref-type="disp-formula">1</xref>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M204" altimg="si516.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">data</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the observed output (Active reported cases, Recovered and Deaths) sourced from public repositories. Confirmed cases may include presumptive positive cases and probable cases.</p>
              <p id="p0070">The ODE system <xref rid="e0005" ref-type="disp-formula">1</xref> was integrated by using a <inline-formula><mml:math id="M205" altimg="si517.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">th</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> order Runge–Kutta method. These kind of methods are easy to implement and very stable. For straightforward dynamical systems, this method can converge fast if we use an integration step in the order <inline-formula><mml:math id="M206" altimg="si518.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Although from the computational point of view this method is expensive compared to simpler methods such as Euler’s, the error of approximation is considerably less. On the other hand, this type of method has greater stability, especially when applied to non-linear systems <xref rid="b0155" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. The fitted parameters are the confinement rate, the infection rate, the incubation rate, the quarantine rate, the coefficients that determine the recovery rate and the coefficients and that determine the mortality rate. Thus, the optimization problem described in Eq. <xref rid="e0015" ref-type="disp-formula">3</xref> is subject to the constraints specified by the vectors <inline-formula><mml:math id="M207" altimg="si519.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">lb</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mtext>;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mtext>;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mtext>;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mtext>;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mtext>;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mtext>;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mtext>;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M208" altimg="si520.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ub</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mtext>;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mtext>;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mtext>;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mtext>;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mtext>;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mtext>;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mtext>;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, lower limit and upper limit, respectively. The algorithm chosen to minimize the problem was a trust-region because this type of algorithm is especially useful for solving non-linear optimization constrained problems.</p>
              <p id="p0075">To obtain a representative measure of the optimal set of parameters, 500 iterations of the method were performed taking initial values for the parameters, randomly within a uniform distribution. The same algorithm was run using incremental data set sizes (from 10 points to 50 points, the equivalent of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M209" altimg="si521.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>80</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> of the data set). This procedure was carried out point by point 100 times with stochastic initial conditions in order not to always fall into the same local minimum. <xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>
shows a measure of the uncertainties of the fit using both a data set of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M210" altimg="si522.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>80</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> of the total values and how the remaining values (not used in the training of the model), were correctly predicted. The mean error is of the order of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M211" altimg="si523.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">-</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mn>6</mml:mn><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">-</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M212" altimg="si524.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CI</mml:mi><mml:mn>95</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) <xref rid="b9000" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>.<fig id="f0005"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Model uncertainties (a) dynamics obtained by adding new values to the time series and (b) the fitted parameters variation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig></p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s0015">
              <label>3</label>
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="s0020">
                <label>3.1</label>
                <title>Epidemic curves for Spain and the 17 Autonomous Communities (CCAA)</title>
                <p id="p0080">The model fitting to data aggregated for Spain on reported infected population up to March 23 yields a good approximation to the exponential curve, as well as to the reported evolution in deaths and recovered (<xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>
). The model was fitted from day 1 of the epidemic at the end of February because the initial protection rate is assumed to be 0.<fig id="f0010"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Fitting of the population model implemented on a global scale up to March 23 (all Spain).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="p0085">Progression of infected, deaths, and recovered track very approximately observations. With data up to March 22, the model predicts the first peak in cases around the end of April or early days in May with an error of the approximation of less than <inline-formula><mml:math id="M213" altimg="si525.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The current scenario may already include to some extent the effects of the partial ”confinement” measures imposed on March 13, therefore it is likely that total projected infections would be much higher should these restrictions not exist. More than <inline-formula><mml:math id="M214" altimg="si526.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>million people would have been recovered from SARS-CoV-2 infection by mid-May and total deaths for the entire country at that time would rise over 100 thousand people (<xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>
).<fig id="f0015"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Control scenarios for the global model up to March 23 (all Spain).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3_lrg"/></fig><fig id="f0020"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Aggregated CCAA model fitting up to March 23 for Spain.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr4_lrg"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s0025">
                <label>3.2</label>
                <title>Evolution of SARS-CoV-2 in the 17 autonomous regions (CCAA)</title>
                <p id="p0090">To approach the degree of colonization of the virus at smaller levels of aggregation than the entire country, we applied the same model framework to each of the 17 individual <italic>CCAA</italic>. The former was an attempt to model the epidemics spatially and approach scale-derived differences with country aggregated data (e.g. municipality-level data is not yet available). Results on July 2020 are shown in <xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>
and display varying developmental stages of the COVID-19 epidemic outbreak, thereby recovering the different demographic topologies for the variety of CCAA and <xref rid="f0030" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>
shows the extended fitting to have a better understanding of different development stages at the community level.<fig id="f0025"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Model fitting for the 17 CCAA of Spain up tu March 23.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr5_lrg"/></fig><fig id="f0030"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Model extended fitting for the 17 CCAA of Spain up to March 23.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr6_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="p0095">The largest increases of infected “in absolute terms- to the month of may were expected according to the CCAA curves, in the coming weeks for Madrid, Catalunya, Castilla La Mancha, Paìs Valencià, Castilla León and Andalucía. All the former displays -under the current scenario evolution- peak cases occurring from late April to early May.</p>
                <p id="p0100">To compare <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> above with the effect of community dis-aggregation on the evolution of reported cases for Spain, simulations were performed individually and results aggregated together as shown in <xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>. Results are comparable despite they show relatively larger values for total infected than those arising from the simulations on the country’s total cases.</p>
                <sec id="s0030">
                  <label>3.2.1</label>
                  <title>Control scenarios for Spain</title>
                  <p id="p0105">The situation in Spain is at April 2020 yet very severe, based on public data until March 25. To this end, we tested the potential effects of intervention strategies to control and reduce social contacts. Effects of the adopted policies on March, 14 are not yet known or they can barely begin to show up as substantial changes in the epidemic curve at this date (see Appendix for an update to March 31. To help in the evaluation, we generated different scenarios with varying values of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M215" altimg="si527.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, to simulate the effects of social protection. Increases in <inline-formula><mml:math id="M216" altimg="si528.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> were structured in scenarios representing up to 10 times larger values than in that obtained from observations up to March 23. The results of these scenarios are summarised in <xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>. A drastic decrease in the resulting number of cases can be seen, if we increase the actual daily protection rate around ten times.</p>
                  <p id="p0110">Results with the current epidemic evolution for Spain, show that over <inline-formula><mml:math id="M217" altimg="si529.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>400</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> quarantined infections would be reported by the end of April, with an estimated burden of over <inline-formula><mml:math id="M218" altimg="si530.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> deaths. A four times increase in the levels of the protected population would represent a huge gain in the number of both clinically diagnosed infections and casualties (<xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>). A decrease to around <inline-formula><mml:math id="M219" altimg="si531.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>200</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> infected is achieved and a reduction to below <inline-formula><mml:math id="M220" altimg="si532.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>50</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> deaths. Much larger reductions in both infected and deaths can be achieved if much stricter measures result in more drastic reductions in the number of effective contacts. Best case scenario simulated with ten times the efficacy of the observed α on March, 23, can result in a more recent arrival to a peak of around <inline-formula><mml:math id="M221" altimg="si533.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> cases (around early April) and with a decrease in casualties to around <inline-formula><mml:math id="M222" altimg="si534.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>30</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s0035">
                <label>3.3</label>
                <title>Evolution of the main active foci (Barcelona and Madrid)</title>
                <p id="p0115">Active discussion on the convenience of imposing stricter measures is underway on March 22, with the overall effect of yet acting on the more active COVID-19 foci being under large debate. Given the large associated uncertainties and enormous public health and economic costs, timely actions at this point might represent large gains or losses. To aid in this respect, we simulated the effect of imposing stricter measures of social distancing also on two of the most active foci, namely Madrid and Catalunya. Madrid was the CCAA where the initial outbreak evolved more rapidly and on March 23, it concentrates over 30 percent of total cases and a large majority of deaths. Similarly, Catalunya is now showing a significant increase in new infected and both areas share similar populations albeit Madrid has in comparison, higher population density.</p>
                <p id="p0120">Results are shown in <xref rid="f0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>
for Madrid and in <xref rid="f0040" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>
for Catalunya, respectively. Similar conclusions on the large effect of imposing stricter epidemic containment measures can be seen in both regions, even if imposed at the current stage of the epidemic development.<fig id="f0035"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Extended fitting for Madrid up to March 23.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr7_lrg"/></fig><fig id="f0040"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Extended fitting for Catalunya up to March 23.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr8_lrg"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s0040">
                <label>3.4</label>
                <title>Model uncertainties</title>
                <p id="p0125">Because the strength of this type of model, both to adjust and to predict future dynamics, depends on the accuracy in case reporting, it is important to analyze the uncertainties in the adjustment and evaluate the degree of variation of the parameter estimates. To get a better idea of its performance, the model was fitted with a successively longer data series, adding a new day to the data window with which the fitting was computed. The shortest time series used was of 5 days from February 29 to March 3 and the longest covered up to March 31. The temporal span of the time series used can seriously affect the value of the fitted parameters. This is especially true at the beginning of the epidemic when the relationship between infected, dead, and recovered is not entirely clear. For example, if the number of confirmed cases is small, it is difficult to ascertain whether the quarantine has been rigorously applied or not. Also, such under-representation would suggest that the number of infectious people is much larger than the number of confirmed cases. Results of the different dynamics and the parameter space can be seen in <xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>. Those parameters most affected are the ones directly related to the infection rate and the recovery rate, as well as the protection rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="M223" altimg="si535.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s0045">
                <label>3.5</label>
                <title>The case of Italy</title>
                <p id="p0130">To see the performance of applying the same model framework in the other European country with more quarantine cases to date, we fitted the model to the COVID-19 epidemic in Italy. This way, as the situation in Italy precedes that of Spain by around one week, evaluation of control scenarios can be done at a more advanced stage of confinement measures. As the first cases in Italy were reported at the end of February, two different sets of fittings were performed to compare the confinement restrictions imposed by the Italian authorities on March <inline-formula><mml:math id="M224" altimg="si536.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">th</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The NMSE in this case was <inline-formula><mml:math id="M225" altimg="si537.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2.7</mml:mn><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">-</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mn>3.6</mml:mn><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">-</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M226" altimg="si538.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ci</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>95</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) and the parameters for each case are summarized in <xref rid="t0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>
.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0015"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Fitted model parameters for Italy up to March 31.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Escenario</th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M227" altimg="si160.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M228" altimg="si161.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M229" altimg="si162.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M230" altimg="si163.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M231" altimg="si164.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M232" altimg="si165.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M233" altimg="si166.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M234" altimg="si167.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Before control</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M235" altimg="si168.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0001</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M236" altimg="si169.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>955</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M237" altimg="si170.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>200</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M238" altimg="si171.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>897</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M239" altimg="si172.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>052</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M240" altimg="si173.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>99</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M241" altimg="si174.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>059</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M242" altimg="si175.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>051</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>After Control</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M243" altimg="si176.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>025</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M244" altimg="si177.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>341</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M245" altimg="si178.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>712</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M246" altimg="si179.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>221</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M247" altimg="si180.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>035</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M248" altimg="si181.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>027</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M249" altimg="si182.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>020</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M250" altimg="si183.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>017</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
                <p id="p0135"><xref rid="f0045" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>
displays model results for the two different scenarios. The bottom panel shows the effect of different measures of confinement since day 1 in a hypothetical control scenario. These dynamics are the result of increasing the fitted <inline-formula><mml:math id="M251" altimg="si539.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> until approx <inline-formula><mml:math id="M252" altimg="si540.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> daily. This is a significant increase having into account the initial value of the protection rate.<fig id="f0045"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>Model fitting and control scenarios for Italy. (a) fitting before confinement restrictions (b) fitting after confinement restrictions and (c) Control scenarios.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr9_lrg"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s0050">
              <label>4</label>
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p id="p0140">Current estimates of future trends in new infections in the weeks after March 23 largely compromise the capacity of the Spanish health system, as it happened for Italy. This is especially critical in particular for intensive care units from the end of March <xref rid="b0160" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. Our projections for the forthcoming evolution in the COVID-19 epidemic curve for Spain show a pessimistic scenario unless current social distancing measures are effective (see Appendix for an update as of March 31. With the estimates at hand, over <inline-formula><mml:math id="M253" altimg="si541.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> million people would be clinically diagnosed at the disease maximum and over <inline-formula><mml:math id="M254" altimg="si542.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>100.000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> resulting in deaths. Imposing stricter measures under the current uncertainties seems a logical preventive option given the considerable gains in terms of infection and casualties, even at moderate increases in alpha. Assessment of total country changes through aggregated and CCAA disaggregated data estimates, provides similar dynamical evolution despite different absolute values. Discrepancies to larger values might partly come from the heterogeneous population landscape in the different CCAA (e.g. cities with high population density), as opposed to the homogeneous contact assumption in the aggregated model estimates. Gaining extra time for exerting alternative interventions, such as temporary increases in public health responses, or increasing the capacity of massively screening the population to gain an accurate value of the real prevalence of SARS-CoV-2, or to develop disease treatment strategies seem a logical conclusion. While two of the most populated CCAA (namely Catalunya with roughly <inline-formula><mml:math id="M255" altimg="si543.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>7.7</mml:mn><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> people and Madrid Community, with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M256" altimg="si544.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>6.7</mml:mn><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> people) are already in the lead in terms of epidemic progression, other similarly populated regions lag only a few days entering a similar slope in their respective epidemic growths. The largest population density in Madrid compared to other CCAA together with its more advanced epidemic progression cast urgent attention on the evolution of this highly active epidemic focus. Those regions where the outbreak was initiated earlier (e.g. Madrid, Catalunya, Euskadi, and Navarra) or appear to have more connectivity to the initial foci and largest population density tend to show earlier peaks. Those regions yet in the early stages of the exponential increase are those where strong initial social isolation measures (therefore protection of the population), would have the largest effects in resulting infected (<xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>).</p>
              <p id="p0145">The projected rise in the number of infections shown in <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> is very sensitive to the latest data used, as these data are the ones governing the changes in trends, therefore errors in reporting or other large uncertainties associated with these values may dramatically alter the outcome in terms of the number of infected and associated mortality. For the curve to happen as shown, the simulation assumes the initial conditions hold, therefore if that were not the case and measures were lifted before the epidemic reaches <inline-formula><mml:math id="M257" altimg="si545.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, infections might rise again. Improvements can be achieved with more complete integration of time-delay coordinates in classical <italic>SEIR</italic> models <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. This way, both the incubation period and the period before recovery, as well as the precise role of the asymptomatic population, can be better represented at times when this information is highly uncertain. A substantial gain in the epidemic projection in the form of reduced infections in the population would already be achieved with a four-times rise in the efficacy of the control situation we had around March <inline-formula><mml:math id="M258" altimg="si546.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>9</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">-</mml:mo><mml:mn>16</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. This was the time when social distancing/confinement was imposed (March 13). Time will show to which extent current measures manage to increase the value of alpha. Application of strict containment measures clearly shows a drastic effect on the epidemic progression and a substantial reduction in both infected and to a lesser extent, deaths (<xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>).</p>
              <p id="p0150">The control scenarios presented contemplate a significant increase in the percentage of the population under confinement, ranging from <inline-formula><mml:math id="M259" altimg="si547.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> percent daily to 13 percent daily. These percentages imply that after a week of starting this control, the percentage of protected susceptible population is <inline-formula><mml:math id="M260" altimg="si548.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>9.1</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M261" altimg="si549.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>91</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, respectively, from the start of the measurement. These numbers explain the drastic differences in the two dynamics observed and the huge gain in lowering the toll of infected.</p>
              <p id="p0155">Update of the epidemic situation in Spain partially showing the effect of partial lockdown and the current values for alpha are shown in the Appendix as for March 31. Later we update the model for May 30 in the case of Spain and its communities and until July 4 for Italy. This actualization suggests that the model first predictions and scenarios formulated are not to far from the reality.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s0055">
              <label>5</label>
              <title>Conclusions</title>
              <p id="p0160">The results presented in this study and the writing of this article were completed by mid-March and were later updated several times until the month of July. Therefore the references to 'now' should be seen as of March 2020. The Covid-19 pandemic is exerting unprecedented stress on the public health systems of many countries. Those at major risk now are Italy and Spain, and for them, the efficacy of the partial confinement or total lockdown effects are yet unknown. Under this situation, we implemented a modified SEIR compartmental model accounting for infection from undiagnosed individuals and for different levels of population isolation, to evaluate the effects of contacts reduction in the epidemic temporal dynamics.</p>
              <p id="p0165">In this manuscript, we present a simple model that allows us to evaluate confinement strategies for the initial stages of the pandemic. The scenarios are counterfactual since, in reality, the confinement strategies carried out by each community and by each country were very heterogeneous, but the results obtained suggest that the model accurately adjusts to reality and that the projections are reliable.</p>
              <p id="p0170">Among the advantages of the implemented model, it should be noted that despite the simplicity of the hypotheses, the adjustments obtained were accurate and the projections made do not differ much from those other more complex models. Also, the instantaneous increment of cumulative diagnosed people depends on the history of cumulative infected people, by which the latent period can be taken into consideration.</p>
              <p id="p0175">The results of the implemented control scenarios for March 23 show that drastic isolation of the susceptible population should be implemented as soon as possible. Even not so drastic increases in alpha (two or three times the current rate) imply also significant reductions in the incidence of cases. The adjustments made in different CCAA also serve to verify the efficacy of the isolation hypothesis for the most affected communities (Madrid and Catalunya). They also serve as a basis for timely action in those communities that do not yet have a significant number of cases that jeopardize their health systems.</p>
              <p id="p0180">Policymakers should weigh in the values and ethical considerations of employing now maximum strength in actions to help reduce the slope of the epidemic curve against the enormous associated economic cost. However, our study indicates that a three-week interruption of labor activities, thereby a drastic reduction in contacts, could end the current epidemic in around two months and drastically reduce both the burden of this disease and much lower the toll of lives.</p>
              <p id="p0185">Our results could also provide useful suggestions for the prevention and control of the COVID-19 outbreaks in different countries and locations such as Argentina and the USA lagging behind the current epidemic wave in Spain and Italy. These represent two very different scenarios. In the case of the USA, no radical control measure was initially implemented by the federal government and the epidemic seems to be in a phase of uncontrolled growth. In Argentina, the health authorities seem to have taken note of what is happening in Europe and more strict movement restrictions have been implemented, although it is difficult to determine the degree of commitment by the population.</p>
              <p id="p0190">However, our model does not consider space explicitly as we approached aggregated data. This lack of spatial granularity may affect the accuracy of simulations when the spread of infections in a territory reaches and takes off in a populated city. The former might alter results-producing more new cases than expected, exactly what the aggregation for CCAA data clearly shows. Spatial modeling should also be incorporated explicitly and an extension of this modeling approach to incorporate the movement of individuals should follow. Results should be interpreted with care as projections at these initial stages of the epidemic are very dependent on the quality of data, with small changes in observed values producing large variations in trends. However, even with this limitation in mind, the magnitude of positive increments in cases suggests these results are strong. Variable isolation strength measures can be tested with this model and inform governments of the most probable effects of their actions on the initial course of the COVID-19 disease.</p>
              <p id="p0195">In general terms, the model is quite stable, as shown in the uncertainty analysis carried out. On the other hand, it can be seen in the successive updating of the parameters that the initial projections of the proposed model were not too far from the real data reported. This gives a special value to the work since it somehow justifies the previous discussion. Although the scenario is counterfactual and it is not possible to determine whether a more severe increase in the confinement rate would have reduced the number of cases if it can be said that the model did not depart too far from the initial projections.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s0075">
              <title>Funding</title>
              <p id="p0200">This research did receive funding from the Spanish Ministry of Science and Innovation through the ‘Centro de Excelencia Severo Ochoa 2019 2023’ Program (CEX2018 000806S). Partial funding support was received from the ISCIII COVID-19 project COV20/0014, and from a project by the Fundació Daniel Bravo Andreu.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s0080">
              <title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title>
              <p id="p0205"><bold>Leonardo L</bold>ó<bold>pez:</bold> Conceptualization, Methodology, Investigation, Writing - original draft, Writing - review &amp; editing, Formal analysis. <bold>Xavier Rod</bold>ó<bold>:</bold> Conceptualization, Methodology, Investigation, Writing - original draft, Writing - review &amp; editing, Supervision, Formal analysis, Funding acquisition, Project administration.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="COI-statement">
              <title>Declaration of Competing Interest</title>
              <p id="p1415">The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list id="bi005">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="b0005">
                <label>1</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0005">Worldometers, Worldometers coronavirus; 2020.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus/" id="ir005">https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0010">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0010">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Soper</surname>
                      <given-names>G.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The lessons of the pandemic</article-title>
                  <source>Science</source>
                  <volume>49</volume>
                  <issue>1274</issue>
                  <year>1919</year>
                  <fpage>501</fpage>
                  <lpage>506</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.49.1274.501</pub-id>
                  <comment>URL: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://science.sciencemag.org/content/49/1274/501" id="ir010">https://science.sciencemag.org/content/49/1274/501</ext-link></comment>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17793800</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0015">
                <label>3</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0015">McKibbin WJ, Fernando R. The global macroeconomic impacts of covid-19: Seven scenarios.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0020">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0020">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Martini</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gazzaniga</surname>
                      <given-names>V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bragazzi</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Barberis</surname>
                      <given-names>I.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The spanish influenza pandemic: a lesson from history 100 years after 1918</article-title>
                  <source>J Preventive Med Hygiene</source>
                  <volume>60</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <fpage>E64</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0025">
                <label>5</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0025">Li R, Pei S, Chen B, Song Y, Zhang T, Yang W, Shaman J. Substantial undocumented infection facilitates the rapid dissemination of novel coronavirus (sars-cov2), Science.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0030">
                <label>6</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0030">Peng L, Yang W, Zhang D, Zhuge C, Hong L. Epidemic analysis of covid-19 in china by dynamical modeling, arXiv preprint arXiv:2002.06563.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0035">
                <label>7</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0035">Buckee CO, Balsari S, Chan J, Crosas M, Dominici F, Gasser U et al. Aggregated mobility data could help fight covid-19, Science.<ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1126/science.abb8021" id="ir015">https://doi.org/10.1126/science.abb8021</ext-link>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://science.sciencemag.org/content/early/2020/03/20/science.abb8021" id="ir020">https://science.sciencemag.org/content/early/2020/03/20/science.abb8021</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0040">
                <label>8</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0040">Thorp HH. Underpromise, overdeliver, Science.<ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1126/science.abb8492" id="ir025">https://doi.org/10.1126/science.abb8492</ext-link>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://science.sciencemag.org/content/early/2020/03/20/science.abb8492" id="ir030">https://science.sciencemag.org/content/early/2020/03/20/science.abb8492</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0045">
                <label>9</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0045">Chen Y, Cheng J, Jiang Y, Liu K. A time delay dynamical model for outbreak of 2019-ncov and the parameter identification, arXiv preprint arXiv:2002.00418.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0050">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0050">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cantó</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Coll</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sánchez</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Estimation of parameters in a structured sir model</article-title>
                  <source>Adv Diff Eqs</source>
                  <volume>2017</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0055">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="h0055">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ma</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xia</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <series>Mathematical understanding of infectious disease dynamics</series>
                  <volume>vol. 16</volume>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <publisher-name>World Scientific</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0060">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0060">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ding</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gong</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cheng</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Studies on mathematical models for sars outbreak prediction and warning</article-title>
                  <source>Chinese Sci Bull</source>
                  <volume>49</volume>
                  <issue>21</issue>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <fpage>2245</fpage>
                  <lpage>2251</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0065">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0065">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sardar</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ghosh</surname>
                      <given-names>I.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rodó</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chattopadhyay</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A realistic two-strain model for mers-cov infection uncovers the high risk for epidemic propagation</article-title>
                  <source>PLOS Neglected Tropical Diseases</source>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0008065</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0070">
                <label>14</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0070">Li Q, Guan X, Wu P, Wang X, Zhou L, Tong Y, et al. Early transmission dynamics in wuhan, china, of novel coronavirus–infected pneumonia, New England J Med.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0075">
                <label>15</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0075">Fang Y, Nie Y, Penny M. Transmission dynamics of the covid-19 outbreak and effectiveness of government interventions: a data-driven analysis. J Med Virol.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0080">
                <label>16</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0080">Nesteruk I. Estimations of the coronavirus epidemic dynamics in South Korea with the use of sir model [Preprint.] ResearchGate.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0085">
                <label>17</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0085">Wu Z, McGoogan JM. Characteristics of and important lessons from the coronavirus disease 2019 (covid-19) outbreak in China: summary of a report of 72 314 cases from the chinese center for disease control and prevention, Jama.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0090">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0090">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rothan</surname>
                      <given-names>H.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Byrareddy</surname>
                      <given-names>S.N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The epidemiology and pathogenesis of coronavirus disease (covid-19) outbreak</article-title>
                  <source>J Autoimmun</source>
                  <volume>102433</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0095">
                <label>19</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0095">Mohammad M, Trounev A, Cattani C. The dynamics of covid-19 in the uae based on fractional derivative modeling using riesz wavelets simulation.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0100">
                <label>20</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0100">Khan MA, Atangana A. Modeling the dynamics of novel coronavirus (2019-ncov) with fractional derivative. Alexand Eng J.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0105">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0105">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Singh</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kumar</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hammouch</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Atangana</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A fractional epidemiological model for computer viruses pertaining to a new fractional derivative</article-title>
                  <source>Appl Math Comput</source>
                  <volume>316</volume>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <fpage>504</fpage>
                  <lpage>515</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0110">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0110">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gao</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baskonus</surname>
                      <given-names>H.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shi</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>New investigation of bats-hosts-reservoir-people coronavirus model and application to 2019-ncov system</article-title>
                  <source>Adv Diff Eqs</source>
                  <volume>2020</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>11</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0115">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0115">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Boccaletti</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ditto</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mindlin</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Atangana</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Modeling and forecasting of epidemic spreading: the case of covid-19 and beyond</article-title>
                  <source>Chaos Solitons Fractals</source>
                  <volume>135</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">109794</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0120">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0120">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lalmuanawma</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hussain</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chhakchhuak</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Applications of machine learning and artificial intelligence for covid-19 (sars-cov-2) pandemic: a review</article-title>
                  <source>Chaos Solitons Fractals</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">110059</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0125">
                <label>25</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0125">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cooper</surname>
                      <given-names>I.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mondal</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Antonopoulos</surname>
                      <given-names>C.G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A sir model assumption for the spread of covid-19 in different communities</article-title>
                  <source>Chaos Solitons Fractals</source>
                  <volume>139</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">110057</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0130">
                <label>26</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0130">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ndairou</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Area</surname>
                      <given-names>I.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nieto</surname>
                      <given-names>J.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Torres</surname>
                      <given-names>D.F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Mathematical modeling of covid-19 transmission dynamics with a case study of wuhan</article-title>
                  <source>Chaos Solitons Fractals</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">109846</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b9000">
                <label>27</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h9000">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>López</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rodó</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The end of social confinement and COVID-19 re-emergence risk</article-title>
                  <source>Nat Hum Behav</source>
                  <volume>4</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>746</fpage>
                  <lpage>755</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41562-020-0908-8</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32572175</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0135">
                <label>28</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0135">Cheynet, E. Generalized SEIR Epidemic Model (Fitting and Computation). Zenodo; 2020. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5281/ZENODO.3911854</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0140">
                <label>29</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0140">Spain Health Ministry. Reportes coronavirus ministerio de sanidad. gobierno de españa; 2020. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://covid19.isciii.es/" id="ir0505">https://covid19.isciii.es/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0145">
                <label>30</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0145">Delgado. https://github.com/datadista/datasets/tree/master/COVIDCovid-dataspain; 2020. https://github.com/datadista/datasets/tree/master/COVID.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0150">
                <label>31</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0150">W.H. Organization, WHO daly covid-19 report; 2020.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/situation-reports" id="ir045">https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/situation-reports</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0155">
                <label>32</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0155">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tostado-Véliz</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kamel</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jurado</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparison of various robust and efficient load-flow techniques based on runge–kutta formulas</article-title>
                  <source>Electric Power Syst Res</source>
                  <volume>174</volume>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">105881</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0160">
                <label>33</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0160">Arenas A, Cota W, Gomez-Gardenes J, Gómez S, Granell C, Matamalas JT et al. A mathematical model for the spatiotemporal epidemic spreading of covid19, medRxiv arXiv:https://www.medrxiv.org/content/early/2020/03/23/2020.03.21.20040022.full.pdf,<ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1101/2020.03.21.20040022" id="ir050">https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.03.21.20040022</ext-link>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.medrxiv.org/content/early/2020/03/23/2020.03.21.20040022" id="ir055">https://www.medrxiv.org/content/early/2020/03/23/2020.03.21.20040022</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
            <sec id="s0060">
              <label>Appendix A</label>
              <title>Updated results for Spain</title>
              <p id="p0210">In this appendix, we show an update of the fitted model with the data reported up to March 31 first, and then we fit the model with data reported until May 30. By doing this we can compare the firsts model’s predictions with the actual data reported at the end of the first epidemic wave. <xref rid="f0050" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10</xref>
shows the fitting and projections of the model with the new data. On the left panel, the results for March 31 are showed while in the right panel the model fitting until May 30 is showed. If we compare these results with those in the previous sections, the model now predicts an epidemic peak much lower than before. Also watching the update to May 30 we can see Eq. <xref rid="e0010" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref> that the peak it’s a little lower than the first predictions but the result it’s acceptable if we have into account the few data points used at the beginning of the fitting (less than 20 data-points). This may be mainly because of the Spanish government control measures imposed and a harder confinement restriction. The model parameters for March 31 are <inline-formula><mml:math id="M262" altimg="si552.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.087</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.305</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.044</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.510</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.095</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.017</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.026</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.022</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, while for May 30 are <inline-formula><mml:math id="M263" altimg="si553.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.092</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.05</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.03</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.610</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.093</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.015</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.02</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.018</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. A significant increase in the control rate is mostly evident from the first fitting but the change in general terms from March until May it’s not that significant.<fig id="f0050"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p>Model fitting for Spain updated to March 31 (a) and model fitting for Spain updated to May 30 (b).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr10_lrg"/></fig></p>
              <p id="p0215">In <xref rid="f0055" ref-type="fig">Fig. 11</xref>
and to better understand the scenario of Match 31 is showed in dashed lines in the context of the scenarios previously outlined in <xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>, the dynamics of the update until May 30 it’s not showed in this figure due to the similarity of the previous dynamic in terms of the peak. The corresponding populations to the parameters indicated above are added as dashed lines for each panel (Reported, Recovered, and Deaths).<fig id="f0055"><label>Fig. 11</label><caption><p>Control scenarios for the global model (all Spain) with the predictions as for March 31st added as dashed lines.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr11_lrg"/></fig></p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s0065">
              <label>Appendix B</label>
              <title>Updated scenario for each CCAA in Spain</title>
              <p id="p0220">In the same way than we did for Spain, in this section we show results of the model fitting with the data updated until March <inline-formula><mml:math id="M264" altimg="si554.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>31</mml:mn><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">st</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and until the end of the first epidemic wave in May 30. In <xref rid="f0060" ref-type="fig">Fig. 12</xref>
the new fittings are showed and in <xref rid="t0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>
the fitted parameters are listed. Notice the closeness to the epidemic peak in some of the CCAA, a fact that can be real or be due to the yet low prevalence of the disease in parts of Spain. <xref rid="f0065" ref-type="fig">Fig. 13</xref>
the fittings until May 30, the end of the first epidemic wave, are showed and in <xref rid="t0025" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>
the fitted parameters for this update are listed. As can be seen, there is a great discrepancy in the reported data for some communities that are certainly not reflected not only in the adjustments at the CCAA level but also at the level of the whole of Spain. This uncertainty in the data makes it difficult to adjust the model, but even taking this aspect into account, the adjustments are quite good and the updated results are not too far from the initial results, especially at the national level.<fig id="f0060"><label>Fig. 12</label><caption><p>Model extended fitting for the 17 CCAA of Spain until March 31.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr12_lrg"/></fig><table-wrap position="anchor" id="t0020"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Model fitted parameters for the 17 AA CC in Spain and for all Spain up to March 31.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Comunity</th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M265" altimg="si184.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M266" altimg="si185.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M267" altimg="si186.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M268" altimg="si187.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M269" altimg="si188.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M270" altimg="si189.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M271" altimg="si190.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M272" altimg="si191.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Andalucía</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M273" altimg="si192.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.015</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M274" altimg="si193.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.133</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M275" altimg="si194.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.357</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M276" altimg="si195.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.279</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M277" altimg="si196.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.071</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M278" altimg="si197.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.005</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M279" altimg="si198.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.008</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M280" altimg="si199.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.040</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Aragón</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M281" altimg="si200.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.005</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M282" altimg="si201.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.419</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M283" altimg="si202.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.809</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M284" altimg="si203.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.906</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M285" altimg="si204.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.088</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M286" altimg="si205.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.001</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M287" altimg="si206.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.024</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M288" altimg="si207.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.071</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Asturias</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M289" altimg="si208.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.017</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M290" altimg="si209.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.700</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M291" altimg="si210.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.884</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M292" altimg="si211.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.858</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M293" altimg="si212.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.128</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M294" altimg="si213.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.005</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M295" altimg="si214.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.003</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M296" altimg="si215.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.001</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Illes Balears</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M297" altimg="si216.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.021</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M298" altimg="si217.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.022</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M299" altimg="si218.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.256</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M300" altimg="si219.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.101</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M301" altimg="si220.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.042</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M302" altimg="si221.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.019</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M303" altimg="si222.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.020</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M304" altimg="si223.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.082</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Canarias</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M305" altimg="si224.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.022</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M306" altimg="si225.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.854</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M307" altimg="si226.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.189</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M308" altimg="si227.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.075</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M309" altimg="si228.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.076</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M310" altimg="si229.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.003</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M311" altimg="si230.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.005</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M312" altimg="si231.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.015</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Cantabria</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M313" altimg="si232.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.016</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M314" altimg="si233.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.086</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M315" altimg="si234.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.217</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M316" altimg="si235.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.010</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M317" altimg="si236.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.014</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M318" altimg="si237.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.607</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M319" altimg="si238.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.004</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M320" altimg="si239.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.012</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Castilla-La Mancha</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M321" altimg="si240.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.017</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M322" altimg="si241.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.637</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M323" altimg="si242.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.870</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M324" altimg="si243.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.811</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M325" altimg="si244.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.079</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M326" altimg="si245.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.006</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M327" altimg="si246.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.015</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M328" altimg="si247.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Castilla y León</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M329" altimg="si248.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.025</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M330" altimg="si249.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.225</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M331" altimg="si250.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.550</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M332" altimg="si251.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.338</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M333" altimg="si252.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.268</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M334" altimg="si253.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.002</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M335" altimg="si254.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.012</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M336" altimg="si255.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.003</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Catalunya</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M337" altimg="si256.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.018</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M338" altimg="si257.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.523</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M339" altimg="si258.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.750</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M340" altimg="si259.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.532</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M341" altimg="si260.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.433</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M342" altimg="si261.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.002</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M343" altimg="si262.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.010</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M344" altimg="si263.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.002</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>País Valencià</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M345" altimg="si264.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.025</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M346" altimg="si265.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.263</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M347" altimg="si266.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.509</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M348" altimg="si267.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.372</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M349" altimg="si268.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.080</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M350" altimg="si269.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.003</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M351" altimg="si270.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.013</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M352" altimg="si271.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.013</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Extremadura</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M353" altimg="si272.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.017</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M354" altimg="si273.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.017</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M355" altimg="si274.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.272</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M356" altimg="si275.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.203</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M357" altimg="si276.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.026</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M358" altimg="si277.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.013</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M359" altimg="si278.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.028</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M360" altimg="si279.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.080</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Galicia</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M361" altimg="si280.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.011</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M362" altimg="si281.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.835</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M363" altimg="si282.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.915</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M364" altimg="si283.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.892</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M365" altimg="si284.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.076</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M366" altimg="si285.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.004</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M367" altimg="si286.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.003</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M368" altimg="si287.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Madrid</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M369" altimg="si288.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.025</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M370" altimg="si289.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.624</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M371" altimg="si290.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.993</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M372" altimg="si291.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.681</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M373" altimg="si292.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.430</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M374" altimg="si293.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.006</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M375" altimg="si294.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.026</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M376" altimg="si295.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.001</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Murcia</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M377" altimg="si296.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.020</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M378" altimg="si297.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.871</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M379" altimg="si298.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.908</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M380" altimg="si299.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.090</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M381" altimg="si300.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.019</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M382" altimg="si301.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.006</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M383" altimg="si302.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.001</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M384" altimg="si303.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.037</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Navarra</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M385" altimg="si304.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.025</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M386" altimg="si305.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.770</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M387" altimg="si306.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.884</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M388" altimg="si307.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.909</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M389" altimg="si308.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.029</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M390" altimg="si309.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.004</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M391" altimg="si310.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.003</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M392" altimg="si311.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.001</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Euskadi</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M393" altimg="si312.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.025</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M394" altimg="si313.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.667</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M395" altimg="si314.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.829</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M396" altimg="si315.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.712</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M397" altimg="si316.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.189</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M398" altimg="si317.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.007</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M399" altimg="si318.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.011</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M400" altimg="si319.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.004</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>La Rioja</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M401" altimg="si320.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.025</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M402" altimg="si321.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2.000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M403" altimg="si322.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M404" altimg="si323.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.174</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M405" altimg="si324.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.326</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M406" altimg="si325.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.001</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M407" altimg="si326.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.003</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M408" altimg="si327.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="f0065"><label>Fig. 13</label><caption><p>Model fitting for the 17 CCAA of Spain until May 30.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr13_lrg"/></fig><table-wrap position="anchor" id="t0025"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Model fitted parameters for the 17 AA CC in Spain and for all Spain up to May 30.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Comunity</th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M409" altimg="si328.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M410" altimg="si329.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M411" altimg="si330.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M412" altimg="si331.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M413" altimg="si332.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M414" altimg="si333.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M415" altimg="si334.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M416" altimg="si335.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Andalucía</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M417" altimg="si336.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.054</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M418" altimg="si337.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.928</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M419" altimg="si338.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.927</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M420" altimg="si339.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.148</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M421" altimg="si340.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.144</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M422" altimg="si341.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.001</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M423" altimg="si342.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.024</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M424" altimg="si343.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.050</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Aragón</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M425" altimg="si344.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.005</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M426" altimg="si345.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M427" altimg="si346.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M428" altimg="si347.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.095</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M429" altimg="si348.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.025</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M430" altimg="si349.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.094</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M431" altimg="si350.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.023</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M432" altimg="si351.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.036</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Asturias</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M433" altimg="si352.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.018</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M434" altimg="si353.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.913</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M435" altimg="si354.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.839</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M436" altimg="si355.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.269</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M437" altimg="si356.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.015</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M438" altimg="si357.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.847</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M439" altimg="si358.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.011</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M440" altimg="si359.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.029</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Illes Balears</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M441" altimg="si360.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.002</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M442" altimg="si361.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.526</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M443" altimg="si362.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.817</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M444" altimg="si363.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.484</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M445" altimg="si364.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.046</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M446" altimg="si365.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.306</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M447" altimg="si366.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.011</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M448" altimg="si367.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.019</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Canarias</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M449" altimg="si368.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.019</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M450" altimg="si369.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.757</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M451" altimg="si370.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.867</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M452" altimg="si371.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.143</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M453" altimg="si372.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.053</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M454" altimg="si373.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.023</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M455" altimg="si374.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.010</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M456" altimg="si375.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.045</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Cantabria</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M457" altimg="si376.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.029</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M458" altimg="si377.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.629</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M459" altimg="si378.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.955</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M460" altimg="si379.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.145</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M461" altimg="si380.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.962</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M462" altimg="si381.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.001</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M463" altimg="si382.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.010</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M464" altimg="si383.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.032</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Castilla-La Mancha</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M465" altimg="si384.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.034</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M466" altimg="si385.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M467" altimg="si386.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M468" altimg="si387.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.224</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M469" altimg="si388.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.012</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M470" altimg="si389.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2.000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M471" altimg="si390.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.030</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M472" altimg="si391.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.045</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Castilla y León</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M473" altimg="si392.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.012</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M474" altimg="si393.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M475" altimg="si394.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M476" altimg="si395.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.334</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M477" altimg="si396.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.016</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M478" altimg="si397.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2.000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M479" altimg="si398.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.031</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M480" altimg="si399.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.054</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Catalunya</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M481" altimg="si400.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.017</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M482" altimg="si401.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.959</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M483" altimg="si402.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M484" altimg="si403.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.311</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M485" altimg="si404.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.029</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M486" altimg="si405.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2.000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M487" altimg="si406.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.030</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M488" altimg="si407.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.040</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>País Valenciá</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M489" altimg="si408.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.034</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M490" altimg="si409.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M491" altimg="si410.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M492" altimg="si411.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.205</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M493" altimg="si412.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.066</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M494" altimg="si413.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.028</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M495" altimg="si414.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.018</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M496" altimg="si415.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.032</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Extremadura</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M497" altimg="si416.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.016</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M498" altimg="si417.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.540</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M499" altimg="si418.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.633</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M500" altimg="si419.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.264</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M501" altimg="si420.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.946</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M502" altimg="si421.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.001</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M503" altimg="si422.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.023</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M504" altimg="si423.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.041</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Galicia</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M505" altimg="si424.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.021</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M506" altimg="si425.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.814</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M507" altimg="si426.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.470</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M508" altimg="si427.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.272</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M509" altimg="si428.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.605</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M510" altimg="si429.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.001</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M511" altimg="si430.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M512" altimg="si431.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.103</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Madrid</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M513" altimg="si432.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.031</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M514" altimg="si433.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M515" altimg="si434.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M516" altimg="si435.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.243</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M517" altimg="si436.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.041</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M518" altimg="si437.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2.000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M519" altimg="si438.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.036</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M520" altimg="si439.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.034</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Murcia</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M521" altimg="si440.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.016</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M522" altimg="si441.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.803</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M523" altimg="si442.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.716</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M524" altimg="si443.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.416</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M525" altimg="si444.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.039</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M526" altimg="si445.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.081</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M527" altimg="si446.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.359</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M528" altimg="si447.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.334</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Navarra</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M529" altimg="si448.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.018</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M530" altimg="si449.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.846</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M531" altimg="si450.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.989</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M532" altimg="si451.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.185</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M533" altimg="si452.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.156</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M534" altimg="si453.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.004</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M535" altimg="si454.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.013</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M536" altimg="si455.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.039</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>Euskadi</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M537" altimg="si456.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.030</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M538" altimg="si457.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.744</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M539" altimg="si458.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M540" altimg="si459.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.128</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M541" altimg="si460.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.908</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M542" altimg="si461.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.001</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M543" altimg="si462.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.014</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M544" altimg="si463.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.018</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>La Rioja</td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M545" altimg="si464.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.025</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M546" altimg="si465.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.751</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M547" altimg="si466.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.407</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M548" altimg="si467.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.523</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M549" altimg="si468.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.030</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M550" altimg="si469.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2.000</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M551" altimg="si470.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.013</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td><inline-formula><mml:math id="M552" altimg="si471.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.035</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s0070">
              <label>Appendix C</label>
              <title>Updated results for Italy: increasing the initial protection rate</title>
              <p id="p0225">With the purpose of making an hypothetical evaluation of the impact of a more severe protection rate for Italy we perform several control scenarios since March when the control measures were completely implemented were run where the alpha value was gradually increasing from <inline-formula><mml:math id="M553" altimg="si555.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3.5</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> daily up to the post-control scenario assumption of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M554" altimg="si556.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>7.2</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> daily. Results can be seen in <xref rid="f0070" ref-type="fig">Fig. 14</xref>
.<fig id="f0070"><label>Fig. 14</label><caption><p>Control scenarios for Italy using as a starting point the parameters obtained with the post-control fitting (<xref rid="t0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr14_lrg"/></fig></p>
              <p id="p0230">Also and to compare these early projections with the real data reported at the end of the first wave, we fit the model with data reported until July 4 since on that date the end of the first wave is clear. In <xref rid="f0075" ref-type="fig">Fig. 15</xref>
the results of the adjustment obtained for the first wave of the pandemic in Italy can be observed. As can be seen, the first approximation of the model was quite successful. This can be seen especially in the final size of the peak of reported cases. On the other hand, the adjusted parameters do not vary significantly from those reported in <xref rid="t0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). For July 4 the mean fitted parameters are: <inline-formula><mml:math id="M555" altimg="si557.svg"><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>035</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>712</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>25</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>023</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>013</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>020</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M556" altimg="si558.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.017</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.<fig id="f0075"><label>Fig. 15</label><caption><p>Updated Italy model until July 4.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr15_lrg"/></fig></p>
            </sec>
            <ack id="ak005">
              <title>Acknowledgments</title>
              <p id="p0235">We acknowledge support from the Spanish Ministry of Science and Innovation through the ‘Centro de Excelencia Severo Ochoa 2019 2023’ Program (CEX2018 000806S), and support from the Generalitat de Catalunya through the CERCA Program. Partial funding support for X.R. was received from the ISCIII COVID-19 project COV20/0014 and from WINDBIOME project by the Fundació Daniel Bravo Andreu. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish or preparation of the manuscript.</p>
            </ack>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
