<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-03-11T00:59:44Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7706427" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7706427</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-12-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>pheelsevier</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Bus Res</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Bus Res</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Journal of Business Research</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0148-2963</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">0148-2963</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Elsevier Inc.</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC7706427</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7706427</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">7706427</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33281248</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pii">S0148-2963(20)30807-9</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbusres.2020.11.054</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>A novel diffusion-based model for estimating cases, and fatalities in epidemics: The case of COVID-19</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au005">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Eryarsoy</surname>
                    <given-names>Enes</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="af005" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au010">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Delen</surname>
                    <given-names>Dursun</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="af010" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
                  <xref rid="af015" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
                  <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au015">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Davazdahemami</surname>
                    <given-names>Behrooz</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="af020" ref-type="aff">d</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au020">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Topuz</surname>
                    <given-names>Kazim</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="af025" ref-type="aff">e</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="af005"><label>a</label>Sabanci University, Sabanci Business School, Turkey</aff>
                <aff id="af010"><label>b</label>Spears School of Business, Oklahoma State University, United States</aff>
                <aff id="af015"><label>c</label>School of Management, Department of MIS, Halic University, Istanbul, Turkey</aff>
                <aff id="af020"><label>d</label>University of Wisconsin-Whitewater, Department of IT and Supply Chain Management, United States</aff>
                <aff id="af025"><label>e</label>The University of Tulsa, School of Finance, Operations Management, and International Business, United States</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author at: Department of Management Science and Information Systems, Spears School of Business, Oklahoma State University, United States.</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>1</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2020</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.-->
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <month>1</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>1</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2020</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>124</volume>
              <fpage>163</fpage>
              <lpage>178</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>3</day>
                  <month>7</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>24</day>
                  <month>11</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>25</day>
                  <month>11</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2020 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2020</copyright-year>
                <copyright-holder>Elsevier Inc.</copyright-holder>
                <license>
                  <license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="ab005">
                <p>While the COVID-19 pandemic is still ongoing in a majority of countries, a wealth of literature published in reputable journals attempted to model the spread of the disease. A vast majority of these studies dealt with compartmental models such as susceptible-infected-recovered (SIR) model. Although these models are rather simple, intuitive, and insightful, we argue that they do not necessarily provide a good enough fit to the reported data, which are usually reported in the form of daily fatalities and cases during pandemics. This study proposes an alternative analytics approach that relies on diffusion models to predict the number of cases and fatalities in epidemics. After evaluating several of the well-known and widely used diffusion models in business literature, including ADBUDG, Gompertz, and Bass models, we developed and used a modified/improved version of the original Bass diffusion model to address the shortcomings of the ordinary compartmental models such as SIR and demonstrated its applicability on the portrayal of the COVID-19 pandemic incident data. The proposed model differentiates itself from other similar models by fitting the data without the need for preprocessing, requiring no initial conditions and assumptions, not involving in heavy parameterization, and also properly addressing the pressing issues such as undocumented cases, length of infectious or recovery periods.</p>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group id="kg005">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>Diffusion models</kwd>
                <kwd>Epidemic</kwd>
                <kwd>COVID-19</kwd>
                <kwd>Prediction</kwd>
                <kwd>Fatality</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="s0005">
              <label>1</label>
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p id="p0005">Recently at the end of 2019, Wuhan, an emerging business hub of China, reported the first case of an unknown type of pneumonia to the World Health Organization (WHO). At the time, nobody thought that the new disease would shut down everyday life in &gt;200 countries around the globe in around three months, reach 59 million confirmed cases and claim nearly 1.4 million deaths across the world (as of November 20, 2020). The Coronavirus Disease of 2019 (COVID-19) was characterized as a pandemic by the World Health Organization (WHO) in early March of 2020. In a short time and in parallel to the vast amount of medical research aiming at finding a remedy for the disease, a large number of epidemiologists and data analysts began to study the spread of COVID infections using the limited data available. While individual countries often provide data at varying levels of detail, the globally reported data is limited to daily cases, recovery, and fatality numbers for each country.</p>
              <p id="p0010">Notably, multiple research works have been done to simulate the spread of the disease relying on some widely accepted epidemiologic models such as susceptible-infected-recovered (SIR) (<xref rid="b0175" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0410" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0430" ref-type="bibr">You et al., 2020</xref>), susceptible-exposed-infected-recovered (SEIR) (<xref rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr">Cheng and Shan, 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr">Ferguson et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0335" ref-type="bibr">Tang et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0415" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2020</xref>), and susceptible-infected-recovered-dead (SIRD) (<xref rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr">Anastassopoulou et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr">Fanelli and Piazza, 2020</xref>) models. These studies mainly aimed at estimating the key transmission parameters of the disease such as reproduction number (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) (i.e., the average number of people getting infected by each infected individual), incubation rate (i.e., the rate at which the symptoms show up in an infected individual), and recovery rate (i.e., the rate at which the symptoms go away after they emerged). However, as we will discuss in more detail, the results reported by these studies are often remarkably inconsistent. For instance, estimates for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M2" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in the Diamond Princess cruise ship range from 2.28 (<xref rid="b0445" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2020</xref>) to numbers as large as 11 (<xref rid="b0235" ref-type="bibr">Mizumoto &amp; Chowell, 2020</xref>) and 14.8 (<xref rid="b0290" ref-type="bibr">Rocklöv et al., 2020</xref>). This inconsistency is not surprising given the volatility and misleading nature of available data at the present time combined with the rigidity of the mentioned compartmental models.</p>
              <p id="p0015">Diffusion models are widely used in various areas of research, from politics and social sciences (<xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">de Tarde, 1895</xref>, <xref rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr">Givan et al., 2010</xref>) to marketing (<xref rid="b0015" ref-type="bibr">Bass, 1969</xref>, <xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">Basu et al., 1995</xref>, <xref rid="b0050" ref-type="bibr">Chang et al., 2015</xref>, <xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr">Darrat, 2000</xref>, <xref rid="b0185" ref-type="bibr">Li and Shiu, 2012</xref>, <xref rid="b0195" ref-type="bibr">Little, 1970</xref>, <xref rid="b0255" ref-type="bibr">Nguimkeu, 2014</xref>, <xref rid="b0280" ref-type="bibr">Peres et al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="b0310" ref-type="bibr">Schramm et al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="b0320" ref-type="bibr">Sood et al., 2012</xref>, <xref rid="b0355" ref-type="bibr">Van Den Bulte, 2000</xref>, <xref rid="b0405" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2012</xref>), and medicine (<xref rid="b0205" ref-type="bibr">Lou and Zhao, 2011</xref>, <xref rid="b0380" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2016</xref>). While models such as SIR, SEIR, and their variations seem more capable of traditional diffusion models from which they were derived, they are basically meant to be used by healthcare practitioners as they simulate the whole course of the disease from exposure through recovery or death. Diffusion models, on the other hand, do not model stages and transitions of the disease and fit only to one quantity, such as the number of cases or the number of fatalities.</p>
              <p id="p0020">We argue that at the time being, the reported case numbers are misleading or varying across (or even within) individual countries. For example, how many and how diagnostic tests are carried out will influence the number of cases reported. Therefore, reported cases may not necessarily reflect the actual spread of the virus. Especially considering reports affirming the possibility of entirely asymptomatic development of COVID-19 in some patients (<xref rid="b0010" ref-type="bibr">Bai et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0240" ref-type="bibr">Mizumoto et al., 2020</xref>) as well as the unreliability of some of the test kits<xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref>
that are still being employed in developing countries make this issue even more arguable. Furthermore, each country may differ in reporting speed, or frequency, or even accuracy of reporting, leading to varying parameter values for individual country models.</p>
              <p id="p0025">Having that said, in the present study, we take a diffusion model approach and focus on the reported data, i.e., the number of recovered/deceased population rather than the whole transition process. Hence, instead of forcing our model to fit into both inaccurately reported cases and fatality/recovery numbers simultaneously, we only fit our model into infections or fatalities. Specifically, we use data from individual countries to estimate the parameters of multiple well-known diffusion models and assess their fit. These models have been widely used in business literature. Following that, we utilize numbers from existing literature (e.g., mortality, recovery rate, and demographic breakdown) along with model parameters, in a backward manner, to estimate the number of symptomatic cases, hospitalizations, and deaths in the United States. A similar backward approach has been recently employed by Flaxman et al. (<xref rid="b0110" ref-type="bibr">Flaxman et al., 2020</xref>) to estimate the reproduction number of COVID-19 in different European countries.</p>
              <p id="p0030">Modeling product growth by forecasting adoption can be considered analogous to disease spread models. Analogies such as product-disease, infection-purchase, reinfection-repeat purchase, susceptible-market potential suggest using similar models for disease spreads may be viable. For example, (<xref rid="bib451" ref-type="bibr">Olson &amp; Choi, 1985</xref>) used a logistic-based diffusion model for forecasting the rate of diffusion with repeat purchases. This is analogous to forecasting the infection rates when individuals can be reinfected. However, unlike compartmental models such as SIR, the diffusion models work without compartments, focusing only on one compartment (fatality, in our case).</p>
              <p id="p0035">After illustrating how to fit several general diffusion models on the COVID-19 data, we then customize one of the top-performing ones (the Bass diffusion model) to address several shortcomings of both compartmental models and off-the-shelf diffusion models.</p>
              <p id="p0040">The contribution of the present study is two-fold: 1) compared to the majority of similar studies, we rely on a simplistic innovative approach with a considerably easier setup and less computational requirements, and yet providing comparably even possibly better estimates. 2) By customizing the Bass diffusion model, we build an easy-to-use model that fits the data well with reasonable parameterization.</p>
              <p id="p0045">The rest of this paper is organized as follows. In the following section, we discuss various methods -with an emphasis on SIR models- being used by epidemiologists to study the spreading behavior of infectious diseases. Next, we elaborate on the diffusion models, as well as our modification, followed by an illustration of the results. We conclude the paper by discussing the findings and providing guidelines for future research.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s0010">
              <label>2</label>
              <title>Background</title>
              <p id="p0050">There is a wide selection of forecasting models besides compartmental models such as SIR. Machine learning (ML) methods such as support vector machines or artificial neural networks are known to perform very well in various forecasting tasks. However, in the case of modeling an epidemic spread, off-the-shelf machine learning models may not adequately perform due to several reasons. First, ML models do not assume any underlying distribution or trajectory beyond the available data. Therefore, they are traditionally better fit to predict “between other” observed situations, such as interpolation tasks. However, estimating fatalities, for instance, requires making predictions beyond the observed range. For instance, a polynomial function may suggest exponential growth at the early stages of the spread and then change shape only after more daily data is observed. While ML methods excel in interpolation related tasks, this is a time-series forecasting task with no calculable seasonality or trend components. This also avoids using the off-the-shelf ARIMA-based family of models.</p>
              <p id="p0055">Diffusion models (a.k.a. growth curves) are widely adopted in various areas of research, from politics and social sciences (<xref rid="b0070" ref-type="bibr">de Tarde, 1895</xref>, <xref rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr">Givan et al., 2010</xref>) to marketing (<xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">Basu et al., 1995</xref>, <xref rid="b0050" ref-type="bibr">Chang et al., 2015</xref>, <xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr">Darrat, 2000</xref>, <xref rid="b0185" ref-type="bibr">Li and Shiu, 2012</xref>, <xref rid="b0195" ref-type="bibr">Little, 1970</xref>, <xref rid="b0255" ref-type="bibr">Nguimkeu, 2014</xref>, <xref rid="b0280" ref-type="bibr">Peres et al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="b0310" ref-type="bibr">Schramm et al., 2010</xref>, <xref rid="b0320" ref-type="bibr">Sood et al., 2012</xref>, <xref rid="b0355" ref-type="bibr">Van Den Bulte, 2000</xref>, <xref rid="b0405" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2012</xref>), information systems (<xref rid="b0155" ref-type="bibr">Jeyaraj and Sabherwal, 2014</xref>, <xref rid="b0265" ref-type="bibr">Ntwoku et al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="b0350" ref-type="bibr">Udo et al., 2018</xref>), finance (<xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">Boratyńska and Grzegorzewska, 2018</xref>, <xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr">Hongmei, 2012</xref>, <xref rid="b0160" ref-type="bibr">Jibao et al., 2010</xref>), economics (<xref rid="b0425" ref-type="bibr">Yang, 2012</xref>, <xref rid="b0435" ref-type="bibr">Yuhn et al., 2015</xref>), and medicine (<xref rid="b0205" ref-type="bibr">Lou and Zhao, 2011</xref>, <xref rid="b0380" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2016</xref>). In his original work <xref rid="b0340" ref-type="bibr">Tarde (1890)</xref> noted the power of imitation as one of the driving factors behind the spread of political ideas. These models have certain mathematical properties that help get insights into the diffusion process.</p>
              <p id="p0060">Generally, the diffusion models follow an S-shape curve representing the spread or growth. Analogous to cumulative distribution functions (cdf), the models map the independent variable (time) to the dependent variable, diffusion (see <xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>
).<fig id="f0005"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>A typical S-shape curve of a diffusion model.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig></p>
              <p id="p0065"><xref rid="b0220" ref-type="bibr">Mahajan and Schoeman, 1977</xref>, <xref rid="b0225" ref-type="bibr">Mahajan and Wind, 1985</xref> generalized diffusion models as <inline-formula><mml:math id="M3" altimg="si6.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, where M is the limit for diffusion and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M4" altimg="si7.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M5" altimg="si8.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are diffusion rate and cumulative diffusion, respectively. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M6" altimg="si9.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, known as the “pressure function”, is used to characterize the structure of the diffusion model. There are a variety of models/functions that offer different kinds of pressure functions such as, <xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">Gompertz, 1825</xref>, <xref rid="b0385" ref-type="bibr">Weibull, 1951</xref>, <xref rid="b0285" ref-type="bibr">Richards, 1959</xref>, <xref rid="b0370" ref-type="bibr">Von Bertalanffy, 1957</xref>, and <xref rid="b0015" ref-type="bibr">Bass (1969)</xref>. Many of these models share similar characteristics (e.g., Bertalanffy is a special case of generalized logistic function). <xref rid="b0150" ref-type="bibr">Jaakkola (1996)</xref> offers a useful review of the existing diffusion models.</p>
              <p id="p0070">More recently, a new generation of modified forecasting diffusion models with enhanced capabilities has emerged. These models may use simulation techniques, dynamic programming, or feedback mechanisms for model fit; and may incorporate exogenous variables or perform multi-phased analyses. Some of them are already widely used in epidemics such as susceptible-infected-recovered (SIR) (<xref rid="b0175" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0410" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0430" ref-type="bibr">You et al., 2020</xref>), susceptible-exposed-infected-recovered (SEIR) (<xref rid="b0055" ref-type="bibr">Cheng and Shan, 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr">Ferguson et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0335" ref-type="bibr">Tang et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0415" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2020</xref>), or susceptible-infected-recovered-dead (SIRD) (<xref rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr">Anastassopoulou et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr">Fanelli and Piazza, 2020</xref>). For example, SIR models (<xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>
) are often employed to model infectious diseases using three states (susceptible, infectious, and recovered). It employs three differential equations that manage the transitions from one state to another.<fig id="f0010"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>SIR model with four stages.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2_lrg"/></fig></p>
              <p id="p0075">The number of susceptible, infectious, and recovered individuals are represented by S(t), I(t), and R(t), respectively. Denoting the population size as M, the corresponding fraction of the population can be obtained by dividing those three values by M. The quantities in each compartment depend on the inter-compartment transitions, which can be written as a set of differential Eqs. <xref rid="e0005" ref-type="disp-formula">(1)</xref>, <xref rid="e0010" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref>, <xref rid="e0015" ref-type="disp-formula">(3)</xref>. Solving SIR requires specialized algorithms such as Runge-Kutta method to estimate model parameters (<xref rid="b0440" ref-type="bibr">Zeb et al., 2014</xref>) needed to simulate the disease's spread.<disp-formula id="e0005"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M7" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dS</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dt</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">-</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="e0010"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M8" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dI</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dt</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">-</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="e0015"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M9" altimg="si12.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dR</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dt</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
              <p id="p0080">Perhaps the most critical parameter for a disease spread is the basic reproduction number, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M10" altimg="si13.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. This number is also used to estimate the number of total infections. For seasonal flu, for example, this number hovers around 1.3, meaning each infected person infects 1.3 people (<xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr">Biggerstaff et al., 2014</xref>). Parameters' infectious rate (<italic>β</italic>), and recovery rate (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M11" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) manage the transition between states (<xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>). Recovery rate (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M12" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) refers to the inverse of the average infectious period. Using Lambert W function to numerically solve Eq. <xref rid="e0010" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref> for <italic>S</italic>, the model can also be used to estimate the percentage of the susceptible population for given <inline-formula><mml:math id="M13" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>
). The model indicates that even considering an optimistic estimate of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M14" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> of 2.2 for COVID-19, as suggested by <xref rid="b0175" ref-type="bibr">Li et al. (2020)</xref>, 84% of the population is susceptible to infection.<fig id="f0015"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Different <inline-formula><mml:math id="M15" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> values and corresponding percentages of the susceptible population using SIR model: R0 = 1.3 for seasonal flu, and R0 = 2.2 for COVID-19.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3_lrg"/></fig></p>
              <p id="p0085">Also, <xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>
indicates the percentage of the population involved through the overall course of the COVID-19 progress based on SIR model and using the estimates provided by <xref rid="b0175" ref-type="bibr">Li et al. (2020)</xref>. Again, the curve (<italic>S</italic>) does not drop down to zero, indicating a maximum susceptible fraction of near 84%.<fig id="f0020"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>A sample run for the overall course of progress for COVID-19 outbreak using SIR model, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M16" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> = 2.2, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M17" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>=0.275, γ = 0.125.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr4_lrg"/></fig></p>
              <p id="p0090">The SIR model requires three initial state values indicating (i) the number of susceptible population (or population at time <italic>t</italic>), (ii) number of active infections, and (iii) currently recovered patients. While this model is very intuitive, the three model parameters for COVID-19 have been widely studied and reported in recent literature with significantly inconsistent results. <xref rid="b0175" ref-type="bibr">Li et al. (2020)</xref>, for example, estimated basic reproduction number <inline-formula><mml:math id="M18" altimg="si14.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> as 2.2, and recovery rate as <inline-formula><mml:math id="M19" altimg="si15.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (i.e., average infectious period is 2.3 days). In another study, <xref rid="b0410" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al.(2020)</xref> provided an estimate of 1.94 for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M20" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Other studies have also provided estimates ranging from 2.0 to 6.7 for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M21" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr">Anastassopoulou et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0100" ref-type="bibr">Fanelli and Piazza, 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0275" ref-type="bibr">Organization and Organization, 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0335" ref-type="bibr">Tang et al., 2020</xref>).</p>
              <p id="p0095">Perhaps one reason behind this inconsistency is that the reported incident data and the SIR model are not compatible. SIR model estimates (and therefore fits to) the number of infectious and recovered. Countries report only daily new cases, new fatalities, and recoveries. The active number of cases is, therefore, the difference between cumulative figures of the reported cases and recoveries. This figure indicates the number of cases that are under medical supervision as inpatient or outpatients. However, the model relies on the number of infectious individuals who may be unattended but still infectious. So, it is important to estimate the active number of infections, given the number of cases. Within SIR this estimation relies on the parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="M22" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and using a sliding window with a length of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M23" altimg="si16.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. <xref rid="b0075" ref-type="bibr">Delen et al. (2020)</xref> estimated the size of this window for the reported data as 8 days for COVID-19. Therefore <inline-formula><mml:math id="M24" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is typically invariant, and we can calculate the active infections by aggregating the reported number of daily cases over a sliding window. This, however, limits the capability of SIR model as only parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="M25" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> can be adjusted to fit the data throughout the analysis. We believe this is one of the reasons why SIR may not be the most suitable model for fitting to spread data. Below we summarize three principal reasons for using diffusion models besides SIR:<list list-type="simple" id="l0005"><list-item id="o0005"><label>i.</label><p id="p0100"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M26" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><italic>parameter alone is not sufficient to mimic the spread:</italic> As mentioned above, if we consider the number of susceptible in the population as fixed, the only remaining parameter to be estimated is, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M27" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. However, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M28" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> alone may not be sufficient to fit the data (See <xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>
) tightly. The figure suggests that changing <inline-formula><mml:math id="M29" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> values is not sufficient to fit the real data, and that there is a need for a time shift, at the very least.<fig id="f0025"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Different “Infected” compartment trajectories for Belgium COVID-19 data using SIR with different <inline-formula><mml:math id="M30" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> values and most suitable initial susceptible population (not assumed equal to the population size for better fit).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr5_lrg"/></fig></p></list-item><list-item id="o0010"><label>ii.</label><p id="p0105">Even without fixing recovery rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="M31" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the model may not fit: This is possibly due to the undocumented cases making fitting data more difficult. The model formulation, given in Eqs. (1)–(3), assumes all infections being documented. However, there may be cases of infection that go undocumented. These cases may as well be the key driving factor behind new infections.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0015"><label>iii.</label><p id="p0110"><italic>Using the reported number of cases and fatalities is more direct</italic>: In the case of COVID-19, standardized reports contain only daily cases and fatalities for individual countries. In SIR, the transition between compartments is managed through the two parameters. These parameters are used to estimate the number of susceptible, infectious, and recovered individuals. The SIR model is fit by using the infectious compartment (Eq. (2)) as it contains both parameters. Therefore, unfortunately, the model cannot be used to fit to, say, reported fatality numbers only. The model fits to fatality and infection numbers together. However, keeping track of the number of infectious is not straightforward. The number of reported cases varies from one country to another depending on their practices, such as the number of tests they conduct each day. The data available offers only two ways of calculating the number of infected: (i) computing the difference between the recovered compartment and the cumulative number of cases reported. This number can be used as the number of the currently infected population. (ii) estimating infectious patients using a sliding window with a length of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M32" altimg="si16.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). This length can be estimated by calculating a lag parameter between the recovery and infection data (<xref rid="b0075" ref-type="bibr">Delen et al., 2020</xref>). We argue that being able to use fatality numbers alone is more reliable, especially since the reported case numbers depend on the specific country's reporting style (such as testing frequency or reporting speed). This can be easily seen by looking at the significantly varying crude CFR rates (#of cases / #of deaths) across individual countries. This may be due to highly varying levels of testing across countries. For example, denser testing may reveal more cases, including milder ones or asymptomatic ones, whereas less frequent testing may only be applied to patients with more obvious symptoms. Although fatality numbers might still be biased due to misclassification of the reason for some deaths or even intentional underreporting by the health authorities, however, they are expected to provide a more accurate image of the reality than the infection numbers given the less biasing factors involved in their reporting process. Therefore, fitting a diffusion model on fatality data only might be easier.</p></list-item></list>
</p>
              <p id="p0115">We attempted to compute SIR model parameters that fit COVID-19 data using both methods. However, we were unable to compute a consistent set of parameters providing a good fit to the data reported (<xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>).</p>
              <p id="p0120">As mentioned earlier, a review of literature on employing compartmental models such as SIR for estimating parameters of the COVID-19 spread also shows a lack of consensus among researchers. Of course, this inconsistency is not surprising given the volatility and misleading nature of available data, the number of tests carried out, various interventions implemented in different countries to combat the spread of the disease, the intensive parameter calculations required for these compartment models. One way of fitting the SIR model is by modifying and letting <inline-formula><mml:math id="M33" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> vary across time (<xref rid="b0075" ref-type="bibr">Delen et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0165" ref-type="bibr">Katriel and Stone, 2012</xref>). However, this kind of over-parametrization may make the model overfit the data, and still does not address the issue of underreporting. Diffusion models, as opposed to SIR, do not model stages and transitions and fit only to one quantity, such as the number of cases or the number of fatalities, and hence, have fewer parameters to be estimated.</p>
              <p id="p0125">In this paper, we first take a diffusion model approach by employing a variety of well-accepted general diffusion models and focus only on the recovered/deceased population as opposed to modeling the whole transition process. Observing the early stages of the spread, experts may use their domain knowledge and make forecasts on, for example, the number of fatalities at the end of the infection cycle. Incorporating such experts' knowledge in the modeling efforts could be beneficial, given the high degree of uncertainty when a new disease emerges. By design, this additional domain information cannot be embedded in the SIR model. However, the diffusion models we use in this study let us incorporate such domain knowledge. For example, including expert opinions based on the total number of fatalities is possible by adjusting the upper-asymptotes in a diffusion model. Also, diffusion models can be used to fit fatality or infection data independently. We argue that such an approach may yield more reliable estimates. Furthermore, fitting a model to fatality numbers using diffusion models is algebraically more straightforward than a set of differential equations.</p>
              <p id="p0130">At the next stage, we modify the Bass diffusion model (one of the best-performing ones from the previous stage) and relax the domain knowledge required for setting upper-asymptotes and attempt to address some of the shortcomings of both diffusion and compartmental models. The model can be directly used on daily reported data. Our model is composed of two sub-models: (i) a modified Bass diffusion sub-model to fit reported cases data, and (ii) a sliding window sub-model to fit fatality data.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s0015">
              <label>3</label>
              <title>Method and data</title>
              <sec id="s0020">
                <label>3.1</label>
                <title>Data</title>
                <p id="p0135">Seven weeks after curfew, on March 12 of 2020, the Chinese government declared a triumph over COVID-19 after curbing the spread of the virus. There are several different data providers on the latest COVID-19 spread, such as European Union Center for Disease Prevention and Control (ECDC), World Health Organization (WHO), and Johns Hopkins University (JHU). For this study, we make use of the dataset maintained by ECDC<xref rid="fn2" ref-type="fn">2</xref>
. The dataset starts with the first reported cases by China, on December 31, 2019. It contains 210 countries and regions with their populations, continents, and country geographical IDs. Based on the dataset as of June 23, several other countries, including Italy, and Spain, are reaching the end of the COVID-19 spread cycle.</p>
                <p id="p0140">As the spread dynamics are age-sensitive, we also make use of data on population pyramids of countries maintained by the United Nations. For diffusion models, we benchmark our analysis using US data. We then estimate age-adjusted incident expectations using conditional probabilities that help create higher quality upper asymptotes for the models. The reason for this adjustment is that age-disparities can account for as much as 22-folds of difference in case fatality rate (CFR) depending on the specific country's population pyramid (<xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr">Eryarsoy et al., 2020</xref>).</p>
                <p id="p0145">Diffusion models fit better when data spans wider time periods. At the time of this paper's writing, not all countries have reached the peak of disease spread. In order to be able to compare parameter values across countries, we first check spread maturities in these countries (whether the spread is still at its infancy, or maturing, or towards the ending stage). While we use data from the top 50 countries based on their reported number of fatalities, we discard those that are still experiencing the early stages of the spread (such as India, Bangladesh, and Panama). We indicate the maturity levels of spread for those that are included in our analysis.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s0025">
                <label>3.2</label>
                <title>Basic diffusion models</title>
                <p id="p0150">We first compile a list of diffusion models to use on our dataset. A typical diffusion process for a disease involves huge amounts of data and a high number of interrelated variables. The diffusion models we use are simplified mathematical representations for the major aspects of the diffusion process. We use the following set of diffusion models to test on COVID-19 data: ADBUDG, Bass diffusion model, Gompertz, Weibull-Gamma, Logistic, and Chapman-Richards models. These models have been extensively used in business literature, specifically in marketing, information systems, and finance: ADBUDG (<xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr">Basu et al., 1995</xref>, <xref rid="b0080" ref-type="bibr">Dong et al., 2007</xref>, <xref rid="b0195" ref-type="bibr">Little, 1970</xref>, <xref rid="b0325" ref-type="bibr">Streukens et al., 2011</xref>, <xref rid="b0405" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2012</xref>), Bass (<xref rid="b0095" ref-type="bibr">Fan et al., 2017</xref>, <xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr">Hsiao et al., 2009</xref>, <xref rid="b0155" ref-type="bibr">Jeyaraj and Sabherwal, 2014</xref>, <xref rid="b0245" ref-type="bibr">Naseri and Elliott, 2013</xref>, <xref rid="b0265" ref-type="bibr">Ntwoku et al., 2017</xref>), Gompertz (<xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr">Darrat, 2000</xref>, <xref rid="b0245" ref-type="bibr">Naseri and Elliott, 2013</xref>, <xref rid="b0255" ref-type="bibr">Nguimkeu, 2014</xref>, <xref rid="b0320" ref-type="bibr">Sood et al., 2012</xref>, <xref rid="b0350" ref-type="bibr">Udo et al., 2018</xref>), Logistics (<xref rid="b0040" ref-type="bibr">Boratyńska and Grzegorzewska, 2018</xref>, <xref rid="b0245" ref-type="bibr">Naseri and Elliott, 2013</xref>, <xref rid="b0255" ref-type="bibr">Nguimkeu, 2014</xref>, <xref rid="b0355" ref-type="bibr">Van Den Bulte, 2000</xref>, <xref rid="b0360" ref-type="bibr">Van Den Bulte and Joshi, 2007</xref>), Weibull (<xref rid="b0360" ref-type="bibr">Van Den Bulte &amp; Joshi, 2007</xref>). We must also note that other diffusion models have also been used in literature. Interested readers may refer to Mahajan (<xref rid="b0215" ref-type="bibr">Mahajan et al., 1990</xref>) for an earlier, but insightful discussion of using a variety of such models in marketing.</p>
                <p id="p0155">While these models have been widely used in especially business literature, they are not exclusively built to analyze the dynamics of the spread of infectious diseases. However, by nature, their formulations can accommodate such dynamics. The number of infected persons (inverted-S), recovered ones, and the number of fatalities typically follow an S-shaped distribution (see <xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). Below, we briefly introduce the diffusion models we used in our study.</p>
                <sec id="s0030">
                  <label>3.2.1</label>
                  <title>ADBUDG model</title>
                  <p id="p0160">The Advertising Budgeting (ADBUDG) model proposed by <xref rid="b0195" ref-type="bibr">Little (1970)</xref> is basically designed as a marketing mix model focusing on advertising budget management. The original model is meant to fit advertising efforts to market responses. Hence it is not designed to map time to diffusion. In the context of disease spread over time, the model can be reformulated as follows:<disp-formula id="e0020"><mml:math id="M34" altimg="si17.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where:<list list-type="simple" id="l0010"><list-item id="o0020"><p id="p0165"><italic>t</italic> : time period</p></list-item><list-item id="o0025"><p id="p0170">A: Upper asymptote</p></list-item><list-item id="o0030"><p id="p0175">L: Lower asymptote</p></list-item><list-item id="o0035"><p id="p0180">C: Shape parameter (concave for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M35" altimg="si18.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and s-shaped for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M36" altimg="si19.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>)</p></list-item><list-item id="o0040"><p id="p0185">D: Second shape parameter</p></list-item><list-item id="o0045"><p id="p0190"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M37" altimg="si20.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> : cumulative number of fatalities</p></list-item></list>
</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s0035">
                  <label>3.2.2</label>
                  <title>Bass diffusion model</title>
                  <p id="p0195">Developed by Frank <xref rid="b0015" ref-type="bibr">Bass (1969)</xref>, the original Bass model describes the adoption process of new products over time by taking into account the interactions of potential adopters. Bass classifies new product adopters as innovators and imitators and implies that the speed and time of adoption depend on the degree of innovativeness (p) and imitation (q) among them, respectively, where the latter can be controlled by the decision-maker while the former is out of her control.</p>
                  <p id="p0200">We adapt the Bass diffusion model in the context of the number of disease fatalities over time as follows:<disp-formula id="e0025"><mml:math id="M38" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where:<list list-type="simple" id="l0015"><list-item id="o0050"><p id="p0205">A: diffusion upper asymptote</p></list-item><list-item id="o0055"><p id="p0210"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M39" altimg="si22.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> time period</p></list-item><list-item id="o0060"><p id="p0215"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M40" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>number of periods during which the disease is infectious<xref rid="fn3" ref-type="fn">3</xref></p></list-item><list-item id="o0065"><p id="p0220"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M41" altimg="si24.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>: number of infections during period <inline-formula><mml:math id="M42" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0070"><p id="p0225"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M43" altimg="si26.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> : cumulative number of fatalities</p></list-item><list-item id="o0075"><p id="p0230"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M44" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>: Imitation coefficient. This manages the deaths due to disease transmission from an individual to an individual that can be controlled by the decision-maker.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0080"><p id="p0235"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M45" altimg="si28.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>: Innovation coefficient. This coefficient is typically smaller than <inline-formula><mml:math id="M46" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and this is the coefficient that the decision-maker cannot control. This is basically due to the transmissions that will happen regardless of the number of measures taken by the governments. Typically curve fitting yields a smaller number for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M47" altimg="si28.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> than <inline-formula><mml:math id="M48" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></list-item></list>
</p>
                  <p id="p0240">The model in the original form is essentially in the quadratic form where:<disp-formula id="e0030"><mml:math id="M49" altimg="si29.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s0040">
                  <label>3.2.3</label>
                  <title>Gompertz and Shifted Gompertz models</title>
                  <p id="p0245">Gompertz model (<xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr">Gompertz, 1825</xref>), similar to Weibull model, is one of the proportional hazard models used for diffusion widely used in marketing for modeling new products adoption (<xref rid="b0365" ref-type="bibr">Van den Bulte &amp; Stremersch, 2004</xref>) as well as in information systems for modeling new technology adoption (<xref rid="b0230" ref-type="bibr">Mann et al., 2011</xref>).</p>
                  <p id="p0250">The original Gompertz curve is formulated as follows:<disp-formula id="e0035"><mml:math id="M50" altimg="si30.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">-</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>η</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">bt</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
                  <p id="p0255">Shifted Gompertz distribution, first introduced by <xref rid="b0025" ref-type="bibr">Bemmaor (1992)</xref> for modeling adoption of innovation, is a modified version of Gompertz curve where the cumulative distribution function is:<disp-formula id="e0040"><mml:math id="M51" altimg="si31.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">-</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>η</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where (in the context of disease fatalities):<list list-type="simple" id="l0020"><list-item id="o0085"><p id="p0260">A: upper asymptote/population size parameter</p></list-item><list-item id="o0090"><p id="p0265"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M52" altimg="si32.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>: shape parameter (typically <inline-formula><mml:math id="M53" altimg="si33.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>η</mml:mi><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for an S-shaped curve)</p></list-item><list-item id="o0095"><p id="p0270"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M54" altimg="si34.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> scale parameter (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M55" altimg="si35.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</p></list-item><list-item id="o0100"><p id="p0275"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M56" altimg="si36.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mo>:</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> cumulative number of fatalities</p></list-item></list>
</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s0045">
                  <label>3.2.4</label>
                  <title>Weibull distribution</title>
                  <p id="p0280">Weibull is a continuous probability distribution (<xref rid="b0385" ref-type="bibr">Weibull, 1951</xref>) that is widely used in forecasting using time series (e.g., <xref rid="b0170" ref-type="bibr">Kulkarni et al., 2012</xref>, <xref rid="b0400" ref-type="bibr">Wright and Stern, 2015</xref>). The cumulative density function for Weibull is (for values t &gt; 0):<disp-formula id="e0045"><mml:math id="M57" altimg="si37.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">-</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where:<list list-type="simple" id="l0025"><list-item id="o0105"><p id="p0285"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M58" altimg="si38.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>: shape parameter (typically k &gt; 1 for S-shaped curves)</p></list-item><list-item id="o0110"><p id="p0290"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M59" altimg="si39.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the scale parameter</p></list-item><list-item id="o0115"><p id="p0295"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M60" altimg="si36.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mo>:</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> cumulative number of fatalities</p></list-item></list>
</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s0050">
                  <label>3.2.5</label>
                  <title>Logistic model</title>
                  <p id="p0300">Logit models are discrete-time form hazard models. We set upper and lower asymptotes at 0 and 1 respectively, and used a generalized logistic growth model of the form:<disp-formula id="e0050"><mml:math id="M61" altimg="si40.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where<list list-type="simple" id="l0030"><list-item id="o0120"><p id="p0305"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M62" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>: Growth range</p></list-item><list-item id="o0125"><p id="p0310">k: Growth rate</p></list-item><list-item id="o0130"><p id="p0315"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M63" altimg="si41.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>:</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> Timeshift parameter</p></list-item><list-item id="o0135"><p id="p0320"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M64" altimg="si36.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close=")" open="("><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mo>:</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> cumulative number of fatalities</p></list-item></list>
</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s0055">
                  <label>3.2.6</label>
                  <title>Chapman-Richards model</title>
                  <p id="p0325">The Chapman-Richards growth curve is a generalization of von Bertalanffy’s growth model (<xref rid="b0370" ref-type="bibr">Von Bertalanffy, 1957</xref>). It is a popular model in forestry science for modeling the height of trees over time. Its S-shape cumulative distribution function is as follows:<disp-formula id="e0055"><mml:math id="M65" altimg="si42.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">-</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<list list-type="simple" id="l0035"><list-item id="o0140"><p id="p0330"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M66" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>: Growth range</p></list-item><list-item id="o0145"><p id="p0335">k: Growth rate</p></list-item><list-item id="o0150"><p id="p0340">m: Slope of the growth</p></list-item></list>
</p>
                  <p id="p0345">For a more in-depth discussion of Gompertz, Logit and Probit models, and ADBUDG model, readers can refer to (<xref rid="b0390" ref-type="bibr">Wierenga &amp; van der Lans, 2017</xref>). <xref rid="f0030" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>
demonstrates the steps we followed to perform our analyses using basic diffusion models.<fig id="f0030"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>A graphical depiction of the proposed methodology.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr6_lrg"/></fig></p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s0060">
                <label>3.3</label>
                <title>Modified Bass diffusion model</title>
                <p id="p0350">While using diffusion models to predict cases or fatalities has its merits, it has several shortcomings as well, such as having to set initial conditions and upper-asymptotes to fit the data well. On the other hand, reported data includes daily numbers of infections, rather than the number of active infections. This is not well-suited for compartmental models as they take the numbers of active infections as inputs. This is also suggested in the literature. <xref rid="bib452" ref-type="bibr">Tuncer and Le (2018)</xref> suggested that if health agencies report prevalence data rather than incidence data, compartmental models would better fit the data. While most of the diffusion models, as well as the SIR model, use two parameters, modeling complex processes such as epidemic disease spread typically will require more parameters or experimental data does not fit well. For example, compartmental models, as well as diffusion models, assume a fixed transmission rate throughout the spread. Letting the transmission rate parameter be time-variant will result in a tighter fit. However, it will also impede model identifiability and will cause over-parametrization, and therefore, overfitting.</p>
                <p id="p0355">In this section, we present a modified version of the original Bass diffusion model that can be used to work directly with incidence data and address some of the shortcomings mentioned above. Our model is given below:<disp-formula id="e0060"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="M67" altimg="si43.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced close="]" open="["><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="e0065"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="M68" altimg="si44.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where:<list list-type="simple" id="l0040"><list-item id="o0155"><p id="p0360"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M69" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>: time period</p></list-item><list-item id="o0160"><p id="p0365"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M70" altimg="si45.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> duration of being infectious</p></list-item><list-item id="o0165"><p id="p0370"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M71" altimg="si46.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>population</p></list-item><list-item id="o0170"><p id="p0375"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M72" altimg="si47.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>: reported number of infections for period <italic>t</italic></p></list-item><list-item id="o0175"><p id="p0380"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M73" altimg="si48.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>: <inline-formula><mml:math id="M74" altimg="si49.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> cumulative reported number of infections for period <italic>t</italic>
</p></list-item><list-item id="o0180"><p id="p0385"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M75" altimg="si24.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>: reported deaths during period <italic>t</italic></p></list-item><list-item id="o0185"><p id="p0390"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M76" altimg="si50.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> Initial transmission rate: This corresponds to the innovation coefficient in the original Bass model. This parameter initiates and drives initial transmissions when there is no infected in the country, such as transmissions coming from other countries. The rate also corresponds to the transmissions that cannot be controlled.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0190"><p id="p0395"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M77" altimg="si51.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> Transmission rate: This corresponds to the imitation coefficient in the original Bass model. This rate links new cases due to transmission from an individual to an individual. This is similar to the transmission rate coefficient <inline-formula><mml:math id="M78" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in SIR model.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0195"><p id="p0400"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M79" altimg="si52.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> scaling parameter measuring the level of reporting.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0200"><p id="p0405"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M80" altimg="si53.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> average duration length from infection date to fatality date</p></list-item><list-item id="o0205"><p id="p0410"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M81" altimg="si54.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> crude case fatality rate</p></list-item></list>
</p>
                <p id="p0415">Eq. <xref rid="e0060" ref-type="disp-formula">(4)</xref> is analogous to compartment <italic>I</italic> in the SIR model. The reported data do not reveal the number of infectious individuals. Therefore, one way of fitting SIR model is by including a separate step to estimate the number of active <italic>infectious</italic> cases among the reported ones considering the duration of being infectious. While this duration may seem to be disease-dependent or may even vary from an individual to another, in our model, we assume this value to be fixed for each region/country and associate this value to parameter <italic>d</italic>. We let this parameter to be country-specific as each country may have a different reporting system so that the calculated <italic>d</italic> values may differ across countries. For example, being quicker or slower in reporting, or conducting more or less number of tests on asymptomatic patients may change corresponding <italic>d</italic> values.</p>
                <p id="p0420">Perhaps the major shortcoming of diffusion models is the need for defining an upper asymptote. This is mainly due to the fact that diffusion models are designed to converge to an upper asymptote as the time progresses, and not all who catch the infection are reported. We address this shortcoming by introducing a scaling parameter <italic>k</italic>. The parameter <italic>k,</italic>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M82" altimg="si55.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, corresponds to the level of reporting. Larger <italic>k</italic> values indicate larger cases going unreported. <italic>k</italic> = 1 corresponds to perfect reporting.</p>
                <p id="p0425">Eq. <xref rid="e0065" ref-type="disp-formula">(5)</xref> links reported case data to reported fatalities. It simply adjusts a lag parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="M83" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to reported cases by multiplying with a case fatality rate (<italic>c</italic>). We also let <inline-formula><mml:math id="M84" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to be country-specific due to their diverse individual reporting procedures.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s0065">
              <label>4</label>
              <title>Analysis and results</title>
              <p id="p0430">One of the possible shortcomings of diffusion models is that in the absence of sufficient empirical data (short time period) or improper asymptote, they may not yield a stable model (sensitivity problem). Therefore upper-asymptote selection is crucial. We calculated asymptotes based on <xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr">Eryarsoy et al. (2020)</xref>). However, the reliability of these asymptotes depends on factors such as how well the country is managing (lower than expected, for instance), or how accurately they are reporting. The calculations are briefly discussed in the following section. For more detail, users may refer to <xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr">Eryarsoy et al. (2020)</xref>.</p>
              <sec id="s0070">
                <label>4.1</label>
                <title>Calculating upper asymptotes</title>
                <p id="p0435">Calculating upper-asymptotes translates to finding a rough approximation of the total number of incidents. The total number of fatalities or the total disease spread may depend on age/gender disparities. For COVID-19, prior studies show that age is a critical factor in the recovery/death of infected patients (<xref rid="b0260" ref-type="bibr">Novel, 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0420" ref-type="bibr">Wu and McGoogan, 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0450" ref-type="bibr">Zhou et al., 2020</xref>). So, it may not be accurate to expect similar death tolls in Niger and Japan (countries with the youngest and oldest populations, respectively). We, therefore, make use of conditional probabilities, fatality estimates, and already existing parameters from literature (e.g., recovery rate and demographic breakdown), to address these disparities. We propose two steps for calculating upper-asymptotes: (i) compute other country upper-asymptotes using conditional probabilities following the setting depicted in <xref rid="f0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>
; (ii) find good quality upper-asymptote candidates for a benchmark country (the US, in our case).<fig id="f0035"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Using conditional probabilities for calculating the upper-asymptotes of incidents.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr7_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <sec id="s0075">
                  <label>4.1.1</label>
                  <title>Using conditional probabilities for incidents</title>
                  <p id="p0440">The present study takes into account age standardization using the age pyramids of countries as a complementary piece of information to map parameters from other countries. <xref rid="f0040" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>
visualizes this phenomenon. Also, <xref rid="f0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> visualizes the spread from our analysis point of view. While we include other stages in <xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, for the sake of simplicity, we will only focus on Reported cases (R) and Deaths (D) stages for this study. We also make use of age-dependent incident data from four different countries: Spain<xref rid="fn4" ref-type="fn">4</xref>
, Italy (<xref rid="b0035" ref-type="bibr">Bignami &amp; Ghio, 2020</xref>), United States<xref rid="fn5" ref-type="fn">5</xref>
, and South Korea (<xref rid="b0315" ref-type="bibr">Shim et al., 2020</xref>). It can be seen that countries whose age pyramids are more stretched at the top experienced relatively higher numbers of infections and fatalities. The age standardization is done using simple conditional probability formulas, for example, for reported cases (R) as: <inline-formula><mml:math id="M85" altimg="si56.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. We use these conditional probabilities to compute the upper-asymptote for fatality for the US. We then estimate upper-asymptotes for other countries using their population pyramids and conditional probabilities. While this is not central to our study, we provide our estimation of age breakdowns for the US in <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>
.<fig id="f0040"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Age sensitivity of COVID-19 for Italy data.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr8_lrg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="t0005"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Calculating age breakdowns of the US data.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Age Group</th><th>P(A)-Spain</th><th>P(A)-US</th><th>P(A|C) US</th><th>P(A|H)-Spain</th><th>P(A|H)-US*</th><th>P(A|Ic)-Spain</th><th>P(A|Ic)-US*</th><th>P(A|D)-US</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>0–9</td><td>9.3%</td><td>12.1%</td><td>2.5%</td><td>0.5%</td><td>0.4%</td><td>0.2%</td><td>0.2%</td><td>0.6%</td></tr><tr><td>10–19</td><td>10.0%</td><td>12.9%</td><td>2.5%</td><td>0.3%</td><td>0.4%</td><td>0.2%</td><td>0.3%</td><td>1.0%</td></tr><tr><td>20–29</td><td>10.0%</td><td>14.0%</td><td>11.5%</td><td>2.6%</td><td>4.4%</td><td>1.7%</td><td>2.8%</td><td>6.0%</td></tr><tr><td>30–39</td><td>13.2%</td><td>13.4%</td><td>11.5%</td><td>5.6%</td><td>6.7%</td><td>3.1%</td><td>3.6%</td><td>10.3%</td></tr><tr><td>40–49</td><td>17.0%</td><td>12.2%</td><td>14.5%</td><td>10.1%</td><td>8.7%</td><td>7.9%</td><td>6.4%</td><td>13.7%</td></tr><tr><td>50–59</td><td>14.9%</td><td>12.9%</td><td>17.5%</td><td>13.9%</td><td>14.4%</td><td>18.5%</td><td>18.1%</td><td>14.9%</td></tr><tr><td>60–69</td><td>11.1%</td><td>11.5%</td><td>17.1%</td><td>18.6%</td><td>22.8%</td><td>28.3%</td><td>32.8%</td><td>14.7%</td></tr><tr><td>70–79</td><td>8.4%</td><td>7.0%</td><td>12.6%</td><td>24.1%</td><td>23.9%</td><td>33.5%</td><td>31.3%</td><td>18.2%</td></tr><tr><td>80+</td><td>6.2%</td><td>3.9%</td><td>10.2%</td><td>24.3%</td><td>18.3%</td><td>6.6%</td><td>4.7%</td><td>20.6%</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>*The probabilities in this table are computed using conditional probabilities on the dataset from the Spanish Ministry of Health (<xref rid="bib453" ref-type="bibr">Ministerio de Sanidad, 2020</xref>)</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s0080">
                  <label>4.1.2</label>
                  <title>Finding upper-asymptotes for the US</title>
                  <p id="p0445">A recent study by Oxford scientists (<xref rid="b0210" ref-type="bibr">Lourenco et al., 2020</xref>) estimated a possibility of as high as 64% of UK citizens already being infected by COVID-19 during the first 45 days of post-introduction (using <inline-formula><mml:math id="M86" altimg="si57.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.25</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). However, the article assumed a mere 0.1% of the population to require hospital care and contradicts another UK report by scientists at Imperial College in London (<xref rid="b0105" ref-type="bibr">Ferguson et al., 2020</xref>) predicted approximately 510 K fatalities, and the peak influx of patients during June (around 120 days after the first infection) for the UK (and 2.2 M for the US). Both of these studies used the SIR type of models. As noted earlier, fitting a SIR model using Runga-Kutta algorithm and reported cases, fatalities, and recoveries on COVID-19 does not provide a good fit to data. <xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>
gives different estimates for the SIR model parameters in different countries. This is possibly due to a significant number of undocumented cases. Therefore using better estimates is crucial in model fitting.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0010"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Different estimates for the SIR model parameters in different countries.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>SIR Model Parameters</th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M87" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M88" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M89" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Japan</td><td>9.7e-2</td><td>1.5e-2</td><td>6.36</td><td><inline-graphic xlink:href="fx5_lrg.gif"/></td></tr><tr><td>South Korea</td><td>1e-1</td><td>2.7e-2</td><td>3.59</td><td><inline-graphic xlink:href="fx6_lrg.gif"/></td></tr><tr><td>Italy</td><td>1.17e-1</td><td>6e-3</td><td>19.3</td><td><inline-graphic xlink:href="fx7_lrg.gif"/></td></tr><tr><td>Iran</td><td>1.2e-1</td><td>8.2e-3</td><td>15.3</td><td><inline-graphic xlink:href="fx8_lrg.gif"/></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
                  <p id="p0450"><italic>Determining R<sub>0</sub> and Susceptible Population:</italic> Different studies give different estimates of R<sub>0</sub> for COVID-19 (<xref rid="b0295" ref-type="bibr">Roques et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0330" ref-type="bibr">Sugishita et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0335" ref-type="bibr">Tang et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0345" ref-type="bibr">Trilla, 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0445" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2020</xref>) ranging from 1.4 to as high as 6.7 (usually early studies suggest larger numbers). The government measures also are effective in reducing R<sub>0</sub> of the virus. <xref rid="b0330" ref-type="bibr">Sugishita et al. (2020)</xref> study the effect of voluntary event cancellation on R<sub>0</sub> values. They found that in Japan, the R<sub>0</sub> was reduced from 2.29 to 1.99. Another study from South Korea (<xref rid="b0145" ref-type="bibr">Hwang et al., 2020</xref>) revealed effective R<sub>0</sub> values near 1 in some of the regions. However, as of the writing of this paper, keeping a world-wide spread virus R<sub>0</sub> at 1 seems overly optimistic. Therefore, we select an interval for R<sub>0</sub> as [1.8–2.2] to design our scenarios for this study.</p>
                  <p id="p0455"><italic>Determining the probability of developing symptoms, infections being reported, and hospitalization:</italic> Population with asymptomatic infections are still infectious, and their CT images can still exhibit those of typical infected COVID-19 patients. In order to compute different asymptote candidates, the probability of developing symptoms once infected is also another parameter we need to consider (P(S|I) in <xref rid="f0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>). <xref rid="b0410" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al. (2020)</xref>, in their study, assumed a 50% probability of developing symptoms after infection. Using IFR and cCFR in Russel et al. (2020), this number is at 45.5%. A more recent study suggested this number to be as low as 20% (<xref rid="b0065" ref-type="bibr">Day, 2020</xref>). For our scenarios, we consider a probability interval of [0.20–0.50] for developing symptoms given infection. In a similar manner, we consider a range of [0.11, 0.20] for P(R|S), probability of being reported given developing symptoms. Also, P(H|R), the probability of hospitalization of reported cases is considered 36% across all scenarios (<xref rid="bib453" ref-type="bibr">Ministerio de Sanidad, 2020</xref>).</p>
                  <p id="p0460"><italic>Determining underreporting:</italic> Many studies highlight under-reporting or undocumented cases. A peer-reviewed paper states as much as 86% of the cases in Wuhan went undocumented (<xref rid="b0180" ref-type="bibr">R. Li et al., 2020</xref>). Another study put the same figure at around 55–68% (<xref rid="b0305" ref-type="bibr">Russell et al., 2020</xref>). Also, an article by the Economist<xref rid="fn6" ref-type="fn">6</xref>
visualized total death numbers for several cities from Europe. After accounting for the expected number of deaths, and deaths reported due to pandemic, the unexplained numbers suggest that undocumented death cases may actually be even higher than the COVID-19 fatalities reported by countries. Depending on the scenario, we assume the number of reported cases to be between %11 and 60% of the symptomatic cases.</p>
                  <p id="p0465"><italic>Determining Case Fatality Rates:</italic> Crude estimates of case fatality rates are calculated by simply dividing the number of deaths (D) by the number of reported ((R) in <xref rid="f0035" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>). Studies focusing on fatality rates of COVID-19 also report different findings. While earlier studies (<xref rid="b0200" ref-type="bibr">Livingston and Bucher, 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0375" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2020</xref>) estimated case fatality risk (CFR) as high as 6–7% percent, the numbers were found to be inflated because recovery or death is not known for all the cases (hence referred to as naïve or crude CFR). Studies typically report fatalities based on the number of reported cases and therefore are region-specific (<xref rid="b0270" ref-type="bibr">Onder et al., 2020</xref>). Some studies analyze fatality rates by taking the median time from the onset of symptoms (case reporting) until the time of the death into account. <xref rid="b0395" ref-type="bibr">Wilson et al. (2020)</xref> estimate this time around 13 days. The length of this time period is consistent across other studies as well (<xref rid="b0190" ref-type="bibr">Linton et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0305" ref-type="bibr">Russell et al., 2020</xref>). Two recent studies estimated CFR at 1.4% (<xref rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr">Guan et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b0410" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al., 2020</xref>). The CFRs reported by such countries are arguably a better indicator of the lethalness of the virus. However, assuming that even this level of screening can potentially miss some cases, then we opt for a mild CFR at 1.5% for our scenarios. We acknowledge that the above approach is fairly simplistic and only used it to create different analysis scenarios.</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s0085">
                <label>4.2</label>
                <title>Scenarios development</title>
                <p id="p0470">Following the previous discussion on estimated ranges for R<sub>0</sub>, CFR (corrected), and conditional probabilities of developing symptoms, infections being reported, and hospitalization, we decide on the following three scenarios for this study:<list list-type="simple" id="l0045"><list-item id="o0210"><p id="p0475"><bold>Scenario 1</bold>: R<sub>0</sub> of 2.2; P(S|I):50% of infected show symptoms, P(R|S): 20% reported cases, P(H|R): 36% hospitalization of reported cases, CFR of 1.5%</p></list-item><list-item id="o0215"><p id="p0480"><bold>Scenario 2</bold>: R<sub>0</sub> of 2, P(S|I):35% infected show symptoms, P(R|S): 15% of symptomatic cases are being reported, P(H|R): 36% of hospitalization of reported cases, CFR of 1.5%</p></list-item><list-item id="o0220"><p id="p0485"><bold>Scenario 3</bold>: R<sub>0</sub> of 1.8, P(S|I):20% infected show symptoms, P(R|S): 11% of symptomatic cases are being reported, P(H|R): 36% of hospitalization of reported cases, CFR of 1.5%</p></list-item></list>
</p>
                <p id="p0490">A published poll (from the CDC experts) on four possible scenarios based on COVID-19 characteristics states that between 160 (best case scenario) to 240 million (worst case scenario) people in the United States could be infected throughout the course of the epidemic, in which case between 2.4 and 21 million people may require hospitalization and between 200,000 to 1.7 million people could die<xref rid="fn7" ref-type="fn">7</xref>
. Another recent estimate by Murray (2020) as of April 12, 2020 forecasts the number of fatalities for the US to be between 26 K and 155 K. Table indicates the breakdowns for our scenarios 1–3, and the expert estimates. The estimated numbers for susceptible people and fatalities yielded by our 1st and 2nd scenarios roughly match the CDC estimates, while 2nd and 3rd scenarios also roughly match Murray (2020). Scenario 3 also uses the parameters that demonstrate a good fit with the Wuhan and Italy data. We decided to use the 2nd scenario that matches both CDC estimates as well as Murray (2020) to determine upper asymptotes (see <xref rid="t0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>
).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0015"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Research scenarios.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>COVID-19 parameters (based on estimates from the literature)</th><th>US Scenario 1</th><th>US Scenario 2</th><th>US Scenario 3</th><th>Estimate 1</th><th>Estimate 2</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Susceptible population (R<sub>0</sub> = {2.2, 2.0, 1.8})</td><td>276.4</td><td>263.2</td><td>240.2</td><td>160–210</td><td>–</td></tr><tr><td>Population with symptoms (50%,35%,20%)</td><td>138</td><td>92</td><td>48</td><td>–</td><td>–</td></tr><tr><td>Reported cases (11%–60%)</td><td>27.6</td><td>14</td><td>5.28</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Hospitalization*</td><td>10</td><td>5.0</td><td>1.90</td><td>2.4–21</td><td>–</td></tr><tr><td>ICU cases</td><td>0.7</td><td>0.37</td><td>0.141</td><td>–</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Fatality</td><td>0.41</td><td>0.21</td><td>0.079</td><td>0.2–1.7</td><td>0.026–0.155</td></tr><tr><td>CFR</td><td>1.50%</td><td>1.50%</td><td>1.50%</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>IFR</td><td>0.15%</td><td>0.08%</td><td>0.03%</td><td/><td/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s0090">
                <label>4.3</label>
                <title>Curve fitting with diffusion models</title>
                <p id="p0495">Computing parameters of diffusion models are usually done by non-linear optimization with box-constraints. For curve fitting, we minimized the sum of squared error and used <xref rid="b0250" ref-type="bibr">Nelder and Mead, 1965</xref>, <xref rid="b0135" ref-type="bibr">Hooke and Jeeves, 1961</xref>, and Subplex (Nelder Mead algorithm on the sequence of subspaces) (<xref rid="b0300" ref-type="bibr">Rowan, 1991</xref>) algorithms to report the best set of parameters corresponding to the lowest RMSE. All of the diffusion models converged and fit the data.</p>
                <p id="p0500">We coded all our datasets in R language. We performed all analyses on a personal laptop equipped with 7th generation Intel® i5 processor and with 16 GB of memory.</p>
                <p id="p0505">We fit diffusion models to the selected top countries in terms of the number of fatalities. For each country and model, we report RMSE. The numbers suggest that the Chapman-Richards and Bass models fit data better than other diffusion models. They outperformed others on more country data (Chapman-Richards on 27, Bass on 13 country datasets), and the variance of RMSE is small for both of these models, indicating consistency. Details are given in <xref rid="t0025" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>. The average RMSEs are given in <xref rid="t0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>
. The table suggests that Scenario #2 enables the best fit for four of the diffusion models. Hence, the data on hand is arguably in line with Scenario #2 being the most likely scenario.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0020"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Average RMSE of standard diffusion models.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Scenario/RMSE</th><th>BASS</th><th>Gompertz</th><th>ADBUDG</th><th>Logistic</th><th>Chapman Richards</th><th>Weibull</th><th>Averages</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Scenario 1</td><td>2.62E−01</td><td>3.17E+00</td><td><bold>6.72E−01</bold></td><td>6.72E−01</td><td>2.07E−01</td><td>4.10E−01</td><td>8.99E−01</td></tr><tr><td>Scenario 2</td><td><bold>2.45E−01</bold></td><td><bold>3.08E+00</bold></td><td>1.27E+00</td><td>1.27E+00</td><td><bold>1.64E−01</bold></td><td><bold>3.82E−01</bold></td><td>1.07E+00</td></tr><tr><td>Scenario 3</td><td>9.78E−01</td><td>3.80E+01</td><td>3.81E+01</td><td><bold>2.20E−02</bold></td><td>5.05E−01</td><td>3.21E−02</td><td>1.29E+01</td></tr><tr><td>Averages</td><td>4.95E−01</td><td>1.47E+01</td><td>1.33E+01</td><td>6.54E−01</td><td>2.92E−01</td><td>2.75E−01</td><td>4.96E+00</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>*Bold numbers represent best model fit for each scenario.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
                <p id="p0510">Also, <xref rid="f0045" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>
depicts the fitted curve for each model in comparison to <xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, for Belgium. Even though the models had a good fit (low RMSEs) they pointed out a range of diffusion patterns.<fig id="f0045"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>Diffusion models on normalized Belgium data in comparison to <xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr9_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="p0515">The shape parameters of the fitted diffusion models suggested that even though the median age of China and the US are very similar (37.4 and 38.1, respectively), much faster diffusion taking place in the US. For example, the Bass diffusion model that has the innovator, and imitator coefficients, both measures of spread rates over a period, were (p = 0.0045, q = 0.14) and (p = 0.00001, q = 0.17314) for China and the US, respectively. While p, the innovation coefficient is dominant during the first stages of Bass diffusion, the imitation coefficient becomes much more dominant at later stages. These differences between the p and q coefficients for US and China diffusions suggest that even though the US had a slower pace at the beginning, the spread in the US became significantly faster than that in China.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s0095">
                <label>4.4</label>
                <title>Curve fitting with modified Bass diffusion model</title>
                <p id="p0520">The modified Bass diffusion model tends to require heavier parameterization. Computing parameters of the modified model is also done by using non-linear optimization methods with box-constraints. While using the same set of optimization methods we used for diffusion models such as Nelder-Mead, or Hooke Jeeves is possible, these algorithms did not converge for some of the instances. We used Shuffled Complex Evolution (SCE) optimization due to <xref rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr">Duan et al. (1992)</xref> for curve fitting. The algorithm took less than 5 s of computing time per country. We also cross-checked the results implementing a Genetic Algorithms search with BFGS due to <xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr">Byrd et al. (1995)</xref>. While GA took significantly more time to converge, it was unable to outperform the SCE on any country data. Both of the algorithms converged to a very similar set of parameter values across the countries we tested. <xref rid="f0050" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10</xref>
illustrates the fit over Belgium case data for comparison.<fig id="f0050"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p>Fitting the modified Bass model to Belgium data.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr10_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="p0525">The last column of <xref rid="t0025" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>
indicates the RMSEs of our modified Bass model for different countries. As shown, for all countries, the proposed model outperforms all the regular diffusion models in fitting COVID-19 data.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0025"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Diffusion model results.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Countries</th><th>Estimated Upper Asymptote (Fatality per 1 M)</th><th>BASS</th><th>Gompertz</th><th>ADBUDG</th><th>Logistic</th><th>Chapman Richards</th><th>Weibull</th><th>Modified Bass Fit</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Afghanistan</td><td>69.81</td><td>2.72E−04</td><td>5.10E−04</td><td>1.94E−04</td><td>1.94E−04</td><td><bold>1.88E−04</bold></td><td>1.90E−04</td><td><bold>3.03E−06</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Argentina</td><td>307.26</td><td>4.38E−05</td><td>8.65E−05</td><td>1.67E−05</td><td><bold>1.67E−05</bold></td><td>1.12E−04</td><td>1.68E−05</td><td><bold>3.63E−06</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Austria</td><td>807.55</td><td>2.23E−04</td><td>5.87E−03</td><td>5.56E−03</td><td>5.56E−03</td><td><bold>5.46E−05</bold></td><td>5.69E−03</td><td><bold>9.00E−06</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Bangladesh</td><td>180.13</td><td><bold>1.01E−05</bold></td><td>1.01E−05</td><td>2.75E−05</td><td>2.75E−05</td><td>1.37E−05</td><td>2.70E−05</td><td><bold>1.10E−06</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Belgium</td><td>679.57</td><td>4.95E−02</td><td>3.38E−01</td><td>1.61E−02</td><td>1.61E−02</td><td><bold>5.97E−03</bold></td><td>1.46E−01</td><td><bold>2.06E−05</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Bolivia</td><td>134.76</td><td>4.09E−04</td><td>4.10E−04</td><td>2.64E−03</td><td>2.64E−03</td><td><bold>3.66E−04</bold></td><td>2.13E−03</td><td><bold>8.39E−06</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Brazil</td><td>334.82</td><td>3.88E−04</td><td>7.57E−03</td><td>4.57E−04</td><td>4.57E−04</td><td><bold>2.54E−04</bold></td><td>4.14E−04</td><td><bold>1.70E−05</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Canada</td><td>717.68</td><td><bold>1.74E−03</bold></td><td>2.51E−02</td><td>1.02E−02</td><td>1.02E−02</td><td>1.65E−02</td><td>1.21E−02</td><td><bold>6.13E−06</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Chile</td><td>394.23</td><td><bold>2.77E−03</bold></td><td>3.16E−03</td><td>6.85E−03</td><td>6.85E−03</td><td>3.33E−03</td><td>6.31E−03</td><td><bold>2.64E−05</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Colombia</td><td>259.09</td><td><bold>1.19E−04</bold></td><td>1.19E−04</td><td>2.16E−04</td><td>2.16E−04</td><td>1.81E−04</td><td>2.01E−04</td><td><bold>5.31E−06</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Czech Republic</td><td>712.85</td><td><bold>7.30E−05</bold></td><td>6.73E−04</td><td>4.80E−04</td><td>4.80E−04</td><td>1.68E−03</td><td>4.87E−04</td><td><bold>1.25E−05</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Denmark</td><td>717.68</td><td><bold>4.66E−04</bold></td><td>7.30E−03</td><td>6.68E−03</td><td>6.68E−03</td><td>1.92E−02</td><td>7.02E−03</td><td><bold>1.70E-05</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Dominican Republic</td><td>211.28</td><td><bold>1.26E−03</bold></td><td>5.38E−03</td><td>3.57E−03</td><td>3.57E−03</td><td>2.02E−02</td><td>4.21E−03</td><td><bold>9.67E−06</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Ecuador</td><td>202.03</td><td>1.85E−02</td><td>1.68E−01</td><td>4.17E−02</td><td>4.17E−02</td><td><bold>1.55E−02</bold></td><td>7.75E−02</td><td><bold>7.29E−05</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Egypt</td><td>128.19</td><td>3.15E−04</td><td>3.31E−04</td><td>2.62E−04</td><td>2.62E−04</td><td><bold>2.40E−04</bold></td><td>2.51E−04</td><td><bold>1.06E−06</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Finland</td><td>732.26</td><td>1.22E−04</td><td>3.12E−03</td><td>2.68E−03</td><td>2.68E−03</td><td><bold>9.22E−05</bold></td><td>2.74E−03</td><td><bold>1.15E−06</bold></td></tr><tr><td>France</td><td>679.57</td><td>1.91E−02</td><td>5.35E−01</td><td>2.90E−01</td><td>2.90E−01</td><td><bold>2.52E−03</bold></td><td>3.69E−01</td><td><bold>1.25E−05</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Germany</td><td>975.72</td><td>2.61E−04</td><td>6.98E−03</td><td>5.57E−03</td><td>5.57E−03</td><td><bold>7.15E−06</bold></td><td>5.76E−03</td><td><bold>8.45E−06</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Hungary</td><td>722.52</td><td><bold>1.43E−04</bold></td><td>2.21E−03</td><td>1.54E−03</td><td>1.54E−03</td><td>3.71E−03</td><td>1.59E−03</td><td><bold>2.17E−06</bold></td></tr><tr><td>India</td><td>211.28</td><td>4.94E−06</td><td>1.35E−05</td><td>1.47E−06</td><td>1.47E−06</td><td>2.34E−06</td><td><bold>1.44E−06</bold></td><td><bold>2.36E−07</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Indonesia</td><td>264.49</td><td>2.54E−05</td><td>3.40E−05</td><td><bold>1.64E−05</bold></td><td>1.64E−05</td><td>8.36E−05</td><td>1.65E−05</td><td><bold>4.21E−07</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Iraq</td><td>78.87</td><td>2.79E−03</td><td>2.83E−03</td><td>4.00E−03</td><td>4.00E−03</td><td><bold>2.26E−03</bold></td><td>3.94E−03</td><td><bold>2.25E−06</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Ireland</td><td>482.33</td><td>6.34E−03</td><td>3.62E−01</td><td>1.67E−01</td><td>1.67E−01</td><td><bold>4.53E−03</bold></td><td>2.36E−01</td><td><bold>2.41E−05</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Italy</td><td>886.80</td><td>1.80E−02</td><td>2.47E−01</td><td>1.27E−01</td><td>1.27E−01</td><td><bold>2.03E−03</bold></td><td>1.75E−01</td><td><bold>9.54E−06</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Japan</td><td>987.15</td><td><bold>8.23E−07</bold></td><td>2.97E−05</td><td>1.80E−05</td><td>1.80E−05</td><td>1.88E−06</td><td>1.80E−05</td><td><bold>1.05E−06</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Mexico</td><td>216.02</td><td>1.33E−03</td><td>2.52E−03</td><td>2.97E−03</td><td>2.97E−03</td><td><bold>6.97E−04</bold></td><td>1.36E−03</td><td><bold>2.57E−06</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Moldova</td><td>478.46</td><td>5.46E−04</td><td>2.59E−03</td><td><bold>3.81E−04</bold></td><td><bold>3.81E−04</bold></td><td>1.94E−03</td><td>5.04E−04</td><td><bold>1.57E−05</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Netherlands</td><td>737.15</td><td>6.09E−03</td><td>1.37E−01</td><td>8.86E−02</td><td>8.86E−02</td><td><bold>3.76E−04</bold></td><td>1.08E−01</td><td><bold>7.30E−06</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Nigeria</td><td>66.39</td><td>1.76E−05</td><td>7.27E−05</td><td>2.53E−05</td><td>2.53E−05</td><td><bold>8.31E−06</bold></td><td>2.58E−05</td><td><bold>3.79E−07</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Pakistan</td><td>126.59</td><td>7.23E−05</td><td>9.85E−05</td><td>5.72E−05</td><td>5.72E−05</td><td>5.85E−05</td><td><bold>5.33E−05</bold></td><td><bold>2.23E−06</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Panama</td><td>238.19</td><td><bold>5.93E−03</bold></td><td>1.91E−02</td><td>6.52E−03</td><td>6.52E−03</td><td>2.03E−02</td><td>8.47E−03</td><td><bold>2.15E−05</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Peru</td><td>208.94</td><td>3.02E−03</td><td>1.53E−02</td><td>5.59E−03</td><td>5.59E−03</td><td><bold>3.98E−04</bold></td><td>4.71E−04</td><td><bold>3.39E−05</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Philippines</td><td>121.90</td><td>2.48E−04</td><td>3.18E−03</td><td>1.72E−03</td><td>1.72E−03</td><td><bold>5.30E−05</bold></td><td>1.77E−03</td><td><bold>1.18E−06</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Poland</td><td>647.15</td><td>6.64E−04</td><td>6.71E−04</td><td><bold>4.13E−04</bold></td><td><bold>4.13E−04</bold></td><td>1.06E−03</td><td>4.21E−04</td><td><bold>2.54E−06</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Portugal</td><td>717.68</td><td><bold>1.51E−03</bold></td><td>7.35E−03</td><td>6.19E−03</td><td>6.19E−03</td><td>2.08E−02</td><td>6.79E−03</td><td><bold>1.76E−05</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Romania</td><td>665.57</td><td>5.31E−05</td><td>1.36E−03</td><td>9.12E−04</td><td>9.12E−04</td><td><bold>4.30E−05</bold></td><td>9.72E−04</td><td><bold>4.26E−06</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Saudi Arabia</td><td>197.51</td><td><bold>1.67E−04</bold></td><td>1.76E−04</td><td>5.29E−04</td><td>5.29E−04</td><td>2.76E−04</td><td>5.00E−04</td><td><bold>1.24E−05</bold></td></tr><tr><td>South Africa</td><td>188.68</td><td><bold>2.28E−05</bold></td><td>2.41E−05</td><td>2.03E−04</td><td>2.03E−04</td><td>4.36E−05</td><td>1.90E−04</td><td><bold>4.79E−06</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Spain</td><td>742.07</td><td>2.57E−02</td><td>4.94E−01</td><td>2.57E−01</td><td>2.57E−01</td><td><bold>6.65E−03</bold></td><td>3.82E−01</td><td><bold>1.80E−05</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Sudan</td><td>77.96</td><td>3.49E−04</td><td>3.66E−04</td><td>3.09E−04</td><td>3.09E−04</td><td><bold>2.87E−04</bold></td><td>3.04E−04</td><td><bold>1.89E−06</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Sweden</td><td>670.22</td><td>1.60E−02</td><td>1.08E−01</td><td>2.55E−02</td><td>2.55E−02</td><td><bold>3.56E−03</bold></td><td>4.68E−02</td><td><bold>2.45E−05</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Switzerland</td><td>727.38</td><td>1.84E−03</td><td>5.38E−02</td><td>4.52E−02</td><td>4.52E−02</td><td><bold>1.47E−04</bold></td><td>4.92E−02</td><td><bold>1.43E−05</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Turkey</td><td>283.96</td><td>7.93E−04</td><td>1.43E−02</td><td>1.12E−02</td><td>1.12E−02</td><td><bold>7.80E−05</bold></td><td>1.21E−02</td><td><bold>5.35E−06</bold></td></tr><tr><td>Ukraine</td><td>642.59</td><td>5.99E−06</td><td>6.68E−05</td><td>1.88E−05</td><td>1.88E−05</td><td><bold>4.45E−06</bold></td><td>1.94E−05</td><td><bold>3.51E−06</bold></td></tr><tr><td>United Kingdom</td><td>638.04</td><td>4.07E−02</td><td>3.33E−01</td><td>6.48E−02</td><td>6.48E−02</td><td><bold>5.58E−03</bold></td><td>1.56E−01</td><td><bold>1.23E−05</bold></td></tr><tr><td>United States</td><td>534.29</td><td>1.71E−02</td><td>1.67E−01</td><td>5.66E−02</td><td>5.66E−02</td><td><bold>2.56E−03</bold></td><td>8.43E−02</td><td><bold>1.75E−05</bold></td></tr><tr><td/><td>Grand Ave</td><td>2.45E−01</td><td>3.08E+00</td><td>1.27E+00</td><td>1.27E+00</td><td>1.64E−01</td><td>3.82E−01</td><td><bold>1.09E−05</bold></td></tr><tr><td/><td>Std Dev</td><td><bold>0.01</bold></td><td>0.13</td><td>0.06</td><td>0.06</td><td><bold>0.01</bold></td><td>0.09</td><td><bold>1.23E−05</bold></td></tr><tr><td/><td>Best</td><td>13</td><td/><td>3</td><td>2</td><td><bold>27</bold></td><td>2</td><td><bold>46</bold></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
                <p id="p0530">We run the modified bass diffusion model with the following upper and lower bounds: {<inline-formula><mml:math id="M90" altimg="si58.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>20</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M91" altimg="si59.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M92" altimg="si60.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M93" altimg="si61.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak" linebreakstyle="after">-</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M94" altimg="si62.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak" linebreakstyle="after">-</mml:mo><mml:mn>30</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>}. We ran parameter optimization ten times to avoid inconsistencies and reported the averages. <xref rid="t0030" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>
shows the parameter estimates for each country. These parameters should not be seen as parameters of the disease, but rather be seen as parameters corresponding to the reported spread. For instance, the results show that <italic>d</italic>, duration of being infectious, is roughly the same (around 11 days) for the countries in the initial or mid-stages of the spread, while it is shorter (on average 8 days) for countries in the ending stages. Parameter <italic>d</italic> depends on the average duration for a case to be actually tested positive, so the variation could be due to testing and reporting differences. While our model is rather parsimonious, it still indicates a large number of unreported cases (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M95" altimg="si63.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>"</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> almost for all countries except Sweden). This is in accordance with one of the most recent press releases by CDC that suggests the number of infected Americans to be at least 10 times higher than the reported 2.3 million<xref rid="fn8" ref-type="fn">8</xref>
(<inline-formula><mml:math id="M96" altimg="si64.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">US</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>43</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in our model).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0030"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Modified diffusion model parameters.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th/><th colspan="5">Submodel 1 - Cases<hr/></th><th colspan="3">Submodel 2 - Fatalities<hr/></th></tr><tr><th>Country</th><th>Stage</th><th>RMSE</th><th>d</th><th>p</th><th>q</th><th>k</th><th>RMSE</th><th><inline-formula><mml:math id="M97" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th>c</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Argentina</td><td>initial</td><td>3.6E−06</td><td>11</td><td>7E−06</td><td>0.13</td><td>114</td><td>1.8E−04</td><td>19</td><td>0.07</td></tr><tr><td>Bangladesh</td><td>initial</td><td>1.1E−06</td><td>11</td><td>3E−05</td><td>0.14</td><td>321</td><td>6.6E−06</td><td>5</td><td>0.02</td></tr><tr><td>Bolivia</td><td>initial</td><td>8.4E−06</td><td>10</td><td>5E−05</td><td>0.14</td><td>137</td><td>5.7E−04</td><td>5</td><td>0.04</td></tr><tr><td>Colombia</td><td>initial</td><td>5.3E−06</td><td>10</td><td>1E−05</td><td>0.13</td><td>40</td><td>1.4E−04</td><td>5</td><td>0.04</td></tr><tr><td>Egypt</td><td>initial</td><td>1.1E−06</td><td>12</td><td>2E−05</td><td>0.13</td><td>483</td><td>1.3E−04</td><td>6</td><td>0.05</td></tr><tr><td>India</td><td>initial</td><td>2.4E−07</td><td>14</td><td>3E−05</td><td>0.10</td><td>1001</td><td>2.4E−06</td><td>6</td><td>0.03</td></tr><tr><td>Iraq</td><td>initial</td><td>2.3E−06</td><td>11</td><td>2E−08</td><td>0.22</td><td>1010</td><td>2.2E−05</td><td>8</td><td>0.05</td></tr><tr><td>Nigeria</td><td>initial</td><td>3.8E−07</td><td>10</td><td>3E−05</td><td>0.11</td><td>446</td><td>6.7E−07</td><td>5</td><td>0.03</td></tr><tr><td>Pakistan</td><td>initial</td><td>2.2E−06</td><td>9</td><td>6E−06</td><td>0.14</td><td>42</td><td>6.1E−06</td><td>6</td><td>0.02</td></tr><tr><td>Philippines</td><td>initial</td><td>1.2E−06</td><td>11</td><td>7E−07</td><td>0.11</td><td>10</td><td>1.0E−04</td><td>7</td><td>0.06</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Averages</td><td>2.6E−06</td><td>11</td><td>1E−05</td><td>0.125</td><td>240.9</td><td>1E−05</td><td>7.2</td><td>0.04</td></tr><tr><td>Afghanistan</td><td>mid</td><td>3.0E−06</td><td>11</td><td>5E−05</td><td>0.15</td><td>588</td><td>5.5E−05</td><td>6</td><td>0.02</td></tr><tr><td>Brazil</td><td>mid</td><td>1.7E−05</td><td>13</td><td>4E−05</td><td>0.12</td><td>90</td><td>1.3E−02</td><td>5</td><td>0.07</td></tr><tr><td>Chile</td><td>mid</td><td>2.6E−05</td><td>10</td><td>4E−05</td><td>0.15</td><td>30</td><td>2.3E−03</td><td>19</td><td>0.04</td></tr><tr><td>Guatemala</td><td>mid</td><td>2.5E−06</td><td>11</td><td>1E−05</td><td>0.14</td><td>396</td><td>3.7E−05</td><td>16</td><td>0.08</td></tr><tr><td>Mexico</td><td>mid</td><td>2.6E−06</td><td>10</td><td>6E−05</td><td>0.14</td><td>164</td><td>6.6E−05</td><td>8</td><td>0.15</td></tr><tr><td>Peru</td><td>mid</td><td>3.4E−05</td><td>12</td><td>1E−04</td><td>0.13</td><td>50</td><td>2.1E−03</td><td>6</td><td>0.03</td></tr><tr><td>Poland</td><td>mid</td><td>2.6E−06</td><td>10</td><td>9E−05</td><td>0.09</td><td>44</td><td>1.8E−04</td><td>5</td><td>0.05</td></tr><tr><td>South Africa</td><td>mid</td><td>4.8E−06</td><td>10</td><td>1E−05</td><td>0.14</td><td>76</td><td>3.0E−06</td><td>12</td><td>0.04</td></tr><tr><td>Sudan</td><td>mid</td><td>1.9E−06</td><td>9</td><td>5E−05</td><td>0.15</td><td>1820</td><td>8.7E−06</td><td>7</td><td>0.07</td></tr><tr><td>Sweden</td><td>mid</td><td>2.5E−05</td><td>13</td><td>2E−05</td><td>0.07</td><td>2</td><td>6.6E−02</td><td>5</td><td>0.12</td></tr><tr><td>Ukraine</td><td>mid</td><td>3.5E−06</td><td>10</td><td>7E−05</td><td>0.11</td><td>49</td><td>1.4E−05</td><td>5</td><td>0.03</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Averages</td><td>1.1E−05</td><td>11</td><td>5E−05</td><td>0.125</td><td>300.9</td><td>7.6E−03</td><td>8.6</td><td>0.06</td></tr><tr><td>Austria</td><td>ending</td><td>9.1E−06</td><td>5</td><td>6E−03</td><td>0.26</td><td>440</td><td>8.2E−04</td><td>13</td><td>0.04</td></tr><tr><td>Belgium</td><td>ending</td><td>2.1E−05</td><td>9</td><td>2E−03</td><td>0.15</td><td>125</td><td>3.8E−02</td><td>7</td><td>0.17</td></tr><tr><td>Canada</td><td>ending</td><td>6.3E−06</td><td>9</td><td>5E−04</td><td>0.13</td><td>154</td><td>7.5E−04</td><td>11</td><td>0.09</td></tr><tr><td>Czech</td><td>ending</td><td>1.2E−05</td><td>8</td><td>2E−02</td><td>0.09</td><td>1115</td><td>6.4E−05</td><td>8</td><td>0.04</td></tr><tr><td>Denmark</td><td>ending</td><td>1.7E−05</td><td>7</td><td>3E−03</td><td>0.14</td><td>300</td><td>1.8E−03</td><td>6</td><td>0.06</td></tr><tr><td>France</td><td>ending</td><td>1.3E−05</td><td>11</td><td>1E−04</td><td>0.17</td><td>354</td><td>5.1E−03</td><td>8</td><td>0.20</td></tr><tr><td>Germany</td><td>ending</td><td>8.5E−06</td><td>7</td><td>2E−03</td><td>0.19</td><td>300</td><td>3.0E−04</td><td>15</td><td>0.05</td></tr><tr><td>Hungary</td><td>ending</td><td>2.2E−06</td><td>9</td><td>1E−03</td><td>0.14</td><td>1376</td><td>3.4E−05</td><td>9</td><td>0.14</td></tr><tr><td>Ireland</td><td>ending</td><td>2.4E−05</td><td>11</td><td>5E−04</td><td>0.17</td><td>154</td><td>2.2E−03</td><td>9</td><td>0.07</td></tr><tr><td>Italy</td><td>ending</td><td>1.0E−05</td><td>10</td><td>8E−04</td><td>0.13</td><td>160</td><td>1.6E−03</td><td>5</td><td>0.14</td></tr><tr><td>Japan</td><td>ending</td><td>1.2E−06</td><td>9</td><td>2E−04</td><td>0.15</td><td>2000</td><td>6.2E−06</td><td>16</td><td>0.05</td></tr><tr><td>Netherlands</td><td>ending</td><td>7.5E−06</td><td>8</td><td>1E−03</td><td>0.16</td><td>214</td><td>1.5E−03</td><td>5</td><td>0.13</td></tr><tr><td>Portugal</td><td>ending</td><td>1.8E−05</td><td>5</td><td>3E−03</td><td>0.16</td><td>156</td><td>5.6E−04</td><td>8</td><td>0.05</td></tr><tr><td>Romania</td><td>ending</td><td>4.3E−06</td><td>8</td><td>2E−03</td><td>0.09</td><td>354</td><td>5.7E−05</td><td>5</td><td>0.07</td></tr><tr><td>Spain</td><td>ending</td><td>1.9E−05</td><td>8</td><td>2E−03</td><td>0.19</td><td>140</td><td>1.8E−02</td><td>7</td><td>0.12</td></tr><tr><td>Switzerland</td><td>ending</td><td>1.4E−05</td><td>7</td><td>2E−03</td><td>0.21</td><td>200</td><td>3.2E−03</td><td>12</td><td>0.05</td></tr><tr><td>Turkey</td><td>ending</td><td>5.8E−06</td><td>6</td><td>1E−03</td><td>0.18</td><td>242</td><td>9.3E−05</td><td>6</td><td>0.03</td></tr><tr><td>United Kingdom</td><td>ending</td><td>1.3E−05</td><td>10</td><td>5E−04</td><td>0.13</td><td>108</td><td>1.1E−01</td><td>5</td><td>0.15</td></tr><tr><td>United States</td><td>ending</td><td>1.8E−05</td><td>10</td><td>3E−04</td><td>0.11</td><td>43</td><td>8.8E−03</td><td>5</td><td>0.06</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Averages</td><td>1.2E−05</td><td>8</td><td>2E−03</td><td>0.156</td><td>417.6</td><td>1.0E−02</td><td>8.4</td><td>0.09</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
                <p id="p0535">Submodel 2 works in tandem with Submodel 1. As all COVID-19 data resources omit daily recoveries data (except for Johns Hopkins), we setup Submodel 2 to predict the number of deaths rather than recoveries. Therefore, <italic>c</italic> corresponds to the time-adjusted CFR rate. The average of time adjustment parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="M98" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is around 7 days globally.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s0100">
              <label>5</label>
              <title>Summary, discussion, and conclusions</title>
              <p id="p0540">Compartmental models have been widely used in the literature and have been shown to be very effective—they do not require heavy parametrization and are quite intuitive. However, they have their shortcomings, especially in this application domain. In our opinion, these flaws are surfacing because of the reporting styles and inherent noise in the reported data. The top three flaws are: (i) Health organizations report incidence data on COVID-19 while the SIR model is better suited to work with prevalence data rather than incidence data (<xref rid="bib452" ref-type="bibr">Tuncer &amp; Le, 2018</xref>). (ii) Incidences, such as the number of new infections, are not accurately reported. (iii) The transmission-rate parameter may be time-variant, depending on the rapidly changing government policies during a pandemic. In this study, we propose a model that help mitigate the effects of (i) and (ii).</p>
              <p id="p0545">While the COVID-19 pandemic is in its mid-stages in many countries, several countries seem to have gone through the first wave of the spread. We fit COVID-19 infection and fatality data using multiple well-known diffusion models. These diffusion models required calculating upper-asymptotes for the diffusion, which has proven to be rather problematic. However, in this study, we provided our estimates based on three different scenarios from the early COVID-19 literature (optimistic, moderate, and pessimistic). Our results suggest that the medium scenario fitted the data better. We noted that having to estimate upper asymptotes is impractical, and introduced our own model.</p>
              <p id="p0550">Our model consists of two sub-models working in tandem. Our first sub-model, the modified Bass diffusion model, does not require initial conditions, upper-asymptote or population adjustments, or length of the infectious period to fit cases, and deaths data. The model can fit directly to the reported incident data, while its parameters help us understand more about the spread. To this end, we relax SIR model assumptions and shortcomings by introducing other parameters such as <inline-formula><mml:math id="M99" altimg="si65.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M100" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. In practice, each country may apply different measures to control the speed of spread. Therefore, this may influence the parameters p and q mirroring transmission. By letting these parameters vary along the time axis, we can make the model fit data even tighter. This can also help to model the second wave of the spread in some countries. However, using heavier parametrization will also cause the model to overfit the data. To avoid over-fitting, we assume fixed transmission rates (p and q) for each country throughout the spread. We argue that this is one of the key contributions of the present study, which is disregarded in many other fatality estimation studies.</p>
              <p id="p0555">While multi-modal (such as a second or third waves) pandemic spreads cannot be scientifically defined, many countries have experienced beyond unimodal spread patterns. One way of dealing with such spread patterns is by modeling each wave using a separate diffusion model. Also, our study can be extended by relaxing our assumption of fixed transmission rates and letting rates to be time-variant. Altough, the model would become overly complicated, and potentially overfit, this approach may be used to handle multiple-waves of spread.</p>
              <p id="p0560">The second sub-model simply applies a lag parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="M101" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and CFR (<italic>c</italic>) to the reported data. The estimated CFR (<italic>c</italic>) is time-adjusted but does not take unreported cases into account. The actual CFR, which takes asymptomatic and unreported fatalities, can be obtained by multiplying <italic>c</italic> with <italic>k.</italic> Our results suggest the actual disease to be much less lethal than we believed.</p>
              <p id="p0565">While developing plans to better handling the limited healthcare resources at the time of epidemics highly depends on reliable and accurate estimates of the demands, providing such estimates using popular compartmental models (e.g., SIR or MSIR) is challenging at the early stages of the spread. This is particularly true given the complex nature of those models, which require large amounts of data to be trained. Our proposed methodology enables healthcare managers and decision-makers to achieve comparably good estimates with fewer data available at the early stages of the disease and plan their resources accordingly.</p>
              <p id="p0570">While our model fits COVID-19 data well, there is a need for a follow-up study for model identifiability. Model identifiability is important to avoid over-parametrization where “data does not provide enough information for uniquely estimating al parameters” (<xref rid="bib454" ref-type="bibr">Kreutz, 2018</xref>). A recent paper by <xref rid="bib452" ref-type="bibr">Tuncer and Le (2018)</xref> studied model identifiability of other outbreak models. Our study can potentially be extended by providing non-identifiability of the modified Bass model. Given that age has been recognized as a critical factor affecting infections and deaths, this study can be extended by using age-pyramids to readjust our model parameters. This can make model parameters more comparable across countries. Another extension is to modify the model to estimate the number of hospitalizations and intensive care unit requirements during the course of an epidemic. Finally, both our model and SIR model assume life-long immunity and fit to unimodal disease spread patterns.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="COI-statement">
              <title>Declaration of Competing Interest</title>
              <p id="p0575">None.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list id="bi005">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="b0005">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0005">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Anastassopoulou</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Russo</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tsakris</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Siettos</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Data-Based Analysis, Modelling and Forecasting of the novel Coronavirus (2019-nCoV) outbreak</article-title>
                  <source>MedRxiv</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0010">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0010">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bai</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yao</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wei</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tian</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jin</surname>
                      <given-names>D.-Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Presumed asymptomatic carrier transmission of COVID-19</article-title>
                  <source>JAMA</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0015">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0015">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bass</surname>
                      <given-names>F.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A new product growth for model consumer durables</article-title>
                  <source>Management Science</source>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <year>1969</year>
                  <fpage>215</fpage>
                  <lpage>227</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0020">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0020">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Basu</surname>
                      <given-names>A.K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Basu</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Batra</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Modeling the response pattern to direct marketing campaigns</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Marketing Research</source>
                  <volume>32</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>1995</year>
                  <fpage>204</fpage>
                  <lpage>212</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/002224379503200207</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0025">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="h0025">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bemmaor</surname>
                      <given-names>A.C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Modeling the diffusion of new durable goods: Word-of-mouth effect versus consumer heterogeneity</chapter-title>
                  <source>Research traditions in marketing</source>
                  <year>1992</year>
                  <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
                  <lpage>229</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0030">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0030">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Biggerstaff</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cauchemez</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reed</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gambhir</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Finelli</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Estimates of the reproduction number for seasonal, pandemic, and zoonotic influenza: A systematic review of the literature</article-title>
                  <source>BMC Infectious Diseases</source>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <fpage>480</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25186370</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0035">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0035">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bignami</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ghio</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A demographic adjustment to improve measurement of COVID-19 severity at the developing stage of the pandemic</article-title>
                  <source>MedRxiv</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2020.03.23.20040998</pub-id>
                  <comment>2020.03.23.20040998</comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0040">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0040">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Boratyńska</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Grzegorzewska</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Bankruptcy prediction in the agribusiness sector: Lessons from quantitative and qualitative approaches</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Business Research</source>
                  <volume>89</volume>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <lpage>181</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbusres.2018.01.028</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0045">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0045">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Byrd</surname>
                      <given-names>R.H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lu</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nocedal</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhu</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A limited memory algorithm for bound constrained optimization</article-title>
                  <source>SIAM Journal on Scientific Computing</source>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <year>1995</year>
                  <fpage>1190</fpage>
                  <lpage>1208</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1137/0916069</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0050">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0050">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chang</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.-T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yu</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lu</surname>
                      <given-names>H.-P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Persuasive messages, popularity cohesion, and message diffusion in social media marketing</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Business Research</source>
                  <volume>68</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <fpage>777</fpage>
                  <lpage>782</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0055">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0055">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cheng</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shan</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>2019 Novel coronavirus: Where we are and what we know</article-title>
                  <source>Infection</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>9</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31919762</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0060">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="h0060">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Darrat</surname>
                      <given-names>A.F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>On the gompertz process and new product sales: some further results from cointegration analysis</chapter-title>
                  <series>Quarterly Journal of Business and Economics</series>
                  <volume>Vol. 39</volume>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <publisher-name>Creighton University</publisher-name>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <lpage>56</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/40473283</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0065">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="h0065">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Day</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Covid-19: four fifths of cases are asymptomatic, China figures indicate</chapter-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <publisher-name>British Medical Journal Publishing Group</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0070">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0070">de Tarde, G. (1895). La logique sociale p. G [abr.] Tarde. G. Baillière &amp; C.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0075">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0075">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Delen</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eryarsoy</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davazdahemami</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>No Place Like Home: A Cross-National Assessment of the Efficacy of Social Distancing during the COVID-19 Pandemic (Preprint)</article-title>
                  <source>JMIR Public Health and Surveillance</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/19862</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0080">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0080">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dong</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Swain</surname>
                      <given-names>S.D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Berger</surname>
                      <given-names>P.D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The role of channel quality in customer equity management</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Business Research</source>
                  <volume>60</volume>
                  <issue>12</issue>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <fpage>1243</fpage>
                  <lpage>1252</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbusres.2007.05.005</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0085">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0085">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Duan</surname>
                      <given-names>Q.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sorooshian</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gupta</surname>
                      <given-names>V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effective and efficient global optimization for conceptual rainfall-runoff models</article-title>
                  <source>Water Resources Research</source>
                  <volume>28</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <year>1992</year>
                  <fpage>1015</fpage>
                  <lpage>1031</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1029/91WR02985</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0090">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0090">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eryarsoy</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Delen</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davazdahemami</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Adjusting COVID-19 Reports for Countries’ Age Disparities: A Comparative Framework for Reporting Performances</article-title>
                  <source>MedRxiv</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2020.08.31.20185223</pub-id>
                  <comment>2020.08.31.20185223</comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0095">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0095">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fan</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.-P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Che</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.-J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.-Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Product sales forecasting using online reviews and historical sales data: A method combining the Bass model and sentiment analysis</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Business Research</source>
                  <volume>74</volume>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <fpage>90</fpage>
                  <lpage>100</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbusres.2017.01.010</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0100">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0100">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fanelli</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Piazza</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Analysis and forecast of COVID-19 spreading in China, Italy and France</article-title>
                  <source>Chaos, Solitons &amp; Fractals</source>
                  <volume>134</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>109761</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0105">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0105">Ferguson, N., Laydon, D., Nedjati Gilani, G., Imai, N., Ainslie, K., Baguelin, M., … &amp; Cuomo-Dannenburg, G. (2020). Report 9: Impact of non-pharmaceutical interventions (NPIs) to reduce COVID19 mortality and healthcare demand.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0110">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0110">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Flaxman</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mishra</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gandy</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Estimating the number of infections and the impact of non-pharmaceutical interventions on COVID-19 in 11 European countries</article-title>
                  <source>Imperial College Preprint</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0115">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="h0115">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Givan</surname>
                      <given-names>R.K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Roberts</surname>
                      <given-names>K.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Soule</surname>
                      <given-names>S.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>The diffusion of social movements: Actors, mechanisms, and political effects</chapter-title>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0120">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0120">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gompertz</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>On the nature of the function expressive of the law of human mortality, and on a new mode of determining the value of life contingencies</article-title>
                  <source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London</source>
                  <volume>115</volume>
                  <year>1825</year>
                  <fpage>513</fpage>
                  <lpage>583</lpage>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/107756" id="ir045">http://www.jstor.org/stable/107756</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0125">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0125">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Guan</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ni</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hu</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liang</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ou</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>He</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <x>…</x>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhong</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Clinical characteristics of coronavirus disease 2019 in China</article-title>
                  <source>New England Journal of Medicine</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/nejmoa2002032</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0130">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0130">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hongmei</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The medium and long term forecast of China’s vehicle stock per 1000 person based on the gompertz model</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Industrial Technological Economics</source>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <issue>003</issue>
                  <year>2012</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0135">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0135">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hooke</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jeeves</surname>
                      <given-names>T.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>“Direct Search” Solution of Numerical and Statistical Problems</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of the ACM (JACM)</source>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>1961</year>
                  <fpage>212</fpage>
                  <lpage>229</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1145/321062.321069</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0140">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0140">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hsiao</surname>
                      <given-names>J.-P.-H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jaw</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huan</surname>
                      <given-names>T.-C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Information diffusion and new product consumption: A bass model application to tourism facility management</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Business Research</source>
                  <volume>62</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <fpage>690</fpage>
                  <lpage>697</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbusres.2008.08.002</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0145">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0145">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hwang</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Park</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jung</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kim</surname>
                      <given-names>S.-H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kim</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Basic and effective reproduction numbers of COVID-19 cases in South Korea excluding Sincheonji cases</article-title>
                  <source>MedRxiv</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2020.03.19.20039347</pub-id>
                  <comment>2020.03.19.20039347</comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0150">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="h0150">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jaakkola</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Comparison and analysis of diffusion models</chapter-title>
                  <source>Diffusion and adoption of information technology</source>
                  <year>1996</year>
                  <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                  <lpage>82</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0155">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0155">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jeyaraj</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sabherwal</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The bass model of diffusion: Recommendations for use in information systems research and practice</article-title>
                  <source>JITTA: Journal of Information Technology Theory and Application</source>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <fpage>5</fpage>
                  <lpage>30</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0160">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0160">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jibao</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fangfang</surname>
                      <given-names>Q.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jianlin</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Forecasting on China’s civil automobile-owned based on gompertz model</article-title>
                  <source>Technology Economics</source>
                  <volume>29</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <fpage>57</fpage>
                  <lpage>62</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0165">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0165">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Katriel</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stone</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Attack rates of seasonal epidemics</article-title>
                  <source>Mathematical Biosciences</source>
                  <volume>235</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <fpage>56</fpage>
                  <lpage>65</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22094376</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib454">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="opttlpTTgwAgj">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kreutz</surname>
                      <given-names>Clemens</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An easy and efficient approach for testing identifiability</article-title>
                  <source>Bioinformatics</source>
                  <volume>34</volume>
                  <issue>11</issue>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <fpage>1913</fpage>
                  <lpage>1921</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bty035</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29365095</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0170">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0170">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kulkarni</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kannan</surname>
                      <given-names>P.K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Moe</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Using online search data to forecast new product sales</article-title>
                  <source>Decision Support Systems</source>
                  <volume>52</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <fpage>604</fpage>
                  <lpage>611</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0175">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0175">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>Q.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Guan</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhou</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tong</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ren</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leung</surname>
                      <given-names>K.S.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lau</surname>
                      <given-names>E.H.Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wong</surname>
                      <given-names>J.Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Early transmission dynamics in Wuhan, China, of novel coronavirus–infected pneumonia</article-title>
                  <source>New England Journal of Medicine</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0180">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0180">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pei</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Song</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shaman</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Substantial undocumented infection facilitates the rapid dissemination of novel coronavirus (SARS-CoV2)</article-title>
                  <source>Science</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>eabb3221</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abb3221</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0185">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0185">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.-M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shiu</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.-L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A diffusion mechanism for social advertising over microblogs</article-title>
                  <source>Decision Support Systems</source>
                  <volume>54</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <lpage>22</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0190">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0190">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Linton</surname>
                      <given-names>N.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kobayashi</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hayashi</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Akhmetzhanov</surname>
                      <given-names>A.R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jung</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yuan</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kinoshita</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nishiura</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Incubation period and other epidemiological characteristics of 2019 novel coronavirus infections with right truncation: A statistical analysis of publicly available case data</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Clinical Medicine</source>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>538</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/jcm9020538</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0195">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0195">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Little</surname>
                      <given-names>J.D.C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Models and managers: The concept of a decision calculus</article-title>
                  <source>Management Science</source>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <issue>8</issue>
                  <year>1970</year>
                  <fpage>B-466</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0200">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0200">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Livingston</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bucher</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID-19) in Italy</article-title>
                  <source>JAMA</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.4344</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0205">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0205">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lou</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhao</surname>
                      <given-names>X.-Q.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A reaction–diffusion malaria model with incubation period in the vector population</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Mathematical Biology</source>
                  <volume>62</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <fpage>543</fpage>
                  <lpage>568</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20431888</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0210">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0210">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lourenco</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Paton</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ghafari</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kraemer</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thompson</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Simmonds</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <x>…</x>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gupta</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Fundamental principles of epidemic spread highlight the immediate need for large-scale serological surveys to assess the stage of the SARS-CoV-2 epidemic</article-title>
                  <source>MedRxiv</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2020.03.24.20042291</pub-id>
                  <comment>2020.03.24.20042291</comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0215">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0215">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mahajan</surname>
                      <given-names>V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Muller</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bass</surname>
                      <given-names>F.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>New product diffusion models in marketing: A review and directions for research</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Marketing</source>
                  <volume>54</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>1990</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>26</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/002224299005400101</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0220">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0220">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mahajan</surname>
                      <given-names>V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schoeman</surname>
                      <given-names>M.E.F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Generalized model for the time pattern of the diffusion process</article-title>
                  <source>IEEE Transactions on Engineering Management</source>
                  <volume>1</volume>
                  <year>1977</year>
                  <fpage>12</fpage>
                  <lpage>18</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0225">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0225">Mahajan, V., &amp; Wind, Y. (1985). Innovation diffusion models of new product acceptance: A reexamination.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0230">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0230">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mann</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kauffman</surname>
                      <given-names>R.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Han</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nault</surname>
                      <given-names>B.R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Are there contagion effects in information technology and business process outsourcing?</article-title>
                  <source>Decision Support Systems</source>
                  <volume>51</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <fpage>864</fpage>
                  <lpage>874</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib453">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="ce.other-ref_l4t_nhj_xnb">Ministerio de Sanidad. (2020). (Accessed 15 June 2020).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0235">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0235">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mizumoto</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chowell</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Transmission potential of the novel coronavirus (COVID-19) onboard the diamond Princess Cruises Ship, 2020</article-title>
                  <source>Infectious Disease Modelling</source>
                  <volume>5</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>264</fpage>
                  <lpage>270</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.idm.2020.02.003</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32190785</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0240">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0240">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mizumoto</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kagaya</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zarebski</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chowell</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Estimating the asymptomatic proportion of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) cases on board the Diamond Princess cruise ship, Yokohama, Japan, 2020</article-title>
                  <source>Eurosurveillance</source>
                  <volume>25</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0245">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0245">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Naseri</surname>
                      <given-names>M.B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Elliott</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The diffusion of online shopping in Australia: Comparing the Bass, Logistic and Gompertz growth models</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Marketing Analytics</source>
                  <volume>1</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <lpage>60</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0250">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0250">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nelder</surname>
                      <given-names>J.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mead</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A simplex method for function minimization</article-title>
                  <source>The Computer Journal</source>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <year>1965</year>
                  <fpage>308</fpage>
                  <lpage>313</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/comjnl/7.4.308</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0255">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0255">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nguimkeu</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A simple selection test between the Gompertz and Logistic growth models</article-title>
                  <source>Technological Forecasting and Social Change</source>
                  <volume>88</volume>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <fpage>98</fpage>
                  <lpage>105</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.techfore.2014.06.017</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0260">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0260">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Novel</surname>
                      <given-names>C.P.E.R.E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The epidemiological characteristics of an outbreak of 2019 novel coronavirus diseases (COVID-19) in China</article-title>
                  <source>Zhonghua Liu Xing Bing Xue Za Zhi= Zhonghua Liuxingbingxue Zazhi</source>
                  <volume>41</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>145</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32064853</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0265">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0265">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ntwoku</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Negash</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Meso</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>ICT adoption in Cameroon SME: Application of Bass diffusion model</article-title>
                  <source>Information Technology for Development</source>
                  <volume>23</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <fpage>296</fpage>
                  <lpage>317</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02681102.2017.1289884</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib451">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="opt0Ipp8AOcfP">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Olson</surname>
                      <given-names>Jerome</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Choi</surname>
                      <given-names>Seungmook</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A product diffusion model incorporating repeat purchases</article-title>
                  <source>Technological Forecasting and Social Change</source>
                  <volume>27</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <year>1985</year>
                  <fpage>385</fpage>
                  <lpage>397</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0040-1625(85)90019-8</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0270">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="h0270">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Onder</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rezza</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brusaferro</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Case-fatality rate and characteristics of patients dying in relation to COVID-19 in Italy</chapter-title>
                  <source>JAMA - Journal of the American Medical Association</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <publisher-name>American Medical Association</publisher-name>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.4683</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0275">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0275">Organization, W. H., &amp; Organization, W. H. (2020). Report of the who-china joint mission on coronavirus disease 2019 (covid-19). Available On-Line: Https://Www.Who.Int/Docs/Default-Source/Coronaviruse/Who-China-Joint-Mission-on-Covid-19-Final-Report.Pdf.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0280">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0280">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Peres</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Muller</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mahajan</surname>
                      <given-names>V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Innovation diffusion and new product growth models: A critical review and research directions</article-title>
                  <source>International Journal of Research in Marketing</source>
                  <volume>27</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <fpage>91</fpage>
                  <lpage>106</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0285">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0285">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Richards</surname>
                      <given-names>F.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A flexible growth function for empirical use</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Experimental Botany</source>
                  <volume>10</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>1959</year>
                  <fpage>290</fpage>
                  <lpage>301</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0290">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0290">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rocklöv</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sjödin</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wilder-Smith</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>COVID-19 outbreak on the Diamond Princess cruise ship: Estimating the epidemic potential and effectiveness of public health countermeasures</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Travel Medicine</source>
                  <volume>27</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>7</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jtm/taaa030</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0295">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0295">Roques, L., Klein, E., Papaix, J., &amp; Soubeyrand, S. (2020). Modèle SIR mécanistico-statistique pour l’estimation du nombre d’infectés et du taux de mortalité par COVID-19. INRAE.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0300">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0300">Rowan, T. H. (1991). Functional stability analysis of numerical algorithms.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0305">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0305">Russell, T. W., Hellewell, J., Abbott, S., Jarvis, C. I., van Zandvoort, K., Ratnayake, R., … &amp; Kucharski, A. J. (2020). Using a delay-adjusted case fatality ratio to estimate under-reporting.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0310">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0310">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schramm</surname>
                      <given-names>M.E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Trainor</surname>
                      <given-names>K.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shanker</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hu</surname>
                      <given-names>M.Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An agent-based diffusion model with consumer and brand agents</article-title>
                  <source>Decision Support Systems</source>
                  <volume>50</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <fpage>234</fpage>
                  <lpage>242</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0315">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0315">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shim</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tariq</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Choi</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lee</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chowell</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Transmission potential and severity of COVID-19 in South Korea</article-title>
                  <source>International Journal of Infectious Diseases</source>
                  <volume>93</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>339</fpage>
                  <lpage>344</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2020.03.031</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32198088</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0320">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0320">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sood</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>James</surname>
                      <given-names>G.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tellis</surname>
                      <given-names>G.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhu</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Predicting the path of technological innovation: SAW vs. Moore, Bass, Gompertz, and Kryder</article-title>
                  <source>Marketing Science</source>
                  <volume>31</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <fpage>964</fpage>
                  <lpage>979</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1287/mksc.1120.0739</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0325">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0325">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Streukens</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>van Hoesel</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>de Ruyter</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Return on marketing investments in B2B customer relationships: A decision-making and optimization approach</article-title>
                  <source>Industrial Marketing Management</source>
                  <volume>40</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <lpage>161</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0330">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0330">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sugishita</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kurita</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sugawara</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ohkusa</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Insignificant effect of counter measure for coronavirus infectious disease-19 in Japan</article-title>
                  <source>MedRxiv</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0335">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0335">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tang</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>Q.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bragazzi</surname>
                      <given-names>N.L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tang</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xiao</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Estimation of the transmission risk of the 2019-nCoV and its implication for public health interventions</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Clinical Medicine</source>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>462</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0340">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="h0340">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tarde</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Les lois de l’imitation [The laws of imitation]</chapter-title>
                  <year>1890</year>
                  <publisher-name>Félix Alcan</publisher-name>
                  <publisher-loc>Paris</publisher-loc>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0345">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0345">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Trilla</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>One world, one health: The novel coronavirus COVID-19 epidemic</article-title>
                  <source>Medicina Clínica (English Edition)</source>
                  <volume>154</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <lpage>177</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.medcle.2020.02.001</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32289080</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib452">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="optIRRvUeHfQL">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tuncer</surname>
                      <given-names>Necibe</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Le</surname>
                      <given-names>Trang</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Structural and practical identifiability analysis of outbreak models</article-title>
                  <source>Mathematical Biosciences</source>
                  <volume>299</volume>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>18</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mbs.2018.02.004</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29477671</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0350">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0350">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Udo</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bagchi</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kirs</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Analysis of the growth of security breaches: A multi-growth model approach</article-title>
                  <source>Issues in Information Systems</source>
                  <volume>19</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <year>2018</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0355">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0355">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Van Den Bulte</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>New product diffusion acceleration: Measurement and analysis</article-title>
                  <source>Marketing Science</source>
                  <volume>19</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <year>2000</year>
                  <fpage>366</fpage>
                  <lpage>380</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1287/mksc.19.4.366.11795</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0360">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0360">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Van Den Bulte</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Joshi</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>New product diffusion with influential and imitators</article-title>
                  <source>Marketing Science</source>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <fpage>400</fpage>
                  <lpage>421</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1287/mksc.1060.0224</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0365">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0365">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Van den Bulte</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stremersch</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Social contagion and income heterogeneity in new product diffusion: A meta-analytic test</article-title>
                  <source>Marketing Science</source>
                  <volume>23</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <fpage>530</fpage>
                  <lpage>544</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0370">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0370">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Von Bertalanffy</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Quantitative laws in metabolism and growth</article-title>
                  <source>The Quarterly Review of Biology</source>
                  <volume>32</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <year>1957</year>
                  <fpage>217</fpage>
                  <lpage>231</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13485376</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0375">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0375">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hu</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hu</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhu</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xiang</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cheng</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xiong</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhao</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Peng</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Clinical Characteristics of 138 Hospitalized Patients with 2019 Novel Coronavirus-Infected Pneumonia in Wuhan, China</article-title>
                  <source>JAMA - Journal of the American Medical Association</source>
                  <volume>323</volume>
                  <issue>11</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1061</fpage>
                  <lpage>1069</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.1585</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32031570</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0380">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0380">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>Q.-H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cai</surname>
                      <given-names>S.-M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tang</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Braunstein</surname>
                      <given-names>L.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stanley</surname>
                      <given-names>H.E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Suppressing disease spreading by using information diffusion on multiplex networks</article-title>
                  <source>Scientific Reports</source>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <fpage>29259</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27380881</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0385">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0385">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Weibull</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Wide applicability</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Applied Mechanics</source>
                  <volume>103</volume>
                  <issue>730</issue>
                  <year>1951</year>
                  <fpage>293</fpage>
                  <lpage>297</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0390">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="h0390">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wierenga</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>van der Lans</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Marketing decision models: Progress and perspectives</chapter-title>
                  <series>International Series in Operations Research and Management Science</series>
                  <volume>vol. 254</volume>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
                  <publisher-loc>New York LLC</publisher-loc>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>11</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-319-56941-3_1</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0395">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0395">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wilson</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kvalsvig</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Barnard</surname>
                      <given-names>L.T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baker</surname>
                      <given-names>M.G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Case-Fatality Risk Estimates for COVID-19 Calculated by Using a Lag Time for Fatality</article-title>
                  <source>Emerging Infectious Diseases</source>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid2606.200320</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0400">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0400">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wright</surname>
                      <given-names>M.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stern</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Forecasting new product trial with analogous series</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Business Research</source>
                  <volume>68</volume>
                  <issue>8</issue>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <fpage>1732</fpage>
                  <lpage>1738</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0405">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="h0405">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>ADBUDG model optimization and practical analysis</chapter-title>
                  <source>Proceedings of the 2012 International Conference on Industrial Control and Electronics Engineering, ICICEE 2012</source>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/ICICEE.2012.118</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0410">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0410">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>J.T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leung</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bushman</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kishore</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Niehus</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>de Salazar</surname>
                      <given-names>P.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <x>…</x>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leung</surname>
                      <given-names>G.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Estimating clinical severity of COVID-19 from the transmission dynamics in Wuhan, China</article-title>
                  <source>Nature Medicine</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>5</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0415">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0415">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>J.T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leung</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leung</surname>
                      <given-names>G.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Nowcasting and forecasting the potential domestic and international spread of the 2019-nCoV outbreak originating in Wuhan, China: A modelling study</article-title>
                  <source>The Lancet</source>
                  <volume>395</volume>
                  <issue>10225</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>689</fpage>
                  <lpage>697</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0420">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0420">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McGoogan</surname>
                      <given-names>J.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Characteristics of and important lessons from the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) outbreak in China: Summary of a report of 72 314 cases from the Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention</article-title>
                  <source>JAMA</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0425">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0425">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>H.-L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Two-warehouse partial backlogging inventory models with three-parameter Weibull distribution deterioration under inflation</article-title>
                  <source>International Journal of Production Economics</source>
                  <volume>138</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <fpage>107</fpage>
                  <lpage>116</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0430">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="h0430">You, C., Deng, Y., Hu, W., Sun, J., Lin, Q., Zhou, … Zhou, X.-H. (2020). Estimation of the time-varying reproduction number of COVID-19 outbreak in China. Available at SSRN 3539694.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0435">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0435">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yuhn</surname>
                      <given-names>K.-H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kim</surname>
                      <given-names>S.B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nam</surname>
                      <given-names>J.H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Bubbles and the Weibull distribution: Was there an explosive bubble in US stock prices before the global economic crisis?</article-title>
                  <source>Applied Economics</source>
                  <volume>47</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <fpage>255</fpage>
                  <lpage>271</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0440">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0440">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zeb</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Khan</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zaman</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Momani</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ertürk</surname>
                      <given-names>V.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparison of numerical methods of the SEIR epidemic model of fractional order</article-title>
                  <source>Zeitschrift Für Naturforschung A</source>
                  <volume>69</volume>
                  <issue>1–2</issue>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <fpage>81</fpage>
                  <lpage>89</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0445">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0445">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Diao</surname>
                      <given-names>M.Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yu</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pei</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lin</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Estimation of the reproductive number of novel coronavirus (COVID-19) and the probable outbreak size on the Diamond Princess cruise ship: A data-driven analysis</article-title>
                  <source>International Journal of Infectious Diseases</source>
                  <volume>93</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>201</fpage>
                  <lpage>204</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2020.02.033</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32097725</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b0450">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="h0450">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhou</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yu</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Du</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fan</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xiang</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Song</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gu</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Clinical course and risk factors for mortality of adult inpatients with COVID-19 in Wuhan, China: A retrospective cohort study</article-title>
                  <source>The Lancet</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
            <bio>
              <graphic xlink:href="fx1_lrg"/>
              <p><bold>Dr. Enes Eryarsoy</bold> is an Associate Professor of Information Systems in Sabanci Business School at Sabanci University, Istanbul, Turkey. He received his Ph.D. degree from Warrington College of Business at the University of Florida in 2005, He worked as a teaching and research assistant at the University of Florida, as an assistant professor at Sabanci University, and as associate professor at Istanbul Sehir University. He also spent 6 months as a visiting researcher at MIT. He is currently the director of the professional business analytics master's program at Sabanci University. His research lies on different facets of the field defined by machine learning, statistics and operations research.</p>
            </bio>
            <bio>
              <graphic xlink:href="fx2_lrg"/>
              <p><bold>Dr. Dursun Delen</bold> is the holder of Spears and Patterson Endowed Chairs in Business Analytics, Director of Research for the Center for Health Systems Innovation, and Regents Professor of Management Science and Information Systems in the Spears School of Business at Oklahoma State University. He authored/co-authored 100+ journal and 40+ peer-reviewed conference proceeding articles. His research has appeared in major journals including Decision Sciences, Journal of Production Operations Management, Decision Support Systems, Communications of the ACM, Computers and Operations Research, Computers in Industry, Artificial Intelligence in Medicine, International Journal of Medical Informatics, Expert Systems, among others. He has recently published ten books/textbooks in the broad area of Business Intelligence and Business Analytics. He is often invited to national and international conferences and symposiums for keynote addresses, and companies and government agencies for consultancy and professional education engagements on analytics and data science related topics. Dr. Delen served as the general co-chair for the 4th International Conference on Network Computing and Advanced Information Management (September 2-4, 2008 in Soul, South Korea), and regularly chairs tracks and mini-tracks at various information systems and analytics conferences. He is currently serving as the editor-in-chief, senior editor, associate editor, and editorial board member of more than a dozen academic journals.</p>
            </bio>
            <bio>
              <graphic xlink:href="fx3_lrg"/>
              <p><bold>Dr. Behrooz Davazdahemami</bold> is an Assistant Professor of Information Technology and Supply Chain Management (IT&amp;SCM) at University of Wisconsin-Whitewater. He received his M.S. in Industrial Engineering from University of Tehran and his Ph.D. in Management Science and Information Systems from Oklahoma State University. His research interests include health analytics, business analytics, IT privacy, and technology addiction. He is a member of the Association for Information Systems, The Institute for Operations Research and the Management Sciences, and the Decision Sciences Institute. Behrooz has published in journals such as Journal of the American Medical Informatics Association (JAMIA), International Journal of Medical Informatics, Information &amp; Management, Expert Systems with Applications, Communications of the Association for Information Systems, Health Informatics Journal, as well as IS proceedings such as the Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences (HICSS) and the International Conference on Information Systems (ICIS).</p>
            </bio>
            <bio>
              <graphic xlink:href="fx4_lrg"/>
              <p><bold>Dr. Kazim Topuz</bold> is an Assistant Professor of Operations Management and Business Analytics in the School of Finance, Operations Management and International Business in the Collins College of Business at the Tulsa University (TU). Prior to joining Collins College of Business, he taught at the Division of Management Information Systems in the Price College of Business at the University of Oklahoma (OU) as a lecturer, and he worked for the Center for Health Systems Innovation at Oklahoma State University (OSU) as a Research Fellow. In addition to his doctorate in philosophy (Ph.D.) from the Wichita State University (WSU), Dr. Topuz holds masters‘ degrees in Information Systems Engineering from Lehigh University, and Industrial and Systems Engineering from Rutgers University. He is a member of Industrial Engineering Honor Society, Alpha Phi Mu, INFORMS, Decision Sciences Institute (DSI), and American Medical Informatics Association (AMIA). He has served as a session chair and organized workshops at the national conferences.</p>
            </bio>
            <fn-group>
              <fn id="fn1">
                <label>1</label>
                <p id="np005"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.reuters.com/article/us-health-coronavirus-china-testkits/china-clamps-down-on-coronavirus-test-kit-exports-after-accuracy-questioned-idUSKBN21J51S" id="ir005">https://www.reuters.com/article/us-health-coronavirus-china-testkits/china-clamps-down-on-coronavirus-test-kit-exports-after-accuracy-questioned-idUSKBN21J51S</ext-link>.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="fn2">
                <label>2</label>
                <p id="np010"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ecdc.europa.eu/en" id="ir010">https://www.ecdc.europa.eu/en</ext-link>.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="fn4">
                <label>4</label>
                <p id="np020"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.mscbs.gob.es/profesionales/saludPublica/ccayes/alertasActual/nCov-China/documentos/Actualizacion_52_COVID-19.pdf" id="ir020">https://www.mscbs.gob.es/profesionales/saludPublica/ccayes/alertasActual/nCov-China/documentos/Actualizacion_52_COVID-19.pdf</ext-link>.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="fn5">
                <label>5</label>
                <p id="np025"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/volumes/69/wr/mm6912e2.htm" id="ir025">https://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/volumes/69/wr/mm6912e2.htm</ext-link>.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="fn6">
                <label>6</label>
                <p id="np030">Fatal flaws - COVID-19’s death toll appears higher than official figures suggest|Graphic detail|The Economist. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.economist.com/graphic-detail/2020/04/03/COVID-19s-death-toll-appears-higher-than-official-figures-suggest" id="ir030">https://www.economist.com/graphic-detail/2020/04/03/COVID-19s-death-toll-appears-higher-than-official-figures-suggest</ext-link>.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="fn7">
                <label>7</label>
                <p id="np035"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/03/13/us/coronavirus-deaths-estimate.html" id="ir035">https://www.nytimes.com/2020/03/13/us/coronavirus-deaths-estimate.html</ext-link>.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="fn8">
                <label>8</label>
                <p id="np040"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nbcnews.com/health/health-news/cdc-says-covid-19-cases-u-s-may-be-10-n1232134" id="ir040">https://www.nbcnews.com/health/health-news/cdc-says-covid-19-cases-u-s-may-be-10-n1232134</ext-link>.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <fn-group>
              <fn id="fn3">
                <label>3</label>
                <p id="np015">This is 7 days. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.channelnewsasia.com/news/singapore/people-with-COVID-19-are-most-infectious-in-first-7-days-after-12567526" id="ir015">https://www.channelnewsasia.com/news/singapore/people-with-COVID-19-are-most-infectious-in-first-7-days-after-12567526</ext-link>.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
