<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-03-11T00:59:57Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7598795" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7598795</identifier>
        <datestamp>2020-11-02</datestamp>
        <setSpec>pheelsevier</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Chaos Solitons Fractals</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Chaos Solitons Fractals</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Chaos, Solitons, and Fractals</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0960-0779</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">0960-0779</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Elsevier Ltd.</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC7598795</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7598795</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">7598795</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33162689</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pii">S0960-0779(20)30782-7</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chaos.2020.110388</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">110388</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>SIRSi compartmental model for COVID-19 pandemic with immunity loss</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0001">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Batistela</surname>
                    <given-names>Cristiane M.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0002">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Correa</surname>
                    <given-names>Diego P.F.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0003">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Bueno</surname>
                    <given-names>Átila M</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0004">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Piqueira</surname>
                    <given-names>José Roberto C.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="cor0001" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="aff0001"><label>a</label>Polytechnic School of University of São Paulo - EPUSP, São Paulo, SP, Brazil</aff>
                <aff id="aff0002"><label>b</label>Federal University of ABC - UFABC, São Bernardo do Campo, SP, Brazil</aff>
                <aff id="aff0003"><label>c</label>São Paulo State University - UNESP, Sorocaba, SP, Brazil</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor0001"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author.</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>29</day>
                <month>10</month>
                <year>2020</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.-->
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <month>1</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>29</day>
                <month>10</month>
                <year>2020</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>142</volume>
              <fpage>110388</fpage>
              <lpage>110388</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>3</day>
                  <month>7</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>18</day>
                  <month>9</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>20</day>
                  <month>10</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2020 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2020</copyright-year>
                <copyright-holder/>
                <license>
                  <license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="absh001">
                <title>Highlights</title>
                <p>
                  <list list-type="simple" id="lst0001">
                    <list-item id="lstitem0001">
                      <label>•</label>
                      <p id="p0001">A modification of SIR model, SIRSi model, was fitted to data of the Covid-19 outbreak.</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item id="lstitem0002">
                      <label>•</label>
                      <p id="p0002">The model is able to estimate the duration and peaks of the outbreak.</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item id="lstitem0003">
                      <label>•</label>
                      <p id="p0003">Additionally, the model allows to infer unreported and asymptomatic cases.</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item id="lstitem0004">
                      <label>•</label>
                      <p id="p0004">The model contains a feedback loop considering different immunity responses.</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                </p>
              </abstract>
              <abstract id="abs0001">
                <p>The coronavirus disease 2019 (Covid-19) outbreak led the world to an unprecedented health and economic crisis. In an attempt to respond to this emergency, researchers worldwide are intensively studying the dynamics of the Covid-19 pandemic. In this study, a Susceptible - Infected - Removed - Sick (SIRSi) compartmental model is proposed, which is a modification of the classical Susceptible - Infected - Removed (SIR) model. The proposed model considers the possibility of unreported or asymptomatic cases, and differences in the immunity within a population, i.e., the possibility that the acquired immunity may be temporary, which occurs when adopting one of the parameters (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>) other than zero. Local asymptotic stability and endemic equilibrium conditions are proved for the proposed model. The model is adjusted to the data from three major cities of the state of São Paulo in Brazil, namely, São Paulo, Santos, and Campinas, providing estimations of duration and peaks related to the disease propagation. This study reveals that temporary immunity favors a second wave of infection and it depends on the time interval for a recovered person to be susceptible again. It also indicates the possibility that a greater number of patients would get infected with decreased time for reinfection.</p>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group id="keys0001">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>Covid-19</kwd>
                <kwd>Compartmental models</kwd>
                <kwd>Equilibrium analysis</kwd>
                <kwd>Parameter fitting</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="sec0001">
              <label>1</label>
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p id="p0005">The Wuhan Municipal Health Commission reported a cluster of 27 pneumonia cases on December 31, 2019, in Wuhan city, Hubei Province in China. On January 1, 2020 the World Health Organization (WHO) set up an Incident Management Support Team for dealing with the emergency. On January 5, 2020 WHO published the first news of a new viral disease outbreak. On January 7, 2020 the causative agent was identified and named as severe acute respiratory syndrome corona virus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) and the disease was named as Covid-19. On January 13, 2020 the first case, outside China, was reported in Thailand. On January 22, 2020 WHO stated that there was evidence of human-to-human transmission, and approximately 7 weeks later, on March 13, 2020, WHO declared Covid-19 a pandemic <xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0002" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>.</p>
              <p id="p0006">In Brazil, the first confirmed Covid-19 case was reported on February 26, 2020. By June 25, 2020 there were 1,188,631 confirmed cases with 53,830 deaths in Brazil <xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref> and 9,292,202 confirmed cases and 479,133 deaths globally according to <xref rid="bib0004" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>
<xref rid="fn0001" ref-type="fn">1</xref>
.</p>
              <p id="p0007">Most patients were asymptomatic carriers and resolved spontaneously; however, some, particularly those with comorbidities, developed fatal complications <xref rid="bib0002" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, resulting in the rapid spread of the disease. This global emergency brings with it important and yet unanswered questions related to the dynamic behavior of the contagion and its mitigation and control strategies. As a result, measures carried out to contain the contagion such as social distancing, quarantine, and complete lock-down of areas have been studied <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>.</p>
              <p id="p0008">In Mexico, on March 18, 2020, the Mexican Health Secretariat reported that the pandemic was going to last 90 days, with 250,656 expected cases. On the next day, the Health Secretariat informed that approximately 9.8% (24,594) of the patients would need hospitalization and 4.2% (10,528) of the total cases would be critical and need intensive care. The number of available Health Care units at that time was 4291 with 2053 ventilators <xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. The situation in Mexico led to the adoption of non-pharmaceutical interventions, such as washing hands, social distancing, cough/sneeze etiquette, etc.</p>
              <p id="p0009">In Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, social distancing measures were introduced on March 17, 2020 <xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, and the government of the state of São Paulo, Brazil, decreed quarantine on March 23, 2020. By June 25, 2020, the State of São Paulo had 248,587 confirmed cases with 13,759 deaths.</p>
              <p id="p0010">An important question related to patients’ immunity after recovery was raised. Differences in immunity after recovery have been reported in humans <xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, and in experiments with rhesus macaques <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. The experiment in <xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref> collected plasma from 175 recovered Covid-19 patients, and SARS-CoV-2-specific neutralizing antibodies (NAbs) were detected from day 10 to 15, after the onset of the disease and remained thereafter. Nonetheless, the NAbs levels were variable in the cohort. Among them, 52 (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M2" altimg="si16.svg"><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>30%) patients developed low levels of these antibodies, in 10 (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M3" altimg="si16.svg"><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>6%) the NAbs levels were undetectable, and 25 (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M4" altimg="si16.svg"><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>14%) developed high levels.</p>
              <p id="p0011">In <xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, data suggests an imbalance between the control of virus replication and activation of the adaptive immune responses. In some patients, lung cells remain vulnerable to infection due to immune system deficiencies. The virus continues replicating while the immune system attacks infected cells, also killing healthy cells in the vicinity, thereby severely inflaming the lung tissues. This seems to be the mechanism, which makes some patients severely ill weeks after their initial infection. Additionally, SARS-CoV-2 probably induces immunity like other coronaviruses; however, this mechanism is not fully understood <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>.</p>
              <p id="p0012">The economic crisis due to the pandemic is another important issue. According to <xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref> the mortality rate of Covid-19 is not necessarily correlated with the global economic crisis, since governments, companies, consumers, and media have reacted to the economic shock. However, a global recession seems to be inevitable, and its duration and intensity will depend on the success of the measures taken to prevent the spread of the disease.</p>
              <p id="p0013">Taking the whole scenario into account, researchers worldwide are intensively studying and developing mathematical models of the Covid-19 outbreak. The knowledge on the dynamics of this pandemic is important to estimate the duration and peaks of the outbreak.</p>
              <p id="p0014">Macro-modeling of propagation of infectious diseases has been a field of research since the Kermack and McKendrick proposition <xref rid="bib0017" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0019" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>. It is a dynamic model that classifies individuals in a population as Susceptible - Infected - Removed (SIR) <xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. Since then, several modifications of the SIR model <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref> such as, the Susceptible - Exposed - Infected - Removed (SEIR) model, <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0026" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref> have been proposed for epidemic modeling.</p>
              <p id="p0015">In addition, studies considering time delay <xref rid="bib0027" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref> and fractional-order <xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0029" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref> dynamical systems have been applied to disease propagation and could be useful to model the Covid-19 outbreak, and other biological systems <xref rid="bib0031" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0032" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>.</p>
              <p id="p0016">In <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref> a SIRD (SIR with delay) model had been adjusted to Covid-19 spread in China, Italy, and France. The results have shown that the recovery rates were similar for the three countries. In <xref rid="bib0034" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, a mixed analytical-statistical inverse problem is used to predict the Covid-19 progression in Brazil. A SIRU model, Susceptible - Infected - Removed - Unreported, was used to estimate the direct problem and a Bayesian parameter was used for the inverse problem.</p>
              <p id="p0017">Compartmental models considering immigration and home isolation, or quarantine, were proposed by <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. All the situations presented an infection-endemic equilibrium with results showing that home isolation or lock down mitigates the infection probability.</p>
              <p id="p0018">In this work the proposed model is a modification of the original compartmental SIR model of Kermack and McKendrick <xref rid="bib0017" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0019" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, which includes a sick (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M5" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>) population compartment representing nodes of the networks that manifest the symptoms of the disease.</p>
              <p id="p0019">Although, several relevant questions are raised about the spread of the disease, we will focus on two of them in this study. The first one is associated with the group of asymptomatic individuals, who constitute the majority of the cases of the disease, and the second is related to the possibility that the immunity acquired by an infected person may be temporary.</p>
              <p id="p0020">As the mechanism of the spread of this disease is associated with the number of infected people and contact of this group to the susceptible group, it is important that the group of asymptomatic or unreported individuals be studied. Asymptomatic individuals are the group of infected people who do not manifest the symptoms, but can spread the disease by establishing effective contact with susceptible individuals.</p>
              <p id="p0021">To infer the behavior of asymptomatic individuals, the infected compartment will be divided into infected people who manifest the symptoms (sick) and those who do not, based on public data.</p>
              <p id="p0022">In addition, the influence of acquired immunity among individuals who have recovered from the infection is also being studied. If the acquired immunity is permanent, then the pattern of spread is described as temporal. On the other hand, if the immunity is temporary, it is important to understand the time interval after which the individual becomes susceptible again, changes in the dynamics of disease spread, and, the influence of the time interval for this reinfection on the temporal response.</p>
              <p id="p0023">The proposed Susceptible - Infected - Removed - Sick (SIRSi) model also considers birth and death of individuals in the given population and introduces a feedback from those in the recovered group who did not gain immunity or lost their immunity after a period of time.</p>
              <p id="p0024">The proposed SIRSi model presents both a disease free and an endemic equilibrium. The influence of the re-susceptibility feedback is investigated either analytically or numerically.</p>
              <p id="p0025">The parameters of the proposed SIRSi model are numerically fit to the pandemic situation of three cities in São Paulo State, in Brazil, namely, São Paulo, the capital of the State, Santos, on the coast and approximately 80 Km away from São Paulo, and Campinas, in the interior of the state and approximately 90 Km distant from the capital São Paulo.</p>
              <p id="p0026">The paper is organized as follows, <xref rid="sec0002" ref-type="sec">Section 2</xref> presents the SIRSi compartmental mathematical model. <xref rid="sec0003" ref-type="sec">Section 3</xref> presents the equilibrium points and stability conditions, showing the possible existence.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0002">
              <label>2</label>
              <title>A modified SIR model with birth and death cases</title>
              <p id="p0027">The proposed SIRSi model can be seen in <xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>
. In this model, the susceptible population <inline-formula><mml:math id="M6" altimg="si17.svg"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is infected at a rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="M7" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> when contacted by an infected individuals from <inline-formula><mml:math id="M8" altimg="si18.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. The susceptible compartment also receives a population, at a rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="M9" altimg="si19.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> who did not gain complete immunity after recovering or who lost their immunity after a period of time.<fig id="fig0001"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Epidemiological SIRSi model.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0001">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig></p>
              <p id="p0028">The compartment <inline-formula><mml:math id="M10" altimg="si18.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>represents the infectious population in the incubation stage prior the onset of symptoms. Infection transmission during this period has been reported in <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0036" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0038" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. The infected population can be asymptomatic or symptomatic. The period between infection and onset of symptoms <inline-formula><mml:math id="M11" altimg="si20.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> ranges from 3 to 38 days with a median of 5.2 days. Once the infected individual is tested positive and the case is documented, it is moved to the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M12" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> compartment and those who do not develop severe symptoms become asymptomatic.</p>
              <p id="p0029"><xref rid="bib0039" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref> reported that the estimate of the number of infections originating from undocumented cases is as high as 86%, including infected individuals with mild, limited and lack of symptoms. In other recent studies <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0041" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>, it was found that, 20% - 40% of positive tested patients were asymptomatic.</p>
              <p id="p0030">In this work, and <xref rid="bib0042" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>, under-reporting of asymptomatic cases is considered. The size of this population could be 7 times bigger than that of the documented cases and this group recovers within the period <inline-formula><mml:math id="M13" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
              <p id="p0031">Some of the individuals within this population could develop symptoms. In <xref rid="bib0043" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>, it has been reported that the average time between infection and the onset of symptoms can be 4.6 days. Once the case is documented it should be moved to the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M14" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>compartment, which consists of those patients with severe symptoms seeking medical attention. In <xref rid="bib0044" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref> it was reported that this population could represent up to 19.9% of the total documented cases, of which 13.8% are severe cases and 6.1% require intensive care. The sick population recovers within the period <inline-formula><mml:math id="M15" altimg="si22.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> or removed at a rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="M16" altimg="si7.svg"><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> (see <xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
              <p id="p0032">The effect of social distancing measures in the infected patients and corresponding deaths toll are shown in <xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>. The parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="M17" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is introduced <xref rid="eq0001" ref-type="disp-formula">(1)</xref>, and subject to the constraint <inline-formula><mml:math id="M18" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.33em"/><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Consequently, the SIRSi model is given by <xref rid="eq0001" ref-type="disp-formula">(1)</xref>,<disp-formula id="eq0001"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M19" altimg="si24.svg"><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">SI</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">SI</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow/><mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ick</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ick</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ick</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula> where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M20" altimg="si8.svg"><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M21" altimg="si9.svg"><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> are the birth and death rates, respectively.</p>
              <p id="p0033">The number of documented cases is a key information that should be noted from <xref rid="eq0001" ref-type="disp-formula">(1)</xref> because the number of confirmed cases is publicly available, and will be used to fine-tune the model. Although data on the number of new cases are added daily, it tends to be less representative of the dynamics.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0003">
              <label>3</label>
              <title>Disease-free and endemic equilibrium points</title>
              <p id="p0034">Here, the model given by <xref rid="eq0001" ref-type="disp-formula">(1)</xref> is considered, such that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M22" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M23" altimg="si26.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M24" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">U</mml:mi><mml:mo>⊂</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M25" altimg="si28.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">U</mml:mi><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">U</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the right-hand side of <xref rid="eq0001" ref-type="disp-formula">(1)</xref>, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M26" altimg="si29.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M27" altimg="si30.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M28" altimg="si31.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M29" altimg="si32.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M30" altimg="si33.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M31" altimg="si34.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M32" altimg="si35.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">R</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are the parameters.</p>
              <p id="p0035">To investigate the influence of the introduction of feedback from the recovered individuals with no immunity, the equilibrium points from <xref rid="eq0001" ref-type="disp-formula">(1)</xref> must be determined and their stability must be discussed.</p>
              <p id="p0036">Assuming the realistic hypothesis that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M33" altimg="si36.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>≠</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> i.e., susceptible can be converted into infected, the equilibrium points are <inline-formula><mml:math id="M34" altimg="si37.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
              <p id="p0037">Using the Hartman-Grobman Theorem <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref> the local stability of the equilibrium points can be determined by the eigenvalues of the Jacobian matrix computed on each equilibrium point. The Jacobian <inline-formula><mml:math id="M35" altimg="si38.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> of <xref rid="eq0001" ref-type="disp-formula">(1)</xref> is given by <xref rid="eq0002" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref>.<disp-formula id="eq0002"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M36" altimg="si39.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
              <p id="p0038">The disease-free (<xref rid="sec0004" ref-type="sec">Section 3.1</xref>) and the endemic (<xref rid="sec0005" ref-type="sec">Section 3.2</xref>) equilibrium points are determined in the following section.</p>
              <sec id="sec0004">
                <label>3.1</label>
                <title>Disease-free equilibrium points</title>
                <p id="p0039">The disease-free equilibrium is a state corresponding to the absence of infected individuals, <italic>i.e.</italic>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M37" altimg="si40.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Applying this condition to <xref rid="eq0001" ref-type="disp-formula">(1)</xref>, there is a disease-free equilibrium point <inline-formula><mml:math id="M38" altimg="si41.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> belonging to the first octant of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M39" altimg="si42.svg"><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> and given by:<disp-formula id="eq0003"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M40" altimg="si43.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
                <p id="p0040">Considering <inline-formula><mml:math id="M41" altimg="si44.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the corresponding Jacobian <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M42" altimg="si45.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is<disp-formula id="eq0004"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="M43" altimg="si46.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
                <p id="p0041">By the Laplace determinant development <xref rid="bib0046" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>, the eigenvalues of <xref rid="eq0004" ref-type="disp-formula">(4)</xref> are the elements in the diagonal, that is, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M44" altimg="si47.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M45" altimg="si48.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M46" altimg="si49.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M47" altimg="si50.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                <p id="p0042">The eigenvalues <inline-formula><mml:math id="M48" altimg="si51.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M49" altimg="si52.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M50" altimg="si53.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> are real and negatives, indicating asymptotically stable directions. Consequently, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M51" altimg="si54.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> determines the equilibrium stability. If <inline-formula><mml:math id="M52" altimg="si55.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) the eigenvector associated indicates an asymptotically stable direction. For <inline-formula><mml:math id="M53" altimg="si56.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), the equilibrium point <inline-formula><mml:math id="M54" altimg="si57.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is unstable, with the onset of a bifurcation in the parameter space.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0005">
                <label>3.2</label>
                <title>Endemic equilibrium points</title>
                <p id="p0043">The endemic equilibrium points are characterized by the existence of infected people in the population, that is, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M55" altimg="si58.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>≠</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>).</p>
                <p id="p0044">Therefore, there is an endemic equilibrium point <inline-formula><mml:math id="M56" altimg="si59.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in the first octant of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M57" altimg="si42.svg"><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> given by<disp-formula id="eq0005"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="M58" altimg="si60.svg"><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ick</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula> where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M59" altimg="si61.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                <p id="p0045">Consequently, the existence condition for the endemic equilibrium <inline-formula><mml:math id="M60" altimg="si62.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">R</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is given by<disp-formula id="eq0006"><label>(6)</label><mml:math id="M61" altimg="si63.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
                <p id="p0046">Considering <inline-formula><mml:math id="M62" altimg="si64.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the corresponding Jacobian <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M63" altimg="si65.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is<disp-formula id="eq0007"><label>(7)</label><mml:math id="M64" altimg="si66.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula> with eigenvalues <inline-formula><mml:math id="M65" altimg="si67.svg"><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> given by<disp-formula id="eq0008"><label>(8)</label><mml:math id="M66" altimg="si68.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula> with<disp-formula id="eq0009"><label>(9)</label><mml:math id="M67" altimg="si69.svg"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>]</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:msup><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
                <p id="p0047">Any further effort to analytically obtain <inline-formula><mml:math id="M68" altimg="si67.svg"><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> eigenvalues becomes difficult due to the complexity of the coefficients. A possible alternative approach is to perform numerical calculations.</p>
                <p id="p0048">However, some insight for the model with feedback <inline-formula><mml:math id="M69" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>can be obtained, in terms of bifurcations and stability, analyzing the eigenvalues when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M70" altimg="si70.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M71" altimg="si71.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>≠</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                <sec id="sec0006">
                  <label>3.2.1</label>
                  <title>Eigenvalues for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M72" altimg="si70.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></title>
                  <p id="p0049">Endemic equilibrium exists even with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M73" altimg="si70.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. In this case, the eigenvalues are<disp-formula id="eq0010"><label>(10)</label><mml:math id="M74" altimg="si72.svg"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mstyle mathvariant="normal"><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mstyle mathvariant="normal"><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula> with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M75" altimg="si73.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle mathvariant="normal"><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:msup><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                  <p id="p0050">Consequently, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M76" altimg="si74.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M77" altimg="si54.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> are real and negative, indicating asymptotically stable directions. The conclusion is the same for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M78" altimg="si75.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> because it is real and negative or complex with negative real part.</p>
                  <p id="p0051">The eigenvalue <inline-formula><mml:math id="M79" altimg="si52.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> must be analyzed more accurately because it can be the conjugated to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M80" altimg="si53.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>in a complex case, i.e., in situations with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M81" altimg="si76.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle mathvariant="normal"><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> indicating asymptotic stability. However, in a real case, i.e. when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M82" altimg="si77.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle mathvariant="normal"><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> if <inline-formula><mml:math id="M83" altimg="si78.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mstyle mathvariant="normal"><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> then the endemic equilibrium point is unstable.</p>
                  <p id="p0052">However, in the case of instability due to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M84" altimg="si79.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the existence condition <xref rid="eq0006" ref-type="disp-formula">(6)</xref> for the endemic equilibrium is not satisfied. Consequently, if the endemic equilibrium point <inline-formula><mml:math id="M85" altimg="si80.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> exists, it is asymptotically stable.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="sec0007">
                  <label>3.2.2</label>
                  <title>Eigenvalues for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M86" altimg="si81.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mi>∞</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></title>
                  <p id="p0053">Analyzing how <inline-formula><mml:math id="M87" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> changes the endemic situation, in a case with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M88" altimg="si81.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mi>∞</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is described by<disp-formula id="eq0011"><label>(11)</label><mml:math id="M89" altimg="si82.svg"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>→</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>→</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:msup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>→</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula> following the same existence condition given by <xref rid="eq0006" ref-type="disp-formula">(6)</xref>.</p>
                  <p id="p0054">Under the assumption <inline-formula><mml:math id="M90" altimg="si83.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mi>∞</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the coefficients from <xref rid="eq0008" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (8)</xref> can be approximated by<disp-formula id="eq0012"><label>(12)</label><mml:math id="M91" altimg="si84.svg"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula> and, consequently, <xref rid="eq0008" ref-type="disp-formula">(8)</xref> is rewritten as<disp-formula id="eq0013"><label>(13)</label><mml:math id="M92" altimg="si85.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
                  <p id="p0055">Assuming that at least one root <inline-formula><mml:math id="M93" altimg="si67.svg"><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> goes to infinity as <inline-formula><mml:math id="M94" altimg="si81.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mi>∞</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>:<disp-formula id="eq0014"><label>(14)</label><mml:math id="M95" altimg="si86.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula> then,<disp-formula id="ueq0001"><mml:math id="M96" altimg="si87.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.33em"/><mml:mtext>and</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.33em"/><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mi>∞</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula> so, one eigenvalue goes to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M97" altimg="si88.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>∞</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> as <inline-formula><mml:math id="M98" altimg="si81.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mi>∞</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                  <p id="p0056">To find an approximation to the other three roots, the characteristic equation is rewritten in <xref rid="eq0013" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (13)</xref>. It can be also assumed that the other three roots are finite following<disp-formula id="eq0015"><label>(15)</label><mml:math id="M99" altimg="si89.svg"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mi>ξ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0008">
              <label>4</label>
              <title>Parameter fitting by the least-squares method</title>
              <p id="p0057">In this section the parameters of the proposed SIRSi model <xref rid="eq0001" ref-type="disp-formula">(1)</xref> (see <xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>) are numerically adjusted to fit the curve of confirmed symptomatic cases of three major cities in the state of São Paulo - Brazil, using publicly available data from the State Data Analysis System - SEADE (<italic>Sistema Estadual de Análise de Dados</italic>
<xref rid="fn0002" ref-type="fn">2</xref>
) <xref rid="bib0047" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>. The total populations in each of the cities were obtained from the same source and it is shown in <xref rid="tbl0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>
.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Total population collected from SEADE.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0012">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top">City</th><th align="left" valign="top">Total population in 2020</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top">São Paulo</td><td valign="top">11.869.660</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Campinas</td><td valign="top">1.175.501</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Santos</td><td valign="top">428.703</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
              <p id="p0058">Birth and death rates were calculated using <inline-formula><mml:math id="M100" altimg="si8.svg"><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M101" altimg="si9.svg"><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> respectively. Linear interpolation was necessary as the data from the public repository were out of date. Results are shown in <xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>
.<fig id="fig0002"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Birth and death rates per 1000 inhabitants for São Paulo, Santos, and Campinas. Public data is shown in solid lines and interpolated values are shown in dashed lines.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0002">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2_lrg"/></fig></p>
              <p id="p0059">One of the first measures to contain the spread of the virus was the imposition of social distancing. This intervention, represented by <inline-formula><mml:math id="M102" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> in the model, focuses on reducing the possible contact between infected and susceptible individuals, and hence it is introduced as a factor of the transmission rate, i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M103" altimg="si90.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The time series corresponding to the daily measures of this index along with their mean for each one city considered are shown in <xref rid="fig0003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>
. Although this time variation resembles a 7-day periodic function, especially on the second half of the register, the mean of this measure is used as a representative value.<fig id="fig0003"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Percentage of social distancing <xref rid="bib0048" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0003">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3_lrg"/></fig></p>
              <p id="p0060">Information about the duration of antibody response to SARS-CoV-2 is limited; however, currently it is known that the immunity acquired is temporary. Recent research highlights that immune response and antibody protection after recovery may depend on the severity of the infection, in some cases this protection can last for as little as 12 weeks while in others, no antibody protection is observed <xref rid="bib0049" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0051" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0052" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0053" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0054" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>. To assess the influence of this behavior on disease spread, we set the feedback parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="M104" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>at constant values <inline-formula><mml:math id="M105" altimg="si91.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.00</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.01</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.02</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.03</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.04</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in order to map possible scenarios especially those related to second waves of infection.</p>
              <p id="p0061">The disease transmission rate of symptomatic individuals prior to hospitalization is estimated to be between 1.12 and 1.19, while that of asymptomatic cases is between 0.1 and 0.6. In the model <xref rid="eq0001" ref-type="disp-formula">(1)</xref> this parameter is represented by the product <inline-formula><mml:math id="M106" altimg="si92.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> thus, making <inline-formula><mml:math id="M107" altimg="si93.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The mean time between infection and onset-of-symptoms for confirmed cases, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M108" altimg="si20.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is 2 days, making <inline-formula><mml:math id="M109" altimg="si94.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.6</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The time from onset-of-infection to full recovery, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M110" altimg="si95.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is considered to be between a few days to two weeks (5 to 15 days). The time period for a symptomatic patient to overcome the disease, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M111" altimg="si96.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and the time between hospitalization to death, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M112" altimg="si97.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>are both considered to be between 5 to 20 days <xref rid="bib0043" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0044" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">[55]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0056" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>.</p>
              <p id="p0062">The trust-region reflective least-squares algorithm <xref rid="bib0057" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0058" ref-type="bibr">[58]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0059" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">[60]</xref> along with a 4th-order Runge-Kutta integrator were used to fit parameters in model <xref rid="eq0001" ref-type="disp-formula">(1)</xref> to actual data collected from public repositories for each one of the three cities into consideration. All parameters and initial conditions computed are normalized with respect to the total population in each case. For fitting, it was set <inline-formula><mml:math id="M113" altimg="si98.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M114" altimg="si99.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>with initial guess <inline-formula><mml:math id="M115" altimg="si100.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>99.9</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M116" altimg="si101.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.1</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the initial condition for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M117" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M118" altimg="si102.svg"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> was set to zero. Results are shown in
<xref rid="tbl0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, <xref rid="tbl0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, <xref rid="tbl0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>, <xref rid="tbl0005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>, <xref rid="tbl0006" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>, <xref rid="tbl0007" ref-type="table">Table 7</xref>
, and the temporal evolution of the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M119" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> compartment for each city, for both, the fitted model and the public data, is show in <xref rid="fig0006" ref-type="fig">Figs. 6</xref>, <xref rid="fig0008" ref-type="fig">8</xref> and <xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">10</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Fitted parameter for São Paulo.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0013">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top"/><th align="left" valign="top">Fit 1</th><th align="left" valign="top">Fit 2</th><th align="left" valign="top">Fit 3</th><th align="left" valign="top">Fit 4</th><th align="left" valign="top">Fit 5</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M120" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">9.377e-01</td><td valign="top">9.512e-01</td><td valign="top">9.312e-01</td><td valign="top">9.484e-01</td><td valign="top">8.485e-01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M121" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">1.181e-01</td><td valign="top">1.553e-01</td><td valign="top">1.881e-01</td><td valign="top">1.991e-01</td><td valign="top">1.999e-01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M122" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">2.978e-01</td><td valign="top">2.646e-01</td><td valign="top">2.179e-01</td><td valign="top">2.145e-01</td><td valign="top">1.698e-01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M123" altimg="si6.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">6.325e-02</td><td valign="top">8.144e-02</td><td valign="top">1.248e-01</td><td valign="top">1.396e-01</td><td valign="top">1.661e-01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M124" altimg="si7.svg"><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">1.117e-01</td><td valign="top">8.837e-02</td><td valign="top">7.195e-02</td><td valign="top">6.271e-02</td><td valign="top">5.830e-02</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M125" altimg="si8.svg"><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">3.595e-05</td><td valign="top">3.595e-05</td><td valign="top">3.595e-05</td><td valign="top">3.595e-05</td><td valign="top">3.595e-05</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M126" altimg="si9.svg"><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">1.822e-05</td><td valign="top">1.822e-05</td><td valign="top">1.822e-05</td><td valign="top">1.822e-05</td><td valign="top">1.822e-05</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M127" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">5.005e-01</td><td valign="top">5.005e-01</td><td valign="top">5.005e-01</td><td valign="top">5.005e-01</td><td valign="top">5.005e-01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M128" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">0.000e+00</td><td valign="top">1.000e-02</td><td valign="top">2.000e-02</td><td valign="top">3.000e-02</td><td valign="top">4.000e-02</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Fitted initial conditions for São Paulo.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0014">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top"/><th align="left" valign="top">Fit 1</th><th align="left" valign="top">Fit 2</th><th align="left" valign="top">Fit 3</th><th align="left" valign="top">Fit 4</th><th align="left" valign="top">Fit 5</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M129" altimg="si12.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">9.940e-01</td><td valign="top">9.888e-01</td><td valign="top">9.857e-01</td><td valign="top">9.827e-01</td><td valign="top">9.961e-01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M130" altimg="si13.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">4.319e-05</td><td valign="top">4.758e-05</td><td valign="top">5.340e-05</td><td valign="top">5.773e-05</td><td valign="top">7.675e-05</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M131" altimg="si14.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">8.425e-08</td><td valign="top">8.425e-08</td><td valign="top">8.425e-08</td><td valign="top">8.425e-08</td><td valign="top">8.425e-08</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M132" altimg="si15.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">0.000e+00</td><td valign="top">0.000e+00</td><td valign="top">0.000e+00</td><td valign="top">0.000e+00</td><td valign="top">0.000e+00</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0004"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Fitted parameter for Santos.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0015">Table 4</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top"/><th align="left" valign="top">Fit 1</th><th align="left" valign="top">Fit 2</th><th align="left" valign="top">Fit 3</th><th align="left" valign="top">Fit 4</th><th align="left" valign="top">Fit 5</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M133" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">9.131e-01</td><td valign="top">9.479e-01</td><td valign="top">9.835e-01</td><td valign="top">7.840e-01</td><td valign="top">9.355e-01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M134" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">1.600e-01</td><td valign="top">1.884e-01</td><td valign="top">1.932e-01</td><td valign="top">1.652e-01</td><td valign="top">1.929e-01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M135" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">2.440e-01</td><td valign="top">2.261e-01</td><td valign="top">2.459e-01</td><td valign="top">1.760e-01</td><td valign="top">2.024e-01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M136" altimg="si6.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">5.070e-02</td><td valign="top">7.930e-02</td><td valign="top">1.112e-01</td><td valign="top">9.574e-02</td><td valign="top">1.469e-01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M137" altimg="si7.svg"><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">7.973e-02</td><td valign="top">5.095e-02</td><td valign="top">2.750e-02</td><td valign="top">6.898e-02</td><td valign="top">2.503e-02</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M138" altimg="si8.svg"><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">2.693e-05</td><td valign="top">2.693e-05</td><td valign="top">2.693e-05</td><td valign="top">2.693e-05</td><td valign="top">2.693e-05</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M139" altimg="si9.svg"><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">2.710e-05</td><td valign="top">2.710e-05</td><td valign="top">2.710e-05</td><td valign="top">2.710e-05</td><td valign="top">2.710e-05</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M140" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">4.860e-01</td><td valign="top">4.860e-01</td><td valign="top">4.860e-01</td><td valign="top">4.860e-01</td><td valign="top">4.860e-01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M141" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">0.000e+00</td><td valign="top">1.000e-02</td><td valign="top">2.000e-02</td><td valign="top">3.000e-02</td><td valign="top">4.000e-02</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0005"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Fitted initial conditions for Santos.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0016">Table 5</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top"/><th align="left" valign="top">Fit 1</th><th align="left" valign="top">Fit 2</th><th align="left" valign="top">Fit 3</th><th align="left" valign="top">Fit 4</th><th align="left" valign="top">Fit 5</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M142" altimg="si12.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">1.006e+00</td><td valign="top">9.927e-01</td><td valign="top">1.004e+00</td><td valign="top">1.017e+00</td><td valign="top">9.685e-01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M143" altimg="si13.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">1.141e-05</td><td valign="top">1.141e-05</td><td valign="top">1.168e-05</td><td valign="top">1.852e-05</td><td valign="top">1.402e-05</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M144" altimg="si14.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">0.000e+00</td><td valign="top">0.000e+00</td><td valign="top">0.000e+00</td><td valign="top">0.000e+00</td><td valign="top">0.000e+00</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M145" altimg="si15.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">0.000e+00</td><td valign="top">0.000e+00</td><td valign="top">0.000e+00</td><td valign="top">0.000e+00</td><td valign="top">0.000e+00</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0006"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Fitted parameter for Campinas.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0017">Table 6</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top"/><th align="left" valign="top">Fit 1</th><th align="left" valign="top">Fit 2</th><th align="left" valign="top">Fit 3</th><th align="left" valign="top">Fit 4</th><th align="left" valign="top">Fit 5</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M146" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">7.473e-01</td><td valign="top">7.472e-01</td><td valign="top">7.466e-01</td><td valign="top">7.464e-01</td><td valign="top">7.384e-01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M147" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">1.350e-01</td><td valign="top">1.352e-01</td><td valign="top">1.354e-01</td><td valign="top">1.355e-01</td><td valign="top">1.368e-01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M148" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">1.930e-01</td><td valign="top">1.934e-01</td><td valign="top">1.933e-01</td><td valign="top">1.934e-01</td><td valign="top">1.923e-01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M149" altimg="si6.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">5.631e-02</td><td valign="top">5.582e-02</td><td valign="top">5.225e-02</td><td valign="top">5.281e-02</td><td valign="top">5.965e-02</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M150" altimg="si7.svg"><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">1.995e-01</td><td valign="top">1.954e-01</td><td valign="top">1.899e-01</td><td valign="top">1.906e-01</td><td valign="top">1.996e-01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M151" altimg="si8.svg"><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">3.353e-05</td><td valign="top">3.353e-05</td><td valign="top">3.353e-05</td><td valign="top">3.353e-05</td><td valign="top">3.353e-05</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M152" altimg="si9.svg"><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">4.509e-05</td><td valign="top">4.509e-05</td><td valign="top">4.509e-05</td><td valign="top">4.509e-05</td><td valign="top">4.509e-05</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M153" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">4.842e-01</td><td valign="top">4.842e-01</td><td valign="top">4.842e-01</td><td valign="top">4.842e-01</td><td valign="top">4.842e-01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M154" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">0.000e+00</td><td valign="top">1.000e-02</td><td valign="top">2.000e-02</td><td valign="top">3.000e-02</td><td valign="top">4.000e-02</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0007"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Fitted initial conditions for Campinas.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0018">Table 7</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top"/><th align="left" valign="top">Fit 1</th><th align="left" valign="top">Fit 2</th><th align="left" valign="top">Fit 3</th><th align="left" valign="top">Fit 4</th><th align="left" valign="top">Fit 5</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M155" altimg="si12.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">1.008e+00</td><td valign="top">1.008e+00</td><td valign="top">1.007e+00</td><td valign="top">1.007e+00</td><td valign="top">1.005e+00</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M156" altimg="si13.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">8.749e-06</td><td valign="top">9.148e-06</td><td valign="top">9.364e-06</td><td valign="top">9.614e-06</td><td valign="top">1.776e-05</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M157" altimg="si14.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">0.000e+00</td><td valign="top">0.000e+00</td><td valign="top">0.000e+00</td><td valign="top">0.000e+00</td><td valign="top">0.000e+00</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M158" altimg="si15.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">0.000e+00</td><td valign="top">0.000e+00</td><td valign="top">0.000e+00</td><td valign="top">0.000e+00</td><td valign="top">0.000e+00</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
              <p id="p0063">In order to assess the influence of the parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="M159" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> in the endemic equilibrium, the eigenvalues were plotted for the set of fit parameters found, for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M160" altimg="si103.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. In <xref rid="fig0004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>
the eigenvalues are shown for the endemic equilibrium of each city, and for each one of the fit sets.<fig id="fig0004"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Eigenvalues for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M161" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.1</mml:mn><mml:mo>}</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>for the three cities into consideration.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0004">Fig. 4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4_lrg"/></fig></p>
              <p id="p0064">For <inline-formula><mml:math id="M162" altimg="si70.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the eigenvalues are stable for São Paulo and Santos, and as <inline-formula><mml:math id="M163" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> increases, the eigenvalues move towards the left-hand side of the complex plane, whereas for Campinas the eigenvalues are unstable for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M164" altimg="si70.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. In <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>
a closer view of the eigenvalues around the origin is shown.<fig id="fig0005"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Eigenvalues for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M165" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.1</mml:mn><mml:mo>}</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>closer view around the origin.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0005">Fig. 5</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr5_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig0006"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Time evolution for confirmed cases (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M166" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>population) in São Paulo.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0006">Fig. 6</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr6_lrg"/></fig></p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0009">
              <label>5</label>
              <title>Numerical experiments</title>
              <p id="p0065">In this section numerical experiments conducted using the MATLAB-Simulink <xref rid="bib0061" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref> for two different conditions are described. First, the SIRSi model is fit with the real data for the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M167" altimg="si104.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> population and different values of the parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="M168" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. Consequently, the simulation for the infected population <inline-formula><mml:math id="M169" altimg="si18.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> can be inferred from the proposed model.</p>
              <p id="p0066">The numerical experiments, as in <xref rid="sec0008" ref-type="sec">Section 4</xref>, were conducted for three major cities in the state of São Paulo, namely, São Paulo, Campinas, and Santos.</p>
              <p id="p0067">The initial condition is <inline-formula><mml:math id="M170" altimg="si105.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M171" altimg="si12.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M172" altimg="si13.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> are the normalized susceptible and infected populations, which are considered as free parameters as they can be modified by the fitting algorithm.</p>
              <sec id="sec0010">
                <label>5.1</label>
                <title>Simulation results for São Paulo</title>
                <p id="p0068">The <xref rid="fig0006" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> shows that the SIRSi model gives a good adjustment for the data of confirmed cases in the infected population.</p>
                <p id="p0069">Considering that the acquired immunity is permanent, <italic>i.e.</italic>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M173" altimg="si106.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and that the isolation rate is constant, the peak of the infection occurs soon after July 2020, and the disease will not persist, until the end of the year.</p>
                <p id="p0070">On the other hand, assuming that immunity is not permanent and adopting a reinfection rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="M174" altimg="si107.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.01</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> such that every 100 days a recovered individual becomes susceptible again, the model predicts a decrease in the confirmed cases and a new wave of infection in the first half of 2022.</p>
                <p id="p0071">Decreasing the time interval in which a recovered person becomes susceptible (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M175" altimg="si108.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.02</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) to 50 days, the model indicates a second wave of infection in the first half of 2021. Decreasing the time interval in which a recovered person becomes susceptible (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M176" altimg="si109.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.04</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) to 25 days, the model indicates that number of confirmed infected will be reduced by almost two thirds by the end of this year and the number of infected cases with continue to reduce. In this case, the number of confirmed cases will remain higher than the others.</p>
                <p id="p0072">In <xref rid="fig0007" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>
, the infected compartment <inline-formula><mml:math id="M177" altimg="si18.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> inferred from the SIRSi model is presented, showing that the peak of infection is close to July 2020.<fig id="fig0007"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Time evolution for infected population in São Paulo.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0007">Fig. 7</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr7_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig0008"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Time evolution for confirmed cases (sick population) in Santos.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0008">Fig. 8</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr8_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="p0073">Increasing <inline-formula><mml:math id="M178" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> reduces the time for a recovered person to become susceptible again, causing the peaks in <xref rid="fig0007" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> to increase, when compared to the curves for lower values of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M179" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. This behavior, however, cannot be observed in <xref rid="fig0006" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>, indicating that the increase in re-susceptibility feedback gain <inline-formula><mml:math id="M180" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> possibly contributes to the increase of asymptomatic or unreported infected cases.</p>
                <p id="p0074">In addition, it seems that if recovered individuals acquire permanent immunity <inline-formula><mml:math id="M181" altimg="si106.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the number of infected people tends to zero by the end of 2020. For <inline-formula><mml:math id="M182" altimg="si110.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.01</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> there is a small increase in January 2022. For <inline-formula><mml:math id="M183" altimg="si111.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.02</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> a new wave of confirmed cases can be seen in <xref rid="fig0006" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>, and the increase in the infected population is also observed in <xref rid="fig0007" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>.</p>
                <p id="p0075">For São Paulo, the numerical experiments show that considering any reinfection rate, there will be confirmed infected cases and unreported infected cases until 2023, indicating the need for a control strategy and study on preventive inoculation.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0011">
                <label>5.2</label>
                <title>Simulation results for Santos</title>
                <p id="p0076"><xref rid="fig0008" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref> shows the SIRSi model adjusted to the data of confirmed cases in Santos. Assuming that the immunity acquired is permanent, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M184" altimg="si106.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and isolation rate is constant, the peak of the confirmed cases in Santos will occur very close to July 2020, similar to that in São Paulo (see <xref rid="fig0006" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>).</p>
                <p id="p0077">Adopting a nonzero reinfection rate, such that a recovered individual becomes susceptible again in 100 days (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M185" altimg="si107.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.01</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), a second wave of infection can be seen in the coastal city around July 2021, one year before the second wave predicted for São Paulo with the same value for the re-susceptibility feedback gain <inline-formula><mml:math id="M186" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                <p id="p0078">Considering <inline-formula><mml:math id="M187" altimg="si111.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.02</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in which an infected person becomes susceptible again in a time interval of 50 days, the second wave of confirmed cases occurs at the beginning of the first half of 2021 and the number of confirmed infected is reduced to one third of the peak value.</p>
                <p id="p0079">These situations should be analyzed with caution and it is suggested to study the influence of the flow of people between these cities, since the second wave of infection in the city of Santos occurs prior to São Paulo.</p>
                <p id="p0080">When <inline-formula><mml:math id="M188" altimg="si112.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.04</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> after the peak of the confirmed cases, a second wave can be observed in the numerical results before the end of 2020, delaying the reduction of the confirmed cases.</p>
                <p id="p0081">For Santos, the numerical experiments show that when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M189" altimg="si70.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M190" altimg="si113.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.03</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the number of confirmed cases tends to zero in the beginning of 2023.</p>
                <p id="p0082">The infected compartment <inline-formula><mml:math id="M191" altimg="si18.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> inferred from the SIRSi model is presented in <xref rid="fig0009" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>
, showing that the peak of infection is close to July 2020.<fig id="fig0009"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>Time evolution for infected population in Santos.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0009">Fig. 9</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr9_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig0010"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p>Time evolution for confirmed cases (sick population) in Campinas.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0010">Fig. 10</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr10_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="p0083">The increase in re-susceptibility feedback gain <inline-formula><mml:math id="M192" altimg="si34.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> reduces the time for an infected person to be susceptible again, causing higher peaks when compared to the curves for lower values of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M193" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. This behavior does not occur in <xref rid="fig0008" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref> indicating that the increase in feedback possibly contributes to the increase in asymptomatic or unreported infected cases. This situation is similar to that observed for São Paulo.</p>
                <p id="p0084">In addition, when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M194" altimg="si106.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the number of infected people <inline-formula><mml:math id="M195" altimg="si18.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> tends to zero before the end of the 2020 (see the curve for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M196" altimg="si70.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in <xref rid="fig0009" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>).</p>
                <p id="p0085">When <inline-formula><mml:math id="M197" altimg="si110.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.01</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> a new wave of infection can be seen in 2021, and when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M198" altimg="si108.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.02</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the peak of the second wave of infection is near January 2021 (see <xref rid="fig0009" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M199" altimg="si107.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.01</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M200" altimg="si108.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.02</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>).</p>
                <p id="p0086">Unlike São Paulo, the highest peak of infection among the unreported cases occurs when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M201" altimg="si114.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.03</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. This behavior suggests a more detailed study of the dynamics, because together with the situation in which the infected individual acquires permanent immunity, these rates suggest that the number of confirmed cases (see <xref rid="fig0008" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>) and asymptomatic infected individuals tends to zero more quickly.</p>
                <p id="p0087">In the situation in which a recovered person becomes susceptible in 25 days, it is observed that the infection persists in the population for a longer time, as shown by the curve with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M202" altimg="si109.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.04</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in <xref rid="fig0009" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref> justifying an accurate set of public strategies.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0012">
                <label>5.3</label>
                <title>Simulation results for Campinas</title>
                <p id="p0088"><xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10</xref> shows the SIRSi model results adjusted to the confirmed cases of infected people data in Campinas.</p>
                <p id="p0089">For permanent acquired immunity, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M203" altimg="si106.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and constant isolation rate, the peak of confirmed infection cases occur in the beginning of the second half of 2020.</p>
                <p id="p0090">Considering the re-susceptibility feedback gain <inline-formula><mml:math id="M204" altimg="si115.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in <xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10</xref>, it seems that with the increase in <inline-formula><mml:math id="M205" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> the time necessary for the number of confirmed cases tending to zero is slightly higher, which is different from that of Santos and São Paulo. However, Campinas does not present a second wave of infection, even with the variation of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M206" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                <p id="p0091">The general behavior of Campinas, concerning the sensitivity analysis for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M207" altimg="si34.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> presents different results from that of Santos and São Paulo. It can be noticed in <xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10</xref> that the observed data are far from the peak of infection predicted by the SIRSi model. At this point, more data is needed for any further qualitative analysis.</p>
                <p id="p0092">Observing the eigenvalues for the city of Campinas (See <xref rid="fig0004" ref-type="fig">Figs. 4</xref> and <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) it can be noticed that they are all real, indicating that there is no oscillatory behavior in the dynamics of the model. Depending on the new data this situation might change.</p>
                <p id="p0093">The infected compartment of Campinas presents the peak of infection close to the beginning of the second half of 2020, <xref rid="fig0011" ref-type="fig">Fig. 11</xref>
.<fig id="fig0011"><label>Fig. 11</label><caption><p>Time evolution for infected population in Campinas.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0011">Fig. 11</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr11_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="p0094">Increase in the reinfection parameter causes an increase in the infection peak as shown in <xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10</xref> indicating that the increase in feedback possibly contributes to the increase in either asymptomatic or unreported infected cases.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0013">
              <label>6</label>
              <title>Conclusions</title>
              <p id="p0095">The proposed SIRSi model was fit to publicly available data of the Covid-19 outbreak, providing estimates on the duration and peaks of the outbreak. In addition, the model allows us to infer information related to unreported and asymptomatic cases.</p>
              <p id="p0096">The proposed model with re-susceptibility feedback adjusted to the confirmed infection data, suggests the possibility that recovered patients may have temporary immunity <inline-formula><mml:math id="M208" altimg="si116.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> or even permanent <inline-formula><mml:math id="M209" altimg="si70.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
              <p id="p0097">Considering the situation in which immunity is temporary, there is a second wave of infection which, depending on the time interval for a recovered person to be susceptible again, indicates a second wave with a greater or lesser number of reinfected patients.</p>
              <p id="p0098">If the time interval is larger (larger <inline-formula><mml:math id="M210" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>), the second wave of infection will have a greater number of infected people when compared to that of a shorter time interval.</p>
              <p id="p0099">The qualitative behavior for São Paulo and Santos is similar in terms of the sensitivity analysis of the re-susceptibility feedback gain <inline-formula><mml:math id="M211" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. The bigger the value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M212" altimg="si34.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the shorter the time for a recovered person to become susceptible to reinfection, increasing the number of unreported or asymptomatic cases.</p>
              <p id="p0100">It is suggested to collect more data for the city of Campinas because the data of the confirmed infected cases presents a certain distance from the peak of the infection. The dynamics of the model may undergo some significant changes, given the sensitivity of the model to disturbances.</p>
              <p id="p0101">It is inferred from the proposed model that if the acquired immunity is temporary, a second wave of infection is a serious possibility. In addition, the number of asymptomatic patients increases if the acquired immunity lasts for a short period of time.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec0014">
              <title>Availability of data and materials</title>
              <p id="p0102">Data are publicly available with <xref rid="bib0047" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0048" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0014a">
              <title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title>
              <p id="p0102a"><bold>Cristiane M. Batistela:</bold> Conceptualization, Methodology, Validation, Writing - original draft, Visualization. <bold>Diego P.F. Correa:</bold> Conceptualization, Methodology, Software, Validation, Investigation, Writing - original draft. <bold>Átila M Bueno:</bold> Conceptualization, Methodology, Validation, Investigation, Writing - original draft. <bold>José Roberto C. Piqueira:</bold> Conceptualization, Validation, Formal analysis, Resources, Writing - review &amp; editing, Project administration, Funding acquisition.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="COI-statement">
              <title>Declaration of Competing Interest</title>
              <p id="p0103">There is no conflict of interest between the authors.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list id="bib001">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="bib0001">
                <label>1</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0001">World Health Organization WHO Timeline - COVID-192020[online] [cited 25 Jun 2020].</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0002">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0002">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sohrabi</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alsafi</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>O’Neill</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Khan</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kerwan</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Al-Jabir</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>World health organization declares global emergency: a review of the 2019 novel coronavirus (covid-19)</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Surg</source>
                  <volume>76</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>71</fpage>
                  <lpage>76</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijsu.2020.02.034</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32112977</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0003">
                <label>3</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0003">Ministério da Saúde do Brasil 2020[online] [cited 25 Jun 2020].</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0004">
                <label>4</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0004">World Health Organization WHO Coronavirus disease (COVID-19) dashboard2020[online] [cited 25 Jun 2020].</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0005">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0005">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Singh</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Parmar</surname>
                      <given-names>K.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kumar</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Makkhan</surname>
                      <given-names>S.J.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Development of new hybrid model of discrete wavelet decomposition and autoregressive integrated moving average (ARIMA) models in application to one month forecast the casualties cases of COVID-19</article-title>
                  <source>Chaos Solitons Fractals</source>
                  <volume>135</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>109866</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chaos.2020.109866</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32395038</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0006">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0006">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Prem</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Russell</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kucharski</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eggo</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davies</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effect of control strategies to reduce social mixing on outcomes of the COVID-19 epidemic in Wuhan, China: a modelling study</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet Public Health</source>
                  <volume>5</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>e261</fpage>
                  <lpage>e270</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2468-2667(20)30073-6</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32220655</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0007">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0007">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hellewell</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abbott</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gimma</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bosse</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jarvis</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Russell</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Feasibility of controlling COVID-19 outbreaks by isolation of cases and contacts</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet Global Health</source>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>e488</fpage>
                  <lpage>e496</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2214-109X(20)30074-7</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32119825</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0008">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0008">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Crokidakis</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>COVID-19 Spreading in rio de janeiro, Brazil: do the policies of social isolation really work?</article-title>
                  <source>Chaos Solitons Fractals</source>
                  <volume>136</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>109930</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chaos.2020.109930</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32501374</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0009">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0009">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nadanovsky</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Santos</surname>
                      <given-names>A.P.P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Strategies to deal with the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>
                  <source>Braz Oral Res</source>
                  <volume>34</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0010">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0010">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mishra</surname>
                      <given-names>B.K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Keshri</surname>
                      <given-names>A.K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rao</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mishra</surname>
                      <given-names>B.K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mahato</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ayesha</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>COVID-19 Created chaos across the globe: three novel quarantine epidemic models</article-title>
                  <source>Chaos Solitons Fractals</source>
                  <volume>138</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>109928</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chaos.2020.109928</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32501378</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0011">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0011">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Acuña Zegarra</surname>
                      <given-names>M.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Santana-Cibrian</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Velasco-Hernandez</surname>
                      <given-names>J.X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Modeling behavioral change and COVID-19 containment in mexico: a trade-off between lockdown and compliance</article-title>
                  <source>Math Biosci</source>
                  <volume>325</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>108370</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mbs.2020.108370</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32387384</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0012">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0012">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>Q.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xia</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Neutralizing antibody responses to SARS-CoV-2 in a COVID-19 recovered patient cohort and their implications</article-title>
                  <source>SSRN Electron J</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2139/ssrn.3566211</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0013">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0013">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bao</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Deng</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gao</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xiao</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xue</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lv</surname>
                      <given-names>Q.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yu</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xu</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Qi</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Qu</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xiang</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yu</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gong</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Song</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhao</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Han</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhao</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wei</surname>
                      <given-names>Q.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Qin</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Lack of reinfection in rhesus macaques infected with SARS-CoV-2</article-title>
                  <source>bioRxiv</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2020.03.13.990226</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <note>
                  <p>ArXiv:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2020/05/01/2020.03.13.990226.full.pdf" id="intrrf0002">https://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2020/05/01/2020.03.13.990226.full.pdf</ext-link></p>
                </note>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0014">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0014">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Blanco-Melo</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nilsson-Payant</surname>
                      <given-names>B.E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>W.-C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Uhl</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hoagland</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Møller</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jordan</surname>
                      <given-names>T.X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Oishi</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Panis</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sachs</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>T.T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schwartz</surname>
                      <given-names>R.E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lim</surname>
                      <given-names>J.K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Albrecht</surname>
                      <given-names>R.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>tenOever</surname>
                      <given-names>B.R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Imbalanced host response to SARS-CoV-2 drives development of COVID-19</article-title>
                  <source>Cell</source>
                  <volume>181</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1036</fpage>
                  <lpage>1045.e9</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2020.04.026</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32416070</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0015">
                <label>15</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0015">Pappas S.. After recovering from COVID-19, are you immune?2020;[online] [cited 26 Jun 2020].</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0016">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0016">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fernandes</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Economic effects of coronavirus outbreak (COVID-19) on the world economy</article-title>
                  <source>SSRN Electron J</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2139/ssrn.3557504</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0017">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0017">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kermack</surname>
                      <given-names>W.O.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McKendrick</surname>
                      <given-names>A.G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Walker</surname>
                      <given-names>G.T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>A contribution to the mathematical theory of epidemics</chapter-title>
                  <source>Proceedings of the royal society of London. Series A, containing papers of a mathematical and physical character</source>
                  <volume>vol. 115</volume>
                  <year>1927</year>
                  <fpage>700</fpage>
                  <lpage>721</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0018">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0018">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kermack</surname>
                      <given-names>W.O.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McKendrick</surname>
                      <given-names>A.G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Walker</surname>
                      <given-names>G.T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Contributions to the mathematical theory of epidemics. II. The problem of endemicity</chapter-title>
                  <source>Proceedings of the royal society of London. Series A, containing papers of a mathematical and physical character</source>
                  <volume>vol. 138</volume>
                  <year>1932</year>
                  <fpage>55</fpage>
                  <lpage>83</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0019">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0019">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kermack</surname>
                      <given-names>W.O.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McKendrick</surname>
                      <given-names>A.G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Walker</surname>
                      <given-names>G.T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Contributions to the mathematical theory of epidemics. III. Further studies of the problem of endemicity</chapter-title>
                  <source>Proceedings of the royal society of London. Series A, containing papers of a mathematical and physical character</source>
                  <volume>vol. 141</volume>
                  <year>1933</year>
                  <fpage>94</fpage>
                  <lpage>122</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0020">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0020">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bailey</surname>
                      <given-names>N.T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Macro-modelling and prediction of epidemic spread at community level</article-title>
                  <source>Math Modell</source>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <year>1986</year>
                  <fpage>689</fpage>
                  <lpage>717</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0270-0255(86)90128-4</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0021">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0021">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chávez</surname>
                      <given-names>J.P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gürbüz</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pinto</surname>
                      <given-names>C.M.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effect of aggressive chemotherapy in a model for HIV/AIDS-cancer dynamics</article-title>
                  <source>Commun Nonlinear Sci Numer Simul</source>
                  <volume>75</volume>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <fpage>109</fpage>
                  <lpage>120</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0022">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0022">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Piqueira</surname>
                      <given-names>J.R.C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Batistela</surname>
                      <given-names>C.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Considering quarantine in the SIRA malware propagation model</article-title>
                  <source>Math Probl Eng</source>
                  <volume>2019</volume>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>8</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2019/6467104</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0023">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0023">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cantó</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Coll</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sánchez</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Estimation of parameters in a structured sir model</article-title>
                  <source>Adv Differ Eqs</source>
                  <volume>2017</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <fpage>33</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13662-017-1078-5</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0024">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0024">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jajarmi</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yusuf</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baleanu</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Inc</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A new fractional HRSV model and its optimal control: a non-singular operator approach</article-title>
                  <source>Physica A</source>
                  <volume>547</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>123860</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0025">
                <label>25</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0025">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ng</surname>
                      <given-names>T.W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Turinici</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Danchin</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A double epidemic model for the SARS propagation</article-title>
                  <source>BMC Infect Dis</source>
                  <volume>3</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2334-3-19</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0026">
                <label>26</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0026">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Godio</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pace</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vergnano</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>SEIR Modeling of the Italian epidemic of SARS-CoV-2 using computational swarm intelligence</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <issue>3535</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.20944/preprints202004.0073.v1</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0027">
                <label>27</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0027">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cheng</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jiang</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A time delay dynamic system with external source for the local outbreak of 2019-nCOV</article-title>
                  <source>Appl Anal</source>
                  <volume>0</volume>
                  <issue>0</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>12</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0028">
                <label>28</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0028">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abdo</surname>
                      <given-names>M.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shah</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wahash</surname>
                      <given-names>H.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Panchal</surname>
                      <given-names>S.K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>On a comprehensive model of the novel coronavirus (COVID-19) under Mittag-Leffler derivative</article-title>
                  <source>Chaos Solitons Fractals</source>
                  <volume>135</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>109867</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chaos.2020.109867</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32390692</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0029">
                <label>29</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0029">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baleanu</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jajarmi</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sajjadi</surname>
                      <given-names>S.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Asad</surname>
                      <given-names>J.H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The fractional features of a harmonic oscillator with position-dependent mass</article-title>
                  <source>Commun Theor Phys</source>
                  <volume>72</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>055002</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/1572-9494/ab7700</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0030">
                <label>30</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0030">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Carvalho</surname>
                      <given-names>A.R.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pinto</surname>
                      <given-names>C.M.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>de Carvalho</surname>
                      <given-names>J.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Fractional model for type 1 diabetes</chapter-title>
                  <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Machado</surname>
                      <given-names>J.A.T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Özdemir</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baleanu</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Mathematical modelling and optimization of engineering problems</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <publisher-name>Springer Nature</publisher-name>
                  <fpage>175</fpage>
                  <lpage>185</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0031">
                <label>31</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0031">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baleanu</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jajarmi</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mohammadi</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rezapour</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A new study on the mathematical modelling of human liver with Caputo–Fabrizio fractional derivative</article-title>
                  <source>Chaos Solitons Fractals</source>
                  <volume>134</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>109705</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chaos.2020.109705</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0032">
                <label>32</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0032">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sajjadi</surname>
                      <given-names>S.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baleanu</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jajarmi</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pirouz</surname>
                      <given-names>H.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A new adaptive synchronization and hyperchaos control of a biological snap oscillator</article-title>
                  <source>Chaos Solitons Fractals</source>
                  <volume>138</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>109919</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chaos.2020.109919</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0033">
                <label>33</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0033">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fanelli</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Piazza</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Analysis and forecast of COVID-19 spreading in China, Italy and France</article-title>
                  <source>Chaos Solitons Fractals</source>
                  <volume>134</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>109761</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chaos.2020.109761</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32308258</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0034">
                <label>34</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0034">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cotta</surname>
                      <given-names>R.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Naveira-Cotta</surname>
                      <given-names>C.P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>magal</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Parametric identification and public health measures influence on the COVID-19 epidemic evolution in Brazil</article-title>
                  <source>medRxiv</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0035">
                <label>35</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0035">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rothe</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schunk</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sothmann</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bretzel</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Froeschl</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wallrauch</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Transmission of 2019-nCoV infection from an asymptomatic contact in Germany</article-title>
                  <source>N Engl J Med</source>
                  <volume>382</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>970</fpage>
                  <lpage>971</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMc2001468</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32003551</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0036">
                <label>36</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0036">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tian</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lou</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Familial cluster of COVID-19 infection from an asymptomatic</article-title>
                  <source>Crit Care</source>
                  <volume>24</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
                  <lpage>9</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13054-020-2817-7</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31910905</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0037">
                <label>37</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0037">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chan</surname>
                      <given-names>J.F.W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yuan</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kok</surname>
                      <given-names>K.H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>To</surname>
                      <given-names>K.K.W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chu</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A familial cluster of pneumonia associated with the 2019 novel coronavirus indicating person-to-person transmission: a study of a family cluster</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet</source>
                  <volume>395</volume>
                  <issue>10223</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>514</fpage>
                  <lpage>523</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31986261</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0038">
                <label>38</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0038">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tian</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hu</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lou</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kang</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xiang</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Characteristics of COVID-19 infection in Beijing</article-title>
                  <source>J Infect</source>
                  <volume>80</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>401</fpage>
                  <lpage>406</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2020.02.018</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32112886</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0039">
                <label>39</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0039">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pei</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Song</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shaman</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Substantial undocumented infection facilitates the rapid dissemination of novel coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2)</article-title>
                  <source>Science</source>
                  <volume>368</volume>
                  <issue>6490</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>489</fpage>
                  <lpage>493</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32179701</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0040">
                <label>40</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0040">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mizumoto</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kagaya</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zarebski</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chowell</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Estimating the asymptomatic proportion of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) cases on board the diamond princess cruise ship, Yokohama, Japan</article-title>
                  <source>Eurosurveillance</source>
                  <volume>25</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2807/1560-7917.es.2020.25.10.2000180</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0041">
                <label>41</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0041">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nishiura</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kobayashi</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Miyama</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Suzuki</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jung</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hayashi</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kinoshita</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yuan</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Akhmetzhanov</surname>
                      <given-names>A.R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Linton</surname>
                      <given-names>N.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Estimation of the asymptomatic ratio of novel coronavirus infections (COVID-19)</article-title>
                  <source>medRxiv</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0042">
                <label>42</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0042">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ribeiro</surname>
                      <given-names>L.C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bernardes</surname>
                      <given-names>A.T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Estimate of underreporting of COVID-19 in Brazil by acute respiratory syndrome hospitalization reports</chapter-title>
                  <source>Notas Técnicas Cedeplar-UFMG 010</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <publisher-name>Cedeplar, Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0043">
                <label>43</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0043">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ferguson</surname>
                      <given-names>N.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Laydon</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nedjati-Gilani</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Imai</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ainslie</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baguelin</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bhatia</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Boonyasiri</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cucunubá</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cuomo-Dannenburg</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dighe</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dorigatti</surname>
                      <given-names>I.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fu</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gaythorpe</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Green</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hamlet</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hinsley</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Okell</surname>
                      <given-names>L.C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Elsland</surname>
                      <given-names>S.V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thompson</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Verity</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Volz</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Walker</surname>
                      <given-names>P.G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Walters</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Winskill</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Whittaker</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Donnelly</surname>
                      <given-names>C.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Riley</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ghani</surname>
                      <given-names>A.C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Impact of non-pharmaceutical interventions (NPIs) to reduce COVID-19 mortality and healthcare demand</article-title>
                  <source>ImperialAcUk</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>3</fpage>
                  <lpage>20</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.25561/77482</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0044">
                <label>44</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0044">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Verity</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Okell</surname>
                      <given-names>L.C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dorigatti</surname>
                      <given-names>I.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Winskill</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Whittaker</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Imai</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cuomo-Dannenburg</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thompson</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Walker</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fu</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dighe</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Griffin</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cori</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baguelin</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bhatia</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Boonyasiri</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cucunuba</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fitzjohn</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gaythorpe</surname>
                      <given-names>K.A.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Green</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hamlet</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hinsley</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Laydon</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nedjati-Gilani</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Riley</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>van Elsand</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Volz</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xi</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Donnelly</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ghani</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ferguson</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Estimates of the severity of COVID-19 disease</article-title>
                  <source>medRxiv</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0045">
                <label>45</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0045">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Guckenheimer</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Holmes</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Nonlinear oscillations, dynamical systems, and bifurcations of vector fields</chapter-title>
                  <source>Applied mathematical sciences</source>
                  <edition>4th ed.</edition>
                  <volume>vol. 42</volume>
                  <year>1983</year>
                  <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0046">
                <label>46</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0046">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hirsch</surname>
                      <given-names>M.W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Smale</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Differential equations, dynamical systems, and linear algebra</chapter-title>
                  <volume>vol. 1</volume>
                  <year>1974</year>
                  <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>
                  <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0047">
                <label>47</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0047">SEADE Portal estatísticas do Estado de São Paulo2020[online] [cited 19 Jun 2020].</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0048">
                <label>48</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0048">SEADE SP contra o novo coronavírus boletim completo2020[online] [cited 19 Jun 2020].</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0049">
                <label>49</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0049">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kellam</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Barclay</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The dynamics of humoral immune responses following SARS-CoV-2 infection and the potential for reinfection</article-title>
                  <source>J Gen Virol</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/jgv.0.001439</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0050">
                <label>50</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0050">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Callow</surname>
                      <given-names>K.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Parry</surname>
                      <given-names>H.F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sergeant</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tyrrell</surname>
                      <given-names>D.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The time course of the immune response to experimental coronavirus infection of man</article-title>
                  <source>Epidemiol Infect</source>
                  <volume>105</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>1990</year>
                  <fpage>435</fpage>
                  <lpage>446</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2170159</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0051">
                <label>51</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0051">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mo</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zeng</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ren</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ke</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tan</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cai</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lai</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chan-Yeung</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhong</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Longitudinal profile of antibodies against SARS-coronavirus in SARS patients and their clinical significance</article-title>
                  <source>Respirology</source>
                  <volume>11</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <fpage>49</fpage>
                  <lpage>53</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16423201</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0052">
                <label>52</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0052">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Moore</surname>
                      <given-names>J.P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Klasse</surname>
                      <given-names>P.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>SARS-CoV-2 vaccines: ’Warp Speed’ needs mind melds not warped minds</article-title>
                  <source>J Virol</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0053">
                <label>53</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0053">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Seow</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Graham</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Merrick</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Acors</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Steel</surname>
                      <given-names>K.J.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hemmings</surname>
                      <given-names>O.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>O’Bryne</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kouphou</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pickering</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Galao</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Betancor</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wilson</surname>
                      <given-names>H.D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Signell</surname>
                      <given-names>A.W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Winstone</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kerridge</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Temperton</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Snell</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bisnauthsing</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Moore</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Green</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Martinez</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stokes</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Honey</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Izquierdo-Barras</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Arbane</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Patel</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>OConnell</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hara</surname>
                      <given-names>G.O.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>MacMahon</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Douthwaite</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nebbia</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Batra</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Martinez-Nunez</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Edgeworth</surname>
                      <given-names>J.D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Neil</surname>
                      <given-names>S.J.D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Malim</surname>
                      <given-names>M.H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Doores</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Longitudinal evaluation and decline of antibody responses in SARS-CoV-2 infection</article-title>
                  <source>medRxiv</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2020.07.09.20148429</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0054">
                <label>54</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0054">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Edridge</surname>
                      <given-names>A.W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kaczorowska</surname>
                      <given-names>J.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hoste</surname>
                      <given-names>A.C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bakker</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Klein</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jebbink</surname>
                      <given-names>M.F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Matser</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kinsella</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rueda</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Prins</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sastre</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Deijs</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>van der Hoek</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Coronavirus protective immunity is short-lasting</article-title>
                  <source>medRxiv</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2020.05.11.20086439</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0055">
                <label>55</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0055">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pei</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Song</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shaman</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Substantial undocumented infection facilitates the rapid dissemination of novel coronavirus (SARS-CoV2)</article-title>
                  <source>Science</source>
                  <volume>368</volume>
                  <issue>6490</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>489</fpage>
                  <lpage>493</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abb3221</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32179701</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0056">
                <label>56</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0056">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tang</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wei</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Updated understanding of the outbreak of 2019 novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) in Wuhan, China</article-title>
                  <source>J Med Virol</source>
                  <volume>92</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>441</fpage>
                  <lpage>447</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jmv.25689</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31994742</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0057">
                <label>57</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0057">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mehrotra</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>On the implementation of a primal-dual interior point method</article-title>
                  <source>SIAM J Optim</source>
                  <volume>2</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <year>1992</year>
                  <fpage>575</fpage>
                  <lpage>601</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0058">
                <label>58</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0058">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bartholomew-Biggs</surname>
                      <given-names>M.C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Recursive quadratic programming methods based on the augmented lagrangian</article-title>
                  <source>Comput Math Program</source>
                  <year>1987</year>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <lpage>41</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/bfb0121177</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0059">
                <label>59</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0059">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Conn</surname>
                      <given-names>A.R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gould</surname>
                      <given-names>N.I.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Toint</surname>
                      <given-names>P.L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Trust region methods</article-title>
                  <source>Soc Ind Appl Math</source>
                  <year>2000</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0060">
                <label>60</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0060">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rocha</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gouveia</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pinto</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Scotto</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tavares</surname>
                      <given-names>J.N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Valadas</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>On the parameters estimation of HIV dynamic models</article-title>
                  <source>REVSTAT - Stat J</source>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <lpage>222</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0061">
                <label>61</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0061">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Moler</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Numerical computing with MATLAB, other titles in applied mathematics</article-title>
                  <source>Soc Ind Appl Math</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
            <ack id="ack0001">
              <title>Acknowledgement</title>
              <p id="p0104">JRCP is supported by the Brazilian Research Council (<funding-source id="gs00001"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100003593</institution-id><institution>CNPq</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>), grant number: 302883/2018-5.</p>
            </ack>
            <fn-group>
              <fn id="fn0001">
                <label>1</label>
                <p id="notep0001">Reported on 2:25pm CEST.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="fn0002">
                <label>2</label>
                <p id="notep0002"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.seade.gov.br/" id="intrrf0001">www.seade.gov.br/</ext-link>.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
