<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-03-11T00:54:37Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7833124" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:7833124</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-01-26</datestamp>
        <setSpec>pheelsevier</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Value Health</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Value Health</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Value in Health</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">1098-3015</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1524-4733</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>ISPOR-The Professional Society for Health Economics and Outcomes Research. Published by Elsevier Inc.</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC7833124</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7833124</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">7833124</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33933228</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pii">S1098-3015(20)34421-1</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jval.2020.09.013</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Themed Section: COVID-19</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Modeling Social Distancing Strategies to Prevent SARS-CoV-2 Spread in Israel: A Cost-Effectiveness Analysis</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Shlomai</surname>
                    <given-names>Amir</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Leshno</surname>
                    <given-names>Ari</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Sklan</surname>
                    <given-names>Ella H.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref>
                  <xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">∗</xref>
                  <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">∗</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Leshno</surname>
                    <given-names>Moshe</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref>
                  <xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">∗</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Medicine D and The Liver Institute, Rabin Medical Center, Beilinson Hospital, Petah-Tikva, Israel and The Sackler Faculty of Medicine, Tel Aviv University, Tel Aviv, Israel</aff>
                <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Goldschleger Eye Institute, Sheba Medical Center, Ramat Gan, Israel and The Sackler Faculty of Medicine, Tel Aviv University, Tel Aviv, Israel</aff>
                <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Clinical Microbiology and Immunology, The Sackler Faculty of Medicine, Tel Aviv University, Tel Aviv, Israel</aff>
                <aff id="aff4"><label>4</label>The Coller School of Management, Tel Aviv University, Tel Aviv, Israel</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1"><label>∗</label><bold>Correspondence:</bold> Ella H. Sklan, Department of Clinical Microbiology and Immunology, Sackler School of Medicine, Tel-Aviv University, Ramat Aviv, Tel Aviv, Israel 69978.</corresp>
                <fn id="fn1">
                  <label>∗</label>
                  <p id="ntpara0010">Ella H. Sklan and Moshe Leshno contributed equally to this article.</p>
                </fn>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>9</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2020</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.-->
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <month>5</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>9</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2020</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>24</volume>
              <issue>5</issue>
              <fpage>607</fpage>
              <lpage>614</lpage>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2020 ISPOR-The Professional Society for Health Economics and Outcomes Research. Published by Elsevier Inc.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2020</copyright-year>
                <copyright-holder>ISPOR–The Professional Society for Health Economics and Outcomes Research</copyright-holder>
                <license>
                  <license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="abs0010">
                <sec>
                  <title>Objectives</title>
                  <p>While highly effective in preventing SARS-CoV-2 spread, national lockdowns come with an enormous economic price. Few countries have adopted an alternative “testing, tracing, and isolation” approach to selectively isolate people at high exposure risk, thereby minimizing the economic impact. To assist policy makers, we performed a cost-effectiveness analysis of these 2 strategies.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods</title>
                  <p>A modified Susceptible, Exposed, Infectious, Recovered, and Deceased (SEIRD) model was employed to assess the situation in Israel, a small country with ∼9 million people. The incremental cost-effectiveness ratio (ICER) of these strategies as well as the expected number of infected individuals and deaths were calculated.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>A nationwide lockdown is expected to save, on average, 274 (median 124, interquartile range: 71-221) lives compared to the “testing, tracing, and isolation” approach. However, the ICER will be, on average, $45 104 156 (median $49.6 million, interquartile range: 22.7-220.1) to prevent 1 case of death.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusion</title>
                  <p>A national lockdown has a moderate advantage in saving lives with tremendous costs and possible overwhelming economic effects. These findings should assist decision makers dealing with additional waves of this pandemic.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group id="kwrds0010">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>cost-effectiveness</kwd>
                <kwd>SARS-CoV-2</kwd>
                <kwd>SEIR model</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="sec1">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p id="p0025">Since its identification at the very end of 2019, the novel coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) has spread around the world at an extraordinary rate and has been officially declared a pandemic.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> So far, this epidemic has affected more than 23 million people and claimed the lives of more than 819 000 individuals at the time of the submission of this article.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> The first priority in most countries is to enable the local health systems to handle the growing number of patients needing hospitalization and intensive care by “flattening the curve.” Observing the dreadful situation in countries such as Italy and Spain,<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> many countries are now undertaking extreme measures such as national lockdowns in an effort to stay within the boundaries of the local health system capacity.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> However, only a few countries, such as South Korea, have succeeded in slowing the infection rates without enforcing economically damaging lockdowns. Instead, South Korea applied early interventions that included identification and isolation of outbreak sources by massive screening of infected patients and rigorous tracing and isolation of their contacts.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> It is not yet clear whether the apparent success of South Korea could be applied to other countries in North America and Europe. It is, however, obvious that extreme nonspecific measures are associated with tremendous economic costs and will result in a global financial crisis that will most likely affect public health and other essential aspects of our lives in the coming years.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> The International Monetary Fund estimated at the beginning of the pandemic that global growth is expected to fall to −3%, making these lockdowns the worst recession since the Great Depression, and the cumulative loss to global gross domestic product during 2020 and 2021 was estimated to be around $9 trillion.<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> Therefore, in the face of additional waves of this pandemic, it is important to compare the cost-effectiveness of various strategies to reduce COVID-19 spread, the economic consequences of which might affect the lives of the majority of the world’s population. Here we performed a cost-effectiveness analysis comparing national lockdowns and the alternative “testing, tracing, and isolation” approach. The latter approach selectively isolates individuals at high exposure risk, thereby minimizing the economic impact. Our findings should be considered by decision makers during the current pandemic and future pandemics.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec2">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <sec id="sec2.1">
                <title>Model Construction</title>
                <p id="p0030">In this study, we applied a modified Susceptible, Exposed, Infectious, Recovered, and Deceased (SEIRD) model,<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> comparing 2 major strategies: (1) nonselective nationwide lockdown and (2) focused isolation of individuals at high exposure risk who will return to the workforce under social distancing measures after a 14-day isolation period. The model’s variables are compatible with currently established parameters in the literature and our calibration and rely on the actual number of deaths in Israel (according to the Ministry of Health).</p>
                <p id="p0035">Israel has a population of approximately 9 million. A simulation model of SARS-CoV-2 transmission was constructed (see <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix Figure 1</xref> in Supplemental Materials found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.09.013" id="intref0010">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.09.013</ext-link>). The model includes 6 compartments (modified SEIRD model<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref>):<list list-type="simple" id="olist0010"><list-item id="o0010"><label>1.</label><p id="p0040">Susceptible (S): Individuals susceptible to SARS-CoV-2 infection.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0015"><label>2.</label><p id="p0045">Exposed (E): Individuals infected with SARS-CoV-2, who can transmit the virus to susceptible individuals. These exposed individuals may be tested for SARS-CoV-2 and isolated accordingly. We further divided the exposed state into 2 compartments: exposed people who do not develop clinical symptoms (EA) and exposed people who will develop clinical symptoms (I).</p></list-item><list-item id="o0020"><label>3.</label><p id="p0050">Exposed asymptomatic (EA): Patients infected with SARS-CoV-2 who do not develop clinical symptoms and who can transmit the virus to susceptible patients. These patients may be tested for SARS-CoV-2 and isolated accordingly.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0025"><label>4.</label><p id="p0055">Infected (I): Symptomatic SARS-CoV-2 patients who will be completely isolated to prevent further transmission.</p></list-item><list-item id="o0030"><label>5.</label><p id="p0060">Recovered (R): Patients who were infected with SARS-CoV-2 and recovered (recovery does not confer lifelong immunity).</p></list-item><list-item id="o0035"><label>6.</label><p id="p0065">Death (D): Patients who died because of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) complications.</p></list-item></list>
</p>
                <p id="p0070">The mathematical ordinary differential equations that illustrate our model are displayed in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix Figure 1</xref> in Supplemental Materials found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.09.013" id="intref0015">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.09.013</ext-link>.</p>
                <p id="p0075">β is the transmission rate from carriers (E) to the susceptible population (S). We assume that the transmission rates from the infectious population (I) and from the carrier population (EA) are identical. However, if infectious subjects are isolated, the rate of transmission from the “I” to the “S” population will decrease. If the size of the “I” population decreases by 50% due to isolation, the rate of transmission from “I” to “S” will decrease by 50% (β1 = β × 50%). Similarly, if we isolate the “E” population, the transmission rate from “E” to “S” will decrease accordingly (β2).</p>
                <p id="p0080">θ is the the proportion of exposed individuals that will develop symptoms.</p>
                <p id="p0085">σ is the transition rate from carrier state (E) to infected state (the time from exposure to symptom onset), assuming that the incubation period has an exponential distribution.</p>
                <p id="p0090">δ is the mortality rate of the infected population.</p>
                <p id="p0095">γ is the recovery rate of the infected population.</p>
                <p id="p0100">ɑ is the transmission rate from the recovered population to the susceptible population.</p>
                <p id="p0105">R<sub>0</sub> (basic reproductive number) reflects the number of secondary infections where the whole population is susceptible. If R<sub>0</sub> &lt; 1, then the pathogen will be cleared from the population. Otherwise, the pathogen will be able to infect the whole susceptible population. Note that R<sub>0</sub>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                <p id="p0110">We estimated the number of deaths and the total cost of each strategy and calculated the cost per avoided death (denoted by incremental cost-effectiveness ratio [ICER]). Isolation costs for noninfected individuals were based on gross domestic product per capita per day in Israel ($40 270/300 days<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref>), namely $130. Since ∼30% of the individuals were working from home during the lockdown in Israel (Eurofound data<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref>) and 20% of the isolated individuals are retired, we estimated that the cost of isolating 1 individual per day is $70 (range 50-120, <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>
). The average cost of isolating infected individuals was estimated to be $250 per patient per day (150-350, <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). This number sums up loss of workdays $70 (as described above), which applies to all infected individuals. COVID-19 infection is either asymptomatic or causes mild symptoms in most patients. Severe disease typically develops only in ∼20% of infected individuals, ∼5% of which will require intensive care.<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> Thus, we estimated that ∼80% of the infected individuals will be isolated at home or in a dedicated facility, assuming an average cost of $60 per day (0.8 × $75 isolation costs per day). Hospitalization in medicine departments will be required for about 15% of the infected individuals, reaching an average cost of $75 per day (0.15 × $500 hospitalization costs per day). Intensive care unit hospitalization will be required for about 5% of the infected individuals and will cost, on average, $45 (0.05 × $900 hospitalization costs). Prices were determined according to the Ministry of Health publications. The time horizon in the model was 200 days.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>General assumptions including the range for sensitivity analysis.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>Base</th><th>Low</th><th>High</th><th>Comments</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>E0</td><td align="center">10 000</td><td align="center">5000</td><td align="center">30 000</td><td align="center">Initial number of carriers</td></tr><tr><td>I0</td><td align="center">3000</td><td align="center">2000</td><td align="center">4000</td><td align="center">Initial number of infected individuals</td></tr><tr><td>R0</td><td align="center">80</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">100</td><td align="center">Initial number of recovered individuals</td></tr><tr><td>D0</td><td align="center">12</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">Initial number of deaths</td></tr><tr><td>Cost of infected individuals (including isolation, hospitalization, and ICU, $)</td><td align="center">250</td><td align="center">150</td><td align="center">350</td><td/></tr><tr><td>Cost of isolation for 1 person per day ($)</td><td align="center">70</td><td align="center">50</td><td align="center">120</td><td/></tr><tr><td><italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub></td><td align="center">2.6</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">7.8</td><td/></tr><tr><td>γ (gamma)</td><td align="center">0.0556</td><td align="center">0.048</td><td align="center">0.071</td><td align="center">1/infectious period (14 to 21 days)</td></tr><tr><td>β (beta)</td><td align="center">0.1444</td><td align="center">0.095</td><td align="center">0.557</td><td align="center">Calculated <inline-formula><mml:math id="M2" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">×</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td>σ (sigma)</td><td align="center">0.2</td><td align="center">0.08</td><td align="center">0.2500</td><td align="center">1/incubation time (4 to 12 days)</td></tr><tr><td>δ (delta)</td><td align="center">0.001</td><td align="center">0.0005</td><td align="center">0.002</td><td align="center">Rate of deaths per day</td></tr><tr><td>θ (theta)</td><td align="center">0.8</td><td align="center">0.5</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">Proportion of exposed individuals who developed symptoms</td></tr><tr><td>RR1</td><td align="center">0.35</td><td align="center">0.25</td><td align="center">0.45</td><td align="center">Reduction in the rate of contacts due to social distancing</td></tr><tr><td>RR2</td><td align="center">0.85</td><td align="center">0.8</td><td align="center">0.9</td><td align="center">Reduction in the rate of contacts due to national lockdown</td></tr><tr><td>RR3</td><td align="center">0.90</td><td align="center">0.85</td><td align="center">0.95</td><td align="center">Reduction in the rate of contacts due to isolation</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>ICU indicates intensive care unit.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2.2">
                <title>Strategies</title>
                <p id="p0115">We define 3 levels of preventive measures:<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0015"><list-item id="u0025"><label>•</label><p id="p0120">Social distancing – maintaining a 2-meter distance between individuals not living in the same household, wearing face masks in public, and avoiding gatherings.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0030"><label>•</label><p id="p0125">National lockdown (quarantine) – separating and limiting movement of individuals by confining them to their homes to prevent exposure and infection. Individuals are allowed to leave their home for grocery shopping or medical treatment only. There is no limit on interactions among individuals living in the same household.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0035"><label>•</label><p id="p0130">Isolation – complete isolation of infected individuals or individuals at high exposure risk in a dedicated facility. Home isolation could serve as an alternative by preventing interactions with family members and avoiding the use of shared household items.</p></list-item></list>
</p>
                <p id="p0135">We focused on 2 main strategies (see <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix Table 1</xref> in Supplemental Materials found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.09.013" id="intref0020">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.09.013</ext-link>):<list list-type="simple" id="ulist0020"><list-item id="u0040"><label>•</label><p id="p0140">Strategy 1: National lockdown of the susceptible population. Individuals who have essential occupations, as determined by government decisions, will not be quarantined and will be required to maintain social distancing. All known exposed individuals will be completely isolated for a 14-day period according to the standard recommendations by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref>), which are also adopted in Israel.</p></list-item><list-item id="u0045"><label>•</label><p id="p0145">Strategy 2: The susceptible population will be required to maintain social distancing. All known exposed individuals will be isolated. Individuals who are at high exposure risk because of contact with an infected individual or a carrier will be located using detailed epidemiological tracing and/or mobile phone and satellite technology. These people will be isolated for a 14-day period. Under this strategy, only the high exposure risk group will be quarantined, while most of the susceptible population will go back to the workforce under social distancing. In addition to the 2 main strategies mentioned previously, we estimated the number of deaths and the size of the infectious population, without any interventions. The list of parameters in the model as well as the values used for sensitivity analysis are presented in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p></list-item></list>
</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2.3">
                <title>Parameter Estimation and Calibration</title>
                <p id="p0150">To calibrate the model, we fitted the observed number of COVID-19 reported deaths between March 27 and June 30, 2020 in Israel to the number of deaths predicted by the model. We used a simulation annealing method to find the model parameters values. The measure of fitting used the sum of squared errors of the number of deaths obtained by the model output and the observed number of COVID-19 reported deaths from March 27 to June 30, 2020 in Israel.</p>
                <p id="p0155">The following parameter estimates were used to construct the model (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>): Exposed (Carriers E0) was defined as the number of infected individuals who are currently undocumented. We determined the estimate of undocumented carriers to 10 000 according to the calibration. This is compatible with a screening conducted in Iceland,<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> where 0.6%-0.8% of the population were carriers and 46%-59% have developed symptoms. To validate the model, we compared the observed number of deaths in Israel from April 22 to June 30, 2020 to the number of deaths predicted by the model and observed a nearly perfect fit (see <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix Figure 2</xref> in Supplemental Materials found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.09.013" id="intref0025">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.09.013</ext-link>). The initial number of infected individuals (I0) was determined according to the Israeli Ministry of Health publications on March 27, 2020. The number of susceptible individuals was defined as a rounded approximation of the population in Israel (9 million) after subtracting the infected and undocumented carriers.</p>
                <p id="p0160">An estimation of 18 days was used to calculate the recovery rate (γ).<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> The average incubation period (σ) was estimated to be ∼5.1 days.<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref>
</p>
                <p id="p0165">We used R<sub>0</sub> = 2.6 (range 2.0-7.2),<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> assuming that the infectious period is 18 days.<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> Thus the transmission rate from infected (carrier) patients to the susceptible population (β) was 0.144 (range 0.095 to 0.557).<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> As all individuals entering Israel from abroad are isolated, we did not include imported cases in the model. Case fatality rates vary among different countries, ranging from 7.2% in Italy to 0.2% in Germany.<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref> Thus, for the rate of death (δ) in our basic model we considered a moderate estimate of 1.8% or 0.001 per day over 18 days of infection.</p>
                <p id="p0170">RR1-3 represents the reduction rate in contacts due to the implicated preventive measures. The estimation of these parameters was based on the calibration analysis (see <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix Figure 2</xref> in Supplemental Materials found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.09.013" id="intref0030">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.09.013</ext-link>).</p>
                <p id="p0175">The assumptions used to describe the proportion of the population in compliance with the different levels of preventive measures for each strategy are described in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix Table 2</xref> in Supplemental Materials found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.09.013" id="intref0035">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.09.013</ext-link>. For example, we assumed that in strategy 1, the proportion of the susceptible population under lockdown (r_S2) will be 80%, and the proportion of the carrier population that is under isolation in both strategies (r1_E, r2_E) was estimated at 30%. The time horizon was 200 days; therefore, the discount rate was 0. In addition, we assumed that the cost of isolation in strategy 1 is only for 28 days.</p>
                <p id="p0180">The analysis was performed using MATLAB.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2.4">
                <title>Sensitivity Analysis</title>
                <p id="p0185">One-way sensitivity analysis was used for all the parameters in the model (see <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> and <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix Table 2</xref> for the range used for the sensitivity analysis). A tornado diagram was constructed for the ICER and the number of deaths in each strategy.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2.5">
                <title>Probabilistic Sensitivity Analysis</title>
                <p id="p0190">A probabilistic sensitivity analysis (Monte Carlo simulation) was performed to assess the effects of ranging base case variables on the model outcomes with 1000 draws from probability model parameters.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2.6">
                <title>Ethical Considerations</title>
                <p id="p0195">The study has received an institutional review board exemption from the local institute (Rabin Medical Center).</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec3">
              <title>Results</title>
              <p id="p0200">We first tested our model with strategy 1: national lockdown, isolation of all infected individuals, and a 14-day isolation period for the high exposure risk group. Applying this strategy will yield a peak of 7671 infected individuals followed by a rapid decline (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>
, right upper panel) with a total of 9046 infected individuals over the 200-day period. Under this strategy, the number of expected deaths is 303.5 (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>, right lower panel). This number will be reached after ∼110 days. In strategy 2, infected individuals will remain under isolation. However, in strategy 2, instead of a national lockdown, only high exposure risk individuals will be isolated. Following 14 days of isolation, these individuals will return to the workforce while maintaining social distancing. Under these conditions, the maximum number of infected individuals will slightly increase to 19 646, with a total of 38 761 infected individuals over the 200-day period (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>
, right upper panel). The total number of deaths will increase to 577.8 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>, right lower panel).<fig id="fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Infection dynamics under national lockdown (strategy 1). The graphs display the dynamics within the 6 compartments over time. Susceptible (S, blue); Infected (I, red); Carrier (yellow, E); Carrier asymptomatic (yellow, EA); Recovered (R, green), Dead (D, black).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Infection dynamics during isolation of individuals at high risk of exposure (strategy 2). Graphs are labeled as described in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2_lrg"/></fig></p>
              <p id="p0205"><xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix Table 3</xref> in Supplemental Materials found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.09.013" id="intref0040">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.09.013</ext-link> summarizes the costs and the number of expected deaths under each strategy. Factoring the cost of lost workdays and isolation enabled us to calculate the incremental cost. The incremental cost divided by the incremental number of deaths yields the incremental cost-effectiveness ratio (ICER). The calculated cost for strategy 1 was $12 495 million, and for strategy 2 it was $122.9 million. The expected number of deaths was 303.5 for strategy 1 and 577.8 for strategy 2. Thus, incremental cost would be $12 372 million and the incremental number of deaths would be 274, while the resulting ICER would be $45.1 million. Thus, under these conditions, the cost of preventing 1 death case would be $45 104 156.</p>
              <p id="p0210">One quality-adjusted life-year (QALY) equals 1 year of healthy life, and since the majority of patients who succumbed to COVID-19 were older non-healthy individuals (mean age ∼80 in Israel with a life expectancy of 8.56 years), we estimated that, on average, every death case will result in a loss of 10 QALYs. Assuming that 1 case of death is equivalent to a loss of 10 QALYs, the ICER would be $45 104 156 divided by 10, resulting in $4.5 million per QALY. This number is much higher than the internationally accepted ICER threshold values (between $50 000 and 150 000 per QALY<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref>). Furthermore, this number is higher than the $100 000-150 000 per QALY recommended by Neumann et al as the threshold of willingness to pay.<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref> Notably, in Israel, the ICER threshold value is estimated at around $15 243-17 366 per QALY.<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref>
</p>
              <p id="p0215">Another parameter used to assess the cost of death in other fields is the value of a statistical life, a statistical measure of the willingness to pay for small reductions in mortality risks, estimated to be ∼$10 000 000.<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> Similarly, this value is much lower than our calculated ICER.</p>
              <p id="p0220">The results of a 1-way sensitivity analysis for both strategies are displayed in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>
. The virus transmission rate (β) and the daily mortality rate (δ) were among the variables with the strongest influence on ICER (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). A 1-way sensitivity analysis showing the effect of these parameters on ICER is displayed in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix Figure 3</xref> in Supplemental Materials found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.09.013" id="intref0045">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.09.013</ext-link>.<fig id="fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Sensitivity analysis (tornado diagram) of the incremental cost-effectiveness ratio (ICER) between the 2 strategies.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3_lrg"/><attrib>Red bars indicate that the value was produced by the lower bound (low), and dark blue bars indicate that the value was produced by the upper bound (high).</attrib></fig></p>
              <p id="p0225">An additional sensitivity analysis was performed for the number of expected deaths under both strategies. As shown in <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix Figure 4</xref>, the initial carrier population, the daily mortality rate (δ), and the virus transmission rate (β) were the parameters with the greatest effect on the death rate. A probabilistic sensitivity analysis of the cumulative death for each strategy and of the estimated distribution of the ICER are displayed in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref> and <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>
, respectively. The median difference between strategy 1 and 2 in the number of deaths is 124 (interquartile range: 71-221), and the median ICER is $49.6 million (interquartile range: 22.7-220.1 million).<fig id="fig4"><label>Figure. 4</label><caption><p>Probabilistic sensitivity analysis for the number of deaths in each strategy. A probabilistic sensitivity analysis was used to assess the probability distribution of the expected number of deaths according to each strategy.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr4_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Probabilistic sensitivity analysis for the ICER. A probabilistic sensitivity analysis was used to assess the probability distribution of the ICER (expressed in millions of US $). The graph was truncated at $500 million.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr5_lrg"/></fig></p>
              <p id="p0230">Finally, we tested our model without any intervention. Starting from a baseline of 10 000 carriers and 3000 infected individuals, the maximal number of infected individuals is predicted to be 1.94 million (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix Figure 5</xref>, right upper panel). This number will be reached after 200 days. Under these conditions, the expected number of deaths will be 118 130 (<xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix Figure 5</xref>, right lower panel).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec4">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p id="p0235">In this study, we applied cost-effectiveness analysis tools to distinguish between 2 different strategies aimed to slow down the virus spread. We show that a national lockdown (strategy 1) will result in a total of ∼19 646 infected individuals and around 303 deaths over a period of 200 days. An alternative “testing, tracing, and isolation” approach (strategy 2) in which only individuals with a high exposure risk are isolated will result in a total of 38 761 infected individuals and 577.8 deaths. Overall, strategy 1 is expected to save ∼274 more lives, but with a cost of $ 45.1 million to prevent 1 death case, compared to the more focused approach.</p>
              <p id="p0240">One of the major concerns during a pandemic is that the number of patients needing intensive care and mechanical ventilation will overwhelm the local healthcare system. According to our model, a no-intervention approach will result in an unacceptable number of infected individuals (1.94 million) and an extremely high death rate (∼118 130), and therefore is not realistic. In contrast, the difference in the peak number of infected patients between the 2 main strategies tested is ∼1375 patients, in favor of strategy 1. Assuming that ∼20% of the patients are at risk of developing a severe form of the disease,<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> this translates into an additional 275 potential hospitalizations and mechanical ventilations at the peak, which is an acceptable burden.</p>
              <p id="p0245">As with similar models, the validity of this model is based on the correct assumption of the various parameters. Since SARS-CoV-2 is a new virus and the exact infection rates in the population are still unknown, these parameters are subject to variations and may change over time. To validate our model, we calibrated it by comparing the rate of deaths according to our model assumptions with the real-time published numbers of these parameters in Israel (see <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">Appendix Figure 2</xref> in Supplemental Materials found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.09.013" id="intref0050">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.09.013</ext-link>). The obtained graphs were strikingly similar, further confirming our model.</p>
              <p id="p0250">One major limitation of compartment models is that they assume a homogeneous population, which is not the case in many countries. In Israel, for example, the reproductive number (R<sub>0</sub>) is most probably higher among some religious groups. This might alter the infection dynamics and affect the outcome of the model. If R<sub>0</sub> is indeed significantly higher in these specific populations, the average R<sub>0</sub> used in the model will increase. This implies higher infection and death rates. However, if this is indeed the case, specific lockdown measures could be applied to these “red zones.” However, since exact data regarding the R<sub>0</sub> in these populations is not available, our model does not consider areas with different R<sub>0</sub> within the country.</p>
              <p id="p0255">Our sensitivity analysis indicates that the transmission rate (β) is the parameter with the most influence on ICER. β relies on R<sub>0</sub>, which might change, and on the infectious period, which will most likely remain the same. However, since a similar R<sub>0</sub> is used for modeling both strategies, we believe that the difference in the number of deaths and ICER will remain similar.</p>
              <p id="p0260">Obviously, strategy 2 of “testing, tracing and isolation,” largely representing the steps successfully undertaken by South Korea to handle the situation, demands 2 critical components: (1) intensive epidemiological investigations of infected patients combined with surveillance to trace possible interactions and (2) availability of enough testing kits and facilities to enable a large number of daily polymerase chain reaction tests to isolate subjects at high exposure risk.</p>
              <p id="p0265">Obviously, the intensive epidemiological investigations, necessary to define people at high exposure risk who must be isolated, implies massive use of mobile phone and satellite technology, thereby violating citizens’ privacy rights. Therefore, decision makers must carefully weigh their options, keeping in mind the very high economic price associated with national lockdown strategies.</p>
              <p id="p0270">In summary, in this cost-effectiveness analysis, we show that over time a strategy of national lockdown is moderately superior to a strategy of focused isolation in terms of reducing death rates but involves extremely high economic costs to prevent 1 case of death. These economic costs might add to the future economic consequences of this pandemic; thus these options should be carefully considered and balanced.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list id="cebib0010">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="bib1">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bedford</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Enria</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Giesecke</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>COVID-19: towards controlling of a pandemic</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet</source>
                  <volume>395</volume>
                  <issue>10229</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1015</fpage>
                  <lpage>1018</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32197103</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib2">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref2">
                  <article-title>Worldometers.info</article-title>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.worldometers.info/" id="intref0060">https://www.worldometers.info/</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib3">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref3">
                  <article-title>Coronavirus disease (COVID-19) outbreak. World Health Organisation</article-title>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019" id="intref0065">https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib4">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Onder</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rezza</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brusaferro</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Case-fatality rate and characteristics of patients dying in relation to COVID-19 in Italy</article-title>
                  <source>JAMA</source>
                  <volume>12;323</volume>
                  <issue>18</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1775</fpage>
                  <lpage>1776</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib5">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Emanuel</surname>
                      <given-names>E.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Persad</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Upshur</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Fair allocation of scarce medical resources in the time of COVID-19</article-title>
                  <source>N Engl J Med</source>
                  <volume>382</volume>
                  <issue>21</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>2049</fpage>
                  <lpage>2055</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32202722</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib6">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cohen</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kupferschmidt</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Countries test tactics in “war” against COVID-19</article-title>
                  <source>Science</source>
                  <volume>367</volume>
                  <issue>6484</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1287</fpage>
                  <lpage>1288</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32193299</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib7">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bonaccorsi</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pierri</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cinelli</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Economic and social consequences of human mobility restrictions under COVID-19</article-title>
                  <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
                  <volume>117</volume>
                  <issue>27</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>15530</fpage>
                  <lpage>15535</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32554604</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib8">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>McKee</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stuckler</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>If the world fails to protect the economy, COVID-19 will damage health not just now but also in the future</article-title>
                  <source>Nat Med</source>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>640</fpage>
                  <lpage>642</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32273610</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib9">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref9">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gopinath</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The great lockdown: worst economic downturn since the Great Depression. International Monetary Fund</article-title>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://blogs.imf.org/2020/04/14/the-great-lockdown-worst-economic-downturn-since-the-great-depression/" id="intref0070">https://blogs.imf.org/2020/04/14/the-great-lockdown-worst-economic-downturn-since-the-great-depression/</ext-link>
                  <comment>Accessed April 14, 2020.</comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>M.Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Graef</surname>
                      <given-names>J.R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Karsai</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Global dynamics of a SEIR model with varying total population size</article-title>
                  <source>Math Biosci</source>
                  <volume>160</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>1999</year>
                  <fpage>191</fpage>
                  <lpage>213</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10472754</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref11">
                  <article-title>Economic indicators: Israeli economic data. Bank of Israel</article-title>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.boi.org.il/en/DataAndStatistics/Pages/Indicators.aspx?Level=1&amp;IndicatorId=1&amp;sId=0" id="intref0075">https://www.boi.org.il/en/DataAndStatistics/Pages/Indicators.aspx?Level=1&amp;IndicatorId=1&amp;sId=0</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref12">
                  <article-title>Living, working and COVID-19 dataset. Eurofound</article-title>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.eurofound.europa.eu/data/covid-19/working-teleworking" id="intref0080">https://www.eurofound.europa.eu/data/covid-19/working-teleworking</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Guan</surname>
                      <given-names>W.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ni</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hu</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Clinical characteristics of coronavirus disease 2019 in China</article-title>
                  <source>N Engl J Med</source>
                  <volume>382</volume>
                  <issue>18</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1708</fpage>
                  <lpage>1720</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32109013</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref14">
                  <article-title>When to quarantine. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</article-title>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/if-you-are-sick/quarantine.html" id="intref0085">https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/if-you-are-sick/quarantine.html</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gudbjartsson</surname>
                      <given-names>D.F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Helgason</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jonsson</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Spread of SARS-CoV-2 in the Icelandic population</article-title>
                  <source>N Engl J Med</source>
                  <volume>382</volume>
                  <issue>24</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>2302</fpage>
                  <lpage>2315</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32289214</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib16">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref16">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Acemoglu</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chernozhukov</surname>
                      <given-names>V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Werning</surname>
                      <given-names>I.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Whinston</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Optimal targeted lockdowns in a multi-group SIR model. National Bureau of Economic Research Working Paper Series</chapter-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <comment>No. 27102</comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib17">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lauer</surname>
                      <given-names>S.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Grantz</surname>
                      <given-names>K.H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bi</surname>
                      <given-names>Q.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The incubation period of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) from publicly reported confirmed cases: estimation and application</article-title>
                  <source>Ann Intern Med</source>
                  <volume>172</volume>
                  <issue>9</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>577</fpage>
                  <lpage>582</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32150748</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib18">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xu</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhu</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Characteristics of pediatric SARS-CoV-2 infection and potential evidence for persistent fecal viral shedding</article-title>
                  <source>Nat Med</source>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>502</fpage>
                  <lpage>505</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32284613</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib19">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lan</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xu</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ye</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Positive RT-PCR test results in patients recovered from COVID-19</article-title>
                  <source>JAMA</source>
                  <volume>21;323</volume>
                  <issue>15</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1502</fpage>
                  <lpage>1503</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib20">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref20">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Roser</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ritchie</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ortiz-Ospina</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Coronavirus disease (COVID-19). Our World in Data</article-title>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ourworldindata.org/coronavirus" id="intref0090">https://ourworldindata.org/coronavirus</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib21">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" id="sref21">
                  <article-title>2020 value assessment framework: final framework. Institute for Clinical and Economic Review (ICER)</article-title>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://icer-review.org/methodology/icers-methods/icer-value-assessment-framework-2/" id="intref0095">https://icer-review.org/methodology/icers-methods/icer-value-assessment-framework-2/</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib22">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Neumann</surname>
                      <given-names>P.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cohen</surname>
                      <given-names>J.T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Weinstein</surname>
                      <given-names>M.C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Updating cost-effectiveness: the curious resilience of the $50,000-per-QALY threshold</article-title>
                  <source>N Engl J Med</source>
                  <volume>371</volume>
                  <issue>9</issue>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <fpage>796</fpage>
                  <lpage>797</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25162885</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib23">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Woods</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Revill</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sculpher</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Claxton</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Country-level cost-effectiveness thresholds: initial estimates and the need for further research</article-title>
                  <source>Value Health</source>
                  <volume>19</volume>
                  <issue>8</issue>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <fpage>929</fpage>
                  <lpage>935</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27987642</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib24">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref24">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kip</surname>
                      <given-names>V.W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>The value of life. Harvard John M Olin Discussion Paper Series</chapter-title>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <fpage>517</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
            <sec id="appsec1" sec-type="supplementary-material">
              <title>Supplemental Materials</title>
              <p id="p0305">
                <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1">
                  <caption>
                    <title>Figs. E1-E5 and Tables E1-E3</title>
                  </caption>
                  <media xlink:href="mmc1.pdf"/>
                </supplementary-material>
              </p>
            </sec>
            <ack id="ack0010">
              <p id="p0315"><bold>Author Contributions:</bold><italic>Concept and design:</italic> Shlomai, Sklan, M. Leshno</p>
              <p id="p0320"><italic>Acquisition of data:</italic> Shlomai, M. Leshno</p>
              <p id="p0325"><italic>Analysis and interpretation of data:</italic> Shlomai, Sklan, M. Leshno</p>
              <p id="p0330"><italic>Drafting of the manuscript:</italic> Shlomai, A. Leshno, Sklan, M. Leshno</p>
              <p id="p0335"><italic>Critical revision of the paper for important intellectual content:</italic> Shlomai, A. Leshno, Sklan, M. Leshno</p>
              <p id="p0340"><italic>Administrative, technical, or logistic support:</italic> A. Leshno</p>
              <p id="p0290"><bold>Conflict of Interest Disclosures:</bold> The authors reported no conflicts of interest.</p>
              <p id="p0295"><bold>Funding/Support:</bold> The authors received no financial support for this research.</p>
              <p id="p0300"><bold>Acknowledgment:</bold> We thank Gerda Kessler for her assistance in editing this manuscript. Dr Sklan is grateful to the Milner foundation for its support.</p>
            </ack>
            <fn-group>
              <fn id="appsec2" fn-type="supplementary-material">
                <p id="p0310">Supplementary data associated with this article can be found in the online version at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.09.013" id="intref0055">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jval.2020.09.013</ext-link>.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
