<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-03-11T00:51:07Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8320402" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8320402</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-29</datestamp>
        <setSpec>pheelsevier</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.xsd" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Infect Dis</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Infect Dis</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>International Journal of Infectious Diseases</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">1201-9712</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1878-3511</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>The Author(s). Published by Elsevier Ltd on behalf of International Society for Infectious Diseases.</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC8320402</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8320402</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">8320402</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34333119</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pii">S1201-9712(21)00614-7</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2021.07.058</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Effect of Non-lockdown Social Distancing and Testing-Contact Tracing During a COVID-19 Outbreak in Daegu, South Korea, February to April 2020: A Modeling Study</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0001">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Chen</surname>
                    <given-names>Yi-Hsuan</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
                  <xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">†</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0002">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Fang</surname>
                    <given-names>Chi-Tai</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">d</xref>
                  <xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">†</xref>
                  <xref rid="cor0001" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0003">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Huang</surname>
                    <given-names>Yu-Ling</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="aff0001"><label>a</label>Institute of Epidemiology and Preventive Medicine, College of Public Health, National Taiwan University, Taipei, Taiwan</aff>
                <aff id="aff0002"><label>b</label>Ministry of Health and Welfare and National Taiwan University Infectious Diseases Research and Education Center, Taipei, Taiwan</aff>
                <aff id="aff0003"><label>c</label>Epidemiology Advisor, Taiwan Central Epidemic Command for COVID-19, Taipei, Taiwan</aff>
                <aff id="aff0004"><label>d</label>Division of Infectious Diseases, Department of Internal Medicine, National Taiwan University Hospital, Taipei, Taiwan</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor0001"><label>⁎</label><bold>Corresponding author</bold>: Professor Chi-Tai Fang, Institute of Epidemiology and Preventive Medicine, College of Public Health, National Taiwan University, Taipei, Taiwan, 17 Xuzhou Road, Taipei 100, Taiwan; Tel: +886-2-33668035.</corresp>
                <fn id="fn1">
                  <label>†</label>
                  <p id="notep0001">These authors contributed equally.</p>
                </fn>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>29</day>
                <month>7</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.-->
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <month>9</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>29</day>
                <month>7</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>110</volume>
              <fpage>213</fpage>
              <lpage>221</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>25</day>
                  <month>4</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>22</day>
                  <month>7</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>24</day>
                  <month>7</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2021 The Author(s)</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
                <license>
                  <license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="abs0002">
                <sec>
                  <title>Objective</title>
                  <p>In Spring 2020, South Korea applied non-lockdown social distancing (avoiding mass gathering and non-essential social engagement, without restricting the movement of people who were not patients or contacts), testing-and-isolation (testing), and tracing-and-quarantine the contacts (contact tracing) to successfully control the first large-scale COVID-19 outbreak outside China. However, the relative contributions of these two interventions remain uncertain.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods</title>
                  <p>We constructed an SEIR model of SARS-CoV-2 transmission (disproportionately through superspreading events) and fit the model to outbreak data in Daegu, South Korea, from February to April 2020. We assessed the effect of non-lockdown social distancing (population-wide control measures) and/or testing-contact tracing (individual-specific control measures), alone or combined, in terms of the basic reproductive number (R0) and the trajectory of the epidemic.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>The point estimate for baseline R0 is 3.6 (sensitivity analyses range: 2.3 to 5.6). Combined interventions of non-lockdown social distancing and testing-contact tracing can suppress R0 to less than one and rapidly contain the epidemic, even under the worst scenario with a high baseline R0 of 5.6. In contrast, either intervention alone will fail to suppress R0. Non-lockdown social distancing alone just postpones the peak of the epidemic, while testing-contact tracing alone only flattens the curve but does not contain the outbreak.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusions</title>
                  <p>To successfully control a large-scale COVID-19 outbreak, both non-lockdown social distancing and testing-contact tracing must be implemented. The two interventions are synergistic.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="sec0001">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p id="para0011">By July 19, 2021, there were more than 188 million confirmed cases of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) and 4 million deaths globally (<xref rid="bib0043" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization 2021</xref>). Strict lockdown (confining people at home or shelter) has been widely enforced to limit the spread of its etiological agent, severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2) (<xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Kraemer et al., 2020</xref>), but remains highly controversial due to the profound negative impacts on the society (<xref rid="bib0038" ref-type="bibr">The Great Barrington Declaration 2021</xref>). There is an urgent need for alternative strategies to control this pandemic.</p>
              <p id="para0012">On February 18, 2020, the authority detected a cluster of COVID-19 cases in Daegu, South Korea, which rapidly escalated to the first large-scale outbreak outside of China (<xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2020</xref>). Instead of lockdown, South Korea used non-lockdown social distancing (avoiding mass gathering and non-essential social engagement, without restricting the movement of people who are not patients or contacts) combined with quarantining infectious individuals through testing-and-isolation (testing) and tracing-and-quarantine the contacts (contact tracing) and controlled the outbreak rapidly within 4 weeks (<xref rid="bib0034" ref-type="bibr">Ryu et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">Korea Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Park et al., 2020</xref>). However, non-lockdown social distancing yielded mixed results elsewhere (<xref rid="bib0043" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization 2021</xref>), for which the causes remain unsettled.</p>
              <p id="para0013">We hypothesize that prompt quarantining of infectious persons is a prerequisite for the success of a less strict policy on social activities. This modeling study aimed to examine this hypothesis by assessing the effects of non-lockdown social distancing and testing-contact tracing, alone or combined, on the basic reproductive number (R0) of SARS-CoV-2 and the trajectory of the COVID-19 outbreak in Daegu, South Korea, February to April 2020.</p>
              <p id="para0014">This work was initiated, upon request, on February 25, 2020, to help South Korea to control the COVID-19 outbreak in Daegu. Preliminary results had been presented in special meetings with the Korean Mission in Taipei on February 25 and March 6, 2020, and the meeting report had been delivered to the South Korean government. This work had been presented as an oral abstract INT4622 at the International AIDS Society COVID-19 Conference: Prevention (Virtual) on February 2, 2021.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0002">
              <title>Materials and Methods</title>
              <sec id="sec0003">
                <title>Ethics statement</title>
                <p id="para0015">This is a modeling study based on Korean Centers for Disease Control (KCDC) daily statistics without identifiable individual data, and therefore, does not require ethical review and approval.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0004">
                <title>SEIR Model</title>
                <p id="para0016">We constructed a dynamic model of SARS-CoV-2 transmission disproportionately through superspreading events (SSEs) (<xref rid="bib0029" ref-type="bibr">Lloyd-Smith et al., 2005</xref>, <xref rid="bib0036" ref-type="bibr">'Superspreader' in South Korea infects nearly 40 people with coronavirus, 2021</xref>) and fit the model to outbreak data in Daegu, South Korea, from February to April 2020. An earlier version of our model, specifically adapted to inform Taiwan's national policymaking, had been published (<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Chen and Fang, 2021</xref>). The SEIR model (<xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>
) includes key features in the natural history of SARS-CoV-2 infection, including an incubation period of 3.0 days (<xref rid="bib0026" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2020</xref>), a presymptomatic infectious period of 2.5 days (<xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">He et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Slifka and Gao, 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0041" ref-type="bibr">Wei et al., 2020</xref>), and an infectious duration of 8.5 days (up to 6.0 days after illness onset) (<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Cheng et al., 2020</xref>) (all values are mean duration). The model considers a very high heterogeneity in SARS-CoV-2 transmission (<xref rid="bib0029" ref-type="bibr">Lloyd-Smith et al., 2005</xref>, <xref rid="bib0036" ref-type="bibr">'Superspreader' in South Korea infects nearly 40 people with coronavirus, 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">Lim et al., 2021</xref>), with 14.7% of infected individuals as superspreaders who caused 80% of new secondary infections (<xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">Lim et al., 2021</xref>). Infectious individuals, superspreaders or non-superspreaders, can be asymptomatic throughout the course (10%) (<xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">Chang, 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0042" ref-type="bibr">Wong et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">Arons et al., 2020</xref>). Infectiousness of asymptomatic infection is 30% lower than that of symptomatic infections (<xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">Chaw et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">Hu et al., 2021</xref>). Model parameters are listed in <xref rid="tbl0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>
. Model equations are available in Supplementary Material 1.<fig id="fig0001"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Model structure</p><p>S: Susceptible; E: Latent (Infected but not yet infectious); I<sub>SSE</sub>: Infectious and symptomatic superspreaders; I<sub>non-SSE</sub>: Infectious and symptomatic non-superspreaders; A<sub>SSE</sub>: Infectious but asymptomatic superspreaders; A<sub>non-SSE</sub>: Infectious but asymptomatic non-superspreaders; H: Hospitalized due to severe/critical COVID-19; R: Recovered; XQ: Quarantine of uninfected contacts; Q<sub>R</sub>: Isolation/quarantine of infected patients/contacts who either develop a mild illness or remain asymptomatic. Q<sub>H</sub>: Isolation/quarantine of infected patients/contacts who develop severe/critical illnesses.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0001">Figure 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Model parameters</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0007">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top">Parameters</th><th valign="top">Value</th><th valign="top">Derivation and Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top">Transmission probability per contact (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>)</td><td valign="top">0.0437 (Daegu, South Korea)</td><td valign="top">1. The point estimates for baseline R0 and the transmission probability per contact (<italic>b</italic>) in Wuhan, China, were 3.6 and 0.04405, respectively, by fitting the model to the slope of the exponential phase, January 6 to January 22, 2020, Wuhan, China. (<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention 2020</xref>).2. Based on a baseline R0 of 3.6 for the SARS-CoV-2 strain (imported from Wuhan, China) which initiated the Daegu outbreak, the point estimate for the transmission probability per contact (<italic>b</italic>) in Daegu, South Korea is 0.0437, by solving the <xref rid="eqn0001" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (1)</xref> (see Method section).</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">The proportion of superspreaders among infectious patients (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M2" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>)</td><td valign="top">14.7%</td><td valign="top">Based on South Korean data (<xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">Lim et al., 2021</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Contact rate in SSE group (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M3" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>)</td><td valign="top">54.4/day (mean)</td><td valign="top">Based on (1) an average contact rate of 10/day (<xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">Wallinga et al., 2006</xref>); and(2) a <inline-formula><mml:math id="M4" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> ratio of 23.13 (estimated by South Korean data: 14.7% superspreaders caused 80% secondary infections) (<xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">Lim et al., 2021</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Contact rate in the non-SSE group (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M5" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>)</td><td valign="top">2.4/day (mean)</td><td valign="top">Based on (1) an average contact rate of 10/day (<xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">Wallinga et al., 2006</xref>), and (2) a <inline-formula><mml:math id="M6" altimg="si6.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> ratio of 23.13 (estimated by South Korean data: 14.7% of the superspreaders caused 80% of the secondary infections) (<xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">Lim et al., 2021</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">The incubation period (from infection to the onset of illnesses)</td><td valign="top">3.0 days (Daegu, South Korea) (mean)</td><td valign="top">The incubation period can be varied by the different settings and different periods of the COVID-19 pandemic (<xref rid="bib0044" ref-type="bibr">Xin et al., 2021</xref>)1. The point estimate for the incubation period in Wuhan, China, was 5.5 days (mean) (<xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">Lauer et al., 2020</xref>).2. The point estimate for the incubation period in Daegu, South Korea, was 3.0 days (median) (<xref rid="bib0026" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2020</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Presymptomatic infectious period before the onset of illnesses</td><td valign="top">2.5 days (mean)</td><td valign="top">(<xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">He et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Slifka and Gao, 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0041" ref-type="bibr">Wei et al., 2020</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">The latency period (infected but non-infectious) (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M7" altimg="si7.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>)</td><td valign="top">0.5 days (Daegu, South Korea) (mean)</td><td valign="top">1. The point estimate for the bvlatency period in Wuhan, China was 3.0 days, i.e.5.5 days (incubation period) (<xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">Lauer et al., 2020</xref>) minus 2.5 days (pre-symptomatic infectious period before the onset of illnesses) (<xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">He et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Slifka and Gao, 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0041" ref-type="bibr">Wei et al., 2020</xref>) (the uncertainty range: 0–5 days)2. The point estimate for the latency period in Daegu, South Korea was 0.5 days, i.e., 3.0 days (incubation period) (<xref rid="bib0026" ref-type="bibr">Lee et al., 2020</xref>) minus 2.5 days (the presymptomatic infectious period before the onset of illnesses) (<xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">He et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Slifka and Gao, 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0041" ref-type="bibr">Wei et al., 2020</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">The infectious duration after the onset of illnesses</td><td valign="top">6.0 days (mean)(uncertainty range: 4.6 to 9.1 days).</td><td valign="top">The point estimate is based on Taiwan contact-tracing data (<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Cheng et al., 2020</xref>) and is in line with Chinese clinical study data:4.6 days (onset to first medical visit (<xref rid="bib0027" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2020</xref>))to 9.1 days (onset to hospitalization (<xref rid="bib0027" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2020</xref>))(assume that patients were isolated after medical visits or hospitalization).</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">The infectious period (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M8" altimg="si8.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>)</td><td valign="top">8.5 days (mean) (uncertainty range: 7.1 to 11.6 days, i.e., 4.6 to 9.1 days plus 2.5 days, respectively)</td><td valign="top">2.5 infectious days before the onset of symptoms plus 6.0 infectious days after the onset of symptoms.We assume that asymptomatic infections have the same total infectious period.</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Infection-related mortality among severe/critical cases (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M9" altimg="si9.svg"><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>)</td><td valign="top">12%</td><td valign="top"><xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr">(The Novel Coronavirus Pneumonia Emergency Response Epidemiology Team, 2020)</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">The infection-related mortality rate in those who were hospitalized (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M10" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>)</td><td valign="top">0.0097 /day</td><td valign="top">Calculated by the formula (<xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">Keeling and Rohani, 2008</xref>)m = (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M11" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>)<inline-formula><mml:math id="M12" altimg="si12.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.33em"/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">The natural-causes mortality rate (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M13" altimg="si13.svg"><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>)</td><td valign="top">1/78.5 years</td><td valign="top">(<xref rid="bib0039" ref-type="bibr">The World Bank 2021</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">The birth rate (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M14" altimg="si13.svg"><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>)</td><td valign="top">1/78.5 years</td><td valign="top">We assume a stable population size (birth rate identical to natural-cause death rate).</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">The proportion of asymptomatic infection (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M15" altimg="si14.svg"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>)</td><td valign="top">10%</td><td valign="top">(<xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">Chang, 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0042" ref-type="bibr">Wong et al., 2020</xref>), (<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">Arons et al., 2020</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">The ratio of transmission probability of asymptomatic patients versus symptomatic patients (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M16" altimg="si15.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>)</td><td valign="top">0.7</td><td valign="top">(<xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">Chaw et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">Hu et al., 2021</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">The proportion of severe/ critical cases (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M17" altimg="si16.svg"><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>)</td><td valign="top">19%</td><td valign="top"><xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr">(The Novel Coronavirus Pneumonia Emergency Response Epidemiology Team, 2020)</xref></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Time from hospitalization to recovery among severe/critical patients (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M18" altimg="si17.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>)</td><td valign="top">14 days (mean)</td><td valign="top">(<xref rid="bib0017" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2020</xref>).</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Time from onset of symptoms to laboratory confirmation</td><td valign="top">5.3 days</td><td valign="top">For the Shincheonji religious group (<xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2020</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Time from the onset of infectiousness to quarantine (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M19" altimg="si18.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>)</td><td valign="top">7.8 days (mean)</td><td valign="top">5.3 days plus 2.5 days (the presymptomatic infectious period) before the onset of illnesses (<xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">He et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Slifka and Gao, 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0041" ref-type="bibr">Wei et al., 2020</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">The proportion of contact tracing (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M20" altimg="si19.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>)</td><td valign="top">0% to 90%</td><td valign="top">Intervention scenarios</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">The duration of quarantine among mild cases (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M21" altimg="si20.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>)</td><td valign="top">14 days</td><td valign="top">Intervention scenario, based on current standard practice</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">The duration from quarantine to hospitalization among severe/critical patients (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M22" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>)</td><td valign="top">3 days (mean)</td><td valign="top">7 days (mean duration from the onset of symptom to the onset of severe disease (<xref rid="bib0017" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2020</xref>)), minus 4 days (mean duration from the onset of symptom to diagnosis in the intervention scenario).</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">The fraction of the contact rate (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M23" altimg="si22.svg"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>) rendered less effective under social distancing</td><td valign="top">0% to 90%</td><td valign="top">Intervention scenarios</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">The proportion (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M24" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>) of decrease in transmission probability per contact (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M25" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>) under social distancing</td><td valign="top">90%</td><td valign="top">(<xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">Chu et al., 2020</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">The population size (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M26" altimg="si24.svg"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>)</td><td valign="top">30,000 (10,000 to 50,000)</td><td valign="top">The estimated number of Shincheonji Church members and their associates in Daegu, South Korea</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Initial infectious population</td><td valign="top">5</td><td valign="top">Initial condition of simulation.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="fig0002"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Simulating the Daegu outbreak</p><p>Simulations were conducted under a baseline primary reproductive number (R0) of 3.6 (point estimate, based on epidemiological data from Wuhan, China, January 6 to January 20, 2020).</p><p>Panel A: Black line shows predicted cumulative numbers of infections in Daegu (by date of transmission in the model) with testing (mean duration from illness onset to confirmation before quarantine: 5.3 days) and 50% contact tracing, started on February 20, 2020, as well as 50% non-lockdown social distancing, started on February 29, 2020 (purple arrows, respectively). To smooth the curve, testing-contact tracing and non-lockdown social distancing started from zero and gradually increased to the targeted level over a period of 10 days and 3 days, respectively. The population size of Shincheonji members and their close contacts in Daegu was assumed as 30,000. Blue shadow shows the sensitivity analysis on outbreak size by the uncertainty range of the Shincheonji population (range: 10,000 to 50,000). The Red line shows the number of cumulative confirmed cases by date from the Korean Center for Disease Control (KCDC) statistics.</p><p>Panel B: Dark red shadow shows the cumulative numbers of superspreading events (SSEs)-associated infection. Light red shadow shows cumulative numbers of infections that were not associated with SSEs.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0002">Figure 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig0003"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Reproductive number (R0) under social distancing alone (A) or testing-contact tracing alone (B)</p><p>If the R0 is more than one (red color), then the disease will continue to spread. On the other hand, if the R0 is less than 1 (green color), the epidemic can be controlled.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0003">Figure 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig0004"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Heterogeneity in infectiousness per individual: (A) Effect of social distancing (population-wide interventions); (B) Effect of testing-contact tracing (individual-specific interventions)</p><p>Heterogeneity in infectiousness per individual is defined by the ratio between the numbers of secondary infections from superspreaders (I<sub>SSE</sub> and A<sub>SSE</sub>) and that from non-superspreaders (I<sub>Non-SSE</sub> and A<sub>Non-SSE</sub>).</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0004">Figure 4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig0005"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Reproductive number (R0) under combined interventions</p><p>Panel A: Under a baseline R0 of 3.6, combined interventions with 50% non-lockdown social distancing and testing-contact tracing (50%) suppress the R0 to less than 1. Panel B: under a baseline R0 of 5.6, combined interventions with 75% non-lockdown social distancing and testing-contact tracing (75%) suppress the R0 to less than 1.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0005">Figure 5</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr5_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig0006"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Trajectories of COVID-19 epidemic under different scenarios</p><p>Red line: natural course of the epidemic, without interventions. Brown line: non-lockdown social distancing (SD) alone. Green line: testing (with a mean time of 5.3 days from illness onset to confirmation) and contact-tracing (T &amp; T) alone. Blue line: Combined intervention (SD + T &amp; T). All interventions were started when the number of new infections reaches 50 per day (marked by black arrow) in a 30,000 population. The color shadows show sensitivity analyses, ranging from -5% to +5% of the interventions. Panel A: Under a baseline R0 of 3.6, effects of SD 50% alone (brown line), T &amp; T 50% alone (green line), and SD 50% + T &amp;T 50% (blue line). Panel B: Under a baseline R0 of 5.6, effects of SD 75% alone (brown line), T &amp; T 75% alone (green line), and SD 75% + T &amp;T 75% (blue line).</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0006">Figure 6</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr6_lrg"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0005">
                <title>Estimating the Baseline R0</title>
                <p id="para0017">Since the epidemic at Daegu, South Korea, was initiated by COVID-19 cases imported from Wuhan, China, we used publicly available epidemiological data from Wuhan to estimate the baseline (before intervention) R0 (the average number of secondary cases generated by an infectious individual in a non-immune, all susceptible population) of the SARS-CoV-2 strain in this outbreak. China Centers for Disease Control and Prevention released the COVID-19 epidemic curve in Wuhan, by illness onset date, in an epidemic situation report on January 28, 2020 (<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention 2020</xref>). An exponential growth of the COVID-19 epidemic occurred during the period from January 6, 2020, to January 22, 2020, with a linear R-square reaching 98% in regressing natural logarithm of numbers of incident cases (including both laboratory-confirmed and suspected cases, since numbers of the former were limited by diagnostic capacity) on the calendar date. We estimated the transmission probability per contact, <italic>b</italic>, in the following formula of baseline R0 (<xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">Keeling and Rohani, 2008</xref>), by fitting our model to the slope of exponential phase (January 6 to January 22, 2020) (Supplementary Material 2) with a numerical method:<disp-formula id="eqn0001"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M27" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">Baseline</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.33em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">}</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>Here, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M28" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.33em"/></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M29" altimg="si26.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.33em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.7</mml:mn><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>: transmission probability per contact (with infected individuals who are symptomatic or asymptomatic, respectively); <inline-formula><mml:math id="M30" altimg="si14.svg"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>: proportion of infectious individuals who are asymptomatic; <inline-formula><mml:math id="M31" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>: proportion of superspreaders;<inline-formula><mml:math id="M32" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.33em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M33" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>: contact rate of superspreaders and non-superspreaders, respectively; <inline-formula><mml:math id="M34" altimg="si7.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>: average duration of latency period (infected but non-infectious state); <inline-formula><mml:math id="M35" altimg="si8.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>: average duration of infectiousness; <inline-formula><mml:math id="M36" altimg="si13.svg"><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>: natural-causes mortality rate. (see <xref rid="tbl0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. for referenced details)</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0006">
                <title>Simulating the Daegu Outbreak</title>
                <p id="para0018">We used the numbers of Shincheonji church members and their close contacts in Daegu, the predominantly affected group (<xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2020</xref>), to estimate the effective population size of this outbreak. We calibrated the onset date of the epidemic in the model to fit it to the cumulative curve of official statistics on confirmed COVID-19 cases in Daegu (Supplementary Material 2) (<xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">Korea Centers for Disease Control and Prevention 2021</xref>), taking into account the 10-day time lag from SARS-CoV-2 transmission to being listed in KCDC daily reports. This time lag comprises an incubation period (from transmission to onset of illness) of 3.0 days (<xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">Lauer et al., 2020</xref>), a patient delay (from illness onset to laboratory confirmation) of 5.3 days (<xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2020</xref>), and an administrative delay (from laboratory confirmation to being listed in the official statistics) of 2 days (all values are estimated mean duration).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0007">
                <title>Impact of Interventions</title>
                <p id="para0019">After validation of the model, we examined the effect of non-lockdown social distancing and testing-contact tracing, alone or combined, on R0 and trajectory of the COVID-19 epidemic:</p>
                <sec id="sec0008">
                  <title>Non-lockdown Social Distancing</title>
                  <p id="para0020">Non-lockdown social distancing decreases transmission by rendering a fraction <inline-formula><mml:math id="M37" altimg="si22.svg"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> (50% to 75%) of the contact rate between susceptible and infectious individuals, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M38" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> or <inline-formula><mml:math id="M39" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, less effective due to physical distancing between people. For this fraction <inline-formula><mml:math id="M40" altimg="si22.svg"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, we assume that the probability of transmission per contact, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M41" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, decreases by a proportion (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M42" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>) of 90% (<xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">Chu et al., 2020</xref>). We model the overall effect of non-lockdown social distancing on the average probability of transmission by the following formula:<disp-formula id="eqn0002"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M43" altimg="si28.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mtext>'</mml:mtext></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">fp</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="sec0009">
                  <title>Testing-Contact Tracing</title>
                  <p id="para0021">Testing-and-isolation detects and quarantines infectious individuals who are symptomatic by a rate of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M44" altimg="si29.svg"><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Shincheonji religious group members in the Daegu outbreak took an average of 5.3 days from the onset of symptom to laboratory confirmation (<xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2020</xref>) before quarantine, equivalent to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M45" altimg="si30.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mn>7.8</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> days (after adding the 2.5-day presymptomatic infectious period). Tracing contacts of detected infected individuals allows early quarantine of infected persons (<xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>) by a proportion of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M46" altimg="si31.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> ranging from 0% to 90%. The overall effect of test-contact tracing on R0 is given by the formula below: (<xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">Keeling and Rohani, 2008</xref>)<disp-formula id="eqn0003"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M47" altimg="si32.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold-italic">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>(R0 of supersupreaders under testing-contact tracing)<disp-formula id="eqn0004"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="M48" altimg="si33.svg"><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mspace width="2.em"/></mml:mtd><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">non</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">SSE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">SSE</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mspace width="2.em"/></mml:mtd><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">non</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">SSE</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">SSE</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>(R0 of non-superspreaders under testing-contact tracing)</p>
                  <p id="para0022">Here, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M49" altimg="si16.svg"><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the proportion of symptomatic infectious individuals whose diagnosis is delayed till hospitalization due to severe/critical COVID-19.</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0010">
                <title>Sensitivity analyses</title>
                <p id="para0023">We conducted two-way sensitivity analyses on the estimated baseline for R0 across uncertainty ranges of latency period and infectious period (<xref rid="tbl0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> for details). We assess the impact of interventions on R0 and epidemic trajectory across different levels of social distancing or testing-contact tracing, alone or combined.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0011">
              <title>Results</title>
              <p id="para0024">The point estimate for baseline R0 is 3.6 (95% confidence interval: 3.4-3.9). The two-way sensitivity analyses (sensitivity analyses range: 2.3 to 5.6) show that the maximum estimate at the worst-case scenario is 5.6 when the latent period is five days and the infectious period is 11.6 days (Supplementary Figure 1).</p>
              <p id="para0025"><xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> shows the validation of the model. Based on the point estimate for baseline R0 in the Wuhan outbreak, 3.6, and the number of Shincheonji members and their associates in Daegu, 30,000 (range: 10,000 to 50,000), the model predicts that cumulative numbers of all infected individuals (including those asymptomatic and undiagnosed) will reach 7,094 (range: 4,082 to 8,732) by April 6, 2020 (<xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>, Panel A). The model-predicted curve parallels the actually observed curve, with a 10-day time lag from incubation period, laboratory confirmation, and statistic administration. The actual cumulative numbers of laboratory-confirmed COVID-19 cases in KCDC statistics reached 6,794 by April 6, 2020 (red line), within the predicted range (blue shadow). The model simulation results affirm that an overwhelming majority (80%) of infections in this outbreak are associated with SSEs (<xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>, Panel B).</p>
              <p id="para0026">We examined the effect of the single intervention on R0. Either non-lockdown social distancing or testing-contact tracing decreases R0 (<xref rid="fig0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). However, in the absence of testing-contact tracing, non-lockdown (50% to 75%) social distancing measures alone would not suppress R0 to less than 1 when baseline R0 is 3.6 (point estimate) or higher (<xref rid="fig0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>, Panel A). On the other hand, without social distancing measures, feasible testing-contact tracing (with a mean interval from illness onset to isolation of four days, and tracing 50% to 75% contacts) alone would also fail to suppress R0 to less than 1 when baseline R0 is 3.6 (point estimate) or higher (<xref rid="fig0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>, Panel B).</p>
              <p id="para0027">Consistent with the known pattern of epidemics spreading predominantly through SSEs (<xref rid="bib0029" ref-type="bibr">Lloyd-Smith et al., 2005</xref>), our model indicates that non-lockdown social distancing (population-wide control measures) does not alter the ratio between the number of secondary infections from superspreaders and that from non-superspreaders (<xref rid="fig0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>, Panel A). This is in contrast to testing-contact tracing (individual-specific control measures), which sharply increases heterogeneity in infectiousness per individual between these two groups (<xref rid="fig0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>, Panel B), which favors epidemic control (<xref rid="bib0029" ref-type="bibr">Lloyd-Smith et al., 2005</xref>).</p>
              <p id="para0028">In contrast to single interventions, combined interventions with non-lockdown (50%) social distancing and test-contact tracing (50%) decrease the R0 to less than 1 when the baseline R0 is 3.6 (<xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>, Panel A). Even under the worst scenario (a baseline R0 of 5.6), combined interventions with non-lockdown (75%), social distancing, and test-contact tracing (75%) still decrease the R0 to less than one (<xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>, Panel B).</p>
              <p id="para0029">Targeting non-lockdown (50% to 75%) social distancing to superspreaders alone, without any restrictive public health measures on non-superspreaders, does not alter the effectiveness of combined interventions in suppressing R0 to below one (Supplementary Figure 2).</p>
              <p id="para0030"><xref rid="fig0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref> further shows the effects of interventions on the epidemic trajectory. Under a baseline R0 of 3.6 (<xref rid="fig0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>, Panel A) or 5.6 (<xref rid="fig0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>, Panel B), non-lockdown social distancing (50% or 75%) alone just postpones the peak of the epidemic (brown lines), while testing-contact tracing (50% or 75%) alone only flattens the curve but does not contain the outbreak (green lines). In contrast, combined interventions effectively suppress the incidence of new COVID-19 infections to zero (blue lines).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0012">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p id="para0031">To our knowledge, this is the first study to show that the presence of testing-contact tracing is required to ensure the success of non-lockdown social distancing (not restricting the movement of people who are not patients or contacts) to control a large-scale COVID-19 outbreak in Daegu, South Korea, 2020, in term of R0 and epidemic trajectory. Both interventions are necessary for the successful containment of a large-scale COVID-19 outbreak.</p>
              <p id="para0032">Previous studies showed that non-pharmacological interventions (testing-contact tracing and social distancing) effectively reduced SARS-CoV-2 transmission in South Korea (<xref rid="bib0034" ref-type="bibr">Ryu et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Park et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0031" ref-type="bibr">Park et al., 2020</xref>), but it is difficult for empirical studies to separately measure the respective effects of these two almost simultaneously implemented interventions. Using a mathematical modeling approach to examine hypothetical scenarios, our study provided new insight on the necessary conditions for effective SARS-CoV-2 epidemic control.</p>
              <p id="para0033">SARS-CoV-2 spreads predominantly through SSEs, in which a small number of infectious individuals are associated with the vast majority of secondary infections (<xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">Lim et al., 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0002" ref-type="bibr">Adam et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Miller et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">Bi et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Endo et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Hamner et al., 2020</xref>). This suggests that early quarantine of a few superspreaders may yield an out-of-proportion effect to control the spread of SARS-CoV-2 (<xref rid="bib0029" ref-type="bibr">Lloyd-Smith et al., 2005</xref>, <xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">Althouse et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Superspreading drives the COVID pandemic — and could help to tame it 2021</xref>). Althouse et al. suggested that eliminate SSEs through extensive testing, and contact tracing might make it possible to contain the epidemic without strict lockdown (<xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">Althouse et al., 2020</xref>). Based on the empirical data from the Daegu outbreak in 2020, the present work is the first study to demonstrate that testing-contact tracing does have an essential role in South Korea's successful control of a large-scale COVID-19 outbreak using a non-lockdown approach.</p>
              <p id="para0034">An important unsettled question is whether targeting the control effort in "problem places," where SSEs occur, can suppress SARS-CoV-2 transmission to allow the lifting of restrictive public health measures such as physical distancing and mask mandate elsewhere (<xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">Althouse et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Superspreading drives the COVID pandemic — and could help to tame it 2021</xref>). Our modeling results show that, theoretically, this “target control” approach is indeed capable of suppressing R0 to less than 1 when simultaneously implemented with testing-contact tracing (50% to 75%) (Supplementary Figure 2). Nevertheless, practically, it might be challenging to preemptively identify all such places before SSEs occur.</p>
              <p id="para0035">Previous modeling studies show that, when superspreading is the predominant transmission pattern, individual-specific control measures (testing-contact tracing) outperform population-wide control measures (social distancing) (<xref rid="bib0029" ref-type="bibr">Lloyd-Smith et al., 2005</xref>). In keeping with this general rule, the present modeling work in analyzing the Daegu outbreak shows that testing-contact tracing alone will outperform social distancing alone in suppressing the R0 of SARTS-CoV-2 (<xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>) and controlling the COVID-19 outbreak (<xref rid="fig0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>). However, delay in laboratory confirmation is the Achilles' heel of SARS-CoV-2 testing (<xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">Althouse et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Superspreading drives the COVID pandemic — and could help to tame it 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0032" ref-type="bibr">Park et al., 2020</xref>). Studies showed that it took up to 3 days (average) from symptom onset to quarantine in Seoul, Korea (<xref rid="bib0032" ref-type="bibr">Park et al., 2020</xref>) because initial symptoms are often non-specific (<xref rid="bib0017" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2020</xref>). For less cooperative Shincheonji religious group members who avoided epidemiological investigation, there was an even longer delay (5.3 days) between illness onset and laboratory confirmation (<xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2020</xref>). Furthermore, transmission frequently occurs before the onset of illness (<xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">He et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Slifka and Gao, 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0041" ref-type="bibr">Wei et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">Chang, 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0042" ref-type="bibr">Wong et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">Chaw et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">Hu et al., 2021</xref>). Therefore, population-wide control measures (social distancing or mask), which universally decrease transmission probability for all individuals, including undetected superspreaders, are essential for combined interventions to successfully control a COVID-19 outbreak.</p>
              <p id="para0036">We did not consider a separate category for imported cases in outbreak scenarios to avoid unnecessary model complexity. Korea Disease Control and Prevention Agency official statistics showed that, by April 6, 2020, only 12 (0.18%) of the 6,794 COVID-19 cases diagnosed in Daegu were imported cases. While the local outbreak was initiated by imported cases (<xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Kim et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">Korea Centers for Disease Control and Prevention 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0019" ref-type="bibr">Ki, 2020</xref>), the number of imported cases becomes negligible soon after a dramatic increase in locally acquired cases.</p>
              <p id="para0037">In non-outbreak scenarios, however, imported cases carry the risk of initiating new outbreaks. Even though testing-contact tracing and social distancing can keep local transmission levels from escalating to large-scale outbreaks, burdens on medical/public health systems will soon exceed the capacity limit in the absence of strict border control (<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Chen and Fang, 2021</xref>). Our previous modeling work showed that, when the number of escaped imported cases (not detected and quarantined at entry, due to false-negative testing results, and not adhered to 14-days quarantine after entry) increases from one to ten per day, the 90-day cumulative number needed to hospitalize and quarantine will jump from 349 and 4,092 to 3,483 and 40,810, respectively (<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Chen and Fang, 2021</xref>). Once medical and public health systems are overburdened and collapsing, testing-contact tracing will not be timely performed, with the risk of losing epidemic control. Therefore, strict restriction of travel from high-risk areas is needed to prevent new outbreaks.</p>
              <p id="para0038">Our finding has an important implication––adopting a non-lockdown approach to control a large-scale COVID-19 outbreak is feasible but needs to be accompanied by a robust testing-contact tracing mechanism to promptly identify and break chains of transmission. The lack of effective contact tracing thus may explain the unprecedented massive surge of COVID-19 epidemic in Europe after lifting lockdown in 2020 autumn/winter (<xref rid="bib0043" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization 2021</xref>).</p>
              <p id="para0039">Allowing people to freely go outside to receive testing and care, non-lockdown social distancing facilitates early detection/isolation of infected persons and subsequent contact tracing, ensuring the feasibility of a non-lockdown social policy to control an outbreak. Therefore, non-lockdown social distancing and testing-contact tracing not only have an epidemiological synergism in breaking the chains of SARS-CoV-2 transmission but also reinforce each other in practical implementation.</p>
              <p id="para0040">The successful control of the COVID-19 outbreak at Daegu, South Korea, is a public health triumph. This success highlights that a democratic and humane strategy to contain a highly contagious disease is feasible and highly effective.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list id="cebibl1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="bib0002">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0002">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Adam</surname>
                      <given-names>DC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wong</surname>
                      <given-names>JY</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lau</surname>
                      <given-names>EHY</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tsang</surname>
                      <given-names>TK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cauchemez</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Clustering and superspreading potential of SARS-CoV-2 infections in Hong Kong</article-title>
                  <source>Nat Med</source>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <issue>11</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1714</fpage>
                  <lpage>1719</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32943787</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0003">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0003">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Althouse</surname>
                      <given-names>BM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wenger</surname>
                      <given-names>EA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Miller</surname>
                      <given-names>JC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Scarpino</surname>
                      <given-names>SV</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Allard</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hébert-Dufresne</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Superspreading events in the transmission dynamics of SARS-CoV-2: Opportunities for interventions and control</article-title>
                  <source>PLoS Biol</source>
                  <volume>18</volume>
                  <issue>11</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e3000897</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0005">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0005">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Arons</surname>
                      <given-names>MM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hatfield</surname>
                      <given-names>KM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reddy</surname>
                      <given-names>SC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kimball</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>James</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jacobs</surname>
                      <given-names>JR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Presymptomatic SARS-CoV-2 infections and transmission in a skilled nursing facility</article-title>
                  <source>New England Journal of Medicine</source>
                  <volume>382</volume>
                  <issue>22</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>2081</fpage>
                  <lpage>2090</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0006">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0006">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bi</surname>
                      <given-names>Q</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mei</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ye</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zou</surname>
                      <given-names>X</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>Z</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Epidemiology and transmission of COVID-19 in 391 cases and 1286 of their close contacts in Shenzhen, China: a retrospective cohort study</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>
                  <volume>20</volume>
                  <issue>8</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>911</fpage>
                  <lpage>919</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32353347</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0007">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0007">Chang SC. Proportion of asymptomatic SARS-CoV-2 infections among 398 laboratory-confirmed SARS-CoV-2-infected patients in Taiwan [in traditional Chinese]. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://news.ltn.com.tw/news/life/breakingnews/3137967" id="interref0002">https://news.ltn.com.tw/news/life/breakingnews/3137967</ext-link>. Accessed on: 2020-04-18 2021.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0008">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0008">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chaw</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Koh</surname>
                      <given-names>WC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jamaludin</surname>
                      <given-names>SA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Naing</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alikhan</surname>
                      <given-names>MF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wong</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Analysis of SARS-CoV-2 transmission in different settings</article-title>
                  <source>Brunei. Emerg Infect Dis.</source>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <issue>11</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>2598</fpage>
                  <lpage>2606</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33035448</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0009">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0009">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>YH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fang</surname>
                      <given-names>CT.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Combined interventions to suppress R0 and border quarantine to contain COVID-19 in Taiwan</article-title>
                  <source>J Formos Med Assoc</source>
                  <volume>120</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <fpage>903</fpage>
                  <lpage>905</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32855037</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0010">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0010">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cheng</surname>
                      <given-names>HY</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jian</surname>
                      <given-names>SW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>DP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ng</surname>
                      <given-names>TC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huang</surname>
                      <given-names>WT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lin</surname>
                      <given-names>HH.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Contact tracing assessment of COVID-19 transmission dynamics in Taiwan and risk at different exposure periods before and after symptom onset</article-title>
                  <source>JAMA Intern Med</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0011">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0011">Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention. Epidemic update and risk assessment of 2019 Novel Coronavirus. 2020.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0012">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0012">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chu</surname>
                      <given-names>DK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Akl</surname>
                      <given-names>EA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Duda</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Solo</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yaacoub</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schünemann</surname>
                      <given-names>HJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Physical distancing, face masks, and eye protection to prevent person-to-person transmission of SARS-CoV-2 and COVID-19: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>
                  <source>The Lancet</source>
                  <volume>395</volume>
                  <issue>10242</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1973</fpage>
                  <lpage>1987</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0013">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0013">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Endo</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abbott</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kucharski</surname>
                      <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Funk</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Estimating the overdispersion in COVID-19 transmission using outbreak sizes outside China</article-title>
                  <source>Wellcome Open Res</source>
                  <volume>5</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>67</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32685698</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0014">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0014">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hamner</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dubbel</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Capron</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ross</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jordan</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lee</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>High SARS-CoV-2 attack rate following exposure at a choir practice - Skagit County, Washington, March 2020</article-title>
                  <source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source>
                  <volume>69</volume>
                  <issue>19</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>606</fpage>
                  <lpage>610</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32407303</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0015">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0015">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>He</surname>
                      <given-names>X</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lau</surname>
                      <given-names>EHY</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Deng</surname>
                      <given-names>X</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hao</surname>
                      <given-names>X</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Temporal dynamics in viral shedding and transmissibility of COVID-19</article-title>
                  <source>Nat Med</source>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>672</fpage>
                  <lpage>675</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32296168</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0016">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0016">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hu</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Litvinova</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Luo</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ren</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Infectivity, susceptibility, and risk factors associated with SARS-CoV-2 transmission under intensive contact tracing in Hunan, China</article-title>
                  <source>Nat Commun</source>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <fpage>1533</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33750783</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0017">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0017">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huang</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>X</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ren</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhao</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hu</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Clinical features of patients infected with 2019 novel coronavirus in Wuhan</article-title>
                  <source>China. The Lancet.</source>
                  <volume>395</volume>
                  <issue>10223</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>497</fpage>
                  <lpage>506</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0018">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0018">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Keeling</surname>
                      <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rohani</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>Modeling Infectious Diseases in Humans and Animals</part-title>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0019">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0019">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ki</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Epidemiologic characteristics of early cases with 2019 novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) disease in Korea</article-title>
                  <source>Epidemiol Health</source>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e2020007</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0020">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0020">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kim</surname>
                      <given-names>HJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hwang</surname>
                      <given-names>HS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Choi</surname>
                      <given-names>YH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Song</surname>
                      <given-names>HY</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Park</surname>
                      <given-names>JS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yun</surname>
                      <given-names>CY</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The delay in confirming COVID-19 cases linked to a religious group in Korea</article-title>
                  <source>J Prev Med Public Health</source>
                  <volume>53</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>164</fpage>
                  <lpage>167</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32498138</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0021">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0021">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kim</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jeong</surname>
                      <given-names>YD</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Byun</surname>
                      <given-names>JH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cho</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Park</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jung</surname>
                      <given-names>JH</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of COVID-19 epidemic outbreak caused by temporal contact-increase in South Korea</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Infect Dis</source>
                  <volume>96</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>454</fpage>
                  <lpage>457</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32417246</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0022">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0022">Korea Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Press Release. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.go.kr/board/board.es?mid=a30402000000&amp;bid=0030" id="interref0003">https://www.cdc.go.kr/board/board.es?mid=a30402000000&amp;bid=0030</ext-link>. 2021</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0023">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0023">Korea Ministry of Foreign Affairs. COVID-19 in Korea: An Update. Available from: http://overseas.mofa.go.kr/nl-en/brd/m_6988/view.do?seq=759032&amp;srchFr=&amp;srchTo=&amp;srchWord=&amp;srchTp=&amp;multi_itm_seq=0&amp;itm_seq_1=0&amp;itm_seq_2=0&amp;company_cd=&amp;company_nm=. 2021</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0024">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0024">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kraemer</surname>
                      <given-names>MUG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>CH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gutierrez</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>CH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Klein</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pigott</surname>
                      <given-names>DM</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effect of human mobility and control measures on the COVID-19 epidemic in China</article-title>
                  <source>Science</source>
                  <volume>368</volume>
                  <issue>6490</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>493</fpage>
                  <lpage>497</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32213647</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0025">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0025">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lauer</surname>
                      <given-names>SA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Grantz</surname>
                      <given-names>KH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bi</surname>
                      <given-names>Q</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jones</surname>
                      <given-names>FK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zheng</surname>
                      <given-names>Q</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Meredith</surname>
                      <given-names>HR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The incubation period of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) from publicly reported confirmed cases: estimation and application</article-title>
                  <source>Ann Intern Med</source>
                  <volume>172</volume>
                  <issue>9</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>577</fpage>
                  <lpage>582</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32150748</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0026">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0026">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lee</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kim</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Choi</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hong</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Son</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ryu</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Incubation period of the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) in Busan, South Korea</article-title>
                  <source>J Infect Chemother</source>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <issue>9</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1011</fpage>
                  <lpage>1013</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32631735</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0027">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0027">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>Q</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Guan</surname>
                      <given-names>X</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>X</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhou</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tong</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Early transmission dynamics in Wuhan, China, of novel coronavirus-infected pneumonia</article-title>
                  <source>N Engl J Med</source>
                  <volume>382</volume>
                  <issue>13</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1199</fpage>
                  <lpage>1207</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31995857</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0028">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0028">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lim</surname>
                      <given-names>J-S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Noh</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shim</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ryu</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>Temporal changes in the risk of superspreading events of coronavirus disease 2019</part-title>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <publisher-name>Open Forum Infectious Diseases</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0029">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0029">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lloyd-Smith</surname>
                      <given-names>JO</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schreiber</surname>
                      <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kopp</surname>
                      <given-names>PE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Getz</surname>
                      <given-names>WM.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Superspreading and the effect of individual variation on disease emergence</article-title>
                  <source>Nature</source>
                  <volume>438</volume>
                  <issue>7066</issue>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <fpage>355</fpage>
                  <lpage>359</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16292310</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0030">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0030">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Miller</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Martin</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Harel</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tirosh</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kustin</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Meir</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Full genome viral sequences inform patterns of SARS-CoV-2 spread into and within Israel</article-title>
                  <source>Nat Commun</source>
                  <volume>11</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>5518</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33139704</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0031">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0031">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Park</surname>
                      <given-names>SW</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sun</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Viboud</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Grenfell</surname>
                      <given-names>BT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dushoff</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Potential role of social distancing in mitigating spread of coronavirus disease</article-title>
                  <source>South Korea. Emerg Infect Dis.</source>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <issue>11</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>2697</fpage>
                  <lpage>2700</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32795385</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0032">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0032">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Park</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huh</surname>
                      <given-names>IS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lee</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kang</surname>
                      <given-names>CR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cho</surname>
                      <given-names>SI</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ham</surname>
                      <given-names>HJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>application of testing-tracing-treatment strategy in response to the COVID-19 outbreak in Seoul</article-title>
                  <source>Korea. J Korean Med Sci.</source>
                  <volume>35</volume>
                  <issue>45</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>e396</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33230987</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0033">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0033">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Park</surname>
                      <given-names>YJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Choe</surname>
                      <given-names>YJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Park</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Park</surname>
                      <given-names>SY</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kim</surname>
                      <given-names>YM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kim</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>contact Tracing during Coronavirus Disease Outbreak, South Korea, 2020</article-title>
                  <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>2465</fpage>
                  <lpage>2468</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32673193</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0034">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0034">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ryu</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ali</surname>
                      <given-names>ST</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jang</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kim</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cowling</surname>
                      <given-names>BJ.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effect of nonpharmaceutical interventions on transmission of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2, South Korea, 2020</article-title>
                  <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>2406</fpage>
                  <lpage>2410</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32487283</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0035">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0035">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Slifka</surname>
                      <given-names>MK</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gao</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Is presymptomatic spread a major contributor to COVID-19 transmission?</article-title>
                  <source>Nat Med</source>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1531</fpage>
                  <lpage>1533</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32807936</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0036">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0036">'Superspreader' in South Korea infects nearly 40 people with coronavirus. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.livescience.com/coronavirus-superspreader-south-korea-church.html" id="interref0004">https://www.livescience.com/coronavirus-superspreader-south-korea-church.html</ext-link>. 2021</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0037">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0037">Superspreading drives the COVID pandemic — and could help to tame it. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-021-00460-x" id="interref0005">https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-021-00460-x</ext-link>. 2021</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0038">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0038">The Great Barrington Declaration. The Great Barrington Declaration.; 2021. Contract No.: 2021-03-02.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0039">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0039">The World Bank. Life expectancy at birth - United States. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SP.DYN.LE00.IN?locations=US" id="interref0006">https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SP.DYN.LE00.IN?locations=US</ext-link>. 2021</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0001">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0001">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>The Novel Coronavirus Pneumonia Emergency Response Epidemiology Team.</surname>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The epidemiological characteristics of an outbreak of 2019 novel coronavirus diseases (COVID-19)</article-title>
                  <source>China CDC Weekly</source>
                  <volume>2</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <lpage>122</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.46234/ccdcw2020.032</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0040">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0040">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wallinga</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Teunis</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kretzschmar</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Using data on social contacts to estimate age-specific transmission parameters for respiratory-spread infectious agents</article-title>
                  <source>Am J Epidemiol</source>
                  <volume>164</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <fpage>936</fpage>
                  <lpage>944</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16968863</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0041">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0041">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wei</surname>
                      <given-names>WE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>Z</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chiew</surname>
                      <given-names>CJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yong</surname>
                      <given-names>SE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Toh</surname>
                      <given-names>MP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lee</surname>
                      <given-names>VJ.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Presymptomatic Transmission of SARS-CoV-2 - Singapore, January 23-March 16, 2020</article-title>
                  <source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source>
                  <volume>69</volume>
                  <issue>14</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>411</fpage>
                  <lpage>415</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32271722</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0042">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0042">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wong</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abdul Aziz</surname>
                      <given-names>ABZ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chaw</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mahamud</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Griffith</surname>
                      <given-names>MM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lo</surname>
                      <given-names>Y-R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>High proportion of asymptomatic and presymptomatic COVID-19 infections in air passengers to Brunei</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Travel Medicine</source>
                  <volume>27</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0043">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0043">World Health Organization. Coronavirus disease (COVID-19) dashboard. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://covid19.who.int/" id="interref0007">https://covid19.who.int/</ext-link>. Accessed on: July 19, 2021.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0044">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0044">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xin</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wong</surname>
                      <given-names>JY</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Murphy</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yeung</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ali</surname>
                      <given-names>ST</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>The incubation period distribution of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19): a systematic review and meta-analysis</part-title>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <publisher-name>Clinical infectious diseases: an official publication of the Infectious Diseases Society of America</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
            <sec id="sec0017" sec-type="supplementary-material">
              <label>Appendix</label>
              <title>Supplementary materials</title>
              <p id="para0041a">
                <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ecom0001">
                  <media xlink:href="mmc1.docx">
                    <alt-text>Image, application 1</alt-text>
                  </media>
                </supplementary-material>
                <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ecom0002">
                  <media xlink:href="mmc2.xlsx">
                    <alt-text>Image, application 2</alt-text>
                  </media>
                </supplementary-material>
              </p>
            </sec>
            <ack id="ack0001">
              <sec id="sec0013">
                <title>Funding</title>
                <p id="para0043">This study was supported by Taiwan Centers for Disease Control (Taipei, Taiwan) (MOHW-109-CDC-ZH108028, MOHW-110-CDC-ZH109031). The publication fee was supported by the Ministry of Health and Welfare and National Taiwan University Infectious Diseases Research and Education Center (Taipei, Taiwan). Funders have no role in study design, data collection and analysis, or preparation of the manuscript.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0014">
                <title>Conflict of Interest</title>
                <p id="para0044">The authors do not have an association that might pose a conflict of interest.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0015">
                <title>Authors’ Contributions</title>
                <p id="para0045">YHC and CTF designed the study; YHC searched the Korea Disease Control and Prevention Agency website for publicly available epidemiological data on the Daegu outbreak and conducted infectious diseases modeling; YLH communicated with Korean Mission in Taipei; YHC and CTF wrote the manuscript; CTF and YHC contributed equally.</p>
              </sec>
            </ack>
            <fn-group>
              <fn id="sec0016" fn-type="supplementary-material">
                <p id="para0011a">Supplementary material associated with this article can be found, in the online version, at doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijid.2021.07.058" id="interref0001">10.1016/j.ijid.2021.07.058</ext-link>.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
