<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-03-11T00:45:39Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8694818" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8694818</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-12-23</datestamp>
        <setSpec>pheelsevier</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.xsd" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Inform Med Unlocked</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Inform Med Unlocked</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Informatics in Medicine Unlocked</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2352-9148</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>The Authors. Published by Elsevier Ltd.</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC8694818</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8694818</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">8694818</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34961844</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2352-9148(21)00280-X</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.imu.2021.100815</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100815</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Forecasting the spread of the third wave of COVID-19 pandemic using time series analysis in Bangladesh</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au000001">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kibria</surname>
                    <given-names>Hafsa Binte</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au000002">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Jyoti</surname>
                    <given-names>Oishi</given-names>
                  </name>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au000003">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Matin</surname>
                    <given-names>Abdul</given-names>
                  </name>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="aff1">Department of Electrical &amp; Computer Engineering, Rajshahi University of Engineering &amp; Technology, Rajshahi 6204, Bangladesh</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author.</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>22</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.-->
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <year>2022</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>22</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>28</volume>
              <fpage>100815</fpage>
              <lpage>100815</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>28</day>
                  <month>10</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>18</day>
                  <month>11</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>18</day>
                  <month>11</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2021 The Authors</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
                <license>
                  <license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="d1e905">
                <p>During the third wave of the coronavirus epidemic in Bangladesh, the death and infection rate due to this devastating virus has increased dramatically. The rapid spread of the virus is one of the reasons for this terrible condition. So, identifying the subsequent cases of coronavirus can be a great tool to reduce the mortality and infection rate. In this article, we used the autoregressive integrated moving average-ARIMA(8,1,7) model to estimate the expected daily number of COVID-19 cases in Bangladesh based on the data from April 20, 2021, to July 4, 2021. The ARIMA model showed the best results among the five executed models over Autoregressive Model (AR), Moving Average (MA), Autoregressive Moving Average (ARMA), and Rolling Forest Origin. The findings of this article were used to anticipate a rise in daily cases for the next month in Bangladesh, which can help governments plan policies to prevent the spread of the virus. The forecasting outcome indicated that this new trend(named delta variant) in Bangladesh would continue increasing and might reach 18327 daily new cases within four weeks if strict rules and regulations are not applied to control the spread of COVID-19.</p>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group id="d1e911">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>Time series analysis</kwd>
                <kwd>ARIMA model</kwd>
                <kwd>COVID-19</kwd>
                <kwd>Pandemic</kwd>
                <kwd>Bangladesh</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="sec1">
              <label>1</label>
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p id="d1e936">The novel coronavirus originated from Wuhan, China, in 2019 has escalated all over the world so far. The variant of the coronavirus is highly infectious and has a global impact on more than 199,313,422 cases, claiming 4,245,582 lives till August 2, 2021 <xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. The symptoms shown by this virus can be mild, moderate, and intense, which builds severe respiratory distress syndrome <xref rid="b2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. Initially, no COVID-19 vaccination was found. In those circumstances, the only way to prevent the spread of the virus was to identify social distance, to identify positive cases using large-scale testing, and to isolate infected people <xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. Later on, several vaccines were invented to provide acquired immunity against the coronavirus. However, the mutation of COVID-19 prevents the vaccines from being fully effective. Maintaining the necessary measures and proper dose of vaccines, several nations have succeeded in controlling the disease, whereas Bangladesh has faced difficulties in managing the situation. The large population and inadequate supply of vaccines have made it very difficult to normalize the circumstances. Therefore, it is very important to prevent the spread of the virus. Because of the significant impact and easy spreading of the virus, the national government has enforced lockdown in most affected areas or all over the country <xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. In that case, it would be much more effective if the possible number of confirmed cases could be known in advance. Then the lockdown can be implemented in possible afflicted areas in time. As a result, the spread will decrease as well as the number of confirmed cases.</p>
              <p id="d1e955">As of August 02, 2021, the total number of infected people is over 1,309,910 in Bangladesh <xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. Bangladesh reports an average of 14,132 daily new cases, which are the highest of 98% peak as per August 02, 2021 <xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. These numbers are growing significantly and continue to have adverse effects on human lives, medical centers, and nations’ currencies. Therefore, it is clear that predicting the future pandemic outbreak using existing data is significant for understanding the present circumstances and helping authorities take necessary steps and effective ideas for limiting new infections. Several research has been done to evaluate the spread and impact of the virus using machine learning models and various computational analysis <xref rid="b6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>.</p>
              <p id="d1e969">The researchers have used four comparative models to predict coronavirus spread in Saudi Arabia in <xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, and autoregressive integrated moving average-ARIMA (2,1,1) came out as the best model. Data availability was a concern because the research was conducted at an early stage. They have selected their ARIMA order using AIC (Akaike information criterion) approaches. Since it was the beginning period of COVID-19, their data was relatively linearly increasing. Other models were also used to predict the spread, and at last comparative analysis was done among them. Another study <xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref> used the ARIMA model for forecasting in the top five affected countries: India, Brazil, Spain, the US, and Russia. Considering there was no vaccine available at the time, their main focus was to prepare the government to take the necessary steps. Here also, ARIMA gave promising results.</p>
              <p id="d1e979">In another study <xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, ARIMA and nonlinear autoregressive (NAR) models have been used to forecast the COVID-19 in India. ARIMA(1,1,0) was selected based on BIC (Bayesian information criterion) values, and the NAR model consisted of ten neurons. In <xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, adaptive neuro-fuzzy inference system (ANFIS) and long short-term memory networks (LSTM) were implemented to forecast COVID-19 pandemic growth in Bangladesh, and LSTM provided a satisfactory result. LSTM is preferable in forecasting the long term where ARIMA is for the short term, and in our work, we have only used the third wave COVID-19 dataset, which contains approximately three months records of the confirmed cases. That is why we used ARIMA for our prediction. Also, promising result has been found for forecasting COVID-19 cases in other different countries using ARIMA <xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="b13" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. Different order of ARIMA model has been used for the forecasting in Italy, Spain, and France, with satisfactory results <xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. In <xref rid="b15" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, confirmed cases and mortality cases were anticipated using two data-driven approaches for some countries. Both ARIMA and LSTM produced favorable results.</p>
              <p id="d1e1002">Many kinds of research are being conducted in order to alleviate the pandemic’s suffering. Many researchers choose ARIMA as their primary choice for time series analysis. Other algorithms, such as LSTM, NAR, VAR, and other machine learning algorithms, are also being applied. For the performance measurement, RMSE, MAE, and other performance matrices have been used. One of the problems was the availability of data and the correctness of the given data, as in many developing countries, all COVID-19 records were not updated. Even though researchers are trying their best to predict the possible cases or deaths associated with the COVID-19 pandemic in the near future, and many algorithms have provided promising outcomes.</p>
              <p id="d1e1004">ARIMA has shown promising results in various studies for COVID-19 predictions. In <xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, the researchers used ARIMA to estimate the top five afflicted countries, and they got a good result for the first 18 days of July. The MAD and MAPE were found within the acceptable agreement. Also other works have been done using ARIMA <xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="b13" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref> for COVID-19 forecasting. In, <xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref> ARIMA model was used to forecast the new cases along with deaths of COVID-19 in Bangladesh. Researchers conducted the same model in <xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref> to forecast the new cases and deaths in COVID-19 using the European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control data. To identify the confirmed number of diagnoses, besides ARIMA, several models were assigned in <xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. Among these, ARIMA has been specified as the most suitable model.</p>
              <p id="d1e1027">In finance and the economy, ARIMA plays a significant role. It has been widely used in stock market predictions <xref rid="b19" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, <xref rid="b20" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. In <xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, ARIMA was used to forecast the stock change of New York and Nigeria, and the findings show that it can compete favorably with existing techniques. Several researchers have used the ARIMA model for weather forecasting on time series data. ARIMA (2,0,2) and ARIMA (2,1,3) were used respectively for rainfall data and temperature data to predict the weather for fifteen years in Varanasi, India <xref rid="b22" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. Also, ARIMA has been applied to other time-series data like stock prediction <xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, <xref rid="b23" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, detecting malaria <xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, <xref rid="b25" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref> and it showed good results.</p>
              <p id="d1e1050">In this study, the ARIMA model, the Autoregressive Model (AR), Moving Average(MA), ARMA, and Rolling Forest Origin were utilized to forecast the number of new confirmed COVID-19 cases in Bangladesh on a daily basis. On data recorded from April 20, 2021, to July 4, 2021, the assigned models were implemented and verified based on data recorded between July 5, 2021, to July 28, 2021. The train and test ratio was 75:25. Because of its better prediction functionalities, the models are widely recognized and effective. We have also implemented ARIMA(8,1,7) to forecast the coming month and discovered that the confirmed cases might exceed 18327 by August 30, 2021. The rolling forecast has the lowest error of all the models, but it can only predict a single period in our proposed model. Because of this limitation, despite the lowest error, we recognized ARIMA as the best-performing model.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec2">
              <label>2</label>
              <title>Materials and methodology</title>
              <sec id="sec2.1">
                <label>2.1</label>
                <title>Data description</title>
                <p id="d1e1062">The data used in this work is a statistical report of COVID-19 cases of Bangladesh, which is available online <xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. They have the information of all the COVID-19 related data such as death, confirmed cases, and lab tests. For the time being, this web source is the most reliable source for everyday COVID-19 cases. We used confirmed case data in our research to forecast coronavirus spread in Bangladesh. Many academics have conducted their research using data collected from this internet source <xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="b26" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, <xref rid="b27" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. The range of the dataset is from April 20, 2021, to July 28, 2021. For training, the dataset was taken from April 20, 2021, to July 6, 2021, while the remaining days till July 28, 2021, were used for testing.</p>
                <p id="d1e1072"><xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> represents the total number of daily confirmed COVID-19 cases reported in Bangladesh from April 20, 2021, to July 28, 2021. The number of the confirmed cases was limited to six thousand until June 24, 2021; later, it has significantly increased and surpassed that number. Then we observed a significant increase in the first week of July, which is referred to as the third wave in Bangladesh. From April 20, 2021, it took nearly 70 days to double and only 30 days to quadruple. Data was collected from <xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, there was a pattern in the increasing number of confirmed cases of COVID-19. Though it increased from May 1, 2021, to July 15, 2021, then it dropped significantly for a few days displayed in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>. It could be for several reasons, but none of them have been confirmed. We collected data from a single source, and the variables were unchanged. So the possible reason can be a computational error, where the excluded number was added the other day. Or, because of the unpredictable nature of COVID-19, it might show this kind of sudden characteristics. The sudden cases drop in the test data also made it difficult to correctly predict as it was not a predefined characteristic, and it decreased the accuracy of the models. The rolling forecast model captured this characteristic, and that is why only this model was able to predict closely the actual values between July 21 to July 24.<fig id="fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Daily confirmed cases of COVID-19 in Bangladesh from April 20, 2021 to July 6, 2021.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Representation of dataset after first difference.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="d1e1091">We can see that the ARIMA (8,1,7) model outperformed the others except for the rolling forecast by comparing the results from <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figs. 5</xref>, <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> and <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. The predicted confirmed cases from July 29, 2021 to August 30, 2021, are depicted in <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref> and <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>. The yellow line represents the forecasted curve of daily confirmed cases for the following month based on the ARIMA (8,1,7) model of COVID-19. <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref> shows the current number of confirmed cases officially reported by the Bangladesh Ministry of Health from July 2, 2021, to July 5, 2021 (in blue).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2.2">
                <label>2.2</label>
                <title>Data preprocessing</title>
                <p id="d1e1123">In our dataset, the date was the input column, and the confirmed case was the output. First, the time column was arranged according to year-month-day. And we did not have any missing values in our dataset. For training, the dataset was divided into a 75:25 train test ratio. The split can be placed randomly for any other dataset since there is no dependence from one observation to another. In time-series data, samples are observed in fixed time intervals, and the test indices must be higher than the train. So during splitting, we took the first 75% for training and the remaining 25% for testing. In <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>, the procedure of COVID-19 prediction has been displayed. After collecting the data, it was converted into time series and then checked for stationarity which will be discussed later. After preprocessing, it was split and then trained. Trained models used the testing data for forecasting. At last, we evaluated the performance of every model.</p>
                <p id="d1e1129">
                  <fig id="fig3">
                    <label>Fig. 3</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Overall procedure of proposed model.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="gr3_lrg"/>
                  </fig>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2.3">
                <label>2.3</label>
                <title>Description of models</title>
                <p id="d1e1137">This research has focused on using statistical models to predict the spread of the coronavirus in Bangladesh. The Autoregressive (AR) model is the simplest and frequently used model structure. It is called the autoregressive model, as the values are predicted based on past values. As it forecasts based on its values, that is why the model is referred to as auto, and the model is a regression model. Therefore, it is known as a regressive model. The current output <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1140" display="inline" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is expressed by previous values and coefficients (<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1151" display="inline" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>) in the AR model in Eq. <xref rid="fd1" ref-type="disp-formula">(1)</xref>. Here <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1162" display="inline" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> denotes the coefficient, time is <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1167" display="inline" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1172" display="inline" altimg="si31.svg"><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the order of the parameters, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1177" display="inline" altimg="si6.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is the previous value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1192" display="inline" altimg="si31.svg"><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> order. <disp-formula id="fd1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="d1e1203" display="block" altimg="si8.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">⋯</mml:mo><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
                <p id="d1e1290">In the MA model, the measurement of error from the previous period helps better estimate the next period. Here, the model always moves around average; that is why it is called the moving average model. It is always centered to its average. <disp-formula id="fd2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="d1e1299" display="block" altimg="si9.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">⋯</mml:mo><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>In MA model, <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1388" display="inline" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is the predicted value, <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1398" display="inline" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the constant (the mean) in Eq. <xref rid="fd2" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref>. The error is represented by <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1409" display="inline" altimg="si12.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, while the coefficient of error is represented by <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1419" display="inline" altimg="si13.svg"><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                <p id="d1e1423">By merging AR and MA, there is a more improved structure known as the ARMA model, which is defined in <xref rid="fd3" ref-type="disp-formula">(3)</xref>. <disp-formula-group id="fd3"><label>(3)</label><disp-formula id="d1e1435"><mml:math id="d1e1436" display="block" class="aligned" altimg="si15.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">⋯</mml:mo><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="d1e1541"><mml:math id="d1e1542" display="block" class="aligned" altimg="si16.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">⋯</mml:mo><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></disp-formula-group>
</p>
                <p id="d1e1581">A more advanced statistical model is Autoregressive Integrated Moving Average (ARIMA), which includes differences at least once. The ARIMA model formula is stated in Eq. <xref rid="fd4" ref-type="disp-formula">(4)</xref>. <disp-formula-group id="fd4"><label>(4)</label><disp-formula id="d1e1594"><mml:math id="d1e1595" display="block" class="aligned" altimg="si18.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">⋯</mml:mo><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="d1e1697"><mml:math id="d1e1698" display="block" class="aligned" altimg="si19.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">⋯</mml:mo><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ɛ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mtext> where </mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></disp-formula-group>
</p>
                <p id="d1e1783">AR and MA require stationarity, which is a statistical property of a time series. The mean and standard deviation need to be constant for the time series data. Also, there should be no seasonality — these are the criterion of a time series to achieve stationarity. As our model did not have the property, we took the first difference of our dataset. It was achieved by subtracting the previous observation from the current observation. The graph after the first-order difference represents in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>. But for ARIMA, the parameter d makes it stationary, so we do not need to make the difference by subtracting the observant. In our model, d is equal to 1.</p>
                <p id="d1e1789">ARIMA is used when the graph shows stationarity but has a linear moving trend. It forecasts the differences between time series rather than the time series itself. The ARIMA model is identified by arranging the three variables in the following order: <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1792" display="inline" altimg="si31.svg"><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> for the order of AR, <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1797" display="inline" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> for the degree of differencing, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1802" display="inline" altimg="si30.svg"><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> for the order of MA.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2.4">
                <label>2.4</label>
                <title>Parameters estimation</title>
                <p id="d1e1811">The time-series data must be stationary before evaluating the parameters for all models. The stationarity of the data was checked with the augmented dickey fuller test(ADF), for which the null hypothesis H0 indicates that the time series is not stationary. The ADF result suggested that time-series data was non-stationary (<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1815" display="inline" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>99</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in this case). After applying the first difference, the null hypothesis was rejected since the <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1827" display="inline" altimg="si31.svg"><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>-value was.004, which is less than .05.</p>
                <p id="d1e1831">Based on the Akaike information criterion (AIC), the parameters of the ARIMA model were selected, as shown in Eq. <xref rid="fd5" ref-type="disp-formula">(5)</xref>. <disp-formula id="fd5"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="d1e1845" display="block" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
                <p id="d1e1865">AIC assists in the selection of the best model. It is a prominent method in statistics for selecting any model. It is made up of two parts.</p>
                <p id="d1e1867">
                  <list list-type="simple" id="d1e1869">
                    <list-item id="lst1">
                      <label>•</label>
                      <p id="d1e1873">Log-likelihood (<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1877" display="inline" altimg="si26.svg"><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>): It shows how strong the model fits the data. A more sophisticated model can fit the training data better but also introduces overfitting. Also, a complicated model may give incorrect results on testing data.</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item id="lst2">
                      <label>•</label>
                      <p id="d1e1884">Number of parameters in the model (<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1888" display="inline" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>): the fewer the parameters, the simpler the model is. But a too simple model will introduce underfitting, while a too complicated model would introduce overfitting.</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                </p>
                <p id="d1e1892">The AIC needs to be as small as possible, so we will select the model with the lowest AIC. A model with low AIC will have low <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1895" display="inline" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> (number of parameters) that will keep the model as simple as possible. However, we also need to ensure that the model has a high log-likelihood (<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1901" display="inline" altimg="si26.svg"><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>), so it will select a model that fits the data well with relatively few parameters. As a result, it will choose a model that will strike a balance. The order we elected to calculate the AIC values is from the ACF and PACF graphs. For the AR order, the significant lags (0,7,8,9,14) have been chosen from the PACF graph, while the lags (0,7,8,9,14) that are significant in the ACF graph have been selected for the MA order.</p>
                <p id="d1e1905"><xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> displays the AIC values for different <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1914" display="inline" altimg="si31.svg"><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1919" display="inline" altimg="si30.svg"><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> parameters. We evaluated numerous <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1925" display="inline" altimg="si31.svg"><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1930" display="inline" altimg="si30.svg"><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> parameters chosen from the ACF and PACF graphs of the first difference of the data. The ACF and PACF have been shown in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>. We have found that ARIMA(8,1,7) produces the lowest AIC values. Based on the ADF test, <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1939" display="inline" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> was selected as 1 for the ARIMA model.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Order selection of ARIMA based on AIC approach.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e110" display="inline" altimg="si30.svg"><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> in MA</th><th colspan="5" align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e116" display="inline" altimg="si31.svg"><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> in AR<hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">0</th><th align="left">7</th><th align="left">8</th><th align="left">9</th><th align="left">14</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1704</td><td align="left">1682</td><td align="left">1682</td><td align="left">1676</td><td align="left">1674</td></tr><tr><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">1691</td><td align="left">1672</td><td align="left"><bold>1671</bold></td><td align="left">1672</td><td align="left">1671</td></tr><tr><td align="left">9</td><td align="left">1683</td><td align="left">1677</td><td align="left">1677</td><td align="left">1678</td><td align="left">1675</td></tr><tr><td align="left">14</td><td align="left">1688</td><td align="left">1684</td><td align="left">1686</td><td align="left">1688</td><td align="left">1680</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
                <p id="d1e1943">
                  <fig id="fig4">
                    <label>Fig. 4</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>ACF and PACF of the first difference of data.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="gr4_lrg"/>
                  </fig>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2.5">
                <label>2.5</label>
                <title>Models performance measures</title>
                <p id="d1e1951">To evaluate the performance of each model given above, a relatively common accuracy measuring method was applied. These are the performance functions:</p>
                <p id="d1e1953">
                  <list list-type="simple" id="d1e1955">
                    <list-item id="lst3">
                      <label>•</label>
                      <p id="d1e1959">Root mean square error (RMSE): <disp-formula id="fd6"><label>(6)</label><mml:math id="d1e1968" display="block" altimg="si37.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo class="qopname">RMSE</mml:mo><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>~</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2027" display="inline" altimg="si38.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2037" display="inline" altimg="si39.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>~</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> are real and predicted values, respectively.</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item id="lst4">
                      <label>•</label>
                      <p id="d1e2054">Mean absolute error (MAE): <disp-formula id="fd7"><label>(7)</label><mml:math id="d1e2063" display="block" altimg="si40.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">MAE</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>~</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item id="lst5">
                      <label>•</label>
                      <p id="d1e2121">Coefficient of determination (<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2125" display="inline" altimg="si41.svg"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>) <disp-formula-group id="fd8"><label>(8)</label><disp-formula id="d1e2140"><mml:math id="d1e2141" display="block" class="aligned" altimg="si43.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>~</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="d1e2257"><mml:math id="d1e2258" display="block" class="aligned" altimg="si44.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext> where </mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mtext> is defined as </mml:mtext><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></disp-formula-group>
</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item id="lst6">
                      <label>•</label>
                      <p id="d1e2321">Mean absolute percentage error (MAPE): <disp-formula id="fd9"><label>(9)</label><mml:math id="d1e2330" display="block" altimg="si45.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">MAPE</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>~</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>~</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                </p>
                <p id="d1e2400">In this work, we have used five statistical models to forecast the spread of COVID-19 in Bangladesh. AR, MA, ARMA, ARIMA, and Rolling forecast origin models are among them. Each models’ performance has been measured using the above performance metrics. <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> shows that the rolling forecast model has the minimum RMSE, MAPE, and RMSRE values. As a result, the rolling forecast model surpasses all the models. But as in our proposed approach, this model predicts only for one day, observes the predictions, and then includes them in the training set to predict the upcoming day. For this reason, it cannot be employed when we need predictions one week or month in advance. If we apply ARIMA for one-week advance prediction, the performance is substantially better. As a result, we consider ARIMA the best model, with the ARMA model ranking second, followed by the AR and MA models. If we only need the next-day estimate; hence the rolling forecast model will be the best choice.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>All proposed models’ performance to forecast the total number of confirmed cases.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Model</th><th align="left">RMSE</th><th align="left">MAE</th><th align="left">R<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e209" display="inline" altimg="si46.svg"><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th align="left">MAPE</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">ARIMA</td><td align="left">2965</td><td align="left">1965</td><td align="left">−0.06</td><td align="left">0.28</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ARMA</td><td align="left">3486</td><td align="left">2968</td><td align="left">−0.47</td><td align="left">0.29</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AR</td><td align="left">3231</td><td align="left">2023</td><td align="left">−0.26</td><td align="left">0.30</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MA</td><td align="left">3405</td><td align="left">2963</td><td align="left">−0.40</td><td align="left">0.29</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Rolling Forecast</td><td align="left">2693</td><td align="left">1920</td><td align="left">0.12</td><td align="left">0.24</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec3">
              <label>3</label>
              <title>Results</title>
              <p id="d1e2413">As discussed, the expected number of confirmed cases was forecasted using five alternate models. The data was divided into two parts; one was used for training while the other was for testing the models. The data were divided into training and testing sets in the ratio of 75:25. After training, the models were used to forecast the number of confirmed cases using the test set. <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref> shows the residuals of the four models, and <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref> represents the prediction of the test data for the four models.</p>
              <p id="d1e2423">In <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, it is observed that the residual of ARIMA (8,1,7) is more close to zero than any other model. And in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>, all the models’ predictions were near to the actual data until the time of July 21, 2021, when there was a drastic change. As the number of verified cases dropped dramatically, the models could not keep up with the actual data. For this decrease, the error of all the models’ increases; otherwise, the models performed satisfactorily at all the other periods. Here, a thing to notice is that the prediction of the MA model fluctuates a little fast, then it is almost flat. The reason is that a simple moving average model predicts the constant mean of the value. A simple MA has the limitation of only being able to estimate the number of periods equal to the lag employed in MA order.<fig id="fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Residuals of the ARIMA, ARMA, AR, and MA models.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr5_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Prediction result comparison for the daily confirmed cases in Bangladesh. ARIMA, ARMA, AR, and MA models were used for comparison.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr6_lrg"/></fig></p>
              <p id="d1e2437">In our model, the order for MA was (0,7), which explains why the first seven days’ prediction fluctuates. As a result, in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>, it fluctuates a little at first and then produces a constant mean of it. Also, in <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, we see the predictions of MA is constant after July 11, 2021. <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> shows the predicted confirmed cases for the test data from April 5, 2021, to April 28, 2021, along with the actual values. All the five models’ predictions have been shown here, and compared to them, the rolling forecast model comes closest to the actual values, followed by ARIMA, ARMA, AR, and MA.</p>
              <p id="d1e2451">The residuals and prediction of the rolling forecast model are shown in <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>, <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>. This rolling forecast model has used ARIMA(8,1,7) for prediction. As previously said, the rolling forecast only predicts the next day, and after observing the actual value, it learns and forecasts the next period. That is why this type of model is not always applicable.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Comparison of the predicted and actual values of the ARIMA, ARMA, AR, and MA models.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Date</th><th align="left">Actual</th><th align="left">ARIMA</th><th align="left">ARMA</th><th align="left">AR</th><th align="left">MA</th><th align="left">Rolling <break/>prediction</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">2021-07-05</td><td align="left">9964</td><td align="left">10381</td><td align="left">10180</td><td align="left">10511</td><td align="left">9053</td><td align="left">12132</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2021-07-06</td><td align="left">11525</td><td align="left">9908</td><td align="left">9370</td><td align="left">10446</td><td align="left">9328</td><td align="left">9521</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2021-07-07</td><td align="left">11162</td><td align="left">9897</td><td align="left">9082</td><td align="left">10644</td><td align="left">9161</td><td align="left">9752</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2021-07-08</td><td align="left">11651</td><td align="left">10482</td><td align="left">9708</td><td align="left">10505</td><td align="left">9737</td><td align="left">11665</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2021-07-09</td><td align="left">11324</td><td align="left">9725</td><td align="left">8836</td><td align="left">10250</td><td align="left">9287</td><td align="left">10869</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2021-07-10</td><td align="left">8772</td><td align="left">8514</td><td align="left">7336</td><td align="left">8790</td><td align="left">8910</td><td align="left">9826</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2021-07-11</td><td align="left">11874</td><td align="left">10192</td><td align="left">8883</td><td align="left">11050</td><td align="left">9232</td><td align="left">11113</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2021-07-12</td><td align="left">13768</td><td align="left">12041</td><td align="left">10362</td><td align="left">12483</td><td align="left">9232</td><td align="left">13962</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2021-07-13</td><td align="left">12198</td><td align="left">11601</td><td align="left">9302</td><td align="left">12497</td><td align="left">9232</td><td align="left">15250</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2021-07-14</td><td align="left">12383</td><td align="left">11340</td><td align="left">8779</td><td align="left">12206</td><td align="left">9232</td><td align="left">13591</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2021-07-15</td><td align="left">12236</td><td align="left">11858</td><td align="left">9456</td><td align="left">12242</td><td align="left">9232</td><td align="left">13081</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2021-07-16</td><td align="left">12148</td><td align="left">11313</td><td align="left">8726</td><td align="left">11779</td><td align="left">9232</td><td align="left">11809</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2021-07-17</td><td align="left">8489</td><td align="left">10346</td><td align="left">7357</td><td align="left">10987</td><td align="left">9232</td><td align="left">8911</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2021-07-18</td><td align="left">11578</td><td align="left">11602</td><td align="left">8572</td><td align="left">12961</td><td align="left">9232</td><td align="left">12319</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2021-07-19</td><td align="left">13321</td><td align="left">13387</td><td align="left">10042</td><td align="left">14139</td><td align="left">9232</td><td align="left">14195</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2021-07-20</td><td align="left">11579</td><td align="left">13106</td><td align="left">9014</td><td align="left">14040</td><td align="left">9232</td><td align="left">11860</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2021-07-21</td><td align="left">7614</td><td align="left">12627</td><td align="left">8321</td><td align="left">13529</td><td align="left">9232</td><td align="left">11472</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2021-07-22</td><td align="left">3697</td><td align="left">13052</td><td align="left">9072</td><td align="left">13618</td><td align="left">9232</td><td align="left">10901</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2021-07-23</td><td align="left">6364</td><td align="left">12717</td><td align="left">8552</td><td align="left">13128</td><td align="left">9232</td><td align="left">2298</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2021-07-24</td><td align="left">6780</td><td align="left">11927</td><td align="left">7267</td><td align="left">12826</td><td align="left">9232</td><td align="left">2867</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2021-07-25</td><td align="left">11291</td><td align="left">12890</td><td align="left">8250</td><td align="left">14512</td><td align="left">9232</td><td align="left">10804</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2021-07-26</td><td align="left">15192</td><td align="left">14527</td><td align="left">9675</td><td align="left">15485</td><td align="left">9232</td><td align="left">12382</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2021-07-27</td><td align="left">14925</td><td align="left">14404</td><td align="left">8733</td><td align="left">15216</td><td align="left">9232</td><td align="left">13233</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2021-07-28</td><td align="left">16230</td><td align="left">13793</td><td align="left">7911</td><td align="left">14637</td><td align="left">9232</td><td align="left">10014</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
              <p id="d1e2459">
                <fig id="fig7">
                  <label>Fig. 7</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Residuals of Rolling forecast model.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="gr7_lrg"/>
                </fig>
                <fig id="fig8">
                  <label>Fig. 8</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Forecasting results for the daily number of confirmed cases in Bangladesh using rolling forecast origin.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="gr8_lrg"/>
                </fig>
                <fig id="fig9">
                  <label>Fig. 9</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Forecasting results of the total number of daily confirmed cases in Bangladesh from July 29, 2021 to August 30, 2021. (For interpretation of the references to color in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the web version of this article.)</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="gr9_lrg"/>
                </fig>
                <table-wrap position="float" id="tbl4">
                  <label>Table 4</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>The forecasted outcome of the COVID-19 pandemic in Bangladesh for the next month using the ARIMA model.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left">Date</th>
                        <th align="left">Confirmed Case</th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-07-29</td>
                        <td align="left">14092</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-07-30</td>
                        <td align="left">13947</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-07-31</td>
                        <td align="left">13307</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-08-01</td>
                        <td align="left">14044</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-08-02</td>
                        <td align="left">15511</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-08-03</td>
                        <td align="left">15513</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-08-04</td>
                        <td align="left">14844</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-08-05</td>
                        <td align="left">15009</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-08-06</td>
                        <td align="left">15015</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-08-07</td>
                        <td align="left">14518</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-08-08</td>
                        <td align="left">15072</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-08-09</td>
                        <td align="left">16366</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-08-10</td>
                        <td align="left">16460</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-08-11</td>
                        <td align="left">15785</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-08-12</td>
                        <td align="left">15827</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-08-13</td>
                        <td align="left">15938</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-08-14</td>
                        <td align="left">15579</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-08-15</td>
                        <td align="left">15986</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-08-16</td>
                        <td align="left">17110</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-08-17</td>
                        <td align="left">17270</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-08-18</td>
                        <td align="left">16620</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-08-19</td>
                        <td align="left">16561</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-08-20</td>
                        <td align="left">16737</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-08-21</td>
                        <td align="left">16505</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-08-22</td>
                        <td align="left">16799</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-08-23</td>
                        <td align="left">17759</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-08-24</td>
                        <td align="left">17965</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-08-25</td>
                        <td align="left">17359</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-08-26</td>
                        <td align="left">17220</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-08-27</td>
                        <td align="left">17431</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-08-28</td>
                        <td align="left">17311</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-08-29</td>
                        <td align="left">17521</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left">2021-08-30</td>
                        <td align="left">18327</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </table-wrap>
              </p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec4">
              <label>4</label>
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p id="d1e2473">In the current world, there are still frightening increases in the number of cases of new coronavirus. The overall number of people affected is over 199 million, spreading across 222 countries, about 0.64% of Bangladesh. The primary goal of this study is to employ a commonly-used statistical analytic model, known as an ARIMA model, to observe and predict the epidemiology of COVID-19 in Bangladesh based on the data of daily confirmed cases publicly published by the Bangladesh Ministry of Health. We believe that theoretical studies based on statistical modeling are essential for understanding the pandemic features of the epidemic to forecast the COVID-19 pandemic’s possible trend. The results of such statistical models provide a complete picture of the present pandemic condition, allowing authorities to be active by developing plans and effective decisions to battle the pandemic and thereby limiting its impact on the economy, healthcare institutions, and society.</p>
              <p id="d1e2475">According to our findings, the ARIMA model’s prediction outperformed the other models described above. As such, after first-order difference processing, the daily number of confirmed COVID-19 cases in Bangladesh was forecasted using the ARIMA(8,1,7) model. The statistics suggest that the number of daily cases in Bangladesh might increase from 1492 to 17311 daily cases within one month. From this worrying increase in confirmed cases, it is crystal clear that Bangladeshi authorities must take immediate prevention and control strategies, particularly in the worst-affected cities such as Dhaka, Chittagong, Comilla, and Sylhet.</p>
              <p id="d1e2477">To combat the pandemic’s growing impact, different parties, including individuals and administration entities led by the Ministry of Health, must work together intensively. The first and most important proactive strategy is to ensure that everyone is vaccinated. Bangladesh started the first dose of COVID-19 vaccines on 21/2/7, while the second dose began on April 21, 2021. The faster mass vaccination begins, the less likely it is that people will become infected. Using the time series prediction model, lockdown can be applied to a specific district where the coronavirus rate is expected to be very high. Furthermore, more awareness is required, and a strong push to encourage people to practice proper hygiene and sanitation. The health ministry will be able to take effective measures in the coming days using this future prediction of coronavirus spread.</p>
              <p id="d1e2479">Building a reliable model to predict COVID-19 daily cases has constraints that begin with the uniqueness of the virus. It does not seem to follow any trend. After the first wave, the second wave arrived faster, and the third wave came in a flash. This work was completed on July 28, 2021, and we did not use the entire dataset for prediction. The infected rate in Bangladesh was very low at the start of 2020. All death and confirmed case records have surpassed in the third wave, which starts in April 2021. That is why we only used that dataset to predict for the upcoming days.</p>
              <p id="d1e2481">Although the rolling forecast model outperformed ARIMA, we consider ARIMA to be the best model in this case. Because the rolling forecast only predicts for a single day, then it trains itself and predicts the next period based on the accuracy of the previous prediction. As a result, despite having a low error rate, it is never a good choice. A forecast for a single day will not assist control makers in making any decisions. Although the ARIMA model is often an excellent choice for such a forecast problem, it does have a few drawbacks, including the lack of automatic updates. When new data is added, a new run is required. In addition, the structure of the ARIMA model is linear, but there is non-linearity in our problem, which is why accuracy is likely to be reduced.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec5">
              <label>5</label>
              <title>Conclusion</title>
              <p id="d1e2488">More research is being conducted to forecast the COVID-19, as the outcome of this disaster affects our daily lives. Many researchers have been using different types of prediction models. In this work, we used AR (8,0), MA (0,7), ARMA (8,7), ARIMA (8,1,7), and rolling forecast with ARIMA (8,1,7) models to forecast the spread of the COVID-19 outbreak in Bangladesh. The best forecasting model for predicting the daily confirmed cases’ trend in Bangladesh was discovered to be ARIMA (8,1,7). The daily production number of confirmed cases was estimated for the next month using this model. By August 20, 2021, the estimated daily confirmed cases could reach 18327. These findings could motivate policymakers to take the required steps to combat the COVID-19 pandemic, such as implementing new movement restrictions and conducting mass vaccinations for COVID-19 cases across the country.</p>
              <p id="d1e2490">However, further research is needed to analyze which type of forecasting method or model is the most accurate for different situations around the world. Different countries have different patterns in COVID-19 characteristics, and based on their variants, appropriate algorithms need to be selected. There is a high possibility that the input data was not completely accurate for various reasons, such as an infected individual being asymptotic, not being tested, or not being registered in the database. Despite this, the gradual learning strategy can overcome the inaccuracy of the incoming data. Furthermore, an unidentified suspect in the community believes that a few countries are submitting fraudulent data for political purposes. Many countries, including Bangladesh, imposed social distance and lockdown, which impacted the number of cases and casualties. By taking these aspects into account, the forecasts’ outcomes may be affected. While we attempted to produce a promising result for the Bangladesh data, we still need to test on many other databases for more accurate findings. Nonetheless, the data show AI’s promise and success in forecasting a pandemic.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="COI-statement">
              <title>Declaration of Competing Interest</title>
              <p id="d1e2495">The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list id="bib1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="b1">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb1">
                  <part-title>Bangladesh: WHO coronavirus disease (COVID-19) dashboard with vaccination data</part-title>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <comment>[Online]. URL <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://covid19.who.int/region/searo/country/bd/" id="interref1">https://covid19.who.int/region/searo/country/bd/</ext-link>, [Accessed on 02.08.2021]</comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b2">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Surveillances</surname>
                      <given-names>V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The epidemiological characteristics of an outbreak of 2019 novel coronavirus diseases (COVID-19)—China, 2020</article-title>
                  <source>China CDC Weekly</source>
                  <volume>2</volume>
                  <issue>8</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>113</fpage>
                  <lpage>122</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34594836</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b3">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Haghani</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bliemer</surname>
                      <given-names>M.C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goerlandt</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The scientific literature on coronaviruses, COVID-19 and its associated safety-related research dimensions: A scientometric analysis and scoping review</article-title>
                  <source>Saf Sci</source>
                  <volume>129</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">104806</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b4">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb4">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kumar</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Susan</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>Covid-19 pandemic prediction using time series forecasting models</part-title>
                  <source>2020 11th international conference on computing, communication and networking technologies (ICCCNT)</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <publisher-name>IEEE</publisher-name>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>7</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b5">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb5">
                  <part-title>Coronavirus cases: worldometer</part-title>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <comment>[Online]. URL <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus/country/bangladesh/" id="interref2">https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus/country/bangladesh/</ext-link>, [Accessed on 02.08.2021]</comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b6">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb6">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mahalle</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kalamkar</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dey</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chaki</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shinde</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>Forecasting models for coronavirus (COVID-19): a survey of the state-of-the-art</part-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <comment>TechRxiv</comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b7">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb7">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alzahrani</surname>
                      <given-names>S.I.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aljamaan</surname>
                      <given-names>I.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Al-Fakih</surname>
                      <given-names>E.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Forecasting the spread of the COVID-19 pandemic in Saudi Arabia using ARIMA prediction model under current public health interventions</article-title>
                  <source>J Infection Public Health</source>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>914</fpage>
                  <lpage>919</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b8">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb8">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sahai</surname>
                      <given-names>A.K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rath</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sood</surname>
                      <given-names>V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Singh</surname>
                      <given-names>M.P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Arima modelling &amp; forecasting of COVID-19 in top five affected countries</article-title>
                  <source>Diabetes Metab Syndr: Clin Res Rev</source>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1419</fpage>
                  <lpage>1427</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b9">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb9">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Khan</surname>
                      <given-names>F.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gupta</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>ARIMA and NAR based prediction model for time series analysis of COVID-19 cases in India</article-title>
                  <source>J Safety Sci Resilience</source>
                  <volume>1</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>12</fpage>
                  <lpage>18</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb10">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chowdhury</surname>
                      <given-names>A.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hasan</surname>
                      <given-names>K.T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hoque</surname>
                      <given-names>K.K.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Analysis and prediction of COVID-19 pandemic in Bangladesh by using ANFIS and LSTM network</article-title>
                  <source>Cogn Comput</source>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <fpage>761</fpage>
                  <lpage>770</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb11">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kufel</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Arima-based forecasting of the dynamics of confirmed Covid-19 cases for selected European countries</article-title>
                  <source>Equilib Q J Econ Econ Policy</source>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>181</fpage>
                  <lpage>204</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb12">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dehesh</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mardani-Fard</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dehesh</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>Forecasting of covid-19 confirmed cases in different countries with arima models</part-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <comment>MedRxiv</comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb13">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tandon</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ranjan</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chakraborty</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Suhag</surname>
                      <given-names>V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>Coronavirus (COVID-19): ARIMA based time-series analysis to forecast near future</part-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <comment>arXiv preprint <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="arxiv:2004.07859" id="interref3">arXiv:2004.07859</ext-link></comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb14">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ceylan</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Estimation of COVID-19 prevalence in Italy, Spain, and France</article-title>
                  <source>Sci Total Environ</source>
                  <volume>729</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">138817</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb15">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kumar</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gupta</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kumar</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sachdeva</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Spreading of COVID-19 in India, Italy, Japan, Spain, UK, US: a prediction using ARIMA and LSTM model</article-title>
                  <source>Digit Gov: Res Practice</source>
                  <volume>1</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>9</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b16">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb16">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kundu</surname>
                      <given-names>L.R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ferdous</surname>
                      <given-names>M.Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Islam</surname>
                      <given-names>U.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sultana</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Forecasting the spread of COVID-19 pandemic in Bangladesh using arima model</article-title>
                  <source>Asian J Med Biol Res</source>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <lpage>32</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b17">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb17">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bayyurt</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bayyurt</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>Forecasting of COVID-19 cases and deaths using ARIMA models</part-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <comment>Medrxiv</comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b18">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb18">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Barría-Sandoval</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ferreira</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Benz-Parra</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>López-Flores</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Prediction of confirmed cases of and deaths caused by COVID-19 in Chile through time series techniques: A comparative study</article-title>
                  <source>Plos One</source>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0245414</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b19">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb19">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Banerjee</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>Forecasting of Indian stock market using time-series ARIMA model</part-title>
                  <source>2014 2nd international conference on business and information management (ICBIM)</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <publisher-name>IEEE</publisher-name>
                  <fpage>131</fpage>
                  <lpage>135</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b20">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb20">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Meher</surname>
                      <given-names>B.K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hawaldar</surname>
                      <given-names>I.T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Spulbar</surname>
                      <given-names>C.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Birau</surname>
                      <given-names>F.R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Forecasting stock market prices using mixed ARIMA model: A case study of Indian pharmaceutical companies</article-title>
                  <source>Invest Manag Financial Innov</source>
                  <volume>18</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <fpage>42</fpage>
                  <lpage>54</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b21">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb21">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ariyo</surname>
                      <given-names>A.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Adewumi</surname>
                      <given-names>A.O.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ayo</surname>
                      <given-names>C.K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>Stock price prediction using the ARIMA model</part-title>
                  <source>2014 UKSim-AMSS 16th international conference on computer modelling and simulation</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <publisher-name>IEEE</publisher-name>
                  <fpage>106</fpage>
                  <lpage>112</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b22">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb22">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shivhare</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rahul</surname>
                      <given-names>A.K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dwivedi</surname>
                      <given-names>S.B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dikshit</surname>
                      <given-names>P.K.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>ARIMA based daily weather forecasting tool: A case study for varanasi</article-title>
                  <source>MAUSAM</source>
                  <volume>70</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <fpage>133</fpage>
                  <lpage>140</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b23">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb23">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Devi</surname>
                      <given-names>B.U.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sundar</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alli</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An effective time series analysis for stock trend prediction using ARIMA model for nifty midcap-50</article-title>
                  <source>Int J Data Min Knowl Manag Process</source>
                  <volume>3</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <fpage>65</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b24">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb24">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Anokye</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Acheampong</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Owusu</surname>
                      <given-names>I.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Isaac Obeng</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Time series analysis of malaria in Kumasi: Using ARIMA models to forecast future incidence</article-title>
                  <source>Cogent Soc Sci</source>
                  <volume>4</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1461544</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b25">
                <label>25</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb25">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Anwar</surname>
                      <given-names>M.Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lewnard</surname>
                      <given-names>J.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Parikh</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pitzer</surname>
                      <given-names>V.E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Time series analysis of malaria in Afghanistan: using ARIMA models to predict future trends in incidence</article-title>
                  <source>Malar J</source>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>10</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26729363</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b26">
                <label>26</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb26">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pinter</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Felde</surname>
                      <given-names>I.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mosavi</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ghamisi</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gloaguen</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>Covid-19 pandemic prediction for hungary; a hybrid machine learning approach</part-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <comment>MedRxiv</comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b27">
                <label>27</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb27">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tomar</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gupta</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Prediction for the spread of COVID-19 in India and effectiveness of preventive measures</article-title>
                  <source>Sci Total Environ</source>
                  <volume>728</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">138762</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
            <ack id="d1e2497">
              <title>Acknowledgments</title>
              <p id="d1e2500">We want to acknowledge the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering (ECE), Rajshahi University of Engineering &amp; Technology (RUET), to facilitate the work.</p>
            </ack>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
