<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-03-11T00:49:38Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8423815" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8423815</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-09-08</datestamp>
        <setSpec>pheelsevier</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.xsd" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Physica A</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Physica A</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Physica a</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0378-4371</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">0378-4371</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Elsevier B.V.</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC8423815</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8423815</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">8423815</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34511711</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pii">S0378-4371(21)00674-9</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.physa.2021.126401</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">126401</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>An agent-based model of spread of a pandemic with validation using COVID-19 data from New York State</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au000001">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Datta</surname>
                    <given-names>Amitava</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
                  <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au000002">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Winkelstein</surname>
                    <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au000003">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Sen</surname>
                    <given-names>Surajit</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Computer Science and Software Engineering, The University of Western Australia, 35 Stirling Highway, Perth, WA 6009, Australia</aff>
                <aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Institute for Healthcare Informatics, Jacobs School of Medicine, University at Buffalo - The State University of New York, Buffalo, NY, 14203, USA</aff>
                <aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Department of Physics, University at Buffalo - The State University of New York, Buffalo, NY, 14260-1500, USA</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author.</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>8</day>
                <month>9</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.-->
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <day>1</day>
                <month>1</month>
                <year>2022</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>8</day>
                <month>9</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>585</volume>
              <fpage>126401</fpage>
              <lpage>126401</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>3</day>
                  <month>4</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>12</day>
                  <month>8</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2021 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
                <copyright-holder>Elsevier B.V.</copyright-holder>
                <license>
                  <license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="d1e652">
                <p>We introduce a novel agent based model where each agent carries an effective viral load that captures the instantaneous state of infection of the agent. We simulate the spread of a pandemic and subsequently validate it by using publicly available COVID-19 data. Our simulation tracks the temporal evolution of a virtual city or community of agents in terms of contracting infection, recovering asymptomatically, or getting hospitalized. The virtual community is divided into family groups with 2–6 individuals in each group. Agents interact with other agents in virtual public places like at grocery stores, on public transportation and in offices. We initially seed the virtual community with a very small number of infected individuals and then monitor the disease spread and hospitalization over a period of fifty days, which is a reasonable time-frame for the initial spread of a pandemic. An uninfected or asymptomatic agent is randomly selected from a random family group in each simulation step for visiting a random public space. Subsequently, an uninfected agent contracts infection if the public place is occupied by other infected agents. We have calibrated our simulation rounds according to the size of the population of the virtual community for simulating realistic exposure of agents to a contagion. Our simulation results are consistent with the publicly available hospitalization and ICU patient data from three distinct regions of varying sizes in New York state. Our model can predict the trend in epidemic spread and hospitalization from a set of simple parameters and could be potentially useful in <italic>predicting the disease evolution based on available data and observations about public behavior.</italic> Our simulations suggest that relaxing the social distancing measures may increase the hospitalization numbers by some 30% or more.</p>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group id="d1e661">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>Pandemic spreading</kwd>
                <kwd>Agent based modeling</kwd>
                <kwd>COVID-19 spreading</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="sec1">
              <label>1</label>
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p id="d1e680">Epidemiological models for spread of infectious diseases play an important role in policy decisions for mitigating the spread of an outbreak of a highly infectious disease. Perhaps the earliest work on such modeling was by Kermack and McKendrik <xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. They introduced a class of models referred to as compartmental models <xref rid="b2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. Nowadays these models are often referred to as the SIR (Susceptible, Infected, Recovered) models or some equivalent thereof <xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. Here, the entire population is divided into three compartments according to these labels and the transitions of people from one compartment to another determine the <italic>rates</italic> of infected and recovered people. Infected people may infect susceptible people, and infected people may either develop immunity, or may be removed from the population due to death. Similarly new individuals enter the population due to birth. However birth and death may be ignored and the population may be considered as conserved during rapid spread of a disease without incurring significant calculational errors. The transition rates between the compartments are the free parameters in this model.</p>
              <p id="d1e697">The SIR model has been extended in several different ways. For example only two compartments, susceptible and infectious are used when individuals do not develop immunity in case of diseases like influenza. The SIRD (susceptible–infectious–recovered–deceased) model differentiates between the recovered and deceased compartments. Infected individuals can either recover or die. The transitions over time are modeled as first order differential equations in all SIR models. These models also have been discretized and simulated <xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>.</p>
              <p id="d1e703">There are over fifty models currently deployed in Covid-19ForecastHub <xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref> for forecasting the incidence of infection and death due to Covid-19. Most of these models are different adaptations of the SIR model, regression models or ensemble models. The main aim of the models is to accurately predict the spread of infection and deaths by using the data known until now. Hence the objectives of these models are quite different from the model we present in this paper. In spite of their success, the compartmental models are simplistic and consider only homogeneous population groups within each compartment. As a result, complex interactions between individuals or complex behavior of individuals are hard to capture in these models <xref rid="b6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. The spread of a pandemic is a complex phenomenon that is determined largely by the interactions between individuals in a community and, for example, the way a virus can remain active on the surfaces of inanimate objects. These models may not naturally be best suited to make forward predictions. Furthermore, it is unrealistic to assume that each member in a population will behave in an effectively uniform (rationally or irrationally) homogeneous way in a pandemic situation.</p>
              <p id="d1e713">These shortcomings of the compartmental models were pointed out by Epstein <xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref> and Parker and Epstein <xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. They argued that the assumption of a homogeneous nature of population is in particular unrealistic in compartmental models, since complexity of interactions among individuals through their access to public places and social networks are quite often difficult to capture in these models. Agent-based modeling can capture these nuances of interactions in a society more accurately. National Institute of Health’s Models of Infectious Disease Agent Study (MIDAS) program <xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref> based on agent based simulation helped in formulating policies during the avian flu or H5N1 pandemic.</p>
              <p id="d1e727">Parker and Epstein <xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref> reported a global scale agent-based simulation of six billion people for modeling the spread of a pandemic. While the spread of a pandemic is not restricted by national borders in today’s global world, quite often the public policies for preventing the spread of a pandemic are dictated by local situations within a country, state or even a city. Hence it is an important and interesting question to examine whether agent-based models can simulate local situations accurately <xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. In particular, an accurate simulation based on a local trend of the spread of a pandemic can give the authorities the scope to frame local policies regarding social distancing measures to curb the future spread of a pandemic. Local and national governments are grappling with this problem of framing appropriate national and local policies rapidly in many countries around the world, including the USA, India, China and the countries in the European Union.</p>
              <p id="d1e737">Validating a model of pandemic spread is a challenging problem. It is challenging to estimate the extent of the spread, as many infected individuals remain asymptomatic. Testing is often reactive, rather than proactive. Individuals are mostly tested when they display symptoms, hence the number of positive cases identified through testing is often biased. One possibility is to consider death rates due to a pandemic, as has been done in many works such as in Ref. <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. However the death rate alone may not be a reliable measure of the spread of a pandemic, due to the fact that quite often older individuals with other health problems (so called co-morbidity) succumb to a new infection disproportionately. Further, it is likely that the number of COVID deaths may be under-reported and there can be significant lags between the actual time of death and the time the death certificate is issued <xref rid="b13" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. The challenging aspect of framing public policy is to capture the severity of infection, as severity puts pressure on the health infrastructure in terms of provisioning hospital beds and intensive care units (ICU).</p>
              <p id="d1e747">Hence in this paper we consider hospitalization and ICU data for validating our model. As we shall see, our study projects proportions of deaths which seem largely consistent with those reported in various sources. It is possible to use robust and publicly available data as hospitalization and ICU figures are available from the government health departments, for example, from the New York state government <xref rid="b15" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. Of course the assumption here is that all severely infected patients can be accommodated in hospitals, which is the case in most developed countries, e.g., <xref rid="b15" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, and at least in the initial stages of a pandemic in developing countries. It should, however, be noted that in New York as time progressed fewer patients were transferred to the ICUs due to an improved ability to treat these patients in the hospitals. Thus, the proportions of people who ended up in the ICUs did not remain a constant in time <xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. However, in our work we have regarded this number as a constant for the sake of simplicity. Further refinements of the model or reducing the proportion of people who are transferred to ICU can indeed be easily varied in our study.</p>
              <p id="d1e761">The rest of the paper is organized as follows. We discuss the details of our model and the methodology in Section <xref rid="sec2" ref-type="sec">2</xref>, we discuss the results in Section <xref rid="sec3" ref-type="sec">3</xref>, and we conclude with discussions and future work in Section <xref rid="sec4" ref-type="sec">4</xref>.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec2">
              <label>2</label>
              <title>The model</title>
              <sec id="sec2.1">
                <label>2.1</label>
                <title>Geographical considerations</title>
                <p id="d1e789">We present an agent-based modeling framework for local communities and cities in this paper. To our knowledge, this work is distinct from other attempts using an agent based approach (see for example in Ref. <xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>). We introduce two types of entities in this model: home groups and public places. Each home group consists of <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e796" display="inline" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> members and each public place has a fixed capacity. We ignore single family households in this initial study, which is detailed below. We start the simulation with a small percentage of infected agents among the members of the home groups (typically about 0.01% of the total population). In each time step of the simulation, a random member of a randomly chosen home group visits a random public place if all the public places are not filled to capacity. An agent picks up a unit amount of infection from a public place in the presence of other infected agents.</p>
                <p id="d1e805">The present study has a geographical context. It is set up to approximately describe COVID-19 spread for the population of New York State in the early days of the pandemic. Large public places were mostly closed in the state during this period and life was not business as usual. People have hence been mostly going out to get groceries and medicines. Hence, the assumption of a select group of public places with an average fixed capacity is reasonable for our purposes.</p>
                <p id="d1e807">We let there be a population of <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e810" display="inline" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> agents divided into <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e815" display="inline" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> home groups, each with <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e820" display="inline" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> members. The size of a home group <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e831" display="inline" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, denoted by <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e841" display="inline" altimg="si6.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is chosen randomly within this range, although the population <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e856" display="inline" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is fixed. In other words, <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e861" display="inline" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is chosen so that <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e867" display="inline" altimg="si9.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The number of time steps <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e894" display="inline" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> in our simulation is based on the notion of a virtual day. The simulation is run for <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e899" display="inline" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>50</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> days, each day consisting of a number of time steps depending on <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e905" display="inline" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. This is done to create a realistic situation where at least one member from each home group has a chance to visit a public place (e.g., a grocery store for getting provisions) at least four times during the simulation period. Note, however, that it is not guaranteed that members of each home group will visit public places at least four times due to the stochasticity in the choice of agents in each simulation step. Hence the total number of simulation steps is <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e911" display="inline" altimg="si13.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Σ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and a day, denoted by <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e938" display="inline" altimg="si14.svg"><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, consists of <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e943" display="inline" altimg="si15.svg"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Σ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>50</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula> iterations. There are <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e974" display="inline" altimg="si16.svg"><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> public places <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e980" display="inline" altimg="si17.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, each with a presumed average capacity <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1013" display="inline" altimg="si18.svg"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. We have kept the capacities of the public places homogeneous with a realistic assumption that an agent comes into contact with only a small number of other agents irrespective of the total capacity of a public place. We vary the <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1018" display="inline" altimg="si18.svg"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> for implementing social distancing measures in our model. We are hence able to connect the possible outcomes of increased capacity of public places with disease spread. This issue is addressed at a semi-quantitative level towards the end of this work. In our realization, an overall lower capacity in public places would expose a smaller number of agents to infection, which is the aim of social distancing.</p>
                <p id="d1e1022">We note, however, that in reality it is challenging to know the capacity of a public place such as a local grocery store. While the place can, say, accommodate 120 people when it comes to the fire codes, on average the typical crowded store may have a capacity of more like 60 people, thus resulting in an average capacity of 50%. Our assumption of an average capacity of 1% hence should be roughly consistent with the strong social distancing seen in most public places in the early months of the pandemic in New York State.</p>
                <p id="d1e1024">The literature on home infections reflect that the issue is unresolved <xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="b19" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. In our model, the isolation of the exposed agents in their homes is assumed to be essentially perfect for most of the work discussed in Section <xref rid="sec3" ref-type="sec">3</xref>. However, the results of some simulations where this restriction is lifted and the spread of infection at home is made possible if there are one or more infected agents at home are briefly addressed.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2.2">
                <label>2.2</label>
                <title>Viral load and pandemic spread in time</title>
                <sec id="sec2.2.1">
                  <label>2.2.1</label>
                  <title>The viral load parameter</title>
                  <p id="d1e1045">Our aim is to choose parameters from the very early trends of the spread and validate the model through officially reported data on hospitalization and admission to ICU. We have used New York State reported data for benchmarking all our calculations. We note in this context the work on COVID-19 spreading by Keskinocak et al. <xref rid="b20" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref> who exploited an agent-based model to mainly explore the effects of social distancing measures. These authors compare their simulation results with data on spreading of infection. We contend that the data on the spreading of the infection alone may not be accurate enough to make sure if a model is working well due to possible inaccuracies and reliability issues associated with testing.</p>
                  <p id="d1e1051">Our study invokes an effective viral load parameter to describe viral load changes in individuals. This approach has the advantage of having asymptomatic agents who can still infect others. Depending upon the effective viral loads carried, we assume that there are four categories of agents in our simulations. We also let the entire population to be susceptible to infection and allow only a part of the population to have better immune response. This segment of the population can recover from the infection asymptomatically.</p>
                  <p id="d1e1053">The four categories of agents in our model are as follows:<fig id="fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>The growth in the viral loads of agents in all the four categories of agents is captured and averaged over 10 simulations to construct the parameters used in our model (see discussion in Section <xref rid="sec2.2.2" ref-type="sec">2.2.2</xref>). The three transition points are <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e32" display="inline" altimg="si20.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> (category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e42" display="inline" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents start recovering), <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e48" display="inline" altimg="si22.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> (category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e58" display="inline" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents are hospitalized), and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e63" display="inline" altimg="si24.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> (category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e73" display="inline" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents start recovering, whereas, category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e79" display="inline" altimg="si26.svg"><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents progress to death). <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e84" display="inline" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the plateau region. <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> explains <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e93" display="inline" altimg="si20.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e104" display="inline" altimg="si22.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e114" display="inline" altimg="si24.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e124" display="inline" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig></p>
                  <p id="d1e1057">
                    <def-list>
                      <def-item>
                        <term id="dt1">category 1:</term>
                        <def>
                          <p id="d1e1063">Some agents get infected and a subset of them recover asymptomatically as category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1066" display="inline" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents.</p>
                        </def>
                      </def-item>
                      <def-item>
                        <term id="dt2">category 2:</term>
                        <def>
                          <p id="d1e1073">Some of the category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1076" display="inline" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents transition to category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1081" display="inline" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents and their viral loads continue to increase until they are hospitalized. Some of the category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1086" display="inline" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents recover after hospitalization and some develop further complications and are admitted to ICU.</p>
                        </def>
                      </def-item>
                      <def-item>
                        <term id="dt3">category 3:</term>
                        <def>
                          <p id="d1e1093">Some of the agents admitted to ICU eventually die as category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1096" display="inline" altimg="si26.svg"><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents.</p>
                        </def>
                      </def-item>
                      <def-item>
                        <term id="dt4">category 4:</term>
                        <def>
                          <p id="d1e1103">Some of the agents admitted to ICU recover as category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1106" display="inline" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents.</p>
                        </def>
                      </def-item>
                    </def-list>
                  </p>
                  <p id="d1e1110">The effective viral load of a category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1113" display="inline" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agent reaches a low threshold, stabilizes for a certain time and then a typical agent recovers with a presumed exponential decay of the viral load. The exponential decay is assumed because we chose to assign the gradual reduction of the effective viral load to have a characteristic time scale as opposed to being scale-free. We do not consider immunity in this work. Hence agents who have recovered from a mild infection may get infected again.</p>
                  <p id="d1e1117">The effective viral load of a category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1120" display="inline" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agent continues to grow until it reaches a higher value that requires hospitalization. A category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1125" display="inline" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agent has two possible outcomes. One possibility is that a category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1130" display="inline" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agent may stay in the hospital for a certain number of days and then recovers through an exponential decay of its viral load.</p>
                  <p id="d1e1134">Otherwise a category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1137" display="inline" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agent is shifted to ICU after a certain period, and then may either transform into a category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1142" display="inline" altimg="si26.svg"><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agent and dies, or recovers from ICU as a category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1147" display="inline" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agent, again through an exponential decay of its viral load. Since our simulation time frame is rather limited, we assume that agents in categories <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1153" display="inline" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1158" display="inline" altimg="si26.svg"><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1163" display="inline" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> do not visit any public places.</p>
                  <p id="d1e1167">We have chosen these categories in order to validate our model in a robust manner given that the data for hospitalization and admission to ICU are quite robust and publicly available <xref rid="b15" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. Note that we have avoided using the death rate as a quantity that is being tracked in our model except to assume that the number of deaths of the agents in the ICUs should be consistent with the overall number of deaths in the entire period of our simulations.</p>
                  <p id="d1e1173">The main result of this paper is that simple agent-based models provide a way to explain the hospitalization numbers and admission to ICUs based upon parameters that can be constructed through trial and error as well as with directly available data as detailed below.</p>
                  <p id="d1e1176">Our calculated viral load profiles of random individuals from various effective viral load categories, those who get mildly sick, those who get sick enough to be hospitalized, then among them those who transition to ICUs and may or may not survive, are reported in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>. The transition times and the duration of the plateaus are averages of ten random agents from each category by tracking them during the simulation. The plateau regions of infections in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> are between 3–6 days, according to our notion of a virtual day, randomly chosen for each agent. The viral load of a category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1187" display="inline" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agent increases for one day, that of category 2,3 and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1193" display="inline" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents increases for three days. The separation between category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1198" display="inline" altimg="si26.svg"><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1203" display="inline" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents occurs after one day in the ICU, i.e., category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1208" display="inline" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents lose their viral load through an exponential decay and category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1214" display="inline" altimg="si26.svg"><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents progress towards death through an exponential rise in viral load.</p>
                  <p id="d1e1218">The life-cycle of an agent is as follows. An agent either stays at home, or visits a public place. The viral load of an uninfected agent is zero and continues to be so when it stays at home. A random agent is selected from a random home group in each simulation step, provided the agent is not a category 2,3 or <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1221" display="inline" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agent. Category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1226" display="inline" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents may be chosen at any stage and we assume that these agents are asymptomatic and able to visit public places. Once an agent is chosen, it visits a public place depending on the availability of space in the public place. We randomly choose a public place to accommodate the agent. A simulation step is considered as a <italic>failure</italic> if all the public places are already filled. Once an agent enters a public place, it stays there for a small amount of time, arbitrarily fixed at about <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1234" display="inline" altimg="si56.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> minutes according to our calibration. An uninfected agent gets infected if the public place was previously visited by other infected agents, or if there are other infected agents currently visiting the public place. We assume this initial infection to be a small amount of viral load, as a particular agent may visit a public place at most a few times and the duration of the stay at a public place is also short. Finer models of initial infection, e.g., an exponential increase in viral load depending upon how many other infected agents are simultaneously present in the public place, did not show any qualitative differences in our simulation.</p>
                  <p id="d1e1239">Agents spend most of the simulation time in their home groups. An agent enters its home group after returning from a public place and remains there unless chosen again to visit a public place. Only uninfected or category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1242" display="inline" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents can visit a public place. While in a home group, the viral load of each agent increases by a unit amount in each time step until a threshold is reached as discussed below. This is the rationale behind our calibration of the simulation time in terms of days, as the viral loads for the transitions in the model are reached due to this increase over specific number of days of simulation time. Hence there are basically two simple transitions in an agent’s life, home to public place and back. We have assumed that the other members of a home group are not infected due to the presence of an infected member, in other words isolation at home is perfect. However it is easy to lift this restriction in our simulation, though the only qualitative effect is an increased rate of infection. Another way of implementing this infection in home groups is to randomly infect a small number of uninfected agents if there is any infected agents in their home groups. However, this refinement also does not produce qualitatively different results.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="sec2.2.2">
                  <label>2.2.2</label>
                  <title>Fixing the transitions in the parameters</title>
                  <p id="d1e1251">We now discuss the transitions between the categories of agents in our model. <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> shows a flow chart explaining these transitions. There are three transition probabilities in our model, <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1260" display="inline" altimg="si105.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1274" display="inline" altimg="si106.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>34</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1289" display="inline" altimg="si107.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>. These transition probabilities along with the capacity of the public places are the free parameters in our model. When category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1303" display="inline" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents reach their threshold of viral load, a fraction of them transitions into category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1308" display="inline" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents whose viral loads keep on increasing, while the remaining agents remain as category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1313" display="inline" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, enter the plateau of incubation and finally recover through an exponential decay of their viral load, as shown in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>. This transition from category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1323" display="inline" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1328" display="inline" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> occurs according to the probability <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1333" display="inline" altimg="si105.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>. The second probability <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1348" display="inline" altimg="si106.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>34</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> separates the category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1362" display="inline" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents from category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1367" display="inline" altimg="si26.svg"><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1372" display="inline" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents, when category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1378" display="inline" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents reach the higher threshold of viral load in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>. Category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1387" display="inline" altimg="si26.svg"><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1392" display="inline" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents are more vulnerable and their viral loads increase after the incubation period and they are admitted to ICU, while category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1398" display="inline" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents recover. The third probability <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1403" display="inline" altimg="si107.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> separates category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1417" display="inline" altimg="si26.svg"><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1422" display="inline" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents after they are admitted to ICU. There is an initial increase in viral load for both categories, but category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1428" display="inline" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents recover after that, whereas category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1433" display="inline" altimg="si26.svg"><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents progress towards death.<fig id="fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>A flow chart explaining the transitions between different categories of agents.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2_lrg"/></fig></p>
                  <p id="d1e1437">This model captures a realistic scenario of spread of a pandemic in which infection is transmitted through air and different surfaces. Hence public places are the primary source of spreading the infection. There are several sources of stochasticity in our model, the agents who visit the public places are chosen randomly, and category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1440" display="inline" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents may be chosen repeatedly. The incubation time of the virus in an agent is random within a range, and the probabilities with which an agent transitions from one category to another are also sources of stochasticity. We will analyze the results of our simulation in terms of incremental hospitalization and admission to ICU, comparing with such incremental data released by the health authorities. It will be clear that these three probabilities and the initial seeding (the four free parameters) are sufficient to match reliable data for the COVID-19 epidemic. We are not aware of simple modeling efforts that are able to incorporate the considered level of averaged granularity and have attempted to match local level hospitalization data.</p>
                  <p id="d1e1444">We now discuss the parameters in the model. They can be classified into <italic>sensitive</italic> or <italic>robust</italic>. The probabilities <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1453" display="inline" altimg="si81.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>34</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1481" display="inline" altimg="si107.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> are sensitive parameters. Any change of one of these probabilities influences the next probability drastically. For example, if we increase the probability of transition from category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1496" display="inline" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1501" display="inline" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, i.e., <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1506" display="inline" altimg="si105.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, there will be more category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1520" display="inline" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents in the population and consequently there will be more category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1526" display="inline" altimg="si26.svg"><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1531" display="inline" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents. Similarly, if we increase the probability of transition from category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1536" display="inline" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> to categories 3,4, i.e, <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1541" display="inline" altimg="si106.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>34</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, the populations of category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1556" display="inline" altimg="si26.svg"><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1561" display="inline" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents increase. The sensitivity of these probabilities results in higher levels of hospitalization and admission to ICU, the two specific data that we use for validating our model. However, one important aspect of our model is that these probabilities can be tuned by using the hospitalization and ICU data for an initial and relatively short period, and then the trend predicted by the model matches with the actual trend of hospitalization and ICU later.</p>
                  <p id="d1e1565">The robust parameters are related to the different viral load thresholds and the stable levels of viral loads after the thresholds are reached, i.e., the plateau regions in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>. We denote the viral load threshold for category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1572" display="inline" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents as <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1577" display="inline" altimg="si20.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, that of category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1588" display="inline" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents as <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1593" display="inline" altimg="si22.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, and the threshold for separating category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1603" display="inline" altimg="si26.svg"><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents from category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1608" display="inline" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents as <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1614" display="inline" altimg="si24.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>. Recall that the plateau region for a stable viral load for all agents is chosen as between <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1624" display="inline" altimg="si26.svg"><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1629" display="inline" altimg="si101.svg"><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> days, randomly for each agent. This plateau region is denoted by <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1634" display="inline" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. We show in the results section that our simulation results do not have much qualitative changes if we vary the parameters <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1640" display="inline" altimg="si103.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1669" display="inline" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. We summarize these parameters in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. The first four parameters are sensitive and the next five are relatively robust.</p>
                  <p id="d1e1677">The model was simulated with ANSI-C multi-threaded code using the OpenMP library. A distributed memory version was tested using the MPI library, however, the communication overhead caused lower performance. The simulations were run on the Pawsey supercomputer facility in Perth, Western Australia on two different architectures. The first one is Magnus, a Cray XC40 supercomputer, each compute node includes two Intel Xeon E52690-V3 (Haswell) processors, each with 12 cores, 24 cores in total. The second architecture is Zeus, each node containing two Intel Xeon E5-2680 V4 (Broadwell) 14-core CPUs, for a total of 28 cores. It was necessary to run the longer simulations on Zeus due to a 24-hour time limit for each job on Magnus. The simulation time for a population of <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1682" display="inline" altimg="si112.svg"><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> million is about <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1687" display="inline" altimg="si113.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>42</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> hours, and that for a population of 1.2 million is about <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1693" display="inline" altimg="si101.svg"><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> hours. Hence it was difficult to explore the parameter space for the simulation of New York city.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The parameters in our model.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e341" display="inline" altimg="si105.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">transition probability for hospitalization</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e359" display="inline" altimg="si106.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>34</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">transition probability between category 2 and 3,4</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e377" display="inline" altimg="si107.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">transition probability between category 3 and 4</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">seed</td><td align="left">initial seeding of infected agents</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">capacity</td><td align="left">capacity of public places</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td colspan="3"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e407" display="inline" altimg="si20.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">viral load threshold for category 1 agents</td><td align="left">1 day</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e422" display="inline" altimg="si22.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">viral load threshold for category 2 agents</td><td align="left">3 days</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e437" display="inline" altimg="si24.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">viral load threshold for category 4 agents</td><td align="left">3–6 days</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e452" display="inline" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">duration of the plateau or stable viral load</td><td align="left">3–6 days</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
                  <p id="d1e1697">Our simulation strategy is similar to that of Parker and Epstein <xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, as we keep track of only the infected agents and not the whole population. The time for each iteration increases as a result as the simulation progresses. Still the efficiency was higher with this approach particularly for larger populations. The memory requirements were also within the 128GB per compute node of both Magnus and Zeus.</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec3">
              <label>3</label>
              <title>Results</title>
              <p id="d1e1708">We first show the simulation results for New York City with a population of about 8 million. The public place capacity was set at 10% in the simulations. The hospitalization probability in these simulations is set to 0.2, i.e., an infected agent transitions to severe with this probability (category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1715" display="inline" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents in our model). Among the agents whose viral loads require hospitalization, the transition to ICU occurs with a probability 0.3 (category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1720" display="inline" altimg="si26.svg"><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1726" display="inline" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents in our simulation). And among those who are admitted to ICU, recovery occurs with a probability of 0.5 (category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1731" display="inline" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents). The New York State Government data is shown in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> and our simulation results are shown in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>. The assumed values are based on our observations, available information and trial and error to make sure our predictions matched the available data.<fig id="fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Daily hospitalization and ICU admission summary from NY State Government <xref rid="b15" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>The hospitalization and ICU figures from our simulation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr4_lrg"/></fig></p>
              <p id="d1e1743">We also show a direct comparison between government data and simulation data for total hospitalization for NY City in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>. We show the comparison between government data and simulation data for admission to ICU in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>. As can be seen our simulation results match quite accurately with the actual data in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, except for a steeper rise in simulation results. However, our results for admission to ICU overestimates of the actual data. This is due to the fact that we could not explore the parameter space for such a large population due to the very long simulation times.<fig id="fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Comparison of government hospitalization data and our simulation results.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr5_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Comparison of government ICU data and our simulation results.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr6_lrg"/></fig></p>
              <p id="d1e1762">The results for Mid-Hudson valley are shown in <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figs. 7</xref>, <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>, <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>, and <xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>. Though the population of Mid-Hudson valley is about 1.35 million, the dynamics of the spread of the infection seems to be very similar to that of NY city, as all the probabilities as well as the public place capacities are exactly the same in these simulations.<fig id="fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Government hospitalization and ICU data for Mid-Hudson valley.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr7_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig8"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Simulated data for Mid-Hudson valley.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr8_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig9"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>Comparison of government data and simulated data for hospitalization for Mid-Hudson valley.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr9_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig10"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p>Comparison of government data and simulated data for admission to ICU for Mid-Hudson valley.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr10_lrg"/></fig></p>
              <p id="d1e1789">Next, we show the simulation results for a smaller population and compare it with the government data for hospitalization and admission to ICU. This simulation is for the Western New York region with a population of 1.8 million. The overall hospitalization and admission to ICU are much smaller in number compared to that of Mid-Hudson valley, which has a comparable population. These results for the WNY region are shown in <xref rid="fig11" ref-type="fig">Figs. 11</xref>, <xref rid="fig12" ref-type="fig">12</xref>, <xref rid="fig13" ref-type="fig">Fig. 13</xref>, <xref rid="fig14" ref-type="fig">Fig. 14</xref>.</p>
              <p id="d1e1803">We summarize the simulation probabilities and public place capacities for NY City, Mid-Hudson valley and Western New York region in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Public place capacities are shown as a percentage of the population. All simulations were run with initially 0.01% of infected agents (seed infection).<fig id="fig11"><label>Fig. 11</label><caption><p>NY Government hospitalization data for Western NY.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr11_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig12"><label>Fig. 12</label><caption><p>Simulated data for Western NY region.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr12_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig13"><label>Fig. 13</label><caption><p>A comparison of simulated data and NY Government hospitalization data for the Western NY region.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr13_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig14"><label>Fig. 14</label><caption><p>A comparison of simulated data and NY Government ICU data for the Western NY region.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr14_lrg"/></fig></p>
              <p id="d1e1817">We next explore the effects of varying the robust parameters in our model with respect to the simulation of the Western New York region. <xref rid="fig15" ref-type="fig">Figs. 15</xref> and  <xref rid="fig16" ref-type="fig">16</xref> compare the simulation results when the total capacity of public places is <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1830" display="inline" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>% and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1836" display="inline" altimg="si123.svg"><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>% respectively. The changes in the simulation results are not significant. This is due to the fact that though a larger capacity of public places potentially exposes more agents to infection, we have assumed that the initial viral loads are small and hence the increase in viral load over time is more important. In other words, even with a smaller capacity in public places, the number of agents that can be accommodated in public places does not change significantly as the duration of stay of an agent in a public place is on average only about 10 min according to our calibration.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Parameters used in our simulations.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Region</th><th align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e477" display="inline" altimg="si105.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e491" display="inline" altimg="si106.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>34</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e505" display="inline" altimg="si107.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></th><th align="left">Public place</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">NY City</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">10%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mid-Hudson</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">10%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Western NY</td><td align="left">0.017</td><td align="left">0.35</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">0.8%</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
              <p id="d1e1840">It is hence important to note that with increased time spent at a public place the numbers of hospitalized and infected agents can be weakly affected. Given that the number of infections at initiation is likely an important parameter, we further observe that a potential second or third wave could get progressively more dangerous if the number of infections is not nearly obliterated from the prior round. This observation could be relevant to understand why the so-called “third wave” in the US may have reported the highest number of cases ever recorded in many regions.<fig id="fig15"><label>Fig. 15</label><caption><p>Simulation for 50 days with public place capacity 1% of the population.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr15_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig16"><label>Fig. 16</label><caption><p>Simulation for 50 days with public place capacity 5% of the population.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr16_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig17"><label>Fig. 17</label><caption><p>Simulation for 50 days with public place capacity 1% of the population. The viral load thresholds are double of those compared to <xref rid="fig12" ref-type="fig">Fig. 12</xref>, <xref rid="fig15" ref-type="fig">Fig. 15</xref>, <xref rid="fig16" ref-type="fig">Fig. 16</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr17_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig18"><label>Fig. 18</label><caption><p>Simulation for 50 days with public place capacity 1% of the population. The viral incubation period is 6–12 days.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr18_lrg"/></fig></p>
              <p id="d1e1850">We have shown simulation results by doubling the transition thresholds between different categories of agents in <xref rid="fig17" ref-type="fig">Fig. 17</xref>. We also vary the incubation period of the virus randomly between 6–12 days in <xref rid="fig18" ref-type="fig">Fig. 18</xref>. Again, there are no significant changes, except for shifting the hospitalization and ICU admission rates.</p>
              <p id="d1e1860">It is possible to study lockdowns easily in our model. We can choose to prevent the agents from visiting public places for a certain number of simulation steps and that has the effect of lockdowns. For example <xref rid="fig19" ref-type="fig">Fig. 19</xref> shows a simulation for Western New York, with lockdown imposed between days 8–16. As a result, the incremental hospitalization and ICU admission rates drop to zero after a few days, as the early lockdown has not increased the viral loads of infected agents to levels of category 2,3 or 4 agents. On the other hand, a later lockdown would reduce the hospitalization and ICU admission rates.</p>
              <p id="d1e1867">However, a complete lockdown may not be practical or even feasible in a community, due to the difficulty in implementation, as well as due to its impact on the economy. Some kind of social distancing may be a practical alternative. We have studied the effect of more moderate aspects of social distancing by increasing the capacities of the public places. These results show that an increased capacity of public places increase the rate of hospitalization and admission to ICUs. If we increase the capacity of public places by about 40% for the Western NY region, the rate of admission to ICU increases by about 30%. This is less pronounced for the Western NY region as the probability of hospitalization is very low there in our simulation (for matching with the government data). However this is more pronounced in NY city and also in the Mid-Hudson region though the results from these calculations are not presented here. We show this effect for Western NY in the following two figures, <xref rid="fig20" ref-type="fig">Fig. 20</xref> and  <xref rid="fig21" ref-type="fig">21</xref>. The initial rise of infection is slower in these two figures, many of the public places are initially uninfected and it takes more time for the seed infections to take effect.<fig id="fig19"><label>Fig. 19</label><caption><p>Simulation for Western New York, with lockdown imposed between days 8–16.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr19_lrg"/></fig></p>
              <p id="d1e1879">We have not considered the possibility of infection spreading in home groups until now. We show in <xref rid="fig22" ref-type="fig">Fig. 22</xref> the possibility of infection spreading in home groups. There is a possibility of infection spreading among uninfected agents, if there are category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1890" display="inline" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> or category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1896" display="inline" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents (before hospitalization) in a home group. We have assumed that an uninfected agent can become infected with a probability of 0.5 in this case. We impose this condition once a day on the uninfected agents in a home group. The result is an increase in category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1901" display="inline" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> and subsequently category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1906" display="inline" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents. This also increases the numbers of category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1911" display="inline" altimg="si26.svg"><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1917" display="inline" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents subsequently. However, if we reduce the transition probability <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1922" display="inline" altimg="si105.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, the number of category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1936" display="inline" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> agents remains almost the same. This is shown in <xref rid="fig22" ref-type="fig">Fig. 22</xref>, as we have reduced <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1946" display="inline" altimg="si105.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> from 0.2 to 0.15. In other words, the transition to severity occurs with a lower probability if home infection is considered.<fig id="fig20"><label>Fig. 20</label><caption><p>Comparison of hospitalization between public place capacities of 1% and 40%.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr20_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig21"><label>Fig. 21</label><caption><p>Comparison of admission to ICU between public place capacities of 1% and 40%.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr21_lrg"/></fig></p>
              <p id="d1e1959">We have assumed in our simulations that each public place has the same capacity. It is a challenging task to determine the spread of infection in public places of different sizes, as social distancing policies during a pandemic may effectively restrict the number of people in a public place. Hence, we have made the most stringent assumption that a public place becomes infectious if even a single infected agent visits that public place. Though it is known that the viral load decreases over time, the exact decrease is still a research topic. The agents in our simulation visit public places randomly, and hence, we have made this strict assumption. There is hardly any difference in the number of hospitalized agents under this assumption, as shown in <xref rid="fig23" ref-type="fig">Fig. 23</xref>. We have compared the number of hospitalized agents by varying the public place capacities randomly between <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1968" display="inline" altimg="si123.svg"><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1973" display="inline" altimg="si136.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, while keeping the total capacity the same.<fig id="fig22"><label>Fig. 22</label><caption><p>Comparison of hospitalization numbers with and without home infection. The transition probability from category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e308" display="inline" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> to category <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e313" display="inline" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> is 0.2 when home infection is not considered, and 0.15 when home infection is considered.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr22_lrg"/></fig></p>
              <p id="d1e1978">
                <fig id="fig23">
                  <label>Fig. 23</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Comparison of hospitalization with public places of uniform size and varying sizes.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="gr23_lrg"/>
                </fig>
              </p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec4">
              <label>4</label>
              <title>Conclusion</title>
              <p id="d1e1986">We have presented a simple agent-based approach to study the COVID-19 pandemic spread in this paper that can match the actual hospitalization and ICU admittance data well. Once the needed parameters are extracted for a given region and the population involved, our model can predict the future trends in hospitalization and admittance to ICU. Thus, our study may help in preparing for future demands on health care, or in better provisioning of services while keeping the economy from grinding to a standstill.</p>
              <p id="d1e1988">Like most agent-based model studies, this study relies on the knowledge of many “hard to know” parameters. However, if the needed quantities are even approximately known or are not very sensitive to small changes, this approach can be valuable in constructing strategies for improved control of disease spread at the local levels. We would like to highlight that this model can be improved in several different ways to reflect the actual social interactions and hence the spread of a pandemic in the real world. Though this model is inspired by the works by Epstein <xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref> and Parker and Epstein <xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, an important distinction is that their model is of global scale, whereas our model is targeted for much smaller communities in cities and regions.</p>
              <p id="d1e1998">The possible enhancements of our model can motivate the study of spread of a pandemic more precisely. For example, it is possible to impose a spatial grid on our home communities and public places to reflect the different parts of a city or community. It is even possible to simulate movable public places like public transportation and subway systems. A spatial grid will also enable imposing selective lockdown measures on different locations in the community, and study the effect of social distancing more precisely. As the results for NY City with a large population and Mid-Hudson with a much smaller population show, perhaps the location of Mid-Husdon is the reason for similar spread of the infection in these two communities. On the other hand though Western New York has a similar population as Mid-Hudson, the dynamics of spread of infection is quite different there, as is evident from both the government data and our simulation results. These kind of model findings can help suggest directions for further investigations of the pandemic spread in Western New York and other areas.</p>
              <p id="d1e2000">We have assumed that an agent stays at a public place only for a short time, in other words our assumption is that the public places are homogeneous. It is also possible to group public places in our model according to shorter and longer stay, e.g., grocery stores, public transportation and offices. That will again facilitate a finer scale study of the spread of the pandemic. Our model has the capability to make forward predictions on the access needed to public health facilities, and that can help the local and state governments to prepare for the spread of the pandemic. The fine tuning of the parameters by noting the initial spread of the pandemic will help in predicting the medium term requirements of the public health facilities. However, there are many other aspects of a pandemic that we have not considered in this paper, e.g., the economic or financial implications <xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, <xref rid="b22" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="d1e2006">
              <title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title>
              <p id="d1e2009"><bold>Amitava Datta:</bold> Wrote the simulation code, Wrote parts of the manuscript. <bold>Peter Winkelstein:</bold> Analyzed the data, Wrote parts of the manuscript. <bold>Surajit Sen:</bold> Designed the study, Wrote parts of the manuscript.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="COI-statement">
              <title>Declaration of Competing Interest</title>
              <p id="d1e2022">The authors declare the following financial interests/personal relationships which may be considered as potential competing interests: Amitava Datta reports equipment, drugs, or supplies was provided by Pawsey Supercomputing Centre.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list id="bib1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="b1">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb1">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kermack</surname>
                      <given-names>W.O.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McKendrik</surname>
                      <given-names>A.G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A contribution to the mathematical theory of epidemics</article-title>
                  <source>Proc. R. Soc. Lond. Ser. A Math. Phys. Eng. Sci.</source>
                  <volume>115</volume>
                  <issue>772</issue>
                  <year>1927</year>
                  <fpage>700</fpage>
                  <lpage>721</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspa.1927.0118</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b2">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brauer</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                    <name>
                      <surname>F. Brauer</surname>
                      <given-names>P. van den Driessche</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Compartmental Models in Epidemiology</source>
                  <series>Mathematical Epidemiology, Lecture Notes in Mathematics</series>
                  <volume>vol. 1945</volume>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
                  <publisher-loc>Berlin, Heidelberg</publisher-loc>
                  <fpage>19</fpage>
                  <lpage>79</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-3-540-78911-6_2</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b3">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Allen</surname>
                      <given-names>L.J.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Some discrete-time SI, SIR, and SIS epidemic models</article-title>
                  <source>Math. Biosci.</source>
                  <volume>124</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>1994</year>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <lpage>105</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0025-5564(94)90025-6</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7827425</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b4">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb4">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Getz</surname>
                      <given-names>W.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dougherty</surname>
                      <given-names>E.R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Discrete stochastic analogs of erlang epidemic models</article-title>
                  <source>J. Biol. Dyn.</source>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <fpage>16</fpage>
                  <lpage>38</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17513758.2017.1401677</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29157162</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b5">
                <label>5</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sb5">Covid-19ForecastHub. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://covid19forecasthub.org/" id="interref1">https://covid19forecasthub.org/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b6">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb6">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Mathematical models for COVID-19: applications, limitations, and potentials</article-title>
                  <source>J. Public. Health Emerg.</source>
                  <volume>4</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>9</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/jphe-2020-05</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32724894</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b7">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb7">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Epstein</surname>
                      <given-names>J.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Modelling to contain pandemics</article-title>
                  <source>Nature</source>
                  <volume>460</volume>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <fpage>687</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/460687a</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19661897</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b8">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb8">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Parker</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Epstein</surname>
                      <given-names>J.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A distributed platform for global-scale agent-based models of disease transmission</article-title>
                  <source>ACM Trans. Model. Comput. Simul.</source>
                  <volume>22</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>25</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1145/2043635.2043637</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b9">
                <label>9</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sb9">MIDAS: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://midasnetwork.us/" id="interref2">https://midasnetwork.us/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb10">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Danon</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Brooks-Pollock</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bailey</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Keeling</surname>
                      <given-names>M.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A spatial model of CoVID-19 transmission in England and Wales: early spread and peak timing and the impact of seasonality</article-title>
                  <source>Philos. Trans. R. Soc. B</source>
                  <volume>376</volume>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">20200272</object-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2020.0272</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb11">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ghosh</surname>
                      <given-names>I.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chakraborty</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An integrated deterministic-stochastic approach for forecasting the long-term trajectories of COVID-19</article-title>
                  <source>Int. J. Model. Simul. Sci. Comput.</source>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2141001</object-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1142/S1793962321410014</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b12">
                <label>12</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sb12">J. Fernandéz-Villaverde, C.I. Jones, Estimating and simulating a SIRD model of COVID-19 for many countries, states, and cities, NBER Working Paper 27128 (2020). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3386/w27128</pub-id>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb13">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Krantz</surname>
                      <given-names>S.G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Srinivasa Rao</surname>
                      <given-names>A.S.R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Level of underreporting including underdiagnosis before the first peak of COVID-19 in various countries: Preliminary retrospective results based on wavelets and deterministic modeling</article-title>
                  <source>Infect. Control Hosp. Epidemiol.</source>
                  <volume>41</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>857</fpage>
                  <lpage>859</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/ice.2020.116</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32268929</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b14">
                <label>14</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sb14">See for example in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nvss/vsrr/covid19/excess_deaths.htm#dashboard" id="interref4">https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nvss/vsrr/covid19/excess_deaths.htm#dashboard</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b15">
                <label>15</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sb15">New York state hospitalization data: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://forward.ny.gov/daily-hospitalization-summary-region" id="interref5">https://forward.ny.gov/daily-hospitalization-summary-region</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b16">
                <label>16</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sb16">Number of Virus Patients in I.C.U.s Starts to Fall in New York, New York Times, April 10, updated April 15, 2020.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b17">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb17">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rockett</surname>
                      <given-names>R.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Arnott</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lam</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sadsad</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Timms</surname>
                      <given-names>V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gray</surname>
                      <given-names>K.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eden</surname>
                      <given-names>J.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chang</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gall</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Draper</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sim</surname>
                      <given-names>E.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bachmann</surname>
                      <given-names>N.L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Carter</surname>
                      <given-names>I.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Basile</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Byun</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>O?Sullivan</surname>
                      <given-names>M.V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>S.C.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Maddocks</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sorrell</surname>
                      <given-names>T.C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dwyer</surname>
                      <given-names>D.E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Holmes</surname>
                      <given-names>E.C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kok</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Prokopenko</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sintchenko</surname>
                      <given-names>V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Revealing COVID-19 transmission in Australia by SARS-CoV-2 genome sequencing and agent-based modeling</article-title>
                  <source>Nature Med.</source>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1398</fpage>
                  <lpage>1404</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41591-020-1000-7</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32647358</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b18">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb18">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pitzer</surname>
                      <given-names>V.E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cohen</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Household studies provide key insights on the transmission of and susceptibility to SARS-COV0-2</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet Infect. Dis.</source>
                  <volume>20</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1103</fpage>
                  <lpage>1104</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(20)30514-4</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32562602</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b19">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb19">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jing</surname>
                      <given-names>Q.-L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>M.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.-B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fang</surname>
                      <given-names>L.-Q.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yuan</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>A.-R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dean</surname>
                      <given-names>N.E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Luo</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ma</surname>
                      <given-names>M.-M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Longini</surname>
                      <given-names>I.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kenah</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lu</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ma</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jalali</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.-C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Household secondary attack rate of COVID-19 and associated determinants in Guangzhou, China: a retrospective cohort study</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet Infect. Dis.</source>
                  <volume>20</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1141</fpage>
                  <lpage>1150</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(20)30471-0</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32562601</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b20">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb20">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Keskinocak</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aglar</surname>
                      <given-names>B.E.O.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baxter</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Asplund</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Serban</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The impact of social distancing on COVID19 spread: State of Georgia case study</article-title>
                  <source>PLOS ONE</source>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0239798</object-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0239798</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b21">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb21">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kano</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yasui</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mikami</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Asally</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ishiguro</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An agent-based model of the interrelation between the COVID-19 outbreak and economic activities</article-title>
                  <source>Proc. R. Soc. Lond. Ser. A Math. Phys. Eng. Sci.</source>
                  <volume>477</volume>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">20200604</object-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspa.2020.0604</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b22">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb22">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Samuel</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sinha</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Optimal control in pandemics</article-title>
                  <source>Phys. Rev. E</source>
                  <volume>103</volume>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">L010301</object-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevE.103.L010301</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
            <ack id="d1e2024">
              <title>Acknowledgments</title>
              <p id="d1e2027">The authors are thankful to two anonymous reviewers for their valuable comments on an earlier version of this paper. In particular, the comments and suggestions of the first reviewer helped us to improve the presentation of the paper considerably.</p>
            </ack>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
