<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-03-11T00:45:25Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8580864" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8580864</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-11-12</datestamp>
        <setSpec>pheelsevier</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.xsd" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Spat Spatiotemporal Epidemiol</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Spat Spatiotemporal Epidemiol</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Spatial and Spatio-Temporal Epidemiology</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">1877-5845</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1877-5853</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Elsevier Ltd.</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC8580864</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8580864</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">8580864</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">35120681</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pii">S1877-5845(21)00069-1</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sste.2021.100471</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100471</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Spatio-temporal modeling of COVID-19 prevalence and mortality using artificial neural network algorithms</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0001">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kianfar</surname>
                    <given-names>Nima</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
                  <xref rid="cor0001" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0002">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Mesgari</surname>
                    <given-names>Mohammad Saadi</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0003">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Mollalo</surname>
                    <given-names>Abolfazl</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0004">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kaveh</surname>
                    <given-names>Mehrdad</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="aff0001"><label>a</label>Faculty of Geodesy and Geomatics, K. N. Toosi University of Technology, Tehran 19967-15433, Iran</aff>
                <aff id="aff0002"><label>b</label>Department of Public Health and Prevention Science, School of Health Sciences, Baldwin Wallace University, Berea, OH 44017, USA</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor0001"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author.</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>11</day>
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.-->
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <month>2</month>
                <year>2022</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>11</day>
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>40</volume>
              <fpage>100471</fpage>
              <lpage>100471</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>21</day>
                  <month>6</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>3</day>
                  <month>10</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>4</day>
                  <month>11</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2021 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
                <copyright-holder/>
                <license>
                  <license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="abs0002">
                <p>The outbreak of coronavirus disease (COVID-19) has become one of the most challenging global concerns in recent years. Due to inadequate worldwide studies on spatio-temporal modeling of COVID-19, this research aims to examine the relative significance of potential explanatory variables (<italic>n</italic> = 75) concerning COVID-19 prevalence and mortality using multilayer perceptron artificial neural network topology. We utilized ten variable importance analysis methods to identify the relative importance of the explanatory variables. The main findings indicated that several variables were persistently among the most influential variables in all periods. Regarding COVID-19 prevalence, unemployment and population density were among the most influential variables with the highest importance scores. While for COVID-19 mortality, health-related variables such as diabetes prevalence and number of hospital beds were among the most significant variables. The obtained findings from this study might provide general insights for public health policymakers to monitor the spread of disease and support decision-making.</p>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group id="keys0001">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>Artificial neural network</kwd>
                <kwd>COVID-19</kwd>
                <kwd>GIS</kwd>
                <kwd>Spatio-temporal analysis</kwd>
                <kwd>Variable importance analysis</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <p id="para9001">
              <def-list>
                <title>List of Abbreviations</title>
                <def-item>
                  <term id="dt0001">ANN</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="para0006">artificial neural network</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term id="dt0002">CW</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="para0007">connection weights</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term id="dt0003">FR</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="para0008">fatality rate</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term id="dt0004">GA</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="para0009">Garson's algorithm</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term id="dt0005">GIS</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="para0010">geographic information system</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term id="dt0006">GR</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="para0011">growth rate</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term id="dt0007">PR</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="para0012">prevalence rate</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term id="dt0008">PR-IQR</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="para0013">prevalence rate in interquartile range</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term id="dt0009">MR</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="para0014">mortality rate</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term id="dt0010">MR-IQR</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="para0015">mortality rate in interquartile range</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term id="dt0011">MSE</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="para0016">mean squared error</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term id="dt0012">PD</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="para0017">partial derivatives</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term id="dt0013">RMSEIQR</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="para0018">root mean square error in interquartile range</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term id="dt0014">MCW</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="para0019">modified connection weights</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term id="dt0015">MS</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="para0020">model selection</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term id="dt0016">SLP</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="para0021">single-layer perceptron</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term id="dt0017">TMMR</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="para0022">trimmed mean mortality rate</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term id="dt0018">VIA</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="para0023">variable importance analysis</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term id="dt0019">VIF</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="para0024">variance inflation factor</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term id="dt0020">WIC</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="para0025">weighted information criterion</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
              </def-list>
            </p>
            <sec id="sec0001">
              <label>1</label>
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p id="para0026">On January 29, 2020, the World health organization (WHO) declared the coronavirus disease (COVID-19) an epidemic, and shortly after, on March 11, 2020 announced it a pandemic (<xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization (WHO) 2020a</xref>). As of October 1, 2021, almost 234 million cases and more than 4.7 million associated deaths related to the disease have been reported globally (<xref rid="bib0002" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization (WHO) 2021b</xref>). The outbreak of this acute respiratory infection has adversely impacted individuals and societies (<xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2020</xref>). Although initial cases of COVID-19 were found in China, the transmission pattern of the virus has changed many times, causing irreparable damages worldwide (<xref rid="bib0004" ref-type="bibr">Mansour et al., 2021</xref>).</p>
              <p id="para0027">Understanding the interactions between the determinant variables and health outcomes seems incomprehensible. In recent decades, artificial neural networks (ANNs) have been widely utilized to model the relationship between the factors and infectious diseases (<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">Mollalo et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">Mollalo et al., 2019</xref>). The primary aim of ANNs is to predict the future status or unknown values of a particular dependent variable from a given set of independent variables. However, within ANNs, quantifying the contribution of each input variable in predicting the health outcome is difficult (<xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">Ripley, 2007</xref>).</p>
              <p id="para0028">Previous studies have utilized various ANNs topologies to quantify the contribution of explanatory variables on dependent outcomes. <xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">Duh et al. (1998</xref>) proposed multilayer neural networks for evaluating the input weights of ANNs. They validated this technique on three datasets and found that ANNs are effective in epidemiologic problems that require complicated classification techniques. <xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Olden and Jackson (2002</xref>) examined the neural interpretation diagram, Garson's algorithm, and sensitivity analysis to understand neural network relation weights. They showed that by extending randomization methods to ANNs, the black box mechanics of ANNs could be illuminated. <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Olden et al. (2004</xref>) proposed the connection weights approach and argued that this approach is the least biased method that can accurately quantify the variable importance. <xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Ibrahim (2013</xref>) provided a modification to the connection weights algorithm and most squares method in multilayer perceptron (MLP) neural networks. They used crop production as a case study and compared this model with the connection weights algorithm, dominance analysis, Garson's algorithm, partial derivatives, and multiple linear regressions. The proposed algorithms' output was evaluated using empirical evidence. Their findings indicated that the most squares method outperformed other methods, which was consistent with the results of multiple linear regressions in terms of partial R<sup>2</sup> (<xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">Özesmi and Özesmi, 1999</xref>).</p>
              <p id="para0029">Because of the complexity of interactions between variables, particularly in large datasets, variable importance analysis (VIA) has gained attention in many practical applications (<xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Ferretti et al., 2016</xref>). VIA is a critical task in classification or regression problems to improve model interpretability, computational costs, data storage, and ultimately provide a sparse model without sacrificing prediction capacity (<xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Wei et al., 2015</xref>). Dealing with various balance scenarios, <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">Dfuf et al. (2020</xref>) introduced the nonparametric <inline-formula><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>χ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> variable importance technique, which uses a multivariate continuous response system to select and rank the most influential variables. The method measures the dissimilarities between the distribution of errors caused by the base learner before and after permuting the variable. <xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">Casiraghi et al. (2020</xref>) used a prediction model, “an explainable machine learning decision system based on additive trees”, which processed clinical, radiological, and laboratory data of COVID-19 patients to predict the risk of severe outcomes. They combined Boruta and random forest in a 10-fold cross-validation scheme to produce variable importance estimates not affected by the presence of surrogates. <xref rid="bib0017" ref-type="bibr">Pasha et al. (2021</xref>) employed multiple linear regression and a nonlinear regression based on 43 socio-economic and meteorological variables of 31 counties in California, United States. They found that the total population, household income, occupation, and transportation are more influential on COVID-19 spread than other variables. <xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">Shaffiee Haghshenas et al. (2020</xref>) applied ANNs based on particle swarm optimization and differential evolution algorithms to prioritize climatic and urban factors. They found that population density and humidity were the most influential variables to predict the confirmed COVID-19 cases.</p>
              <p id="para0030">In addition to the machine learning algorithms, the geographic information system (GIS) is a robust tool for analysis and visualizing many public health problems (<xref rid="bib0019" ref-type="bibr">Mollalo et al., 2015</xref>, <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Recent GIS-based research has shown that several factors such as air quality (<xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Bashir et al., 2020</xref>), population flow (<xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">Zhang and Schwartz, 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">Jia et al., 2020</xref>), and population density (<xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Ahmadi et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">Ramírez and Lee, 2020</xref>) could contribute to the higher rates of COVID-19 morbidity and mortality. In the Caribbean, <xref rid="bib0026" ref-type="bibr">Moonsammy et al. (2021</xref>) applied spatial lag and linear regression models to identify spatial clusters of COVID-19 and the most influential socio-economic variables. They suggested that COVID-19 cases and deaths in the Caribbean have a spatial connection with mainland countries. They also concluded that population transmission could contribute to higher COVID-19 spread. The consequences of the COVID-19 outbreak on the environment have also been investigated in some studies. For instance, <xref rid="bib0027" ref-type="bibr">Ambade et al. (2021</xref>) examined the levels of three air pollutants, namely particulate matter (PM<sub>2.5</sub>), Black Carbon (BC), and Polycyclic Aromatic Hydrocarbons (PAHs), in Jamshedpur city, India. Their results indicated that the concentrations of the contaminants were reduced during the lockdown compared to unlock down circumstances and regular days. <xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">Gautam (2020</xref>) showed that India experienced a large decrease in aerosol concentration during the lockdown, which led to fewer deaths during the outbreak. <xref rid="bib0029" ref-type="bibr">Gautam (2020</xref>) also suggested that lockdowns could help Asian and European countries experience lower levels of NO2. On the other hand, in China, <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al. (2020</xref>) demonstrated that quarantine actions would not be sufficient to prevent severe air pollution despite reductions in transportation and industrial emissions.</p>
              <p id="para0031">COVID-19 transmission is not limited to national borders and geographical territories. The primary focus of many studies that utilized machine learning methods such as ANNs was limited to a specific geographic location and applied pure spatial analysis with few sets of parameters while disregarding the impact of various potential variables over time. Therefore, to bridge the gap, this study investigates the influence of a broad range of explanatory variables (<italic>n</italic> = 75) on disease prevalence and mortality using VIA methods based on ANNs, across the globe. This research optimized ANNs structure using a weighted information criterion (WIC) index to improve modeling accuracy. Moreover, as COVID-19 has shown various behaviors and mutated several times, different indicators were used to estimate mortality and morbidity rates over time. For this purpose, nine targets have been used to study the neural network's learning process with distinct desires.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0002">
              <label>2</label>
              <title>Materials and methods</title>
              <sec id="sec0003">
                <label>2.1</label>
                <title>Data</title>
                <p id="para0032">The daily COVID-19 data were obtained from WHO (<xref rid="bib0002" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization (WHO) 2021b</xref>) from the beginning of March 2020 to the end of February 2021. The data contained new confirmed COVID-19 cases and newly confirmed deaths for all countries. Moreover, nine different indicators were used to study the learning process of further modeling. The formula for each indicator can be found in <xref rid="tbl0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>
(for prevalence) and <xref rid="tbl0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>
(for mortality). We divided the COVID-19 data into four equal time intervals (3-month periods): early March 2020 to the end of May 2020 (Period 1), early June 2020 to the end of August 2020 (Period 2), early September 2020 to the end of November 2020 (Period 3), and early December 2020 to the end of February 2021 (Period 4). In addition to COVID-19 data, a set of 75 variables, including demographic, environmental, social, economic, cultural, health, and public transportation variables was compiled at the country level as explanatory variables. The category, name, and source of the variables are presented in <xref rid="tbl0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>
.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Various indicators used as target values for prevalence.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0012">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top">Indicator</th><th valign="top">Formula</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top">Prevalence rate (PR)</td><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M2" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mn>19</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Prevalence rate in interquartile range (PR-IQR)</td><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M3" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mn>19</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Trimmed mean rate (TMR)</td><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M4" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mn>19</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Growth rate (GR1)</td><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M5" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mn>19</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Various indicators used as target values for mortality.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0013">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top">Indicator</th><th valign="top">Formula</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top">Mortality rate (MR)</td><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M6" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mn>19</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Mortality rate in interquartile range (MR-IQR)</td><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M7" altimg="si6.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mn>19</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Trimmed mean mortality rate (TMMR)</td><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M8" altimg="si7.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mn>19</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Growth rate (GR2)</td><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M9" altimg="si8.svg"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mn>19</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Fatality rate (FR)</td><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M10" altimg="si9.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mn>19</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>O</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mn>19</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>The category, name, and source of the variables.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0014">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top"><bold>Category</bold></th><th valign="top"><bold>Variable</bold></th><th valign="top"><bold>Source</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top">Demographic<break/>(25 variables)</td><td valign="top">Population, male (% of total population)</td><td valign="top">World bank (<xref rid="bib0031" ref-type="bibr">World Bank February 1, 2021</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Population, female (% of total population)</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Population ages 0-14 (% of total population)</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Population ages 0-14, male (% of male population)</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Population ages 0-14, female (% of female population)</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Population ages 15-64 (% of total population)</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Population ages 15-64, male (% of male population)</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Population ages 15-64, female (% of female population)</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Population ages 65 and above (% of total population)</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Population ages 65 and above, male (% of male population)</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Population ages 65 and above, female (% of female population)</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Population density (people per sq. km of land area)</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Urban population (% of total population)</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Urban population growth (annual %)</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Rural population (% of total population)</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Rural population growth (annual %)</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Population in the largest city (% of urban population)</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Age dependency ratio (% of working-age population)</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Birth rate, crude (per 1,000 people)</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Death rate, crude (per 1,000 people)</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Physicians (per 1,000 people)</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Nurses and midwives (per 1,000 people)</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Hospital beds (per 1,000 people)</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Age dependency ratio, old (% of working-age population)</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Age dependency ratio, young (% of working-age population)</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Economic<break/>(19 variables)</td><td valign="top">Labor force participation rate, total</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Labor force participation rate, male</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Labor force participation rate, female</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Employment to population ratio, 15+, total</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Employers, total (% of total employment)</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Employers, male (% of male employment)</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Employers, female (% of female employment)</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Vulnerable employment, total</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Unemployment, total</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Unemployment with advanced education</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Unemployment, male (% of male labor force)</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Unemployment, female (% of female labor force)</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">International migrant stock</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Poverty headcount ratio at national poverty lines</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Inflation, consumer prices</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">GDP per capita</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">GDP per capita growth</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">GNI per capita</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">GNI per capita growth</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Environmental<break/>(11 variables)</td><td valign="top">CO2 emissions from transport</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">CO2 emissions from electricity and heat production</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">CO2 emissions from manufacturing industries and construction</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">CO2 emissions from residential buildings and commercial and public services</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Methane emissions</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Nitrous oxide emissions</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">PM2.5 air pollution, mean annual exposure</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Tropopause Height</td><td valign="top">Giovanni (<xref rid="bib0032" ref-type="bibr">Giovanni, 2021</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Surface layer height</td><td valign="top">Giovanni</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">surface precipitation</td><td valign="top">Giovanni</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Surface air temperature</td><td valign="top">Giovanni</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Social<break/>(9 variables)</td><td valign="top">Literacy rate, adult total</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Freedom to make life choices</td><td valign="top">World happiness report (<xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">Helliwell et al., 2018</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Happiness</td><td valign="top">World happiness report</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Life Ladder</td><td valign="top">World happiness report</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Social support</td><td valign="top">World happiness report</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Perceptions of corruption</td><td valign="top">World happiness report</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Positive affect</td><td valign="top">World happiness report</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Negative affect</td><td valign="top">World happiness report</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Confidence in national government</td><td valign="top">World happiness report</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Health<break/>(7 variables)</td><td valign="top">Life expectancy at birth, total (years)</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Prevalence of severe food insecurity in the population</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Mortality from CVD, cancer, diabetes or CRD</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Incidence of tuberculosis</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Diabetes prevalence</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Incidence of HIV</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Healthy life expectancy at birth</td><td valign="top">World happiness report</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Public transportation<break/>(2 variables)</td><td valign="top">Air transport, passengers carried</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Railways, passengers carried</td><td valign="top">World bank</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Cultural<break/>(2 variables)</td><td valign="top">Religion diversity index</td><td valign="top">Pew Research Center (<xref rid="bib0034" ref-type="bibr">Pew Research Center 4 April. 2014</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">Generosity</td><td valign="top">World happiness report</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0004">
                <label>2.2</label>
                <title>Variables selection</title>
                <p id="para0033">Existence of many correlated explanatory variables (<italic>n</italic> = 75) may cause multicollinearity which can in turn reduce the generalizability of the models due to overfitting. In order to reduce multicollinearity, variance inflation factor (VIF) was used (<xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">Shrestha, 2020</xref>). Using VIF and also Pearson's correlation analysis, 18 correlated variables were removed, and the most uncorrelated ones were selected as the input of the further employed models.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0005">
                <label>2.3</label>
                <title>Model development</title>
                <p id="para0034">ANNs are computational systems consisting of a large number of connected nodes called neurons (<xref rid="bib0036" ref-type="bibr">Civco, 1993</xref>). ANNs can identify the relationships among dependent and independent variables, which helps in understanding system function (<xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Kang et al., 2011</xref>). Neurons in these networks are structured in different layers, including input layer, output layer, and hidden layer(s). There is full connections between the neurons in the input layer and the ones in the hidden layer. Likewise, each neuron in the hidden layer is connected to the neurons in the output layer (<xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">Mollalo et al., 2019</xref>).
<xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> shows the topology of a single-layer neural network with a non-linear sigmoid transfer function in the hidden layer and a linear function in the output layer. Theoretically, any function with a finite number of discontinuities can be approximated by using a single-layer neural network with a non-linear sigmoid transfer function in the hidden layer and a linear one in the output layer (<xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>) (<xref rid="bib0038" ref-type="bibr">Yonaba et al., 2010</xref>). Therefore, in this study, single-layer perceptron (SLP) neural networks with the mentioned characteristics were employed.<fig id="fig0001"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>A single-layer neural network with a non-linear sigmoid transfer function in the hidden layer and a linear function in the output layer.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0001">Fig 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="para0035">The ultimate purpose of this research is to assess the relative importance of various variables in modeling COVID-19 prevalence and mortality over time. For this purpose, we first optimized the structure of ANNs for hyperparameters, number of neurons in the hidden layer, and learning parameters (<xref rid="bib0039" ref-type="bibr">Ojha et al., 2017</xref>). We used Bayesian regularization method to train the network while addressing overfitting problem and complex interactions between variables (<xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">Kayri, 2016</xref>). Then we determined the optimum number of neurons in the hidden layer using WIC index (<xref rid="bib0041" ref-type="bibr">Eğrioğlu et al., 2008</xref>). Based on this method, the number of neurons in the hidden layer was systematically increased from one to the number of variables, and then the WIC index value of each model was calculated. The lower model's WIC index indicates a more efficient model (<xref rid="bib0041" ref-type="bibr">Eğrioğlu et al., 2008</xref>). <xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>
shows the WIC index model selection process.<fig id="fig0002"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>WIC index for model selection process.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0002">Fig 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="para0036">Different targets were used as the desired value (system output) as COVID-19 has shown various behaviors and mutated several times to estimate mortality and morbidity rates. For this purpose, nine different targets have been used to study the neural network's learning process with different desires. The accuracy for each of these targets was evaluated by ANNs. A target with highest accuracy suggests a highest suitability for determining the importance of variables and thus was selected as the optimum target for modeling.</p>
                <p id="para0037">As the indicators are not in the same scale, the resulting models have been compared with each other by the normalized root mean square error interquartile index (RMSEIQR) (<xref rid="bib0042" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2019</xref>). Compared to the RMSE, which is a scale-dependent index and partly sensitive to outliers and extreme values, RMSEIQR can be used as a practical index for comparing models over various concentration scales (<xref rid="bib0042" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2019</xref>). Moreover, RMSEIQR was used as a common tool to assess and measure the uncertainty of the results (<xref rid="bib0043" ref-type="bibr">Wechsler and Kroll, 2006</xref>).</p>
                <p id="para0038">After variable selection, we assessed the relative importance of the selected variables in modeling COVID-19 prevalence and mortality for each period. The following steps explain the process of determining relative importance of variables in each period (<xref rid="fig0003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>
):<fig id="fig0003"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>The steps for determining the relative importance of variables in each period.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0003">Fig 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="para0039">Step <underline>1</underline>: Different target values from COVID-19 data were generated as described in 2.</p>
                <p id="para0040">Step <underline>2</underline>: WIC index was used to determine optimum network architecture for modeling each type of target (model selection). Nine of them were chosen from the n * m models (n: number of explanatory variables; m: number of targets) in total.</p>
                <p id="para0041">Step <underline>3</underline>: Models were developed based on optimum networks and their RMSEIQR were computed.</p>
                <p id="para0042">Step <underline>4</underline>: Two separate models (prevalence and mortality) with the lowest RMSEIQR values for each period were selected.</p>
                <p id="para0043">Step <underline>5</underline>: The variables were ranked based on relative importance using VIA methods. Ten different methods were used to perform VIA through the MLP artificial neural network. These ten VIA methods are described in the next section.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0006">
                <label>2.4</label>
                <title>Variable importance analysis (VIA)</title>
                <p id="para0044">The relative importance of input variables refers to each variable's contribution to predict the dependent variable (<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Ibrahim, 2013</xref>). Ten VIA methods were used to derive the relative importance of variables from these qualified networks: connection weights algorithm, modified connection weights, most squares, Garson, partial derivatives, stepwise, perturb, Lek's profile, modified Lek's profile, and variance-based approaches. The findings of these approaches can be integrated to draw a general inference. For this purpose, the total of the relative weights obtained from various methods (in percent) was calculated for each variable. This was performed individually for each period, for both infected cases and associated deaths. Below, we briefly explained the VIA techniques used in this study to quantify the relative importance of selected variables used in ANNs.</p>
                <p id="para0045">
                  <italic>
                    <bold>Connection weights (CW) algorithm</bold>
                  </italic>
                </p>
                <p id="para0046">The main benefit of the CW algorithm is that the relative contribution of each connection weight is preserved for both magnitude and sign (<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Olden et al., 2004</xref>, <xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Ibrahim, 2013</xref>). The relative importance of a given input variable can be defined as <xref rid="eqn0001" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (1)</xref>.<disp-formula id="eqn0001"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M11" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
                <p id="para0047">Where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M12" altimg="si12.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the relative importance of the input layer, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M13" altimg="si13.svg"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the input neuron, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M14" altimg="si14.svg"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the total number of neurons in the hidden layer, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M15" altimg="si15.svg"><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the output neuron. This method estimates the final network weights obtained through network training. The estimates of final weights differ depending on the initial weights used at the beginning of the training phase (<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Olden et al., 2004</xref>).</p>
                <p id="para0048">
                  <italic>
                    <bold>Modified connection weights (MCW) algorithm</bold>
                  </italic>
                </p>
                <p id="para0049">Using the same notation as the CW algorithm, after calculating the sum of product of final weights of connections from input neurons to hidden neurons, a correction term (partial correlation) is multiplied by this sum and the absolute value is taken. This absolute value is called the corrected sum. The corrected sum of each input is then divided by the total corrected sum to determine the relative importance of each input in the MCW algorithm, which is calculated as <xref rid="eqn0002" ref-type="disp-formula">Eqs. (2)</xref> and <xref rid="eqn0003" ref-type="disp-formula">(3)</xref> (<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Ibrahim, 2013</xref>).<disp-formula id="eqn0002"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M16" altimg="si16.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="eqn0003"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M17" altimg="si17.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
                <p id="para0050">Where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M18" altimg="si18.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is the partial correlation of input <inline-formula><mml:math id="M19" altimg="si19.svg"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> with output <inline-formula><mml:math id="M20" altimg="si20.svg"><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> after input <inline-formula><mml:math id="M21" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, which assesses the association degree between two random variables. Moreover, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M22" altimg="si22.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> denotes the simple correlation between input <inline-formula><mml:math id="M23" altimg="si19.svg"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and output<inline-formula><mml:math id="M24" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                <p id="para0051">
                  <bold>
                    <italic>Most squares</italic>
                  </bold>
                </p>
                <p id="para0052">Using the same notation as the CW algorithm, the most squares approach computes the sum of the squared between initial weight (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M25" altimg="si24.svg"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula>) and final weight (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M26" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula>) for each input. The sum of squared differences for each input is then divided by the total sum of all inputs. <xref rid="eqn0004" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (4)</xref> is used to calculate the relative importance of each input (<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Ibrahim, 2013</xref>).<disp-formula id="eqn0004"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="M27" altimg="si26.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
                <p id="para0053">
                  <italic>
                    <bold>Garson's algorithm (GA)</bold>
                  </italic>
                </p>
                <p id="para0054">GA partitions the neural network relative weights and then uses the absolute values of the final correlation weights. Thus, GA does not include the direction of the relationship between the input and output variables (<xref rid="eqn0005" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (5)</xref>) (<xref rid="bib0044" ref-type="bibr">Garson, 1991</xref>).<disp-formula id="eqn0005"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="M28" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
                <p id="para0055">
                  <italic>
                    <bold>Partial Derivatives (PD) method</bold>
                  </italic>
                </p>
                <p id="para0056">The output variable in the PD method would decrease when the input variable increases if the PD is negative (<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Ibrahim, 2013</xref>).<disp-formula id="eqn0006"><label>(6)</label><mml:math id="M29" altimg="si28.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="eqn0007"><label>(7)</label><mml:math id="M30" altimg="si29.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
                <p id="para0057">In <xref rid="eqn0006" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (6</xref>), <inline-formula><mml:math id="M31" altimg="si30.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is the output with respect to input <inline-formula><mml:math id="M32" altimg="si31.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M33" altimg="si32.svg"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> denotes the total number of observations in a network with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M34" altimg="si33.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> inputs, one hidden layer with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M35" altimg="si34.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> neurons, and one output neuron. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M36" altimg="si35.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is the derivative of the output neuron with respect to the corresponding input. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M37" altimg="si36.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M38" altimg="si37.svg"><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>
<sub>th</sub> hidden neuron's output, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M39" altimg="si38.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M40" altimg="si39.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> are the correlation weights between the output neuron and the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M41" altimg="si37.svg"><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>
<sub>th</sub> hidden neuron, and between the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M42" altimg="si19.svg"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>
<sub>th</sub> input neuron and the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M43" altimg="si37.svg"><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>
<sub>th</sub> hidden neuron, respectively. In <xref rid="eqn0007" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (7</xref>), <inline-formula><mml:math id="M44" altimg="si40.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the sum of the square partial derivatives.</p>
                <p id="para0058">
                  <italic>
                    <bold>Stepwise method</bold>
                  </italic>
                </p>
                <p id="para0059">The stepwise method involves adding or removing one input variable step by step while considering the effect on the output result. Depending on various arguments, the input variables are ranked according to their significance based on the changes in mean squared error (MSE). The largest increases or decreases in MSE due to input deletions are used to classify inputs in order of importance (<xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">Sung, 1998</xref>).</p>
                <p id="para0060">
                  <italic>
                    <bold>Perturb method</bold>
                  </italic>
                </p>
                <p id="para0061">Perturb method aims to measure how minor changes in each input will affect the neural network output. The algorithm modifies one variable's input values while leaving the others unchanged. The output variable's responses to each change in the input variable are registered. The input variable with the greatest relative effect on the output is the one with the largest changes. The input variables are classified according to the impact of the small changes (<xref rid="bib0046" ref-type="bibr">Gevrey et al., 2003</xref>).</p>
                <p id="para0062">
                  <italic>
                    <bold>Lek's profile method</bold>
                  </italic>
                </p>
                <p id="para0063">In Lek's profile method, each input variable is studied while the others are blocked at fixed values. The basic idea behind this method is to create a fictitious matrix that encompasses the entire range of input variables. Each variable is divided into a set of equal intervals between its minimum and maximum values. Except for one, all variables are set to their minimum, first quartile, median, third quartile, and maximum values at the beginning. The median value is subtracted from these five numbers. The output variable's profile is plotted for the considered values (<xref rid="bib0046" ref-type="bibr">Gevrey et al., 2003</xref>).</p>
                <p id="para0064">
                  <italic>
                    <bold>Modified Lek's profile method</bold>
                  </italic>
                </p>
                <p id="para0065">Despite in Lek's profile method where the input variables were kept constant at five points, Modified Lek's profile method selects an input variable and partitions it into 12 parts. Further, a qualified ANN is evaluated for each point of the partitioned variable's range and is implemented for each fixed values. The average of the outputs for each scale point is determined. This process is repeated until all ANN input variables could be assessed. The resulting curve profile for each input variable is then plotted (<xref rid="bib0047" ref-type="bibr">do Nascimento et al., 2019</xref>).</p>
                <p id="para0066">
                  <italic>
                    <bold>Variance based method</bold>
                  </italic>
                </p>
                <p id="para0067">Variance based method computes and updates the variance for given variables. It has the advantage of not requiring the values to be stored for computing the variance at the end. To measure the variance in this method, the sum of squares is updated by previous values according to <xref rid="eqn0009" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (9)</xref>, and then the variance values are calculated using <xref rid="eqn0010" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (10)</xref> (<xref rid="bib0048" ref-type="bibr">Welford, 1962</xref>).<disp-formula id="eqn0008"><label>(8)</label><mml:math id="M45" altimg="si41.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="eqn0009"><label>(9)</label><mml:math id="M46" altimg="si42.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="eqn0010"><label>(10)</label><mml:math id="M47" altimg="si43.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
                <p id="para0068">Where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M48" altimg="si44.svg"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> represents the mean of values, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M49" altimg="si45.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the corrected sum of squares, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M50" altimg="si46.svg"><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the total number of updates.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0007">
              <label>3</label>
              <title>Results</title>
              <p id="para0069">Based on the lowest obtained values for RMSEIQR, we selected prevalence rate in interquartile range (PR-IQR) as the target for modeling the prevalence rates of COVID-19 in each studied period (<xref rid="tbl0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>
). The spatio-temporal variations of prevalence rates in IQRs for each period has been depicted in <xref rid="fig0004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>
. According to <xref rid="fig0004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>, the countries in North and South America had a persistent higher prevalence rates in IQR than the rest of the world in all periods. In the period 2, the countries in continental Europe and America showed a relatively increasing trend in COVID-19 prevalence compared to the period 1, as the prevalence rates in IQR values have increased in these areas. The period 3 was the peak of the disease prevalence compared to other periods. During this period, Europe and most countries in north Asia were significantly infected by COVID-19.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0004"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Selected models in step 2 and 4.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0015">Table 4</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top"><bold>Period</bold></th><th valign="top"><bold>Target type</bold></th><th valign="top"><bold>Optimum number of neurons</bold></th><th valign="top"><bold>RMSEIQR</bold></th><th valign="top"><bold>Selected to perform VIA?</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="9" align="left" valign="top">Period 1</td><td valign="top">PR</td><td valign="top">23</td><td valign="top">0.017</td><td valign="top">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><bold>PR-IQR</bold></td><td valign="top"><bold>17</bold></td><td valign="top"><bold>0.011</bold></td><td valign="top"><bold>Yes</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">TMR</td><td valign="top">25</td><td valign="top">0.051</td><td valign="top">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">GR1</td><td valign="top">28</td><td valign="top">0.02</td><td valign="top">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><bold>MR</bold></td><td valign="top"><bold>18</bold></td><td valign="top"><bold>0.085</bold></td><td valign="top"><bold>Yes</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">MR-IQR</td><td valign="top">16</td><td valign="top">0.218</td><td valign="top">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">TMMR</td><td valign="top">27</td><td valign="top">0.512</td><td valign="top">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">GR2</td><td valign="top">22</td><td valign="top">0.245</td><td valign="top">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">FR</td><td valign="top">17</td><td valign="top">0.451</td><td valign="top">No</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="9" align="left" valign="top">Period 2</td><td valign="top">PR</td><td valign="top">24</td><td valign="top">0.005</td><td valign="top">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><bold>PR-IQR</bold></td><td valign="top"><bold>5</bold></td><td valign="top"><bold>0.003</bold></td><td valign="top"><bold>Yes</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">TMR</td><td valign="top">7</td><td valign="top">0.022</td><td valign="top">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">GR1</td><td valign="top">3</td><td valign="top">0.419</td><td valign="top">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><bold>MR</bold></td><td valign="top"><bold>13</bold></td><td valign="top"><bold>0.012</bold></td><td valign="top"><bold>Yes</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">MR-IQR</td><td valign="top">9</td><td valign="top">0.021</td><td valign="top">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">TMMR</td><td valign="top">21</td><td valign="top">0.423</td><td valign="top">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">GR2</td><td valign="top">16</td><td valign="top">0.471</td><td valign="top">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">FR</td><td valign="top">28</td><td valign="top">0.474</td><td valign="top">No</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="9" align="left" valign="top">Period 3</td><td valign="top">PR</td><td valign="top">2</td><td valign="top">0.03</td><td valign="top">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><bold>PR-IQR</bold></td><td valign="top"><bold>5</bold></td><td valign="top"><bold>0.02</bold></td><td valign="top"><bold>Yes</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">TMR</td><td valign="top">10</td><td valign="top">0.165</td><td valign="top">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">GR1</td><td valign="top">7</td><td valign="top">0.421</td><td valign="top">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><bold>MR</bold></td><td valign="top"><bold>6</bold></td><td valign="top"><bold>0.08</bold></td><td valign="top"><bold>Yes</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">MR-IQR</td><td valign="top">8</td><td valign="top">0.115</td><td valign="top">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">TMMR</td><td valign="top">23</td><td valign="top">0.776</td><td valign="top">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">GR2</td><td valign="top">7</td><td valign="top">0.841</td><td valign="top">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">FR</td><td valign="top">26</td><td valign="top">0.887</td><td valign="top">No</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="9" align="left" valign="top">Period 4</td><td valign="top">PR</td><td valign="top">2</td><td valign="top">0.057</td><td valign="top">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><bold>PR-IQR</bold></td><td valign="top"><bold>4</bold></td><td valign="top"><bold>0.032</bold></td><td valign="top"><bold>Yes</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">TMR</td><td valign="top">7</td><td valign="top">0.089</td><td valign="top">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">GR1</td><td valign="top">5</td><td valign="top">0.196</td><td valign="top">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><bold>MR</bold></td><td valign="top"><bold>21</bold></td><td valign="top"><bold>0.015</bold></td><td valign="top"><bold>Yes</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top">MR-IQR</td><td valign="top">17</td><td valign="top">0.04</td><td valign="top">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">TMMR</td><td valign="top">24</td><td valign="top">0.426</td><td valign="top">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">GR2</td><td valign="top">18</td><td valign="top">0.359</td><td valign="top">No</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">FR</td><td valign="top">18</td><td valign="top">0.901</td><td valign="top">No</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="fig0004"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Spatio-temporal distribution of the prevalence rates in IQR for all periods.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0004">Fig 4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4_lrg"/></fig></p>
              <p id="para0070">In period 4, the prevalence rates slightly decreased compared to period 3. This reduction in changes is more visible in America, maybe due to earlier initiation of vaccination programs. However, the countries of Central and South Africa have had no remarkable differences in prevalence rates (in all periods), except for the southernmost ones, including South Africa and Namibia, which have had the highest prevalence rates in IQR over time (<xref rid="fig0004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>).</p>
              <p id="para0071">Regarding COVID-19 deaths, we selected mortality rate (MR) as the target indicator in all periods due to the lowest values of RMSEIQRs (<xref rid="tbl0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). The spatio-temporal distribution of the MRs is demonstrated in <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>
. According to <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>, the changes in MR trends is more visible in America and Europe continents. In period 1, the distribution of MR was almost uniform across the world. Moreover, in the first period, most countries experienced lower MR rates compared to the following periods. In the period 2, South American countries including Brazil, Argentina, Bolivia, Peru, and Colombia experienced higher MRs than other countries. The period 3 shows a relatively significant increase in COVID-19 MRs in continental Europe and North America. Although the highest prevalence rates in IQR were found in period 3 (<xref rid="fig0004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>), period 4 was found to be the peak of mortality rates, especially in the United States, Brazil, South Africa, and some European countries (<xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>).<fig id="fig0005"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Spatio-temporal distribution of MRs for all periods.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0005">Fig 5</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr5_lrg"/></fig></p>
              <p id="para0072">Based on the WIC index, the optimum network architecture for modeling each type of target was identified. Nine models were chosen from a total of n * m (n: number of explanatory variables; m: number of targets) models (step 2). Further, two models with the lowest RMSEIQR were selected for each period, one model for prevalence and the other for mortality (step 4). <xref rid="tbl0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> lists the models that were selected in step 2 and 4.</p>
              <p id="para0073">The ANN topologies that were selected to perform VIA are represented as bold rows in <xref rid="tbl0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>. <xref rid="fig0006" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>
to <xref rid="fig0009" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>
depicts the twenty most influential explanatory variables on COVID-19 prevalence and mortality for all selected periods, respectively. As can be seen, some of the explanatory variables were among the twenty most important variables across all periods (non-black horizontal bars). Most economic-related variables such as unemployment, gross national income (GNI) per capita, and GNI per capita growth have always been among the most influential explanatory variables on COVID-19 prevalence. In addition, other variables related to public transportation, including rail and air transportation, as well as surface temperature, population density, and urban population were among the most significant variables for cases at all periods. For mortality, diabetes prevalence, the number of hospital beds (per 1000 people), number of nurses and midwives (per 1000 people), negative affect (negative emotions and experiences during life), and air transportation were the most influential explanatory variables for all periods.<fig id="fig0006"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>The 20 most influential explanatory variables on COVID-19 a) prevalence b) mortality in the period 1.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0006">Fig 6</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr6_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig0007"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>The 20 most influential explanatory variables on COVID-19 a) prevalence b) mortality in the period 2.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0007">Fig 7</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr7_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig0008"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>The 20 most influential explanatory variables on COVID-19 a) prevalence b) mortality in the period 3.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0008">Fig 8</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr8_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig0009"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>The 20 most influential explanatory variables on COVID-19 a) prevalence b) mortality in the period 4.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0009">Fig 9</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr9_lrg"/></fig></p>
              <p id="para0074">In addition, <xref rid="tbl0005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>
lists the two most influential variables for each period based on the median of weights. <xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10</xref>
depicts the worldwide spatial distribution of PR-IQRs in all periods, along with the most influential variables on the disease prevalence. In addition, <xref rid="fig0011" ref-type="fig">Fig. 11</xref>
shows the spatial distribution of MRs for all countries, along with the most influential variables in each period.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0005"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>The two most influential variables for each period based on median of weights classified for prevalence and mortality, separately.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0016">Table 5</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><bold>Period</bold></th><th colspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><bold>prevalence</bold><hr/></th><th colspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><bold>mortality</bold><hr/></th></tr><tr><th valign="top"><bold>Variable</bold></th><th valign="top"><bold>Median of Weights</bold></th><th valign="top"><bold>Variable</bold></th><th valign="top"><bold>Median of Weights</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><bold>Period 1</bold></td><td valign="top">Population density</td><td valign="top">1.778</td><td valign="top">Diabetes prevalence</td><td valign="top">1.755</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">GNI per capita</td><td valign="top">1.775</td><td valign="top">Hospital beds</td><td valign="top">1.675</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><bold>Period 2</bold></td><td valign="top">Unemployment</td><td valign="top">2.11</td><td valign="top">Diabetes prevalence</td><td valign="top">1.995</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Population density</td><td valign="top">1.973</td><td valign="top">Nurses and midwives</td><td valign="top">1.778</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><bold>Period 3</bold></td><td valign="top">Population density</td><td valign="top">1.775</td><td valign="top">Hospital beds</td><td valign="top">1.684</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Air transport, passengers carried</td><td valign="top">1.645</td><td valign="top">Negative affect</td><td valign="top">1.648</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><bold>Period 4</bold></td><td valign="top">GNI per capita</td><td valign="top">1.721</td><td valign="top">Diabetes prevalence</td><td valign="top">1.764</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Unemployment</td><td valign="top">1.673</td><td valign="top">Hospital beds</td><td valign="top">1.688</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="fig0010"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p>Spatio-temporal distribution of the most influential variables on PR-IQRs for each period.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0010">Fig 10</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr10_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig0011"><label>Fig. 11</label><caption><p>Spatio-temporal distribution of the most influential variables on MRs for each period.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0011">Fig 11</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr11_lrg"/></fig></p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0008">
              <label>4</label>
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p id="para0075">The outbreak of COVID-19 has adversely affected many countries around the world. Numerous mutations caused by the SARS-CoV-2 virus have intensified its spread, making the control of the epidemic even more challenging. Identifying the effective variables and their relationship with disease prevalence and mortality over time can be useful for controlling disease outbreak. ANNs are among the most widely used approaches to model this relationship, particularly as the associated data and computations become more readily available (<xref rid="bib0049" ref-type="bibr">Augusta et al., 2019</xref>).</p>
              <p id="para0076">Since the epidemic of COVID-19, as a contagious disease, is directly related to the geographical concept of an area, GIS can play an essential role in its planning, management, and modeling (<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">Mollalo et al., 2020</xref>). GIS has been used in many studies to manage and plan epidemiological issues from spatial perspectives (<xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">Meliker and Sloan, 2011</xref>, <xref rid="bib0051" ref-type="bibr">Shrestha et al., 2020</xref>). It also has been consistently used to analyze health-related data and can be a valuable tool for analyzing the spread of disease in each region (<xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">Meliker and Sloan, 2011</xref>). Increasing the power of computers, improving spatial analysis methods, and developing artificial intelligence models have led to the development of advanced and modern GIS applications in disease modeling and prediction (<xref rid="bib0052" ref-type="bibr">Ghayvat et al., 2021</xref>). Therefore, in this study, we utilized GIS technology to develop a spatio-temporal model for COVID-19 prevalence and mortality.</p>
              <p id="para0077">Given that little space-time COVID-19 modeling has been conducted at the global scale, we compiled a geodatabase of potential influential variables on the prevalence and mortality of the disease and ranked relative importance of variables based on VIA methods for four periods of time. Our findings showed that various VIA algorithms yielded varying results. Although the relative importance of variables on prevalence and mortality changed over time, some variables were identified among the top 20 most relevant variables in all periods.</p>
              <p id="para0078">Dealing with complicated interactions among variables, we applied ten different VIA methods to evaluate the influence of potential explanatory variables by optimizing the data storage, advancing the model interpretability, and providing a smaller number of influential variables without losing accuracy. VIA techniques can be implemented to solve the intricacy of interactions among variables on big datasets (<xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Ferretti et al., 2016</xref>). For instance, these techniques were used to figure out how well each variable influences the COVID-19 prevalence. <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">Dfuf et al. (2020</xref>) implemented a parametric and a nonparametric VIA method and calculated the impact of the 35 companies on the political, economic, and social instability captured by two highly regarded Spanish economic newspapers during the COVID-19 outbreak. The result showed that the nonparametric VIA method outperformed its competitors since it incorporates all the information using the entire distribution errors.</p>
              <p id="para0079">Economic variables have retained their significant impact on higher rates of COVID-19 prevalence over time. Consistent with our findings, unemployment was found strongly correlated with the increased risk of disease prevalence (<xref rid="bib0053" ref-type="bibr">Jin et al., 1995</xref>). Since unemployment and poverty reduce people's ability to access health facilities, unemployed people who are infected communicate with others in the society without being treated, which may increase the severity of the disease transmission. Another hypothesis that can explain this association is unemployed individuals and uneducated people are less likely to get vaccinated due to underestimating the positive impacts or overestimating the risks of getting vaccinated, which can cause a higher prevalence of the COVD-19 in a society (<xref rid="bib0054" ref-type="bibr">Malik et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">Mollalo and Tatar, 2021</xref>). Some other studies, such as (<xref rid="bib0053" ref-type="bibr">Jin et al., 1995</xref>), have shown that unemployment and inadequate social welfare can increase the disease spread.</p>
              <p id="para0080">Demographic variables were other influential variables affecting the COVID-19 spread. Due to the contagious nature of COVID-19, the higher population density and overcrowding in an area are associated with the greater likelihood of disease occurring (<xref rid="bib0056" ref-type="bibr">Sigler et al., 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0057" ref-type="bibr">Sirkeci and Yucesahin, 2020</xref>). On the contrary, countries with a lower population density showed lower prevalence rates of COVID-19 in all periods, such as Australia and Russia. Consistent with our findings, a recent study (<xref rid="bib0004" ref-type="bibr">Mansour et al., 2021</xref>) shows that the higher population density rates in Oman could result in a higher prevalence of COVID-19. A research by <xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Ahmadi et al. (2020</xref>) suggests that population density and intra-provincial movement are directly associated with the spread of the coronavirus in Iran. Other studies confirm that higher population density increases the chance of transmission of the virus (<xref rid="bib0058" ref-type="bibr">Coşkun et al., 2021</xref>, <xref rid="bib0059" ref-type="bibr">Rocklöv and Sjödin, 2020</xref>) and can alter the prevalence and mortality rates (<xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">Bhadra et al., 2021</xref>).</p>
              <p id="para0081">The use of public transit was persistently found significant on COVID-19 prevalence in all periods. A possible explanation might be that many people in public transportation stand together for a long time in a closed environment especially transportation by plane and train. As a result, the contagious virus can rapidly be transmitted from infected individuals to other passengers, causing the disease to spread more severely. <xref rid="bib0061" ref-type="bibr">Zheng et al. (2020</xref>) showed that the infected individuals during the incubation period brought the disease from Wuhan, China to other cities and nations by using public transportation such as flights, trains and buses. In New York, <xref rid="bib0062" ref-type="bibr">Cordes and Castro (2020</xref>) suggested that people who rely on public means of transportation might be at higher risks of COVID-19 due to contact with other infected passengers, consistent with our findings.</p>
              <p id="para0082">Regarding COVID-19 mortality, diabetes prevalence was found to be a significant variable in all periods. Inadequate and poor immunological responses to viral infections may be among the leading cause of mortality in COVID-19 patients with diabetes (<xref rid="bib0063" ref-type="bibr">Critchley et al., 2018</xref>). The increased blood sugar level in a person with diabetes can severely damage the beneficial intracellular bacteria, which in turn increases the viral binding affinity and reduces the virus removal (<xref rid="bib0064" ref-type="bibr">Muniyappa and Gubbi, 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">Gazzaz, 2021</xref>). Exploring the spatial variations of COVID-19 in the Caribbean, <xref rid="bib0026" ref-type="bibr">Moonsammy et al. (2021</xref>) found that the higher prevalence of diabetes in the Caribbean could increase COVID-19 deaths. A meta-analysis on more than 16,000 patients also found that diabetes in patients with COVID-19 doubled the risk of death (<xref rid="bib0066" ref-type="bibr">Kumar et al., 2020</xref>). Consistent with our results, other researchers have shown a strong relationship between diabetes prevalence and COVID-19 mortality (<xref rid="bib0067" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0068" ref-type="bibr">Guo et al., 2020</xref>).</p>
              <p id="para0083">There were several caveats and limitations in this study that should be acknowledged. First, due to the worldwide distribution of this study, it is most likely that some countries have not provided accurate statistics about COVID-19 prevalence and deaths, which may bias the results. Another limitation of this study was associated with different lockdown policies and stay-at-home restrictions for each country. Some countries quickly began quarantine policies after the pandemic was announced than others that did not make any specific lockdown policy. Although we tried to find the most influential factors related to COVID-19 prevalence and mortality for all countries at the same time, a study on a higher spatial resolution (sub-country level) can provide more reliable results. Despite above-mentioned limitations, the findings may help policymakers to track the spread of disease over time based on the most significant variables identified by the employed models.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0009">
              <label>5</label>
              <title>Conclusions</title>
              <p id="para0084">In summary, we examined ten different VIA methods to estimate the relative importance of potential explanatory variables on COVID-19 prevalence and mortality at a global scale. Due to the numerous mutations of the virus, various targets were considered for modeling to enhance the accuracy of the results. Our findings indicated that the extracted relative importance from different models by VIA methods varies over time. However, several variables were persistently among the most influential variables on the prevalence and mortality of the disease in all periods. Unemployment, population density, air and rail transportation, urban population, GNI per capita, GNI per capita growth, and surface air temperature were among the most significant variables on disease prevalence in all periods. Regarding COVID-19 mortality, diabetes, air transportation, number of hospital beds, number of nurses, and negative affect were among the most influential variables. Better spatial resolution can improve the validity of the results in future studies. Policymakers and epidemiologists can use spatio-temporal analysis to monitor and evaluate COVID-19 prevalence and mortality concerning significant variables.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0009a">
              <title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title>
              <p id="para0084a"><bold>Nima Kianfar:</bold> Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Methodology, Visualization, Writing – original draft. <bold>Mohammad Saadi Mesgari:</bold> Validation, Supervision, Investigation, Writing – review &amp; editing. <bold>Abolfazl Mollalo:</bold> Methodology, Validation, Writing – review &amp; editing. <bold>Mehrdad Kaveh:</bold> Investigation, Writing – review &amp; editing.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0009aa">
              <title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title>
              <p id="para0084aa"><bold>Nima Kianfar:</bold> Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Methodology, Visualization, Writing – original draft. <bold>Mohammad Saadi Mesgari:</bold> Validation, Supervision, Investigation, Writing – review &amp; editing. <bold>Abolfazl Mollalo:</bold> Methodology, Validation, Writing – review &amp; editing. <bold>Mehrdad Kaveh:</bold> Investigation, Writing – review &amp; editing.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="COI-statement">
              <title>Declaration of Competing Interest</title>
              <p id="para0085">None.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list id="cebibl1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="bib0001">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0001">World Health Organization (WHO), <italic>Archived: WHO Timeline- COVID-19</italic>. 2020ab; Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/news/item/27-04-2020-who-timeline-covid-19" id="interref0001">www.who.int/news/item/27-04-2020-who-timeline-covid-19</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0002">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0002">World Health Organization (WHO), <italic>WHO Coronavirus (COVID-19) Dashboard</italic>. 2021b; Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://covid19.who.int/" id="interref0002">https://covid19.who.int/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0003">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0003">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A novel coronavirus outbreak of global health concern</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet</source>
                  <volume>395</volume>
                  <issue>10223</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>470</fpage>
                  <lpage>473</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31986257</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0004">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0004">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mansour</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Sociodemographic determinants of COVID-19 incidence rates in Oman: geospatial modelling using multiscale geographically weighted regression (MGWR)</article-title>
                  <source>Sustain. Cities Soc.</source>
                  <volume>65</volume>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">102627</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0005">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0005">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mollalo</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rivera</surname>
                      <given-names>K.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vahedi</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Artificial neural network modeling of novel coronavirus (COVID-19) incidence rates across the continental United States</article-title>
                  <source>Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health</source>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <issue>12</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>4204</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0006">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0006">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mollalo</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A GIS-based artificial neural network model for spatial distribution of tuberculosis across the continental United States</article-title>
                  <source>Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health</source>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <fpage>157</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0007">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0007">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ripley</surname>
                      <given-names>B.D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>Pattern Recognition and Neural Networks</part-title>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <publisher-name>Cambridge university press</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0008">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0008">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Duh</surname>
                      <given-names>M.-S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Walker</surname>
                      <given-names>A.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ayanian</surname>
                      <given-names>J.Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Epidemiologic interpretation of artificial neural networks</article-title>
                  <source>Am. J. Epidemiol.</source>
                  <volume>147</volume>
                  <issue>12</issue>
                  <year>1998</year>
                  <fpage>1112</fpage>
                  <lpage>1122</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9645789</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0009">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0009">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Olden</surname>
                      <given-names>J.D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jackson</surname>
                      <given-names>D.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Illuminating the “black box”: a randomization approach for understanding variable contributions in artificial neural networks</article-title>
                  <source>Ecol. Modell.</source>
                  <volume>154</volume>
                  <issue>1-2</issue>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <fpage>135</fpage>
                  <lpage>150</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0010">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0010">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Olden</surname>
                      <given-names>J.D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Joy</surname>
                      <given-names>M.K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Death</surname>
                      <given-names>R.G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An accurate comparison of methods for quantifying variable importance in artificial neural networks using simulated data</article-title>
                  <source>Ecol. Modell.</source>
                  <volume>178</volume>
                  <issue>3-4</issue>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <fpage>389</fpage>
                  <lpage>397</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0011">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0011">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ibrahim</surname>
                      <given-names>O.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A comparison of methods for assessing the relative importance of input variables in artificial neural networks</article-title>
                  <source>J. Appl. Sci. Res.</source>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <issue>11</issue>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <fpage>5692</fpage>
                  <lpage>5700</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0012">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0012">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Özesmi</surname>
                      <given-names>S.L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Özesmi</surname>
                      <given-names>U.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An artificial neural network approach to spatial habitat modelling with interspecific interaction</article-title>
                  <source>Ecol. Modell.</source>
                  <volume>116</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>1999</year>
                  <fpage>15</fpage>
                  <lpage>31</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0013">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0013">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ferretti</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Saltelli</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tarantola</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Trends in sensitivity analysis practice in the last decade</article-title>
                  <source>Sci. Total Environ.</source>
                  <volume>568</volume>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <fpage>666</fpage>
                  <lpage>670</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26934843</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0014">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0014">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wei</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lu</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Song</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Variable importance analysis: a comprehensive review</article-title>
                  <source>Reliab. Eng. Syst. Saf.</source>
                  <volume>142</volume>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <fpage>399</fpage>
                  <lpage>432</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0015">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0015">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dfuf</surname>
                      <given-names>I.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Variable importance analysis in imbalanced datasets: A new approach</article-title>
                  <source>IEEE Access</source>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>127404</fpage>
                  <lpage>127430</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0016">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0016">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Casiraghi</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Explainable machine learning for early assessment of COVID-19 risk prediction in emergency departments</article-title>
                  <source>IEEE Access</source>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>196299</fpage>
                  <lpage>196325</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34812365</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0017">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0017">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pasha</surname>
                      <given-names>D.F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An analysis to identify the important variables for the spread of COVID-19 using numerical techniques and data science</article-title>
                  <source>Case Stud. Chem. Environ. Eng.</source>
                  <volume>3</volume>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100067</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0018">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0018">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shaffiee Haghshenas</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Prioritizing and analyzing the role of climate and urban parameters in the confirmed cases of COVID-19 based on artificial intelligence applications</article-title>
                  <source>Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health</source>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>3730</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0019">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0019">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mollalo</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Geographic information system-based analysis of the spatial and spatio-temporal distribution of zoonotic cutaneous leishmaniasis in Golestan Province, north-east of Iran</article-title>
                  <source>Zoonoses Public Health</source>
                  <volume>62</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <fpage>18</fpage>
                  <lpage>28</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24628913</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0020">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0020">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mollalo</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Machine learning approaches in GIS-based ecological modeling of the sand fly Phlebotomus papatasi, a vector of zoonotic cutaneous leishmaniasis in Golestan province, Iran</article-title>
                  <source>Acta Trop.</source>
                  <volume>188</volume>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <lpage>194</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30201488</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0021">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0021">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bashir</surname>
                      <given-names>M.F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Correlation between climate indicators and COVID-19 pandemic in New York, USA</article-title>
                  <source>Sci. Total Environ.</source>
                  <volume>728</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">138835</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0022">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0022">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>C.H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schwartz</surname>
                      <given-names>G.G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Spatial disparities in coronavirus incidence and mortality in the United States: an ecological analysis as of May 2020</article-title>
                  <source>J. Rural Health</source>
                  <volume>36</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>433</fpage>
                  <lpage>445</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32543763</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0023">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0023">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jia</surname>
                      <given-names>J.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Population flow drives spatio-temporal distribution of COVID-19 in China</article-title>
                  <source>Nature</source>
                  <volume>582</volume>
                  <issue>7812</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>389</fpage>
                  <lpage>394</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32349120</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0024">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0024">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ahmadi</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Investigation of effective climatology parameters on COVID-19 outbreak in Iran</article-title>
                  <source>Sci. Total Environ.</source>
                  <volume>729</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">138705</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0025">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0025">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ramírez</surname>
                      <given-names>I.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lee</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>COVID-19 emergence and social and health determinants in Colorado: a rapid spatial analysis</article-title>
                  <source>Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health</source>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <issue>11</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>3856</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0026">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0026">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Moonsammy</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>COVID-19 modelling in the Caribbean: spatial and statistical assessments</article-title>
                  <source>Spatial Spatio Temp. Epidemiol.</source>
                  <volume>37</volume>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100416</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0027">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0027">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ambade</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>COVID-19 lockdowns reduce the Black carbon and polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons of the Asian atmosphere: source apportionment and health hazard evaluation</article-title>
                  <source>Environ. Develop. Sustain.</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>20</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0028">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0028">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gautam</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The influence of COVID-19 on air quality in India: a boon or inutile</article-title>
                  <source>Bull. Environ. Contam. Toxicol.</source>
                  <volume>104</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>724</fpage>
                  <lpage>726</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32394052</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0029">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0029">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gautam</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>COVID-19: air pollution remains low as people stay at home</article-title>
                  <source>Air Quality Atmos. Health</source>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>853</fpage>
                  <lpage>857</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0030">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0030">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Severe air pollution events not avoided by reduced anthropogenic activities during COVID-19 outbreak</article-title>
                  <source>Resour. Conserv. Recycl.</source>
                  <volume>158</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">104814</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0031">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0031">World Bank, <italic>World Bank Open Data 2021</italic>. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://data.worldbank.org/" id="interref0003">https://data.worldbank.org/</ext-link>. Accessed February 1, 2021.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0033">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0033">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Helliwell</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Layard</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sachs</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>World Happiness Report</part-title>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <publisher-name>Sustainable Development Solutions Network</publisher-name>
                  <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
                  <comment>Available from:</comment>
                  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://worldhappiness.report/ed/2018/" id="interref0005">https://worldhappiness.report/ed/2018/</ext-link>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0034">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0034">Pew Research Center. (2014) Washington, D.C.<italic>Religious diversity index scores by country</italic>4 April. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pewforum.org/2014/04/04/religious-diversity-index-scores-by-country/" id="interref0006">https://www.pewforum.org/2014/04/04/religious-diversity-index-scores-by-country/</ext-link>. Accessed March 21, 2021.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0035">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0035">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shrestha</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Detecting multicollinearity in regression analysis</article-title>
                  <source>Am. J. Appl. Math. Stat.</source>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>39</fpage>
                  <lpage>42</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0036">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0036">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Civco</surname>
                      <given-names>D.L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Artificial neural networks for land-cover classification and mapping</article-title>
                  <source>Int. J. Geogr. Inform. Sci.</source>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>1993</year>
                  <fpage>173</fpage>
                  <lpage>186</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0037">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0037">Kang, H.-Y., R. Rule, and P. Noble, <italic>Artificial neural network modeling of phytoplankton blooms and its application to sampling sites within the same estuary.</italic>2011.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0038">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0038">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yonaba</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Anctil</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fortin</surname>
                      <given-names>V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Comparing sigmoid transfer functions for neural network multistep ahead streamflow forecasting</article-title>
                  <source>J. Hydrol. Eng.</source>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <fpage>275</fpage>
                  <lpage>283</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0039">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0039">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ojha</surname>
                      <given-names>V.K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abraham</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Snášel</surname>
                      <given-names>V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Metaheuristic design of feedforward neural networks: a review of two decades of research</article-title>
                  <source>Eng. Appl. Artif. Intell.</source>
                  <volume>60</volume>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <lpage>116</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0040">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0040">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kayri</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Predictive abilities of Bayesian regularization and levenberg–marquardt algorithms in artificial neural networks: a comparative empirical study on social data</article-title>
                  <source>Math. Comput. Appl.</source>
                  <volume>21</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <fpage>20</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0041">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0041">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eğrioğlu</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aladağ</surname>
                      <given-names>Ç.H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Günay</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A new model selection strategy in artificial neural networks</article-title>
                  <source>Appl. Math. Comput.</source>
                  <volume>195</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <fpage>591</fpage>
                  <lpage>597</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0042">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0042">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Cluster-based bagging of constrained mixed-effects models for high spatiotemporal resolution nitrogen oxides prediction over large regions</article-title>
                  <source>Environ. Int.</source>
                  <volume>128</volume>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <fpage>310</fpage>
                  <lpage>323</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31078000</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0043">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0043">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wechsler</surname>
                      <given-names>S.P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kroll</surname>
                      <given-names>C.N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Quantifying DEM uncertainty and its effect on topographic parameters</article-title>
                  <source>Photogramm. Eng. Remote Sens.</source>
                  <volume>72</volume>
                  <issue>9</issue>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <fpage>1081</fpage>
                  <lpage>1090</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0044">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0044">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Garson</surname>
                      <given-names>G.D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Interpreting Neural Network Connection Weights</article-title>
                  <source>AI Expert</source>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <year>1991</year>
                  <fpage>47</fpage>
                  <lpage>51</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0045">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0045">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sung</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Ranking importance of input parameters of neural networks</article-title>
                  <source>Expert Syst. Appl.</source>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <issue>3-4</issue>
                  <year>1998</year>
                  <fpage>405</fpage>
                  <lpage>411</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0046">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0046">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gevrey</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dimopoulos</surname>
                      <given-names>I.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lek</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Review and comparison of methods to study the contribution of variables in artificial neural network models</article-title>
                  <source>Ecol. Modell.</source>
                  <volume>160</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <fpage>249</fpage>
                  <lpage>264</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0047">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0047">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>do Nascimento</surname>
                      <given-names>E.O.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tusset</surname>
                      <given-names>A.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lopes</surname>
                      <given-names>E.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Sensitivity analysis of chaos in a nonlinear pendulum through artificial neural networks</article-title>
                  <source>Math. Eng. Sci. Aerospace (MESA)</source>
                  <volume>10</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2019</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0048">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0048">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Welford</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Note on a method for calculating corrected sums of squares and products</article-title>
                  <source>Technometrics</source>
                  <volume>4</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <year>1962</year>
                  <fpage>419</fpage>
                  <lpage>420</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0049">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0049">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Augusta</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Deardon</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Taylor</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Deep learning for supervised classification of spatial epidemics</article-title>
                  <source>Spat. Spatio Temp. Epidemiol.</source>
                  <volume>29</volume>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <lpage>198</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0050">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0050">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Meliker</surname>
                      <given-names>J.R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sloan</surname>
                      <given-names>C.D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Spatio-temporal epidemiology: Principles and opportunities</article-title>
                  <source>Spat. Spatio Temp. Epidemiol.</source>
                  <volume>2</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>9</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0051">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0051">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shrestha</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Spatial epidemiology: an empirical framework for syndemics research</article-title>
                  <source>Soc. Sci. Med.</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">113352</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0052">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0052">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ghayvat</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Recognizing suspect and predicting the spread of contagion based on mobile phone location data (counteract): a system of identifying covid-19 infectious and hazardous sites, detecting disease outbreaks based on the internet of things, edge computing, and artificial intelligence</article-title>
                  <source>Sustain. CitiesSoc.</source>
                  <volume>69</volume>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">102798</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0053">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0053">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jin</surname>
                      <given-names>R.L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shah</surname>
                      <given-names>C.P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Svoboda</surname>
                      <given-names>T.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The impact of unemployment on health: a review of the evidence</article-title>
                  <source>CMAJ</source>
                  <volume>153</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <year>1995</year>
                  <fpage>529</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7641151</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0054">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0054">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Malik</surname>
                      <given-names>A.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Determinants of COVID-19 vaccine acceptance in the US</article-title>
                  <source>EClinicalMedicine</source>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100495</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0055">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0055">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mollalo</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tatar</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Spatial Modeling of COVID-19 vaccine hesitancy in the United States</article-title>
                  <source>Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health</source>
                  <volume>18</volume>
                  <issue>18</issue>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <fpage>9488</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34574416</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0056">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0056">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sigler</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The socio-spatial determinants of COVID-19 diffusion: the impact of globalisation, settlement characteristics and population</article-title>
                  <source>Glob. Health</source>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>14</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0057">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0057">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sirkeci</surname>
                      <given-names>I.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yucesahin</surname>
                      <given-names>M.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Coronavirus and migration: analysis of human mobility and the spread of Covid-19</article-title>
                  <source>Migr. Lett.</source>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>379</fpage>
                  <lpage>398</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0058">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0058">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Coşkun</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yıldırım</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gündüz</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The spread of COVID-19 virus through population density and wind in Turkey cities</article-title>
                  <source>Sci. Total Environ.</source>
                  <volume>751</volume>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">141663</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0059">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0059">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rocklöv</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sjödin</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>High population densities catalyse the spread of COVID-19</article-title>
                  <source>J. Travel Med.</source>
                  <volume>27</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <comment>taaa038</comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0060">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0060">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bhadra</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mukherjee</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sarkar</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Impact of population density on Covid-19 infected and mortality rate in India</article-title>
                  <source>Model. Earth Syst. Environ.</source>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <fpage>623</fpage>
                  <lpage>629</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0061">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0061">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zheng</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Spatial transmission of COVID-19 via public and private transportation in China</article-title>
                  <source>Travel Med. Infect. Dis.</source>
                  <volume>34</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101626</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0062">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0062">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cordes</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Castro</surname>
                      <given-names>M.C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Spatial analysis of COVID-19 clusters and contextual factors in New York City</article-title>
                  <source>Spat. Spat.Tempor. Epidemiol.</source>
                  <volume>34</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100355</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0063">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0063">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Critchley</surname>
                      <given-names>J.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Glycemic control and risk of infections among people with type 1 or type 2 diabetes in a large primary care cohort study</article-title>
                  <source>Diabetes Care.</source>
                  <volume>41</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <fpage>2127</fpage>
                  <lpage>2135</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30104296</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0064">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0064">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Muniyappa</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gubbi</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>COVID-19 pandemic, coronaviruses, and diabetes mellitus</article-title>
                  <source>Am. J. Physiol.Endocrinol. Metab.</source>
                  <volume>318</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>E736</fpage>
                  <lpage>E741</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32228322</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0065">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0065">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gazzaz</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Diabetes and COVID-19</article-title>
                  <source>Open Life Sci.</source>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <fpage>297</fpage>
                  <lpage>302</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33817321</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0066">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0066">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kumar</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Is diabetes mellitus associated with mortality and severity of COVID-19? A meta-analysis</article-title>
                  <source>Diabetes Metab. Syndr. Clin. Res. Rev.</source>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>535</fpage>
                  <lpage>545</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0067">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0067">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huang</surname>
                      <given-names>I.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lim</surname>
                      <given-names>M.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pranata</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Diabetes mellitus is associated with increased mortality and severity of disease in COVID-19 pneumonia–a systematic review, meta-analysis, and meta-regression</article-title>
                  <source>Diabetes Metab. Syndr. Clin. Res. Rev.</source>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>395</fpage>
                  <lpage>403</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0068">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0068">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Guo</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Diabetes is a risk factor for the progression and prognosis of COVID-19</article-title>
                  <source>Diabetes Metab. Res. Rev.</source>
                  <volume>36</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>e3319</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0032">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0032">Giovanni, Greenbelt. NASA/GSFC, MD,USA<italic>, NASA goddard earth sciences data and information services center (GES DISC) (2021).</italic> Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://giovanni.gsfc.nasa.gov/" id="interref0004">https://giovanni.gsfc.nasa.gov/</ext-link>. Accessed March 1, 2021.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
            <ack id="ack0001">
              <sec id="sec0010">
                <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                <p id="para0086">We would like to thank anonymous reviewers for taking the time and effort to review the manuscript.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0011">
                <title>Funding sources</title>
                <p id="para0087">This research did not receive any specific grant from funding agencies in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p>
              </sec>
            </ack>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
