<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-03-11T00:50:52Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8301475" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8301475</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-07-24</datestamp>
        <setSpec>biology</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biology (Basel)</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Biology (Basel)</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">biology</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Biology</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2079-7737</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>MDPI</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC8301475</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8301475</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">8301475</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34356522</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/biology10070667</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">biology-10-00667</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Protection Strategy against an Epidemic Disease on Edge-Weighted Graphs Applied to a COVID-19 Case</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1969-4746</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Manríquez</surname>
                    <given-names>Ronald</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-biology-10-00667">1</xref>
                  <xref rid="c1-biology-10-00667" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6527-6292</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Guerrero-Nancuante</surname>
                    <given-names>Camilo</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-biology-10-00667">2</xref>
                  <xref rid="c1-biology-10-00667" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Taramasco</surname>
                    <given-names>Carla</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-biology-10-00667">3</xref>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4-biology-10-00667">4</xref>
                  <xref rid="c1-biology-10-00667" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="editor">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Moya</surname>
                    <given-names>Andrés</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <role>Academic Editor</role>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="editor">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Davidson</surname>
                    <given-names>Andrew</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <role>Academic Editor</role>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="af1-biology-10-00667"><label>1</label>Laboratorio de Investigación Lab[e]saM, Departamento de Matemática y Estadística, Universidad de Playa Ancha, Valparaíso 2340000, Chile</aff>
              <aff id="af2-biology-10-00667"><label>2</label>Escuela de Enfermería, Universidad de Valparaíso, Viña del Mar 2520000, Chile</aff>
              <aff id="af3-biology-10-00667"><label>3</label>Escuela de Ingeniería Civil Informática, Universidad de Valparaíso, Valparaíso 2340000, Chile</aff>
              <aff id="af4-biology-10-00667"><label>4</label>Centro Nacional de Sistemas de Información en Salud, Santiago 8320000, Chile</aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="c1-biology-10-00667"><label>*</label>Correspondence: <email>ronald.manriquez@upla.cl</email> (R.M.); <email>camilo.guerrero@uv.cl</email> (C.G.-N.); <email>carla.taramasco@uv.cl</email> (C.T.)</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>15</day>
                <month>7</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <month>7</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>10</volume>
              <issue>7</issue>
              <elocation-id>667</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>17</day>
                  <month>5</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>25</day>
                  <month>6</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2021 by the authors.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>Licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland. This article is an open access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution (CC BY) license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <sec>
                  <title>Simple Summary</title>
                  <p>Infectious diseases have been part of human history. Countless epidemics have produced high mortality rates in vulnerable populations. With the understanding of the spread of these types of diseases, population groups have been able to adapt and better cope with infections. Given the COVID-19 pandemic, one of the strategies used is the modeling of infectious diseases with the aim of establishing protection measures for people and stopping the spread of the epidemic. Our study evaluates protection strategies through infectious disease modeling with COVID-19 data in a commune in Chile. The results of the simulations indicate that the model generates important protection for the population by recognizing the super-propagating people (bridge nodes). This type of protection can be key in the fight against COVID-19.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Abstract</title>
                  <p>Among the diverse and important applications that networks currently have is the modeling of infectious diseases. Immunization, or the process of protecting nodes in the network, plays a key role in stopping diseases from spreading. Hence the importance of having tools or strategies that allow the solving of this challenge. In this paper, we evaluate the effectiveness of the DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm1"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> ranking in immunizing nodes in an edge-weighted network with 3866 nodes and 6,841,470 edges. The network is obtained from a real database and the spread of COVID-19 was modeled with the classic SIR model. We apply the protection to the network, according to the importance ranking list produced by DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm2"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, considering different protection budgets. Furthermore, we consider three different values for <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm3"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>; in this way, we compare how the protection performs according to the value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm4"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>edge-weighted graph</kwd>
                <kwd>SIR model</kwd>
                <kwd>graph protection</kwd>
                <kwd>COVID-19</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-biology-10-00667">
              <title>1. Introduction</title>
              <p>Infectious diseases have been the focus of multiple fields of research. In public health and epidemiology, efforts are directed at establishing transmission dynamics, the characteristics of infectious agents, and the populations most affected by pathogens, among others, which are of high importance for science [<xref rid="B1-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. In recent decades, research on infectious diseases has involved the application of complex theories from mathematics and engineering. In particular, the use of network models has allowed explanations of the spread of diseases from infected people (nodes) and their links with others (edges) [<xref rid="B2-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</p>
              <p>Network models establish the connection between population groups, which is useful not only in the field of public health or epidemiology, but also in engineering and social sciences [<xref rid="B3-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] (see [<xref rid="B4-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="B5-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="B6-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B7-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="B8-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]). In the health field, being a theoretical approach, the importance of recognizing the complexities of community structures has been discussed in order to understand social dynamics in the spread of infectious diseases [<xref rid="B9-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. For example, Magelinski et al. developed a model to estimate the role played by certain nodes in community structures [<xref rid="B10-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], while Ghalmane et al. included the dimension of centrality in complex networks [<xref rid="B11-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p>
              <p>Regarding the COVID-19 pandemic, a series of models have been developed which allow the projection and establishment of the progress of this infectious disease based on the data available from different information sources (see, for instance, [<xref rid="B12-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]). In this sense, Manríquez et al. propose the use of weighted graphs at the edges, giving the network model, from a stochastic approach, the possibility of identifying the most important variables in the spread of COVID-19 with real data in a city in Chile [<xref rid="B13-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. The same authors, in order to classify the importance of the nodes, propose the generalization of the measure of importance of the line with the use of degree of centrality (DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm5"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), improving the understanding of the network from a local perspective [<xref rid="B14-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p>
              <p>On the other hand, the same network models have served to search for protection strategies for populations, generally related to the processes of immunization or isolation of people (see [<xref rid="B15-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="B16-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="B17-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="B18-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="B19-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="B20-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]).</p>
              <p>Scientific evidence supports immunization strategies being useful in both homogeneous and heterogeneous networks [<xref rid="B21-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The strategies seek, first, to develop a dynamic experimental model that includes the classic compartmental systems in epidemiology (SIR, SEIR, SIS, among others) and then to establish immunization measures across the nodes. Immunization measures can be applied in static and dynamic networks, in a random or targeted immunization [<xref rid="B22-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p>
              <p>Random immunization refers to random strategies, without determining a particular population in the protection process [<xref rid="B23-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. In contrast, targeted immunization recognizes nodes with a higher degree of connection with other nodes [<xref rid="B24-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Nian et al. conclude, through computational simulations in a free scale graph (Model BA), that targeted immunization is more effective than randomized [<xref rid="B21-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. In the same direction, Wang et al. conclude that, even if the immunization strategy is imperfect or incomplete, it manages to generate positive impacts on the protection of the network [<xref rid="B25-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Another investigation by Xia et al. determined that targeted immunization in two rounds of selection provides a greater protective effect compared to progressive strategies [<xref rid="B24-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].</p>
              <p>According to the above, a study conducted by Ghalmane et al. proposed an immunization strategy considering the influence of the nodes, the number of communities and the links between them [<xref rid="B26-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Along the same lines, Gupta et al. analyzed the importance of protection strategies using information from community networks [<xref rid="B27-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Since edge-weighted graphs have been an important way of understanding epidemic diseases, Manríquez et al. measure the effectiveness of DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm6"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> with the recognition of bridge nodes. The effectiveness of DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm7"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is high compared to other proposals on four real networks [<xref rid="B28-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].</p>
              <p>For all the above, studies that include immunization measures together with community/local network models are highly relevant for public health, both for establishing measures to mitigate epidemic diseases and for the development of vaccination optimization policies to more quickly achieve herd immunization and, therefore, overcome diseases such as COVID-19. This is supported by Zhao et al., who argue that this framework allows for the optimization of immunization resources [<xref rid="B29-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].</p>
              <p>This study aims to analyze the protection effect against COVID-19 using the DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm8"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> ranking with real data from a city in Chile (Olmué-City), obtained from the Epidemiological Surveillance System of the Ministry of Health of Chile, from which we obtain an edge-weighted graph, denoted by <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm9"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="script">E</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, according to the method proposed in [<xref rid="B13-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. We apply the protection to the <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm10"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="script">E</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> network, according to the importance ranking list produced by DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm11"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, considering different protection budgets. For the ranking DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm12"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, we consider three different values for <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm13"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>; they are 0, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm14"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and 1. In this way, we compare how the protection performs according to the value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm15"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. We use a graph-based SIR model, namely, each individual is represented by a vertex in <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm16"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="script">E</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. At time <italic>t</italic>, each vertex <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm17"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is in a state <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm18"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> belonging to <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm19"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">S</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm20"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm21"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> represent the three discrete states: Susceptible (S), Infected (I) and Recovered or Removed (R). Five hundred simulations were performed on <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm22"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="script">E</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>; the initial population contains one infected node and all the simulations, considering <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm23"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>15</mml:mn></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (recovered rate).</p>
              <p>This paper is organized as follows: <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec2-biology-10-00667">Section 2</xref> contains generalities about graph theory, includes a graph from a database, and the DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm24"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> ranking is explained. In <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec3-biology-10-00667">Section 3</xref>, we obtain the graph from a real database from a city in Chile (Olmué-City), and we set the protection strategy. In <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec4-biology-10-00667">Section 4</xref>, the results of the study are presented. <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec5-biology-10-00667">Section 5</xref> provides a discussion of the results and potentialities of the method used. Finally, <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec6-biology-10-00667">Section 6</xref> provides the conclusions.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec2-biology-10-00667">
              <title>2. Basic Definitions</title>
              <p>In this section, we establish the definitions and elements used throughout this paper. We summarize the symbols and notations in <xref rid="biology-10-00667-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p>
              <sec id="sec2dot1-biology-10-00667">
                <title>2.1. Graphs</title>
                <p>The following definitions come from [<xref rid="B30-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="B31-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>].</p>
                <statement>
                  <label><bold>Definition</bold> <bold>1.</bold></label>
                  <p>
                    <italic>A graph G is a finite nonempty set V of objects called vertices, together with a possibly empty set E of 2-element subsets of V called edges.</italic>
                  </p>
                </statement>
                <p>To indicate that a graph <italic>G</italic> has vertex set <italic>V</italic> and edge set <italic>E</italic>, we write <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm25"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. If the set of vertices is <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm26"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, then the edge between vertex <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm27"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and vertex <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm28"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is denoted by <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm29"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                <p>If <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm30"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is an edge of <italic>G</italic>, then <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm31"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm32"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are adjacent vertices. Two adjacent vertices are referred to as neighbors of each other. The set of neighbors of a vertex <italic>v</italic> is called the open neighborhood of <italic>v</italic> (or simply the neighborhood of <italic>v</italic>) and is denoted by <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm33"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. If <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm34"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm35"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are distinct edges in <italic>G</italic>, then <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm36"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm37"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are adjacent edges.</p>
                <statement>
                  <label><bold>Definition</bold> <bold>2.</bold></label>
                  <p>
                    <italic>The number of vertices in a graph G is the order of G and the number of edges is the size of G.</italic>
                  </p>
                </statement>
                <statement>
                  <label><bold>Definition</bold> <bold>3.</bold></label>
                  <p>
                    <italic>The degree of a vertex v in a graph G, denoted by <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm38"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, is the number of vertices in G that are adjacent to v. Thus, the degree of v is the number of vertices in its neighborhood <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm39"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</italic>
                  </p>
                </statement>
                <statement>
                  <label><bold>Definition</bold> <bold>4.</bold></label>
                  <p>
                    <italic>Let G be a graph of order n, where <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm40"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The adjacency matrix of G is the <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm41"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> zero-one matrix <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm42"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, or simply <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm43"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, where</italic>
                    <disp-formula>
                      <mml:math id="mm44">
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:msub>
                              <mml:mi>a</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                              </mml:mrow>
                            </mml:msub>
                            <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mfenced separators="" open="{" close="">
                              <mml:mtable>
                                <mml:mtr>
                                  <mml:mtd columnalign="left">
                                    <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                                  </mml:mtd>
                                  <mml:mtd columnalign="left">
                                    <mml:mrow>
                                      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                                      <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
                                      <mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/>
                                      <mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/>
                                      <mml:msub>
                                        <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                                        <mml:mrow>
                                          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                                          <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                                        </mml:mrow>
                                      </mml:msub>
                                      <mml:mo>∈</mml:mo>
                                      <mml:mi>E</mml:mi>
                                      <mml:mrow>
                                        <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                                        <mml:mi>G</mml:mi>
                                        <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                                      </mml:mrow>
                                    </mml:mrow>
                                  </mml:mtd>
                                </mml:mtr>
                                <mml:mtr>
                                  <mml:mtd columnalign="left">
                                    <mml:mn>0</mml:mn>
                                  </mml:mtd>
                                  <mml:mtd columnalign="left">
                                    <mml:mrow>
                                      <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                                      <mml:mi>f</mml:mi>
                                      <mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/>
                                      <mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/>
                                      <mml:msub>
                                        <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                                        <mml:mrow>
                                          <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                                          <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                                        </mml:mrow>
                                      </mml:msub>
                                      <mml:mo>∉</mml:mo>
                                      <mml:mi>E</mml:mi>
                                      <mml:mrow>
                                        <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                                        <mml:mi>G</mml:mi>
                                        <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                                      </mml:mrow>
                                      <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
                                    </mml:mrow>
                                  </mml:mtd>
                                </mml:mtr>
                              </mml:mtable>
                            </mml:mfenced>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:math>
                    </disp-formula>
                  </p>
                </statement>
                <p>On the other hand, an important generalization of the simple graph consists of the definition of a weighted graph, more specifically an edge-weighted graph. Informally, an edge-weighted graph is a graph whose edges have been assigned a weight.</p>
                <statement>
                  <label><bold>Definition</bold> <bold>5.</bold></label>
                  <p>
                    <italic>An edge-weighted graph is a pair <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm45"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm46"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is a graph and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm47"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is a weight function. If <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm48"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> then <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm49"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</italic>
                  </p>
                </statement>
                <statement>
                  <label><bold>Definition</bold> <bold>6.</bold></label>
                  <p>
                    <italic>The strength of a vertex <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm50"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, denoted by <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm51"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, is defined as the sum of the weights of all edges incident to it, this is to say,</italic>
                    <disp-formula>
                      <mml:math id="mm52">
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                              <mml:msub>
                                <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                              </mml:msub>
                              <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                            </mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                            <mml:munder>
                              <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:msub>
                                  <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                                  <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                                </mml:msub>
                                <mml:mo>∈</mml:mo>
                                <mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mrow>
                                  <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                                  <mml:msub>
                                    <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                                    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                                  </mml:msub>
                                  <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                                </mml:mrow>
                              </mml:mrow>
                            </mml:munder>
                            <mml:msub>
                              <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                              </mml:mrow>
                            </mml:msub>
                            <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:math>
                    </disp-formula>
                  </p>
                </statement>
                <p>The following definition comes from [<xref rid="B32-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].</p>
                <statement>
                  <label><bold>Definition</bold> <bold>7</bold></label>
                  <p>(Degree centrality [<xref rid="B32-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>])<bold>.</bold>
<italic>The degree centrality of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm53"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> of an edge-weighted graph <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm54"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, denoted by <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm55"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, is defined as</italic>
<disp-formula id="FD1-biology-10-00667"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="mm56"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<italic>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm57"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</italic></p>
                </statement>
                <p>The parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm58"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is called the <italic>tuning parameter</italic>. Notice that, when <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm59"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, then <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm60"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and, when <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm61"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, then <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm62"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2dot2-biology-10-00667">
                <title>2.2. DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm63"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> Ranking</title>
                <p>We briefly describe the DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm64"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> ranking in this Section. The DIL ranking is a tool for evaluating the node importance based on degree and the importance of lines (DIL) proposed by Liu et al. in [<xref rid="B33-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] for an undirected and unweighted network. Recently, Manríquez et al. in [<xref rid="B14-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] propose DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm65"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> rank. This ranking method of node importance for undirected and edge-weighted is a generalization of the measure of line importance (DIL) based on the centrality degree (Definition 7) proposed by Opsahl in [<xref rid="B32-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].</p>
                <p>The following comes from [<xref rid="B14-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p>
                <p>Let us consider an undirected weighted graph <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm66"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> with <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm67"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm68"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                <statement>
                  <label><bold>Definition</bold> <bold>8</bold></label>
                  <p>(Importance edge [<xref rid="B14-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>])<bold>.</bold>
<italic>The importance of an edge <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm69"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, denoted by <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm70"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, is defined as</italic>
<disp-formula><mml:math id="mm71"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<italic>where, for <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm72"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm73"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> with p being the number of triangles, one edge of the triangle is <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm74"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm75"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the weight of the sum of the edges incident to <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm76"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> that form a triangle with <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm77"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm78"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfenced><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</italic></p>
                </statement>
                <p>In order to illustrate the above Definition, let us consider the edge-weighted graph in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="biology-10-00667-f001">Figure 1</xref>. Moreover, we consider the edges <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm79"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mn>78</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm80"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mn>75</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Notice that they both have the same weight (three). For this example, we set <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm81"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Applying Definition 7, we get:<disp-formula><mml:math id="mm82"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mn>12</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>12</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="1.em"/><mml:mi>and</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mn>8</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>8</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p>
                <p>From Definition 8:<disp-formula><mml:math id="mm83"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1.em"/><mml:mi>and</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:msup><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mfenced><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p>
                <p>Therefore,
<disp-formula><mml:math id="mm84"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mn>75</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mfenced separators="" open="(" close=")"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mspace width="1.em"/></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>12</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>8</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>28</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p>
                <p>In the same way with the edge <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm85"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mn>78</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, we obtain
<disp-formula><mml:math id="mm86"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mn>78</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>96</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p>
                <p>In conclusion, edge <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm87"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mn>68</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is more important than edge <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm88"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mn>75</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                <p>The latter is reasonable because the edge <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm89"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mn>78</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is a bridging edge of the graph.</p>
                <statement>
                  <label><bold>Definition</bold> <bold>9</bold></label>
                  <p>(Contribution [<xref rid="B14-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>])<bold>.</bold>
<italic>The contribution that <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm90"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> makes to the importance of the edge <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm91"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, denoted by <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm92"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, is defined as</italic>
<disp-formula><mml:math id="mm93"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<italic>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm94"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the weight of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm95"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</italic></p>
                </statement>
                <p>We have calculated the importance of the edge <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm96"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mn>78</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> of the graph in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="biology-10-00667-f001">Figure 1</xref>. The contribution that <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm97"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> makes to it is given by Definition 9:<disp-formula><mml:math id="mm98"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mn>78</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mn>78</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>78</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>78</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mspace width="1.em"/></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>96</mml:mn><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>8</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mspace width="1.em"/></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>432</mml:mn><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p>
                <p>In the same way, the contribution that <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm99"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> makes to <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm100"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mn>78</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is:<disp-formula><mml:math id="mm101"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mn>87</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mn>78</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>78</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>78</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mspace width="1.em"/></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>96</mml:mn><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>8</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>8</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mspace width="1.em"/></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>240</mml:mn><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p>
                <p>The above means that the node <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm102"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> contributes more to the edge <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm103"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mn>78</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> than node <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm104"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                <statement>
                  <label><bold>Definition</bold> <bold>10</bold></label>
                  <p>(Importance of vertex DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm105"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> [<xref rid="B14-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>])<bold>.</bold>
<italic>The importance of a vertex <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm106"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, denoted by <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm107"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, is defined as</italic>
<disp-formula><mml:math id="mm108"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msup><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p>
                </statement>
                <statement>
                  <label><bold>Remark</bold> <bold>1.</bold></label>
                  <p><italic>From the definition of Degree centrality (Definition 7) proposed by Opsahl in [<xref rid="B32-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], we can see that, when the tuning parameter α is</italic> 0<italic>, the Definitions 8–10 are the same than the proposed by Liu et al.</italic></p>
                </statement>
                <p>In order to illustrate the above Definition, we compute the importance of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm109"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm110"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in the graph of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="biology-10-00667-f001">Figure 1</xref>.
<disp-formula><mml:math id="mm111"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msup><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>7</mml:mn><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mn>71</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mn>72</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mn>73</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mn>74</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mn>75</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mn>78</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>12</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>12</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>12</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>24</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>75</mml:mn><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>18</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>432</mml:mn><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>78</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>507</mml:mn><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1053</mml:mn><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
and
<disp-formula><mml:math id="mm112"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msup><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>8</mml:mn><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>8</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mn>87</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>8</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>8</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>240</mml:mn><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>136</mml:mn><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>8</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>2152</mml:mn><mml:mn>35</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>2432</mml:mn><mml:mn>35</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p>
                <p>Since <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm113"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, then node <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm114"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is more important than node <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm115"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (according to DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm116"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> ranking).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2dot3-biology-10-00667">
                <title>2.3. Graph from a Database</title>
                <p>The authors of [<xref rid="B13-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] provide a way to obtain an edge-weighted graph from a database, which we briefly detail.</p>
                <p>Let <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm117"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced separators="" open="{" close="}"><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> be a set of people registered in a database, denoted by <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm118"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, with <italic>K</italic> different variables, denoted by <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm119"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. These variables are separated into two categories: the characteristic variables (CHAR) and the relationship variables (REL) (which are those that allow us to assume that some person meets another). Let us denote by <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm120"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the number of relationship variables and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm121"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the response of the person <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm122"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to the variable <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm123"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                <statement>
                  <label><bold>Definition</bold> <bold>11.</bold></label>
                  <p><italic>We will say that a person <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm124"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is related to a person <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm125"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> if and only if there exists <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm126"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm127"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> such that <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm128"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm129"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>≠</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></italic>.</p>
                </statement>
                <p>To define the weight of each link between two persons, we assume that each <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm130"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> has an associated inherent weight, this is to say, it is possible to discriminate some hierarchical order between the variables. Let <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm131"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> be the weight associated to the variable <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm132"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm133"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                <statement>
                  <label><bold>Definition</bold> <bold>12.</bold></label>
                  <p>
                    <italic>We will say that for <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm134"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm135"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is related to <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm136"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, denoted by <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm137"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, if and only if <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm138"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</italic>
                  </p>
                </statement>
                <statement>
                  <label><bold>Definition</bold> <bold>13.</bold></label>
                  <p>
                    <italic>Let <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm139"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> be the different classes that are defined by the different weights <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm140"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm141"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and its respective cardinalities. Hence,</italic>
                    <disp-formula id="FD2-biology-10-00667">
                      <label>(2)</label>
                      <mml:math id="mm142">
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:msub>
                              <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                            </mml:msub>
                            <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mfrac>
                              <mml:msub>
                                <mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                              </mml:msub>
                              <mml:msub>
                                <mml:mi>K</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                              </mml:msub>
                            </mml:mfrac>
                            <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:math>
                    </disp-formula>
                    <italic>for all <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm143"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</italic>
                  </p>
                </statement>
                <p>We denoted by <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm144"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the number of times that one person is related to another (or the number of variables that matches between them).</p>
                <statement>
                  <label><bold>Definition</bold> <bold>14.</bold></label>
                  <p>
                    <italic>Let <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm145"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> be such that <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm146"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is related to <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm147"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm148"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the weight of the variable in which <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm149"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm150"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> match, for <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm151"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. We will say that</italic>
                    <disp-formula id="FD3-biology-10-00667">
                      <label>(3)</label>
                      <mml:math id="mm152">
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:msub>
                              <mml:mover accent="true">
                                <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mo>˜</mml:mo>
                              </mml:mover>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                              </mml:mrow>
                            </mml:msub>
                            <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                            <mml:munderover>
                              <mml:mo>∑</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                                <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                              </mml:mrow>
                              <mml:msub>
                                <mml:mi>h</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mrow>
                                  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                                  <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                                  <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                                </mml:mrow>
                              </mml:msub>
                            </mml:munderover>
                            <mml:msub>
                              <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
                              <mml:msub>
                                <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mi>r</mml:mi>
                              </mml:msub>
                            </mml:msub>
                            <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:math>
                    </disp-formula>
                    <italic>is the weight of the link between <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm153"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm154"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</italic>
                  </p>
                </statement>
                <p>Finally, the weighted adjacency matrix, which defines the graph obtained from the database, is the <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm155"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> matrix <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm156"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, where
<disp-formula><mml:math id="mm157"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced separators="" open="{" close=""><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mo>˜</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>if</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>if</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>∉</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p>
                <statement>
                  <label><bold>Example</bold> <bold>1.</bold></label>
                  <p>
                    <italic>In the following example, <xref rid="biology-10-00667-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> simulates a database with 20 registered people. The data hosted correspond to the city in which they live (City), the workplace (considering school and university as a workplace), gender (Gen.), age, extracurricular activity (EC activity), address, whether they drink alcohol (Drin.), whether they are smokers (Sm.) and marital status (MS). Let us consider A and B as two different cities, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm158"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>z</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and h as different people’s addresses. Moreover, in the table, Y = Yes, N = No, IC = in couple, M = married, S = single, W = widower.</italic>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                    <italic>From <xref rid="biology-10-00667-t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, we have that <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm159"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>9</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm160"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> City, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm161"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> Workplace, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm162"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> E.P. activity, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm163"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> Address, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm164"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> Sm., <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm165"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> Dri., <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm166"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> Gen., <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm167"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> M.S. and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm168"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>9</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> Age. Then, we obtain the sets:</italic>
                    <list list-type="simple">
                      <list-item>
                        <label><italic>1.</italic> </label>
                        <p>
                          <italic>
                            <inline-formula>
                              <mml:math id="mm169">
                                <mml:mrow>
                                  <mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true">
                                    <mml:mrow>
                                      <mml:mi>R</mml:mi>
                                      <mml:mi>E</mml:mi>
                                      <mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
                                      <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                                      <mml:mo>{</mml:mo>
                                      <mml:msub>
                                        <mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi>
                                        <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                                      </mml:msub>
                                      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                                      <mml:msub>
                                        <mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi>
                                        <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
                                      </mml:msub>
                                      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                                      <mml:msub>
                                        <mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi>
                                        <mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
                                      </mml:msub>
                                      <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                                      <mml:msub>
                                        <mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi>
                                        <mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
                                      </mml:msub>
                                      <mml:mo>}</mml:mo>
                                    </mml:mrow>
                                  </mml:mstyle>
                                </mml:mrow>
                              </mml:math>
                            </inline-formula>
                          </italic>
                          <italic>and</italic>
                        </p>
                      </list-item>
                      <list-item>
                        <label><italic>2.</italic> </label>
                        <p><italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="mm170"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>9</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></italic>.</p>
                      </list-item>
                    </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                    <italic>In our criteria, the hierarchical order of the variables <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm171"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in descending form is <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm172"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm173"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Moreover, we consider that the variables <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm174"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm175"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> have the same weight. Hence, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm176"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm177"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm178"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are the different classes that are defined by the different weights. Hence, by Definition 13</italic>
                    <disp-formula>
                      <mml:math id="mm179">
                        <mml:mrow>
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:msub>
                              <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                            </mml:msub>
                            <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mfrac>
                              <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                              <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
                            </mml:mfrac>
                            <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mspace width="1.em"/>
                            <mml:msub>
                              <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mn>2</mml:mn>
                            </mml:msub>
                            <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mfrac>
                              <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                              <mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
                            </mml:mfrac>
                            <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mspace width="1.em"/>
                            <mml:msub>
                              <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mn>3</mml:mn>
                            </mml:msub>
                            <mml:mo>=</mml:mo>
                            <mml:mfrac>
                              <mml:mn>1</mml:mn>
                              <mml:mn>4</mml:mn>
                            </mml:mfrac>
                            <mml:mo>.</mml:mo>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:mrow>
                      </mml:math>
                    </disp-formula>
                  </p>
                  <p><italic>To construct the graph, we must resort to Definition 11. For instance, person</italic> 17 <italic>is related to all the people who live in city A or who work at Workplace 8 or who have music as an extra curricular activity or whose address is k. With respect to the weights of the edges, Equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD6-biology-10-00667">6</xref>) in Definition 14 gives us the answer. For instance, person 6 matches person</italic> 11 <italic>in the answers of the variables <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm180"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm181"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, this is to say, both people live in city A and have the same workplace. Then, the edge <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm182"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> has weight <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm183"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>6</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.277778em"/><mml:mn>11</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.25</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.75</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="biology-10-00667-f002">Figure 2</xref> shows the obtained graph.</italic></p>
                </statement>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec3-biology-10-00667">
              <title>3. Method</title>
              <p>The data that are modeled correspond to the city of Olmué (Valparaíso region, Chile) and were obtained from the database of the Epidemiological Surveillance System of the Ministry of Health of Chile, which included the notified cases (positive or negative) and their contacts from 3 March 2020 to 15 January 2021 with a total of 3866 registered persons.</p>
              <p>We denote by <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm184"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">E</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the database of the Epidemiological Surveillance System of the Ministry of Health of Chile. From the total of variables included in <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm185"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">E</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm186"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>279</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) 7 of them are relationship variables (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm187"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). They are: full address (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm188"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>); the street where the people live (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm189"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>); town (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm190"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>); place of work (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm191"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>); workplace section (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm192"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>); health facility where they were treated (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm193"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) and the region of the country where the test was taken to confirm, or not, the contagion (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm194"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>).</p>
              <p>In our criteria, the hierarchical order of the seven variables in descending form is <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm195"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Moreover, we consider that the variables <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm196"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm197"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> have the same weight. In the same way, we also consider the variables <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm198"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm199"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> with equal weight. Hence, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm200"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm201"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm202"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm203"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are the different classes that are defined by the different weights. Hence, by Definition 13.
<disp-formula><mml:math id="mm204"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1.em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1.em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1.em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p>
              <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="biology-10-00667-f003">Figure 3</xref> shows the obtained graph.</p>
              <p>Let us denote by <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm205"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="script">E</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the graph obtained from database <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm206"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">E</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
              <sec>
                <title>Strategy Protection</title>
                <p>In this section, we provide definitions of the protection of a graph when disease spreads on it. Moreover, we state the protection strategy used in the graph <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm207"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="script">E</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> obtained in the previous Section. The following definitions come from [<xref rid="B28-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].</p>
                <statement>
                  <label><bold>Definition</bold> <bold>15.</bold></label>
                  <p>
                    <italic>Protecting a vertex means removing all of its corresponding edges. (See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="biology-10-00667-f004">Figure 4</xref>).</italic>
                  </p>
                </statement>
                <p>It is also possible to find in the literature that protecting a vertex means removing the vertex from the graph. See, for instance, [<xref rid="B20-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].</p>
                <statement>
                  <label><bold>Definition</bold> <bold>16.</bold></label>
                  <p>
                    <italic>The number of vertices that are allowed to protect is called the protection budget, denoted by k.</italic>
                  </p>
                </statement>
                <statement>
                  <label><bold>Definition</bold> <bold>17.</bold></label>
                  <p>
                    <italic>We will say that the survival rate, denoted by σ, is the ratio of vertices that remain uninfected at the end of the disease over the total numbers of vertices.</italic>
                  </p>
                </statement>
                <p>Therefore, our problem is: given a graph <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm208"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, SIR model, and a protection budget <italic>k</italic>, the goal is to find a set of vertices <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm209"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">S</mml:mi><mml:mo>⊆</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, such that
<disp-formula id="FD4-biology-10-00667"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="mm210"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:msup><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo form="prefix">arg</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo movablelimits="true" form="prefix">max</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">S</mml:mi><mml:mo>⊆</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
with <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm211"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">S</mml:mi><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. However, the problem (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD4-biology-10-00667">4</xref>) is NP-Hard (see [<xref rid="B34-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]).</p>
                <p>Our chosen protection strategy corresponds to the DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm212"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> ranking (see [<xref rid="B14-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]). It is well known that an index to measure the connection of a graph is the efficiency of the networks (see [<xref rid="B35-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]). High connectivity of the graph indicates high efficiency. In [<xref rid="B14-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], the authors show that the DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm213"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> ranking provides good results regarding the rate of decline in network efficiency (for more detail see [<xref rid="B36-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]), when it comes to eliminating the best positioned nodes by this ranking. One of the good qualities of the DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm214"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> ranking is that it recognizes the importance of bridge nodes (see more in [<xref rid="B37-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]). This quality is inherited from the version of the DIL ranking for graphs not weighted at the edges (see [<xref rid="B33-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]). Furthermore, [<xref rid="B28-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] evaluated the effectiveness of the DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm215"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> ranking in the immunization of nodes that are attacked by an infectious disease that spreads on an edge-weighted graph using a graph-based SIR model.</p>
                <p>Finally, in order to illustrate in a simple way why the DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm216"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> ranking has been chosen, let us consider the graph of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="biology-10-00667-f005">Figure 5</xref> with 16 edges, 15 nodes, and the respective weights on the edges. When we apply the DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm217"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> ranking, the first 3 places are occupied by nodes 3, 5 and 1, respectively. These nodes are precise bridge nodes and, when protecting them, according to Definition 15, the graph loses connectivity (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="biology-10-00667-f006">Figure 6</xref>). If we apply the Strength ranking, the first three places are occupied by nodes 3, 1 and 4, respectively. Note that the order in which it positions the nodes and the importance it gives to node 4 makes the loss of network connectivity lower than the loss when applying DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm218"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="biology-10-00667-f006">Figure 6</xref>).</p>
                <p>In summary, we apply the protection to the <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm219"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="script">E</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> network, according to the importance ranking list produced by DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm220"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, considering different protection budgets. For the ranking DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm221"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, we consider three different values for <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm222"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>; they are 0, <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm223"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and 1. In this way, we compare how the protection performs according to the value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm224"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results" id="sec4-biology-10-00667">
              <title>4. Results</title>
              <p>In this paper, we use a graph-based SIR model in the same way as in [<xref rid="B13-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="B28-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], namely, each individual is represented by a vertex in <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm225"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="script">E</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. At time <italic>t</italic>, each vertex <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm226"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is in a state <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm227"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> belonging to <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm228"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">S</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm229"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm230"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> represent the three discrete states: Susceptible (S), Infected (I) and Recovered or Removed (R). We set
<disp-formula id="FD5-biology-10-00667"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="mm231"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced separators="" open="{" close="}"><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p>
              <p>At time <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm232"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, the vertex <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm233"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> will change state according to probabilistic rules:<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>The probability (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm234"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) that a susceptible vertex <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm235"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is infected by one of its neighbors is given by
<disp-formula id="FD6-biology-10-00667"><label>(6)</label><mml:math id="mm236"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm237"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is a purely biological factor and representative of the disease and <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm238"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the weight of the edge <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm239"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The probability (<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm240"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) that an infected vertex <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm241"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> at time <italic>t</italic> will recover is given by
<disp-formula id="FD7-biology-10-00667"><label>(7)</label><mml:math id="mm242"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="sans-serif">Δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
where <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm243"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the recovery rate.</p></list-item></list></p>
              <p>Moreover, we assume that the disease is present for a certain period of time and that, when individuals recover, they are immune, that is, reinfection is not considered.</p>
              <p>The initial population contains one infected node and all the simulations that consider <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm244"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle scriptlevel="0" displaystyle="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>15</mml:mn></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Five hundred simulations were performed on <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm245"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="script">E</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> with <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm246"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.00121</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="biology-10-00667-f007">Figure 7</xref> shows the average infected curve and the real infected data in <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm247"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">E</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Moreover, it shows a curve fitted to the data following the SIR model; for this, we used the classic method of least squares to compare with our proposal.</p>
              <p>The graph <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm248"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="script">E</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> was protected with different protection budgets according to the importance of the DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm249"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm250"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm251"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> rankings. Protection is carried out in week 1, this is to say, at the beginning of the spread of the disease. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="biology-10-00667-f008">Figure 8</xref> shows the results.</p>
              <p>We can see the survival rate in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="biology-10-00667-f009">Figure 9</xref>.</p>
              <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="biology-10-00667-f010">Figure 10</xref> shows the relationship between the real infected (450 people) and those immunized according to our proposal.</p>
              <p>We can see that 80% of the real infected are located in 60% of the top ranked according to DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm252"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. We think that this is a way to recognize those who will get sick; however, it is not the solution.</p>
              <p>Another element that we have considered investigating is the time at which the protection takes place. We modified the protection in the graph as the weeks advanced. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="biology-10-00667-f011">Figure 11</xref>, we can see the different infected curves, considering the 10% protection according to the DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm253"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> ranking.</p>
              <p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="biology-10-00667-f012">Figure 12</xref> shows the relationship between the survival rate and the week in which the protection is carried out with our proposal.</p>
              <p>The survival rate is clearly decreasing.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec5-biology-10-00667">
              <title>5. Discussion</title>
              <p>The results of the present investigation are directed towards the analysis of the effectiveness of immunization using the DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm254"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> ranking with real COVID-19 data from the city of Olmué-in Chile. Depending on the importance of the rankings, the immunization results were similar, despite the percentage of protection proposed in the simulations. Our method, therefore, goes in the direction of finding new optimization algorithms in network protection strategies [<xref rid="B38-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>].</p>
              <p>At the level of protection, it is evident that when the percentage of initial coverage is higher, the epidemic ends with a smaller fraction of people affected by COVID-19. This event is related not only to the random increase in immunization, but also to the possibility, in the model, of recognizing the bridge nodes to increase the effectiveness of vaccination. This is consistent with other investigations that indicate that the recognition of central nodes or high-risk individuals improves the efficiency of immunization strategies in real networks, a situation that favors the protection of the network and the best use of vaccine doses [<xref rid="B39-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="B40-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. The best use of doses is a challenge for the current scenario of vaccine shortages worldwide, mainly in poor nations [<xref rid="B41-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>].</p>
              <p>On the other hand, the level of effectiveness of the DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm255"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> ranking, given the percentage of protection, is established in the recognition of the bridging nodes in a regular vaccination process. The results using the <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm256"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> parameters of DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm257"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> indicate a high survival rate. DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm258"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> achieves better results with 70% protection and is positioned with the best survival rate, but DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm259"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm260"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> show good results. The difference between the different values of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm261"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is marginal and can be explained by the adequate representation that the DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm262"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> model has and by the values of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm263"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, which do not generate excessive differences in the ranking. This is similar to the results of the research by Ophsal et al. who, through Freeman’s EIES network, mention that the centrality degree (Definition 7) is relatively stable among the different <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm264"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> parameters [<xref rid="B32-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].</p>
              <p>In a real and regular immunization strategy situation, such as the administration of vaccines, determining the population that infects most frequently is relevant since it allows optimization of these processes. Among our findings, it stands out that 80% of the real infected in the Olmué-Chile commune were located in 60% of the top of the DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm265"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> ranking. Consequently, our proposal recognizes the heterogeneity of the network, approaching the reality of human interactions and achieving similar results in complex homogeneous networks [<xref rid="B40-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>].</p>
              <p>Regarding immunization with 10% protection, a decrease in the survival rate is established by 4% from weeks 5 to 45 of protection. Likewise, with the same percentage of protection, the effectiveness of the immunity strategy tends to be important until week 20. After 20 weeks, the fraction of infected is similar with or without protection. Consequently, our model is strongly effective as a measure of rapid recognition of the epidemic outbreak in a given territory.</p>
              <p>Therefore, according to the findings of our research, there are two important variables for the success and effectiveness of immunity strategies against COVID-19: (1) Recognition of bridging nodes (people with the highest probability of contagion) to apply measures of protection; and (2) the development time of this strategy.</p>
              <p>Regarding the recognition of bridging nodes, there is evidence to support that targeted immunization schemes significantly reduce epidemic outbreaks [<xref rid="B42-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. This opens the possibility of changing the traditional perspective of immunization by protecting a small proportion of the population over a long period of time [<xref rid="B43-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. It is important, therefore, not only to direct COVID-19 immunity efforts towards the population most affected by mortality, but also in those population groups that tend to infect with greater force.</p>
              <p>The time of development of the immunization strategy continues to be a variable under discussion in the scientific community regarding the slowness worldwide of the vaccination process, which risks not achieving herd immunity [<xref rid="B44-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. In summary, both at a theoretical and empirical level, the execution time of immunization strategies is important in overcoming the COVID-19 pandemic.</p>
              <p>Finally, our model helps to establish a ranking of bridge nodes in a non-homogeneous network, so it is highly replicable with real COVID-19 dissemination data and it is useful to establish more focused strategies given the reduced number of vaccines available.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec6-biology-10-00667">
              <title>6. Conclusions</title>
              <p>In this paper, we evaluate the effectiveness of the DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm266"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> ranking in the immunization of nodes that are attacked by an infectious disease (COVID-19) that spreads on an edge-weighted graph obtained from the database of the Epidemiological Surveillance System of the Chilean Ministry of Health, using a graph-based SIR model.</p>
              <p>Considering survival rates, the DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm267"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> ranking performs better (by a small margin) than DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm268"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm269"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> rankings, subject to the protection budget being equal to 10% of the network nodes.</p>
              <p>The period in which immunization or protection is given plays a key role in stopping the spread of the disease (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="biology-10-00667-f011">Figure 11</xref>) since around week 25 immunization does not generate a great impact and as time progresses the survival rate decreases almost linearly.</p>
              <p>An interesting and complex task to solve is to determine which value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm270"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to choose in the network so that the ranking generated is the optimal one. The same value does not always make the performance the best. One way to explore this is to continue with the ideas proposed in [<xref rid="B45-biology-10-00667" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], where the selection standard of the optimal turning parameters is proposed for the centrality degree, but is not for DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm271"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> ranking. However, when considering this method, there are as many rankings as there are numbers between 0 and 1.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <fn-group>
              <fn>
                <p><bold>Publisher’s Note:</bold> MDPI stays neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <notes>
              <title>Author Contributions</title>
              <p>The authors R.M., C.G.-N. and C.T. contributed equally to this work. All authors have read and agreed to the published version of the manuscript.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes>
              <title>Funding</title>
              <p>This work was supported and funded by Agencia Nacional de Investigación y Desarrollo (ANID), COVID0739 project.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes>
              <title>Institutional Review Board Statement</title>
              <p>Not applicable.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes>
              <title>Informed Consent Statement</title>
              <p>Not applicable.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="data-availability">
              <title>Data Availability Statement</title>
              <p>The data presented in this study were available after being requested by research project COVID-ANID to the Chilean Ministry of Health. The data are not publicly available due to legal restrictions. The source codes are accessible through the Github link: <uri xlink:href="https://github.com/RonaldManriquez/Prot-stra-aga-epi-ewgraphs.git">https://github.com/RonaldManriquez/Prot-stra-aga-epi-ewgraphs.git</uri>, from 8 June 2021.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="COI-statement">
              <title>Conflicts of Interest</title>
              <p>The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest. The funders had no role in the design of the study; in the collection, analysis, or interpretation of data; in the writing of the manuscript, or in the decision to publish the results.</p>
            </notes>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="B1-biology-10-00667">
                <label>1.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <article-title>Epidemiology is a science of high importance</article-title>
                  <source>Nat. Commun.</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <fpage>1703</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-04243-3</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29736003</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B2-biology-10-00667">
                <label>2.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lloyd</surname>
                      <given-names>A.L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Valeika</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Network models in epidemiology: An overview</article-title>
                  <source>Complex Population Dynamics: Nonlinear Modeling in Ecology, Epidemiology and Genetics</source>
                  <publisher-name>World Scientific</publisher-name>
                  <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <fpage>189</fpage>
                  <lpage>214</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B3-biology-10-00667">
                <label>3.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Haslbeck</surname>
                      <given-names>J.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Waldorp</surname>
                      <given-names>L.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>How well do network models predict observations? On the importance of predictability in network models</article-title>
                  <source>Behav. Res. Methods</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>50</volume>
                  <fpage>853</fpage>
                  <lpage>861</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3758/s13428-017-0910-x</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 28718088?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28718088</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B4-biology-10-00667">
                <label>4.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>An</surname>
                      <given-names>X.L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>J.G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Synchronization analysis of complex networks with multi-weights and its application in public traffic network</article-title>
                  <source>Phys. A Stat. Mech. Appl.</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>412</volume>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                  <lpage>156</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.physa.2014.06.033</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B5-biology-10-00667">
                <label>5.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Montenegro</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cabrera</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>González</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Manríquez</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Linear representation of a graph</article-title>
                  <source>Bol. Soc. Parana. MatemÁTica</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>37</volume>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <lpage>102</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5269/bspm.v37i4.32949</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B6-biology-10-00667">
                <label>6.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cao</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bao</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Han</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A novel local-world evolving network model for power grid</article-title>
                  <source>Acta Phys. Sin.</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <fpage>58</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B7-biology-10-00667">
                <label>7.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mersch</surname>
                      <given-names>D.P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Crespi</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Keller</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Tracking individuals shows spatial fidelity is a key regulator of ant social organization</article-title>
                  <source>Science</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>340</volume>
                  <fpage>1090</fpage>
                  <lpage>1093</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1234316</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 23599264?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23599264</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B8-biology-10-00667">
                <label>8.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Firth</surname>
                      <given-names>J.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sheldon</surname>
                      <given-names>B.C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Experimental manipulation of avian social structure reveals segregation is carried over across contexts</article-title>
                  <source>Proc. R. Soc. B Biol. Sci.</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>282</volume>
                  <fpage>20142350</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2014.2350</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B9-biology-10-00667">
                <label>9.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>How community structure influences epidemic spread in social networks</article-title>
                  <source>Phys. A Stat. Mech. Appl.</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>387</volume>
                  <fpage>623</fpage>
                  <lpage>630</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.physa.2007.09.039</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B10-biology-10-00667">
                <label>10.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Magelinski</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bartulovic</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Carley</surname>
                      <given-names>K.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Measuring Node Contribution to Community Structure With Modularity Vitality</article-title>
                  <source>IEEE Trans. Netw. Sci. Eng.</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <fpage>707</fpage>
                  <lpage>723</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TNSE.2020.3049068</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B11-biology-10-00667">
                <label>11.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ghalmane</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cherifi</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cherifi</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>El Hassouni</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Centrality in complex networks with overlapping community structure</article-title>
                  <source>Sci. Rep.</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>29</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-46507-y</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30626917</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B12-biology-10-00667">
                <label>12.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Guerrero-Nancuante</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Manríquez P</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An epidemiological forecast of COVID-19 in Chile based on the generalized SEIR model and the concept of recovered</article-title>
                  <source>Medwave</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>20</volume>
                  <fpage>e7898</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5867/medwave.2020.04.7898</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32469853</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B13-biology-10-00667">
                <label>13.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Manríquez</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Guerrero-Nancuante</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Martínez</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Taramasco</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Spread of Epidemic Disease on Edge-Weighted Graphs from a Database: A Case Study of COVID-19</article-title>
                  <source>Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>18</volume>
                  <elocation-id>4432</elocation-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph18094432</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33921934</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B14-biology-10-00667">
                <label>14.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Manríquez</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Guerrero-Nancuante</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Martínez</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Taramasco</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A generalization of the importance of vertices for an undirected weighted graph</article-title>
                  <source>Symmetry</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <elocation-id>902</elocation-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/sym13050902</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B15-biology-10-00667">
                <label>15.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tang</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Song</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ding</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ma</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dong</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huang</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Research on the node importance of a weighted network based on the k-order propagation number algorithm</article-title>
                  <source>Entropy</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>22</volume>
                  <elocation-id>364</elocation-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/e22030364</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B16-biology-10-00667">
                <label>16.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fu</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Song</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Drimux: Dynamic rumor influence minimization with user experience in social networks</article-title>
                  <source>IEEE Trans. Knowl. Data Eng.</source>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <volume>29</volume>
                  <fpage>2168</fpage>
                  <lpage>2181</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TKDE.2017.2728064</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B17-biology-10-00667">
                <label>17.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="confproc">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Prakash</surname>
                      <given-names>B.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Dava: Distributing vaccines over networks under prior information</article-title>
                  <source>Proceedings of the 2014 SIAM International Conference on Data Mining</source>
                  <conf-loc>Philadelphia, PA, USA</conf-loc>
                  <conf-date>24–26 April 2014</conf-date>
                  <publisher-name>SIAM</publisher-name>
                  <publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA, USA</publisher-loc>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <fpage>46</fpage>
                  <lpage>54</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B18-biology-10-00667">
                <label>18.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hébert-Dufresne</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Allard</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Young</surname>
                      <given-names>J.G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dubé</surname>
                      <given-names>L.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Global efficiency of local immunization on complex networks</article-title>
                  <source>Sci. Rep.</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>3</volume>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>8</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep02171</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 23842121?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23842121</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B19-biology-10-00667">
                <label>19.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wijayanto</surname>
                      <given-names>A.W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Murata</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effective and scalable methods for graph protection strategies against epidemics on dynamic networks</article-title>
                  <source>Appl. Netw. Sci.</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>4</volume>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>31</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s41109-019-0122-7</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B20-biology-10-00667">
                <label>20.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="confproc">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tong</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Prakash</surname>
                      <given-names>B.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tsourakakis</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eliassi-Rad</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Faloutsos</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chau</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>On the Vulnerability of Large Graphs</article-title>
                  <source>Proceedings of the 2010 IEEE International Conference on Data Mining</source>
                  <conf-loc>Sydney, NSW, Australia</conf-loc>
                  <conf-date>13–17 December 2010</conf-date>
                  <fpage>1091</fpage>
                  <lpage>1096</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/ICDM.2010.54</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B21-biology-10-00667">
                <label>21.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nian</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hu</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yao</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An immunization based on node activity</article-title>
                  <source>Chaos Solitons Fractals</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>107</volume>
                  <fpage>228</fpage>
                  <lpage>233</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chaos.2018.01.013</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B22-biology-10-00667">
                <label>22.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gómez-Gardenes</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Echenique</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Moreno</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Immunization of real complex communication networks</article-title>
                  <source>Eur. Phys. J. Condens. Matter Complex Syst.</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>49</volume>
                  <fpage>259</fpage>
                  <lpage>264</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1140/epjb/e2006-00041-1</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B23-biology-10-00667">
                <label>23.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cohen</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Havlin</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ben-Avraham</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Efficient immunization strategies for computer networks and populations</article-title>
                  <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>91</volume>
                  <fpage>247901</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevLett.91.247901</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14683159</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B24-biology-10-00667">
                <label>24.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xia</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Song</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>C.C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jiang</surname>
                      <given-names>G.P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Improved targeted immunization strategies based on two rounds of selection</article-title>
                  <source>Phys. A Stat. Mech. Appl.</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>496</volume>
                  <fpage>540</fpage>
                  <lpage>547</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.physa.2017.12.017</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B25-biology-10-00667">
                <label>25.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xiao</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hu</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cheng</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Imperfect targeted immunization in scale-free networks</article-title>
                  <source>Phys. A Stat. Mech. Appl.</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>388</volume>
                  <fpage>2535</fpage>
                  <lpage>2546</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.physa.2009.02.036</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B26-biology-10-00667">
                <label>26.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ghalmane</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>El Hassouni</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cherifi</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Immunization of networks with non-overlapping community structure</article-title>
                  <source>Soc. Netw. Anal. Min.</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>22</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13278-019-0591-9</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B27-biology-10-00667">
                <label>27.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="confproc">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gupta</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Singh</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cherifi</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Community-based immunization strategies for epidemic control</article-title>
                  <source>Proceedings of the 2015 7th International Conference on Communication Systems and Networks (COMSNETS)</source>
                  <conf-loc>Bangalore, India</conf-loc>
                  <conf-date>6–10 January 2015</conf-date>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>6</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B28-biology-10-00667">
                <label>28.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Manríquez</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Guerrero-Nancuante</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Taramasco</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Protection Strategy for Edge-Weighted Graphs in Disease Spread</article-title>
                  <source>Appl. Sci.</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>11</volume>
                  <elocation-id>5115</elocation-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/app11115115</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B29-biology-10-00667">
                <label>29.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhao</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gao</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Immunization of epidemics in multiplex networks</article-title>
                  <source>PLoS ONE</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <elocation-id>e112018</elocation-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0112018</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 25401755?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25401755</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B30-biology-10-00667">
                <label>30.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chartrand</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lesniak</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Graphs and Digraphs</source>
                  <edition>1st ed.</edition>
                  <publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name>
                  <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>
                  <year>1996</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B31-biology-10-00667">
                <label>31.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>West</surname>
                      <given-names>D.B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Introduction to Graph Theory</source>
                  <edition>2nd ed.</edition>
                  <publisher-name>Prentice Hall</publisher-name>
                  <publisher-loc>Englewood Cliffs, NJ, USA</publisher-loc>
                  <year>2001</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B32-biology-10-00667">
                <label>32.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Opsahl</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Agneessens</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Skvoretz</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Node centrality in weighted networks: Generalizing degree and shortest paths</article-title>
                  <source>Soc. Netw.</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>32</volume>
                  <fpage>245</fpage>
                  <lpage>251</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socnet.2010.03.006</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B33-biology-10-00667">
                <label>33.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xiong</surname>
                      <given-names>Q.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shi</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shi</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluating the importance of nodes in complex networks</article-title>
                  <source>Phys. A Stat. Mech. Appl.</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>452</volume>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <lpage>219</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.physa.2016.02.049</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B34-biology-10-00667">
                <label>34.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vinterbo</surname>
                      <given-names>S.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Privacy: A machine learning view</article-title>
                  <source>IEEE Trans. Knowl. Data Eng.</source>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <volume>16</volume>
                  <fpage>939</fpage>
                  <lpage>948</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1109/TKDE.2004.31</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B35-biology-10-00667">
                <label>35.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Latora</surname>
                      <given-names>V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Marchiori</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Efficient Behavior of Small-World Networks</article-title>
                  <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <volume>87</volume>
                  <fpage>198701</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevLett.87.198701</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11690461</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B36-biology-10-00667">
                <label>36.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ren</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shao</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Guo</surname>
                      <given-names>Q.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>B.H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Node importance measurement based on the degree and clustering coefficient information</article-title>
                  <source>Acta Phys. Sin.</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <volume>62</volume>
                  <fpage>128901</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B37-biology-10-00667">
                <label>37.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="confproc">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Musiał</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Juszczyszyn</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Properties of bridge nodes in social networks</article-title>
                  <source>Proceedings of the International Conference on Computational Collective Intelligence</source>
                  <conf-loc>Wroclaw, Poland</conf-loc>
                  <conf-date>5–7 October 2009</conf-date>
                  <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
                  <publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg, Germany</publisher-loc>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <fpage>357</fpage>
                  <lpage>364</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B38-biology-10-00667">
                <label>38.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shams</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Using network properties to evaluate targeted immunization algorithms</article-title>
                  <source>Netw. Biol.</source>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <volume>4</volume>
                  <fpage>74</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B39-biology-10-00667">
                <label>39.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Paul</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Havlin</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liljeros</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stanley</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Finding a better immunization strategy</article-title>
                  <source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <volume>101</volume>
                  <fpage>058701</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevLett.101.058701</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 18764435?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18764435</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B40-biology-10-00667">
                <label>40.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nian</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Efficient immunization strategies on complex networks</article-title>
                  <source>J. Theor. Biol.</source>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <volume>264</volume>
                  <fpage>77</fpage>
                  <lpage>83</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtbi.2010.01.007</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 20083123?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20083123</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B41-biology-10-00667">
                <label>41.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wouters</surname>
                      <given-names>O.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shadlen</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Salcher-Konrad</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pollard</surname>
                      <given-names>A.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Larson</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Teerawattananon</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jit</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Challenges in ensuring global access to COVID-19 vaccines: Production, affordability, allocation, and deployment</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(21)00306-8</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B42-biology-10-00667">
                <label>42.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lai</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ye</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Propagation and immunization of infection on general networks with both homogeneous and heterogeneous components</article-title>
                  <source>Phys. Rev. E</source>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <volume>67</volume>
                  <fpage>031911</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevE.67.031911</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 12689105?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12689105</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B43-biology-10-00667">
                <label>43.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pastor-Satorras</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vespignani</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Immunization of complex networks</article-title>
                  <source>Phys. Rev. E</source>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <volume>65</volume>
                  <fpage>036104</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevE.65.036104</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B44-biology-10-00667">
                <label>44.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aschwanden</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Five reasons why COVID herd immunity is probably impossible</article-title>
                  <source>Nature</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>591</volume>
                  <fpage>520</fpage>
                  <lpage>522</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/d41586-021-00728-2</pub-id>
                  <?supplied-pmid 33737753?>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33737753</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B45-biology-10-00667">
                <label>45.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="confproc">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wei</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Deng</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Degree centrality based on the weighted network</article-title>
                  <source>Proceedings of the 24th Chinese Control and Decision Conference (CCDC)</source>
                  <conf-loc>Taiyuan, China</conf-loc>
                  <conf-date>23–25 May 2012</conf-date>
                  <fpage>3976</fpage>
                  <lpage>3979</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
          <floats-group>
            <fig id="biology-10-00667-f001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
              <label>Figure 1</label>
              <caption>
                <p>Simple graph.</p>
              </caption>
              <graphic xlink:href="biology-10-00667-g001"/>
            </fig>
            <fig id="biology-10-00667-f002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
              <label>Figure 2</label>
              <caption>
                <p>Graph obtained from <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm272"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
              </caption>
              <graphic xlink:href="biology-10-00667-g002"/>
            </fig>
            <fig id="biology-10-00667-f003" orientation="portrait" position="float">
              <label>Figure 3</label>
              <caption>
                <p>Graph obtained from database of Olmué city, Chile, with 3866 vertices and 6,841,470 edges.</p>
              </caption>
              <graphic xlink:href="biology-10-00667-g003"/>
            </fig>
            <fig id="biology-10-00667-f004" orientation="portrait" position="float">
              <label>Figure 4</label>
              <caption>
                <p>The left side shows a graph without protection or infection. On the right side, we see an infected node (red) and a protected node (blue) in the same graph.</p>
              </caption>
              <graphic xlink:href="biology-10-00667-g004"/>
            </fig>
            <fig id="biology-10-00667-f005" orientation="portrait" position="float">
              <label>Figure 5</label>
              <caption>
                <p>Graph with 15 nodes, 16 edges, and the respective weights.</p>
              </caption>
              <graphic xlink:href="biology-10-00667-g005"/>
            </fig>
            <fig id="biology-10-00667-f006" orientation="portrait" position="float">
              <label>Figure 6</label>
              <caption>
                <p>In the left, the first 3 protected places generated by the DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm273"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> ranking. On the right, the first 3 protected places generated by Strength ranking.</p>
              </caption>
              <graphic xlink:href="biology-10-00667-g006"/>
            </fig>
            <fig id="biology-10-00667-f007" orientation="portrait" position="float">
              <label>Figure 7</label>
              <caption>
                <p>Real infected data (black), fitted curve (red), and infected curve obtained in the spread on <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm274"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="script">E</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (cyan).</p>
              </caption>
              <graphic xlink:href="biology-10-00667-g007"/>
            </fig>
            <fig id="biology-10-00667-f008" orientation="portrait" position="float">
              <label>Figure 8</label>
              <caption>
                <p>Infected curves obtained according to different values of <italic>k</italic>.</p>
              </caption>
              <graphic xlink:href="biology-10-00667-g008"/>
            </fig>
            <fig id="biology-10-00667-f009" orientation="portrait" position="float">
              <label>Figure 9</label>
              <caption>
                <p>Survival rate of each ranking.</p>
              </caption>
              <graphic xlink:href="biology-10-00667-g009"/>
            </fig>
            <fig id="biology-10-00667-f010" orientation="portrait" position="float">
              <label>Figure 10</label>
              <caption>
                <p>Relationship between the real infected and those immunized according to the different DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm275"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> ranking.</p>
              </caption>
              <graphic xlink:href="biology-10-00667-g010"/>
            </fig>
            <fig id="biology-10-00667-f011" orientation="portrait" position="float">
              <label>Figure 11</label>
              <caption>
                <p>The different infected curves, considering the 10% protection according to the DIL-Wαranking and carried out in different weeks.</p>
              </caption>
              <graphic xlink:href="biology-10-00667-g011a"/>
              <graphic xlink:href="biology-10-00667-g011b"/>
            </fig>
            <fig id="biology-10-00667-f012" orientation="portrait" position="float">
              <label>Figure 12</label>
              <caption>
                <p>Survival rate of each ranking.</p>
              </caption>
              <graphic xlink:href="biology-10-00667-g012"/>
            </fig>
            <table-wrap id="biology-10-00667-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float">
              <object-id pub-id-type="pii">biology-10-00667-t001_Table 1</object-id>
              <label>Table 1</label>
              <caption>
                <p>Summary of Symbols and Notations.</p>
              </caption>
              <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Notations</th>
                    <th align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Definition and Description</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <italic>G</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Graph or network.</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <inline-formula>
                        <mml:math id="mm276">
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mi>G</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mo>,</mml:mo>
                              <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:math>
                      </inline-formula>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Edge-weighted graph.</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <inline-formula>
                        <mml:math id="mm277">
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:msub>
                              <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                            </mml:msub>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:math>
                      </inline-formula>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vertex or node.</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <inline-formula>
                        <mml:math id="mm278">
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mi>N</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                              <mml:msub>
                                <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                              </mml:msub>
                              <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:math>
                      </inline-formula>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neighborhood of a vertex <italic>v</italic>.</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <inline-formula>
                        <mml:math id="mm279">
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:msub>
                              <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                              </mml:mrow>
                            </mml:msub>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:math>
                      </inline-formula>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Edge between vertex <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm280"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and vertex <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm281"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <inline-formula>
                        <mml:math id="mm282">
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:msub>
                              <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                              </mml:mrow>
                            </mml:msub>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:math>
                      </inline-formula>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight of the edge <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm283"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <inline-formula>
                        <mml:math id="mm284">
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mi>d</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mi>g</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                              <mml:msub>
                                <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                              </mml:msub>
                              <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:math>
                      </inline-formula>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Degree of the vertex <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm285"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <inline-formula>
                        <mml:math id="mm286">
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:mi>S</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                              <mml:msub>
                                <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                              </mml:msub>
                              <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:math>
                      </inline-formula>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strength of the vertex <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm287"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <inline-formula>
                        <mml:math id="mm288">
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:math>
                      </inline-formula>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Real number. Tuning parameter.</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <inline-formula>
                        <mml:math id="mm289">
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:msubsup>
                                <mml:mi>C</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mi>D</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mrow>
                                  <mml:mi>w</mml:mi>
                                  <mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
                                </mml:mrow>
                              </mml:msubsup>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                                <mml:msub>
                                  <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                                  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                                </mml:msub>
                                <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                              </mml:mrow>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:math>
                      </inline-formula>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Degree centrality of <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm290"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> of an edge-weighted graph <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm291"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DIL-W<inline-formula><mml:math id="mm292"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow/><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td>
                    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ranking based on Degree and importance of line.</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <inline-formula>
                        <mml:math id="mm293">
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:msup>
                                <mml:mi>I</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
                              </mml:msup>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                                <mml:msub>
                                  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                                  <mml:mrow>
                                    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                                    <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                                  </mml:mrow>
                                </mml:msub>
                                <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                              </mml:mrow>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:math>
                      </inline-formula>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Importance of edge <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm294"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <inline-formula>
                        <mml:math id="mm295">
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:msup>
                                <mml:mi>W</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
                              </mml:msup>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                                <mml:msub>
                                  <mml:mi>e</mml:mi>
                                  <mml:mrow>
                                    <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                                    <mml:mi>j</mml:mi>
                                  </mml:mrow>
                                </mml:msub>
                                <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                              </mml:mrow>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:math>
                      </inline-formula>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Contribution that <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm296"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> makes to the importance of the edge <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm297"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <inline-formula>
                        <mml:math id="mm298">
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mrow>
                              <mml:msup>
                                <mml:mi>L</mml:mi>
                                <mml:mi>α</mml:mi>
                              </mml:msup>
                              <mml:mrow>
                                <mml:mo>(</mml:mo>
                                <mml:msub>
                                  <mml:mi>v</mml:mi>
                                  <mml:mi>i</mml:mi>
                                </mml:msub>
                                <mml:mo>)</mml:mo>
                              </mml:mrow>
                            </mml:mrow>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:math>
                      </inline-formula>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The importance of a vertex <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm299"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <inline-formula>
                        <mml:math id="mm300">
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi mathvariant="script">E</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:math>
                      </inline-formula>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Database.</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <inline-formula>
                        <mml:math id="mm301">
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:msub>
                              <mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
                            </mml:msub>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:math>
                      </inline-formula>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable of a database.</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <inline-formula>
                        <mml:math id="mm302">
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:msub>
                              <mml:mi>p</mml:mi>
                              <mml:mi>k</mml:mi>
                            </mml:msub>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:math>
                      </inline-formula>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight of the variable <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm303"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">X</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <italic>k</italic>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protection budget (the number of nodes in graph <italic>G</italic> that can be protected).</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                      <inline-formula>
                        <mml:math id="mm304">
                          <mml:mrow>
                            <mml:mi>σ</mml:mi>
                          </mml:mrow>
                        </mml:math>
                      </inline-formula>
                    </td>
                    <td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ratio of surviving nodes.</td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </table-wrap>
            <table-wrap id="biology-10-00667-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float">
              <object-id pub-id-type="pii">biology-10-00667-t002_Table 2</object-id>
              <label>Table 2</label>
              <caption>
                <p>Database <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm305"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
              </caption>
              <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                <thead>
                  <tr>
                    <th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Person</th>
                    <th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">City</th>
                    <th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Workplace</th>
                    <th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E. C. Activity</th>
                    <th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Address</th>
                    <th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sm.</th>
                    <th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dri.</th>
                    <th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gen.</th>
                    <th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M. S</th>
                    <th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin;border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age</th>
                  </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Workplace 1</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Theater</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IC</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Workplace 3</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cinema</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">y</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IC</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">School B</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Football</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">z</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Workplace 1</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Photography</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Workplace 5</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Does not have</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">u</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">W</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Workplace 4</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Does not have</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">v</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IC</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Workplace 2</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Does not have</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">University 1</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Photography</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">v</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IC</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">University 2</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Does not have</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">w</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IC</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">School B</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Karate</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">x</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Workplace 4</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ping-pong</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">School A</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Football</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">s</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Workplace 5</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dance</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">r</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">School A</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Handball</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">q</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">University 1</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Does not have</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">t</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Workplace 7</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Singing</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Workplace 8</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Music</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">k</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Workplace 3</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Does not have</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">School A</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Music</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">g</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Workplace 6</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Does not have</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">h</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">M</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">S</td>
                    <td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
                  </tr>
                </tbody>
              </table>
            </table-wrap>
          </floats-group>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
