<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-03-11T00:46:49Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8611333" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8611333</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-11-29</datestamp>
        <setSpec>interface</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J R Soc Interface</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J R Soc Interface</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">RSIF</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">royinterface</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Journal of the Royal Society Interface</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">1742-5689</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1742-5662</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>The Royal Society</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC8611333</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8611333</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">8611333</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34814729</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsif.2021.0648</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">rsif20210648</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline-codes">
                  <compound-subject>
                    <compound-subject-part content-type="code">1004</compound-subject-part>
                  </compound-subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="subject-codes">
                  <compound-subject>
                    <compound-subject-part content-type="code">24</compound-subject-part>
                  </compound-subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Life Sciences–Mathematics interface</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="type-of-publication">
                  <subject>Research Articles</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>A runtime alterable epidemic model with genetic drift, waning immunity and vaccinations</article-title>
                <alt-title alt-title-type="short">A runtime alterable epidemic model with genetic drift, waning immunity and vaccinations</alt-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8784-9354</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Getz</surname>
                    <given-names>Wayne M.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <email>wgetz@berkeley.edu</email>
                  <xref rid="af1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="af2" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="af3" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Salter</surname>
                    <given-names>Richard</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="af3" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="af4" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>4</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Luisa Vissat</surname>
                    <given-names>Ludovica</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="af1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Koopman</surname>
                    <given-names>James S.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="af5" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>5</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="af6" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>6</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Simon</surname>
                    <given-names>Carl P.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="af6" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>6</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="af7" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>7</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="af8" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>8</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="af1">
                  <label>
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </label>
                  <addr-line>Department ESPM, <institution>UC Berkeley</institution>, Berkeley, CA 94720-3114, <country>USA</country></addr-line>
                </aff>
                <aff id="af2">
                  <label>
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </label>
                  <addr-line>School of Mathematical Sciences, <institution>University of KwaZulu-Natal</institution>, Durban, <country>South Africa</country></addr-line>
                </aff>
                <aff id="af3">
                  <label>
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </label>
                  <addr-line><institution>Numerus</institution>, 850 Iron Point Rd., Folsom, CA 95630, <country>USA</country></addr-line>
                </aff>
                <aff id="af4">
                  <label>
                    <sup>4</sup>
                  </label>
                  <addr-line>Computer Science Department, <institution>Oberlin College</institution>, Oberlin, OH 44074, <country>USA</country></addr-line>
                </aff>
                <aff id="af5">
                  <label>
                    <sup>5</sup>
                  </label>
                  <addr-line>School of Public Health, <institution>University of Michigan</institution>, Ann Arbor, MI 48109, <country>USA</country></addr-line>
                </aff>
                <aff id="af6">
                  <label>
                    <sup>6</sup>
                  </label>
                  <addr-line>Center for the Study of Complex Systems, <institution>University of Michigan</institution>, Ann Arbor, MI 48109, <country>USA</country></addr-line>
                </aff>
                <aff id="af7">
                  <label>
                    <sup>7</sup>
                  </label>
                  <addr-line>Gerald R. Ford School of Public Policy, <institution>University of Michigan</institution>, Ann Arbor, MI 48109, <country>USA</country></addr-line>
                </aff>
                <aff id="af8">
                  <label>
                    <sup>8</sup>
                  </label>
                  <addr-line>Department of Mathematics, <institution>University of Michigan</institution>, Ann Arbor, MI 48109, <country>USA</country></addr-line>
                </aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <fn fn-type="other">
                  <p>Electronic supplementary material is available online at <uri xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.c.5705339">https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.c.5705339</uri>.</p>
                </fn>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
                <day>24</day>
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2021</year>
                <string-date>November 24, 2021</string-date>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="collection">
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>24</day>
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2021</year>
                <string-date>November 24, 2021</string-date>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>18</volume>
              <issue>184</issue>
              <elocation-id>20210648</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>13</day>
                  <month>8</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <string-date>August 13, 2021</string-date>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>27</day>
                  <month>10</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <string-date>October 27, 2021</string-date>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2021 The Authors.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>Published by the Royal Society under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="rsif.2021.0648.pdf"/>
              <abstract>
                <p>We present methods for building a Java Runtime-Alterable-Model Platform (RAMP) of complex dynamical systems. We illustrate our methods by building a multivariant SEIR (epidemic) RAMP. Underlying our RAMP is an individual-based model that includes adaptive contact rates, pathogen genetic drift, waning and cross-immunity. Besides allowing parameter values, process descriptions and scriptable runtime drivers to be easily modified during simulations, our RAMP can used within R-Studio and other computational platforms. Process descriptions that can be runtime altered within our SEIR RAMP include pathogen variant-dependent host shedding, environmental persistence, host transmission and within-host pathogen mutation and replication. They also include adaptive social distancing and adaptive application of vaccination rates and variant-valency of vaccines. We present simulation results using parameter values and process descriptions relevant to the current COVID-19 pandemic. Our results suggest that if waning immunity outpaces vaccination rates, then vaccination rollouts may fail to contain the most transmissible variants, particularly if vaccine valencies are not adapted to deal with escape mutations. Our SEIR RAMP is designed for easy use by others. More generally, our RAMP concept facilitates construction of highly flexible complex systems models of all types, which can then be easily shared as stand-alone application programs.</p>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>SEIR individual-based models</kwd>
                <x xml:space="preserve">, </x>
                <kwd>escape mutations</kwd>
                <x xml:space="preserve">, </x>
                <kwd>RAMPs</kwd>
                <x xml:space="preserve">, </x>
                <kwd>SARS-CoV-2</kwd>
                <x xml:space="preserve">, </x>
                <kwd>pathogen variants</kwd>
                <x xml:space="preserve">, </x>
                <kwd>vaccination</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group specific-use="FundRef">
                <award-group>
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution>US National Science Foundation</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                  <award-id>2032264</award-id>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="s1">
              <label>1<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Kermack and McKendrick pioneered the application of differential equations to modelling the dynamics of disease systems that included susceptible (<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>), infected/infectious (<italic toggle="yes">E</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">I</italic>) and recovered (<italic toggle="yes">R</italic>; we use <italic toggle="yes">V</italic> to include vaccinated) classes of individuals [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Subsequent extensions of their formulation include, <italic toggle="yes">inter alia</italic>, additional disease and demographic classes [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], multihost and pathogen strain considerations [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="RSIF20210648C4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], spatial heterogeneity [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="RSIF20210648C6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], network [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] and individual-based formulations [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="RSIF20210648C9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Along with these extensions has come the challenge of ‘not being able to see the forest for the trees’ when questions beyond those pertaining to the profiles of epidemics on homogeneous, well-mixed, large populations arise. As with the current COVID-19 pandemic, these questions may relate to the emergence of new pathogen variants [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], the effects of waning and cross-immunity in hosts with different exposure histories to these variants [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], differential transmission and virulence of these variants, issues of spatial heterogeneity and host heterogeneity related to age, gender, and health status factors [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p>
              <p>From the points of view of both technology and human comprehension, we only have the capacity to understand how a limited number of factors may explain or affect epidemiological outcomes at any one time when measures are applied to mitigate the severity of disease outbreaks. Thus, we are brought to consider the issue of how to craft a model so that it has the appropriate level of complexity to address the questions at hand [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="RSIF20210648C14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. We otherwise follow Einstein’s dictum that ‘models should be as simple as possible, but no simpler.’</p>
              <p>To facilitate the processes of both incorporating complexity into and stripping complexity out of models, we have developed the concept of a Runtime Alterable Model Platform (RAMP). This allows us to focus on outcomes rather than on the logistics of modifying and coding models and carrying out comparative analyses. Our RAMP includes panels, windows and sliders that allow users to specify and manipulate model parameter values and to modify process function descriptions, and scripting drivers for implementing sets of simulations. Furthermore, modifications can be made both at the start of and during the course of a simulation, while protecting the integrity of the underlying code. In addition, our RAMP automates documentation of all parameter values, process descriptions, changes and actions (modifications and substitutions during simulation) in a file that is then saved at the end of each simulation. This file is then ready for later comparative analyses across sets of simulations, or within a data processing environment that incorporates our RAMP as a component package, such as R-Studio.</p>
              <p>RAMPs can be developed for models that address classes of problems, formulated using a Goldilocks principle. Thus, these classes should not be too general so that comparisons within each class require extensive alterations to models (members of the class should share significant structural properties with regard to process dynamics) but also not too specialized so that comparisons across members of the class are not too limited to provide answers to questions of interest. Thus we might develop different RAMPs to study genetic, morphogentics, epidemiological, evolutionary, geological and environmental processes.</p>
              <p>Here, we provide an example of a RAMP that has sufficient breadth to investigate an array of questions pertaining to multivariant epidemiological dynamics for directly transmissible diseases, such as the current SARS-CoV-2 pandemic [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="RSIF20210648C16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], influenza [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] or Ebola [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="RSIF20210648C18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. For simplicity, we refer to this as our M-SEIR (multivariant susceptible-exposed-infected-recovered) RAMP. For the study of water-borne or vector-borne diseases, similar but somewhat more complicated RAMPs will need to be developed. Our M-SEIR RAMP is designed to be used by individuals either with no coding skills, or with minimal coding skills if they desire to modify some of the process descriptions incorporated into the supplied platform. It is sufficiently detailed, however, to allow the user to incorporate either supplied or user-altered versions of the following processes: (i) pathogen variant-specific shedding [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], environmental persistence [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], within-host replication [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] and mortality rates [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]; (ii) immunological waning with variant cross-immunity [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="RSIF20210648C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]; (iii) pathogen variant drift during transmission and within-host replication [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]; (iv) an adaptive contact rate [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]; (v) a time-dependent, uni- or multivalent vaccine rollout [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="RSIF20210648C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] (<xref rid="RSIF20210648F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>; for mathematical details, see §2, and electronic supplementary material, appendix A).
<fig position="float" id="RSIF20210648F1"><label>Figure 1<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label><caption><p>An overview of the processes included in our M-SEIR model (see <xref rid="RSIF20210648TB1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref> for equation references). The probability <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM1"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">inf</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula> of <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">h</italic></sub> being infected primarily with pathogen ℓ in terms of receiving an effective dose from agent <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub> is computed in terms of a concatenation of shedding rates (<italic toggle="yes">ζ</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic>ℓ</sub>), environmental persistence rates (<italic toggle="yes">η</italic><sub>ℓ</sub>) and host transmission (<italic toggle="yes">β</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">h</italic>ℓ</sub>) processes (electronic supplementary material, equation (A.12)) and includes both waning and cross-immunity factors. The probability <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM2"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">inv</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula> that the dominant variant emerging in host <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">h</italic></sub> is variant ℓ′ given initial infection with variant ℓ is computed in terms of within-host mutation and within-host replication process (electronic supplementary material, equation (A.13)) and also includes both waning and cross-immunity factors. These two probabilities are then used to compute the overall probability <italic toggle="yes">π</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ih</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">j</italic>ℓ′</sub> (electronic supplementary material, equation (A.14)) that infector <italic toggle="yes">i</italic>, infected with major variant <italic toggle="yes">j</italic>, infects infectee <italic toggle="yes">h</italic> with major variant ℓ′. The quantity <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sub>eff</sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>′) is the expected number of individuals each infectious agent is expected to infect around time <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>′ ∈ [<italic toggle="yes">t</italic> + <italic toggle="yes">σ</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">E</italic></sub>, <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> + <italic toggle="yes">σ</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">E</italic></sub> + <italic toggle="yes">σ</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">I</italic></sub>], where <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sub>0</sub> = <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sub>eff</sub>(0) is estimated for our model using electronic supplementary material, equation (A.26).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsif20210648f01" position="float"/></fig></p>
              <p>The reason for our inclusion of an adaptive contact rate process is that the local nature of contact rate patterns is well established as an important driver of outbreak dynamics [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. If contact rates remain unchanged during the course of an epidemic, then a classic incidence curve (as in <xref rid="RSIF20210648F2" ref-type="fig">figure 2</xref>) will be the result. However, repeated peaks associated with consecutive outbreak waves arise as a result of implementing and then relaxing social distancing measures [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In the absence of social distancing drivers, which vary greatly from one location/region/country to another, an automated way to evaluate the effects of social distancing measures is through an adaptive contact process of the type that we include in our M-SEIR RAMP.
<fig position="float" id="RSIF20210648F2"><label>Figure 2<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label><caption><p>(<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>) The dashboard of our Java Runtime-Alterable-Model Platform (RAMP) SEIVD (<italic toggle="yes">S</italic> = susceptibles, <italic toggle="yes">E</italic> = exposed, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic> = infectious, <italic toggle="yes">V</italic> = immune, <italic toggle="yes">D</italic> = dead) individual-based model (IBM) and simulations obtained using the parameters values depicted in the slider windows (also see <xref rid="RSIF20210648TB2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>). The top left window of this dashboard contains information on the final state of the population (in this case <italic toggle="yes">S</italic> = 3898 and <italic toggle="yes">D</italic> = 143 in a population of <italic toggle="yes">N</italic><sub>0</sub> = 10 000), the bottom left bar graph of the dashboard panel gives the final values of <italic toggle="yes">E</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">V</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">D</italic> at epidemic cessation at time <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> = 166 (days) or the simulation run time, whichever comes first. The dashboard also shows a graph of incidence (purple: selected using coloured buttons below the graph). The bottom ribbon of the dashboard has a series of radio buttons that respectively open a log, a JavaScript (JS) and a scripting (<italic toggle="yes">S</italic>) window, line and bar graph windows (for multivariant runs), as well as windows for controlling vaccination strategies (<italic toggle="yes">V</italic>), listing realtime agent information (<italic toggle="yes">A</italic>), pathogen parameter values (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic>), monitoring probability computations (Intern), coding and controlling runtime alternative operations (Op), and three runtime buttons (Reset, Step, Run). (<italic toggle="yes">b</italic>) Graphs of prevalence and cumulative deaths (cut out from main panel when only the red and black buttons are on) and (<italic toggle="yes">c</italic>) daily deaths (crimson button) are pasted below the dashboard.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsif20210648f02" position="float"/></fig></p>
              <p>To illustrate the application of our M-SEIR RAMP, we used it to explore aspects of disease incidence and prevalence profiles using parameters that are applicable to the SARS-CoV-2 pathogen at the start of the COVID-19 pandemic. For example, we compare constant and adaptive (viz., prevalence-dependent) contact rate processes under different waning immunity scenarios. We also explore the emergence of variants for different mutation and variant transmission rates. Additionally, we show how our M-SEIR RAMP can be used to evaluate the efficacy of uni- and multivalent vaccines applied at various time-dependent rates, where choice of valency may switch in response to realtime monitoring and surveillance data. Such adaptive vaccination programs may be required to combat the evolutionary arms race between vaccine efficacy and the evolution of new pathogen variants [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="RSIF20210648C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="RSIF20210648C29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. We hope, however, that our results and subsequent investigations using our M-SEIR RAMP will provide the kinds of quantitative analyses that can help formulate highly effective local- or country-level vaccination programs that avoid some of the vaccination rollout pitfalls revealed by our analysis, as well as encourage the adoption of effective adaptive vaccination programs.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="methods" id="s2">
              <label>2<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
              <title>Material and methods</title>
              <sec id="s2a">
                <label>2.1<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <title>Our M-SEIR in a nutshell</title>
                <p>We constructed an individual-based model (IBM) of a susceptible-exposed-infectious-recovered (i.e. an SEIVD model, where removed <italic toggle="yes">R</italic> are split into <italic toggle="yes">V</italic> = immune/vaccinated, and <italic toggle="yes">D</italic> = dead) epidemiological process [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="RSIF20210648C31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] in a homogeneous population with a random encounter contact rate parameter <italic toggle="yes">κ</italic><sub>0</sub> &gt; 0. Our formulation allows for the emergence of multiple variants of the pathogen during a sequence (i.e. concatenation) of process depicted in <xref rid="RSIF20210648F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref> and listed in table 1. Specifically, our formulation includes a host immunological waning process [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="RSIF20210648C32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] and a mutational process that impacts both transmission of mutant variants from the infectee and genetic drift [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="RSIF20210648C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="RSIF20210648C33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] of variants within the infector, with rates impacted by cross-immunity effects. We also allowed for variation in pathogen variant transmissibility (i.e. in the <italic toggle="yes">β</italic> &gt; 0 parameter of the frequency dependent transmission function <italic toggle="yes">βSI</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="RSIF20210648C35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]) and pathogen virulence as represented by the disease-induced host mortality rate in the sense of Anderson &amp; May [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] (and often represented by a parameter <italic toggle="yes">α</italic> ≥ 0 [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]).</p>
                <p>The detailed formulation of our model and its algorithmic implementation is provided in appendix A (electronic supplementary material, SOF), with references to relevant equations in this provided in <xref rid="RSIF20210648TB1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>. In a nutshell we:
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>1.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>Defined a set of 2<sup><italic toggle="yes">J</italic></sup> pathogen variants (user selected value for variant entropy <italic toggle="yes">J</italic> ranging from 0 to 7; pathogen index <italic toggle="yes">j</italic> = 0, …, 2<sup><italic toggle="yes">J</italic></sup> − 1) with a genetic-relatedness topology of a <italic toggle="yes">J</italic>-dimensional unit cube—i.e. each pathogen has <italic toggle="yes">J</italic>-loci that can take on one of two allelic values at each locus with immediate neighbouring variants differing from each other by exactly one allelic value (0 or 1) at only one of the <italic toggle="yes">J</italic> loci.</p></list-item><list-item><label>2.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>Defined a population of <italic toggle="yes">N</italic><sub>0</sub> hosts as belonging at time <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> to either an epidemiologically naive set of susceptible individuals <bold>S</bold> of size <italic toggle="yes">N</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">S</italic></sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>), a set <bold>A</bold> of <italic toggle="yes">N</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">A</italic></sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) identified agents <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub> (<italic toggle="yes">i</italic> = 1, …, <italic toggle="yes">N</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">A</italic></sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>)) whose epidemiological histories are known, or a set <bold>D</bold> of <italic toggle="yes">N</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">D</italic></sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) individuals that have died from the disease.</p></list-item><list-item><label>3.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>Allowed pathogen variant-specific transmission ‘force’ (<inline-formula><mml:math id="IM3"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>) and virulence (<italic toggle="yes">α</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub> ≥ 0) parameters to vary in value among one another within a defined range <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM4"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">min</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">max</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> and <italic toggle="yes">α</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub> ∈ [<italic toggle="yes">α</italic><sub>min</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">α</italic><sub>max</sub>].</p></list-item><list-item><label>4.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>Kept track of the total prevalence <italic toggle="yes">N</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">I</italic></sub> as the sum of the prevalences of the individual variants <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM5"><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, <italic toggle="yes">j</italic> = 0, …, 2<sup><italic toggle="yes">J</italic></sup> − 1—i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM6"><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>J</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></list-item><list-item><label>5.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>Introduced a random contact rate function <italic toggle="yes">κ</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) with a constant parameter <italic toggle="yes">κ</italic><sub>0</sub> that is Poisson distributed on [<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> + 1), <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> = 0, 1, …, multiplied by an adaptive response function that reduces the contact rate with increasing disease prevalence, such that the <italic toggle="yes">κ</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) is reduced to <italic toggle="yes">κ</italic><sub>0</sub>/2 when the <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM7"><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">half</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula>—see electronic supplementary material, equation (A 7)</p></list-item><list-item><label>6.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>Updated the epidemiological state of the agents <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub> with respect to each of the variants <italic toggle="yes">j</italic> = 0, …, 2<sup><italic toggle="yes">J</italic></sup> − 1, where the state with respect to particular variant <italic toggle="yes">j</italic> at time <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> is represented by a list that includes the following <italic toggle="yes">J</italic> entries pertaining to the state of <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub> with respect to pathogen variant <italic toggle="yes">j</italic> = 0, …, 2<sup><italic toggle="yes">J</italic></sup> − 1. If the <italic toggle="yes">j</italic>th entry is:
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>(a)</label><p>0, then agent <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub> has never been infected with this variant</p></list-item><list-item><label>(b)</label><p><italic toggle="yes">E</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">τ</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ij</italic></sub>), then agent <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub> was infected at time <italic toggle="yes">τ</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ij</italic></sub> ≤ <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> with this variant, but is not yet infectious for an expected period of <italic toggle="yes">σ</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">E</italic></sub> units of time</p></list-item><list-item><label>(c)</label><p><italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">τ</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ij</italic></sub>), then agent <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub> was infectious at time <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> with this variant, for an expected period of <italic toggle="yes">σ</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">I</italic></sub> units of time, having been most recently infected (reinfections with the same variant may occur) with this variant at time <italic toggle="yes">τ</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ij</italic></sub> &lt; <italic toggle="yes">t</italic></p></list-item><list-item><label>(d)</label><p><italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">τ</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ij</italic></sub>), then agent <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub> has now recovered from its most recent infection at time <italic toggle="yes">τ</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ij</italic></sub> with this variant and has some level of waning immunity to it</p></list-item></list></p></list-item></list>
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>7.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>Assumed that agent <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub> can be infectious at time <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> with at most one dominant variant (denoted by the index <italic toggle="yes">j</italic>), although due to mutational processes this agent may infect other agents with variants related to this dominant variant at much lower rates (i.e.through application of a mutation factor <italic toggle="yes">μ</italic> ≪ 1, applied in our basic model through electronic supplementary material, equation (A.13)).</p></list-item><list-item><label>8.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>Assumed that agent <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub> will have different levels of waning immunity to all of the variants to which it has been infected in the past.</p></list-item><list-item><label>9.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>Included waning immunity functions <italic toggle="yes">ω</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ij</italic></sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) (electronic supplementary material, equation (A 6)) used to compute the level of immunity that agent <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub> has to its most recent infection by variant <italic toggle="yes">j</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item><label>10.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>Included cross-immunity effects (a <italic toggle="yes">J</italic><sup>2</sup>-matrix <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>) that apply both to the <italic toggle="yes">infector</italic> transmitting the pathogen and the <italic toggle="yes">infectee</italic> being invaded (inv; its ‘airport code’ as described in electronic supplementary material, figure B.3) by the pathogen of interest, both of which reduce the likelihood of infection and variant drift by variant <italic toggle="yes">j</italic> compared with closely related variants ℓ (for a simple example of the matrix <italic toggle="yes">C</italic>, see equation (<xref rid="RSIF20210648M2x1" ref-type="disp-formula">2.1</xref>) in §3 below).</p></list-item><list-item><label>11.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>Computed an <italic toggle="yes">infection probability</italic>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="IM8"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">inf</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula> that agent <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub> infected with variant <italic toggle="yes">j</italic> infects agent <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">h</italic></sub> with variant ℓ in terms of a concatenation of infector viral shedding (<italic toggle="yes">ζ</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic>ℓ</sub>; for a simple example see equation (<xref rid="RSIF20210648M2x6" ref-type="disp-formula">2.6</xref>) in §3 below), viral persistence in the environment (<italic toggle="yes">η</italic><sub>ℓ</sub>), and viral transmission (<italic toggle="yes">β</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">h</italic>ℓ</sub>) processes (<xref rid="RSIF20210648F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>)</p></list-item><list-item><label>12.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>Computed an <italic toggle="yes">invasion probability</italic>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="IM9"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">inv</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula> that an agent <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">h</italic></sub> infected with variant ℓ becomes infectious with variant ℓ′ as its major variant, in terms of the multiplicative effects of viral mutation (<italic toggle="yes">μ</italic>) and replication (<italic toggle="yes">λ</italic><sub>ℓ</sub>) processes ongoing within an infectee <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">h</italic></sub> during this infectees exposed (<inline-formula><mml:math id="IM10"><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>) and infectious (<inline-formula><mml:math id="IM11"><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>) periods (<xref rid="RSIF20210648F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item><label>13.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>Computed the overall probability <italic toggle="yes">π</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ih</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">j</italic>ℓ′</sub> that an infector <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub> infected with major variant <italic toggle="yes">j</italic> results in an infectee <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">h</italic></sub> expressing ℓ′ as its major variant.</p></list-item><list-item><label>14.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>Assumed that waning and cross-immunity to a particular variant is the same for both natural infections and vaccinations that use the antigen associated with that variant (of course we can easily extend our model to remove this assumption once data become available to support different waning and cross-immunity rates for natural infections and particular vaccines).</p></list-item><list-item><label>15.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>Implemented a discrete time individual-based stochastic SEIVD (here <italic toggle="yes">V</italic> represents individuals that have either recovered from infection or have been vaccinated, <italic toggle="yes">D</italic> represents cumulative dead; also see [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]) multivariant model that includes specifiable time-dependent univalent and multivalent vaccination implementations.</p></list-item></list>
<table-wrap position="float" id="RSIF20210648TB1"><label>Table 1<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label><caption><p>Variables, indices and functions in our M-SEIR RAMP.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">symbols</th><th rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1">variables and indices</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">equation</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(see electronic supplementary material)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">variables</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">time (variable and function values depend on time)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">N</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">S</italic></sub>, <italic toggle="yes">N</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">A</italic></sub>, <italic toggle="yes">N</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">D</italic></sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">size of sets <bold>S</bold>, <bold>A</bold> and <bold>D</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">equation (A.1)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">J</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">j</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">m</italic>, ℓ and ℓ′</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">variant entropy and indices (0, …, 2<sup><italic toggle="yes">J</italic></sup> − 1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">equation (A.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">N</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">I</italic></sub>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM12"><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">total and variant <italic toggle="yes">j</italic> infectious class size</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub>, <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">h</italic></sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">specific agents <italic toggle="yes">i</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">h</italic> = 1, …, <italic toggle="yes">N</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">A</italic></sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) in set <bold>A</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">equation (A.3)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">functions</italic></bold> (if a parameter now it may be elaborated later as a function)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">κ</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">adaptive contact rate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">equation (A.7)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ω</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ij</italic></sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">waning immunity of <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub> w.r.t. variant <italic toggle="yes">j</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">equation (A.6)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">c</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">mj</italic></sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">cross-immunity encountered by variant <italic toggle="yes">j</italic> when agent previously infected with variant <italic toggle="yes">m</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">equation (A.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ϕ</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ij</italic></sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">immunity modifier</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">equation (A.8)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">ζ</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ij</italic></sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">shedding rate of variant <italic toggle="yes">j</italic> by infector <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">equation (A.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">η</italic><sub>ℓ</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">environmental persistence</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">equation (A.10)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">β</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">h</italic>ℓ</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">variant transmission to infectee <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">h</italic></sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">equation (A.11)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="IM13"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">inf</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">probability <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub> infects <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">h</italic></sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">equation (A.12)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">μ</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mutation process factor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">equation (A.13)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">λ</italic><sub>ℓ′</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">within-host replication rate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">equation (A.13)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="IM14"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi><mml:mo>′</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">inv</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">probability ℓ′ is major variant when ℓ invades</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">equation (A.13)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">π</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ih</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">j</italic>ℓ′</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">probability ℓ′ is major variant in <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">h</italic></sub>when <italic toggle="yes">j</italic> is major variant in <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">equation (A.14)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2b">
                <label>2.2<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <title>Our RAMP implementation</title>
                <p>Models of systems process can be coded: (i) directly using highly efficiently compilable computer languages (e.g. C++, FORTRAN, Java); or (ii) less efficiently, but more easily, using scriptable (e.g. JavaScript, Python, Perl) computer languages. More conveniently and expeditiously, they can be coded up, as discussed in [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>], using a systems modelling platform that contains precoded modules and graphical elements, such as Matlab’s SIMULINK, Mathematica, Stella, AnyLogic, Numerus or Berkeley Madonna. Advantages of the latter include more rapid and accurate model development, though simulations may be slowed down by platform overhead. Between these extremes, we propose a more general approach to specific classes of systems’ models, where the basic system structure is fixed, but implementation of some elements can be easily and safely altered so that optional implementations are presented at runtime. We call such a design <italic toggle="yes">runtime alterable-model platforms</italic>. (RAMPs); and here we present a Java RAMP implementation of the M-SEIR described in the previous subsection.</p>
                <p>The characteristics we envision for a model platform to be a RAMP are:
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>1.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>RAMPs include a set of model parameters (constants) whose values can be selected or specified (sometimes within a predefined range of values) at simulation runtime using a switch, nob, slider or text-entry window accessed via a platform graphical interface or dashboard (see <xref rid="RSIF20210648F2" ref-type="fig">figure 2</xref> and <xref rid="RSIF20210648TB1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref> which apply to our M-SEIR RAMP).</p></list-item><list-item><label>2.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>RAMPs include a specific set of <italic toggle="yes">runtime alternative modules</italic>, (RAMs), where the original can be redefined in a graphical interface window, and the unaltered original and the alternative routines are stored as a (preferably open-ended) numbered set. The original or any one of the alternatives can be selected for use at runtime (for a list of functions in our RAMP see <xref rid="RSIF20210648TB2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item><label>3.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>RAMP implementations also provide an application programming interface (API) for both remote and on-board scripting. This API enables control of all user aspects of the simulation, including the parameter set, run management, RAM options and data retrieval. Script logic can alter parameter settings and RAM options as the simulation progresses. A Nashorn-based Javascript interpreter enhanced with API methods is provided.</p></list-item><list-item><label>4.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>The API can be accessed remotely using operating system facilities by external applications running concurrently with the simulator. Of particular, interest is the ability to control the simulation from the R statistical platform. An R routine can be formulated to both manage the simulation run and to retrieve and process the resulting data. The RAMP simulation becomes a ‘virtual package’ to the controlling R logic. See electronic supplementary material, appendix B.</p></list-item></list>
<table-wrap position="float" id="RSIF20210648TB2"><label>Table 2<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label><caption><p>Parameter values used to simulate single and multivariant outbreaks.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">parameter</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">symbol</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">value</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">source/comment</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">single-variant simulations</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">time unit</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">daily</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">empirical data are daily</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">nominal pop size</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">N</italic><sub>0</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10<sup>5</sup>–10<sup>7</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">see §3.1<sup>a</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">effective contact rate<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">κ</italic><sub>0</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 per day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">implies <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sub>0</sub> ≈ 3.1<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">transmission</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">β</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">implies <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sub>0</sub> ≈ 3.1<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">latent period</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">σ</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">E</italic></sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 days</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">median time in E<sup>d</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">infectious period</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">σ</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">I</italic></sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 days</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">median time in I<sup>e</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">immunity half-life</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sup>half</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/2 to 1 year<sup>f</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">per run specs.<sup>g</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">disease-induced mort.<sup>j</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">α</italic></sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2% of cases<sup>h</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mortality rate is <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM15"><mml:msup><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">adaptive contact param.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="IM16"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">half</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0, 0.002, 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">decreasing <italic toggle="yes">κ</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">I</italic>)<sup>k</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">seasonal fluctuation param.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">δ</italic><sub>season</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">seasons ignored<sup>l</sup></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">multi-variant simulations</italic></bold> (single-variant parameter values used where applicable)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">mutation factor<sup>m</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">μ</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001<sup>n</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">see electronic supplementary material, equation (A.13)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">variant number</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">j</italic> = 0, …, 2<sup><italic toggle="yes">J</italic>−1</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">J</italic> is 0 to 7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">i.e. 2 to 128 variants</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">cross-immunity</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">c</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">mj</italic></sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">equations (2.1), (2.2)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pathogen shedding</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="IM17"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>ζ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001<sup>n</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">see electronic supplementary material, equation (A.9)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">environmental persistence</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="IM18"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>η</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 for all <italic toggle="yes">j</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">see electronic supplementary material, equation (A.10)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">transmission</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="IM19"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">δ</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">β</italic></sub> ∈ [0, 0.2]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">see electronic supplementary material, equation (2.4)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">within-host replication rate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">λ</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 for all <italic toggle="yes">j</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">see electronic supplementary material, equation (A.13)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">disease-induced mort.<sup>o</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="IM20"><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">see electronic supplementary material, equation (2.5)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><sup>a</sup>In particular see §3.1.3.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>b</sup>See electronic supplementary material, equation (A.26).</p></fn><fn><p><sup>c</sup>See electronic supplementary material, equation (A.7).</p></fn><fn><p><sup>d</sup>Reciprocal of <italic toggle="yes">γ</italic> in continuous time computation of <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sub>0</sub> per electronic supplementary material, equation (A.26).</p></fn><fn><p><sup>e</sup>Reciprocal of <italic toggle="yes">ρ</italic> in continuous time computation of <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sub>0</sub> per electronic supplementary material, equation (A.26).</p></fn><fn><p><sup>f</sup>Based on statement in [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]: ‘· · · studies of animal coronaviruses antibody titers · · · waned substantially 1 year after initial infection · · · and many could be reinfected and shed virus · · ·’.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>g</sup>See electronic supplementary material, equation (A.6): note <italic toggle="yes">w</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) switches from 1 to 0 as immunity goes from complete to absent.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>h</sup>Value at start of the pandemic, but typically lower later in most regional epidemics.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>i</sup>This is the ‘virulence’ parameter of continuous-time SEIR models.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>j</sup>If <italic toggle="yes">α</italic> ≪ 1 then <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM21"><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>k</sup>See electronic supplementary material, equation (A.7). Setting <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM22"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">half</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> implements <italic toggle="yes">κ</italic>(0) = <italic toggle="yes">κ</italic><sub>0</sub>, though <italic toggle="yes">κ</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) → <italic toggle="yes">κ</italic><sub>0</sub> as <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM23"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">half</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">→</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∞</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>l</sup>Implies values of <italic toggle="yes">k</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">θ</italic> in electronic supplementary material, equation (A.10) are irrelevant.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>m</sup>Variant independent—variant dependence requires more elaborate model.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>n</sup>Quantifies the mutation rate observed at a population rather than within-cell replication level.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>o</sup>If <italic toggle="yes">α</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub> ≪ 1 then <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM24"><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
                <p>We implemented our RAMP using Java and made ample use of all of the features described above. Use of the RAM facility permitted experimentation with the several versions of cross-immunity (e.g. equations (<xref rid="RSIF20210648M2x1" ref-type="disp-formula">2.1</xref>) and (<xref rid="RSIF20210648M2x2" ref-type="disp-formula">2.2</xref>)). A Javascript program was used to control an adaptive vaccination strategy. A small R package serving as a driver was used in an R program that ran the simulations multiple times, extracted results into R data structures, and produced graphs showing statistical mean and standard deviation. More details on the graphical structure and implementation of our M-SEIR are provided in the presentation of both the results below and information in electronic supplementary material, appendix B.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2c">
                <label>2.3<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <title>Simplifications and running the model</title>
                <p>In the examples presented in the next section, we have not taken advantage of the full complexity of the model. Thus, for example, in our multivariant simulations, we have assumed that all variants are shed at the same relative rate (i.e. <italic toggle="yes">ζ</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ij</italic></sub> = 1 for relevant <italic toggle="yes">i</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">j</italic> = 0, …, 2<sup><italic toggle="yes">J</italic></sup> − 1), have the same environmental persistence properties (i.e. <italic toggle="yes">η</italic><sub>ℓ</sub> = 1 for all ℓ = 0, …, 2<sup><italic toggle="yes">J</italic></sup> − 1), the same within host replication rates (i.e. <italic toggle="yes">λ</italic><sub>ℓ′</sub> = 1 for all ℓ′ = 0, …, 2<sup><italic toggle="yes">J</italic></sup> − 1), and are all equally virulent (i.e. <italic toggle="yes">α</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub> = <italic toggle="yes">α</italic> for all <italic toggle="yes">j</italic> = 0, …, 2<sup><italic toggle="yes">J</italic></sup> − 1). Obviously, these assumptions can be relaxed once suitable data are available for a particular pathogen to support variant specific shedding, persistence, within-host replication and virulence values.</p>
                <p>If suitable cross-neutralization data are unavailable, then some assumptions must be made regarding the parameter values <italic toggle="yes">c</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">mj</italic></sub> in the cross-immunity matrix <bold>C</bold>. For example, we consider the following two contrasting cross-immunity scenarios with respect to a global cross-immunity constant <italic toggle="yes">c</italic> ∈ (0, 1). The first we call <italic toggle="yes">cascading</italic> cross-immunity because the level of cross-immunity diminishes multiplicatively with genetic distance of the two strains: viz.<disp-formula id="RSIF20210648M2x1"><label>2.1</label><mml:math id="DM1" display="block"><mml:mtable columnalign="left left" rowspacing=".5em" columnspacing="thickmathspace"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Cascading</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mtable columnalign="left left" rowspacing="4pt" columnspacing="1em"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">if</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="2em"/><mml:mrow/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msup><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">if</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">differs</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">from</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">by</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">alleles</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>The second we call <italic toggle="yes">escaping</italic> cross-immunity because when the final allele in the array of <italic toggle="yes">J</italic> loci mutates from 0 to 1, it escapes completely from cross neutralization effects with all strains that have the original allele at the <italic toggle="yes">J</italic>th locus: viz.<disp-formula id="RSIF20210648M2x2"><label>2.2</label><mml:math id="DM2" display="block"><mml:mtable columnalign="left left" rowspacing=".5em" columnspacing="thickmathspace"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Escaping</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mtable columnalign="left left" rowspacing="4pt" columnspacing="1em"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">if</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="2em"/><mml:mrow/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">if</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">and</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi><mml:mo>&lt;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>J</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">provided</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="2em"/><mml:mrow/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msup><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">otherwise</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">where</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">differs</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">from</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">by</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">alleles</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>This is an idealization of the <italic toggle="yes">escape mutation</italic> phenomenon, which we set up here to enable us to evaluate behaviour of such mutations. For the purposes of this paper, idealized escape mutations are defined as those whose level of cross-immunity with the variants from which they arise is 0 (in reality some small level of cross-immunity may remain).</p>
                <p>Also, in the absence of comprehensive data that allow us to use realistic estimates for the relative transmissibility <italic toggle="yes">β</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub> and virulence <italic toggle="yes">α</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub> of various variants <italic toggle="yes">j</italic> = 0, …, <italic toggle="yes">J</italic>, we employ the following scenario-facilitating formulations. These permit us to investigate the potential impacts of increased transmission and virulence with the emergence of new strains based on the number of mutations <italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub> needed to get from variant 0 to variant <italic toggle="yes">j</italic>. Specifically, for<disp-formula id="RSIF20210648M2x3"><label>2.3</label><mml:math id="DM3" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Hamming</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">distance</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">between</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">variants</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">and</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula>and for transmissibility and virulence perturbation parameters <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM25"><mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM26"><mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, respectively, we define<disp-formula id="RSIF20210648M2x4"><label>2.4</label><mml:math id="DM4" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Transmissibility</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula>(the bar notation here reminds us that this value is used in the computation of <italic toggle="yes">β</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ij</italic></sub> according to electronic supplementary material, equation (A.8)) and<disp-formula id="RSIF20210648M2x5"><label>2.5</label><mml:math id="DM5" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Virulence</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula>(this is a probability rather than a rate and we have to ensure <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM27"><mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is selected such that <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM28"><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>J</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>).</p>
                <p>Also for simplicity’s sake, we assumed that infectee with major variant <italic toggle="yes">j</italic> will shed minor variants in the immediate neighbourhood of <italic toggle="yes">j</italic> at comparative rate <italic toggle="yes">ζ</italic> ∈ [0, 1) and be major variant-independent: i.e. we assumed<disp-formula id="RSIF20210648M2x6"><label>2.6</label><mml:math id="DM6" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">shedding</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>ζ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mtable columnalign="left left" rowspacing="4pt" columnspacing="1em"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">if</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="2em"/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>ζ</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">if</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>ℓ</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">differs</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">from</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">by</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">one</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">allele</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">otherwise</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="2em"/></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>Finally, in this paper, we will not investigate any seasonal effects, which is equivalent to setting <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic><sub>season</sub> = 0 in electronic supplementary material, equation (A.10), and using this setting in all our simulation.</p>
                <p>The model itself can be accessed at Github (<uri xlink:href="https://github.com/rmsalter/SEIVAgent_distribution">https://github.com/rmsalter/SEIVAgent_distribution</uri>), where instructions are available for launching and using our SEIVAgent application.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s3">
              <label>3<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
              <title>Illustrative examples</title>
              <sec id="s3a">
                <label>3.1<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <title>Single variant simulations</title>
                <sec id="s3a1">
                  <label>3.1.1<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                  <title>Parameter values and baseline run</title>
                  <p>The first variable that needs to be determined is the unit of time we use for our simulations because all process rate parameters are scaled by its selection. As the time resolution of empirical COVID-19 incidence and mortality data is daily, we selected our unit of time <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> to be days. Additionally, based on various sources including a metapopulation study of COVID-19 parameter estimates [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], we set the latent and infectious periods to be 4 and 7 days, respectively. Basic SEIR epidemiological models do not separate out the processes of contact and transmission-per-contact, so we had some leeway on what values to choose for contact rates and transmission rates per contact because it is the value of the product of these that is important in determining the reproductive value, commonly referred to as ‘<italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sub>0</sub>’ for COVID-19. Hussein <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>’s [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] meta analysis of COVID-19 zeroed in on <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sub>0</sub> = 3.14 as a mean value across a range of studies (95% confidence interval [2.69, 3.59]). By setting our baseline contact rate and transmission parameters to be <italic toggle="yes">κ</italic><sub>0</sub> = 3 and <italic toggle="yes">β</italic> = 0.3, we estimated the value of <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sub>0</sub> in our model to be approximately <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sub>0</sub> = 3.1. These and the remaining values of the parameters used in our simulations are summarized in <xref rid="RSIF20210648TB2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s3a2">
                  <label>3.1.2<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                  <title>Adaptive contact rate</title>
                  <p>None of the major outbreaks of COVID-19 around the world followed a classic ‘rise-and-fall’ incidence curve because of social distancing and other measures taken to mitigate transmission once it had been determined that a full-blown outbreak was underway. These measures waxed and waned with government regulations and the perception that the outbreak was respectively under or out of control. This, in turn, resulted in incidence profiles that rose and fell multiple times (i.e. so-called waves) as these measures waxed and waned. Thus, it is not possible to replicate the incidence curves of any of the country/regional epidemics without characterizing the social distance and subsequent social relaxation measures driving their rise and fall [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p>
                  <p>In a general way, we can capture the dominant feature of this kind of social behaviour by assuming the contact rate <italic toggle="yes">κ</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) is influenced by current or recent prevalence levels, where current prevalence is given by the ratio of the number of infected individuals <italic toggle="yes">N</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">I</italic></sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) to current population size <italic toggle="yes">N</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) − <italic toggle="yes">N</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">D</italic></sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>). Thus, in the various scenarios present below, we assume an adaptive response rate that has a maximum value <italic toggle="yes">κ</italic><sub>0</sub> when <italic toggle="yes">I</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) = 0 and is reduced to half this value, as a declining sigmoidal curve specified in electronic supplementary material, equation (A.7), when <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM29"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">half</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula>. If we simulate the first year of an epidemic using our basic parameters (<xref rid="RSIF20210648TB2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>; also see parameter panel in <xref rid="RSIF20210648F2" ref-type="fig">figure 2</xref>) and adaptive contact half-max parameters for the cases <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM30"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">half</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.01</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> and 0.02 (i.e. 1% and 2% prevalence, respectively), we obtain the per cent of susceptibles (uninfected) and cumulative deaths by day 365 provided in <xref rid="RSIF20210648TB3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>.
<table-wrap position="float" id="RSIF20210648TB3"><label>Table 3<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label><caption><p>Basic runs with one million individuals (<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 1 000 000) using two different half-max adaptive contact parameter values <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM31"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">half</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula> compared with listed countries.<sup>a</sup></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="IM32"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">half</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula><hr/></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">USA</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Italy</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Czechia</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1%</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2%</th><th colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">(values under reported)<sup>c</sup><hr/></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">uninfected at day 365<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">93%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">COVID-19 deaths by day 365<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21%</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><sup>a</sup>Data from <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus/country/us/" ext-link-type="uri">Worldometer</ext-link>.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>b</sup>One year after the first 10 recorded cases in the countries concerned.</p></fn><fn><p><sup>c</sup>Substantial under reporting occurs for both cases [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] and deaths [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>].</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
                  <p>For purposes of comparison, we also provide in <xref rid="RSIF20210648TB3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref> the per cent of susceptible individuals and per cent of deaths due to COVID-19 1 year after the day on which more than 10 cases of COVID-19 were recorded to occur in the USA, Italy and Czech Republic (extracted from data provided at Worldometer (<uri xlink:href="https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus/country/us/">https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus/country/us/</uri>)). As these data are known to be substantially under reported for both cumulative prevalence [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] and deaths [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>], we felt that <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM33"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">half</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.01</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> (i.e. 1% prevalence) provides a reasonable ballpark value for an adaptive contact rate half-max parameter for our various illustrations provided below.</p>
                  <p>Finally, it is worth noting that the adaptive contact rate may be much more complicated than we have represented here. For example, social distancing fatigue may set in over time, effectively inducing a time-varying value on the parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM34"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">half</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula> itself. Our RAMP design allows modellers to readily implement a more complex adaptive response should they choose to do so.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s3a3">
                  <label>3.1.3<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                  <title>Population size and demographic stochasticity</title>
                  <p>Deterministic SIR/SEIR and related models will always produce an epidemic whenever the parameters ensure that <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sub>0</sub> &gt; 1 [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="RSIF20210648C34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. As these models do not include the demographic stochastic effects associated with finite populations, they are unable to capture the phenomenon of stochastic extinction of the epidemic before it gets going when a single infected individual is introduced into an otherwise infected population (with regard to the pathogen in question; see discussion in electronic supplementary material, A.4). In such models, results are either cited using percentages or numbers per thousand or per hundred thousand individuals and the actual population size is not regarded as a factor. Population size, however, is a factor in determining the absolute size of an epidemic once it gets started and deterministic models provided a robust assessment of the course of the epidemic in populations consisting of millions of individuals (other factors, such as spatial or contact network structure play a more important role than size per se [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>–<xref rid="RSIF20210648C7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]).</p>
                  <p>To get a sense of the effects of demographic stochasticity on populations of different sizes in our simulations, we compared the prevalence, incidence and cumulative deaths obtained for single runs (runtime seed = 1) of a basic adaptive contact rate scenario (basic parameters plus <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM35"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">half</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.01</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>) for cases where the initial population sizes where <italic toggle="yes">N</italic><sub>0</sub> = 10 000, 100 000 and 1 000 000 (<xref rid="RSIF20210648F3" ref-type="fig">figure 3</xref><italic toggle="yes">a</italic>–<italic toggle="yes">c</italic>). We also compared the mean prevalence plus/minus 1 s.d. for 100 runs (runtime seeds ranging from 0 to 99) for the two cases <italic toggle="yes">N</italic><sub>0</sub> = 10 000 and 100 000 over both the 1st year (<xref rid="RSIF20210648F3" ref-type="fig">figure 3</xref><italic toggle="yes">d</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">e</italic>) and the first 100 days (<xref rid="RSIF20210648F3" ref-type="fig">figure 3</xref><italic toggle="yes">f</italic>).
<fig position="float" id="RSIF20210648F3"><label>Figure 3<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label><caption><p>(<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>–<italic toggle="yes">c</italic>) Plots of percentage prevalence (red), incidence (purple) and cumulative dead (black) for 365-day simulations using the parameter values given in <xref rid="RSIF20210648TB1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref> with the adaptive contact rate parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM36"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">half</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.01</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> (see electronic supplementary material, equation (A.7) in SOI) and <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 10 000, <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 100 000 and <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 1 000 000, respectively. (<italic toggle="yes">d</italic>–<italic toggle="yes">e</italic>) Plots of mean percentage prevalence (red) over the first year plus (green) minus (blue) 1 s.d. over 100 runs (runtime seeds going from 0 to 99) for the cases <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 10 000 and <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 100 000, respectively. (<italic toggle="yes">f</italic>) Plots of the actual prevalence (number of individuals) for the first 100 days for the cases <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 10 000 (red) and <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 100 000 (black).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsif20210648f03" position="float"/></fig></p>
                  <p>The results depicted in <xref rid="RSIF20210648F3" ref-type="fig">figure 3</xref> can be encapsulated in the following four well-established principles:
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>1.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>The initial phase of an outbreak is independent of population size and establishment of an epidemic depends solely on the value of <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sub>0</sub> (electronic supplementary material, appendix A.4). Thus, as we see in <xref rid="RSIF20210648F3" ref-type="fig">figure 3</xref><italic toggle="yes">f</italic>, the first 50 days of the mean prevalence for the simulations of the cases <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 10 000 and <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 100 000 are virtually identical, only departing from one another from around day 50 onwards.</p></list-item><list-item><label>2.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>Beyond the initial phase, stochastic fluctuations are more evident in smaller than larger populations (compare figure <xref rid="RSIF20210648F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref><italic toggle="yes">a</italic>–<italic toggle="yes">c</italic>).</p></list-item><list-item><label>3.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>Ultimate prevalence levels, aside from stochastic fluctuations, are independent of population size. Thus, for example, we see that prevalence maxes out at round 0.6% in all three cases (dotted lines) across a range of two orders of magnitude in population size.</p></list-item><list-item><label>4.<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>Mean population prevalence will always max out at lower levels than the prevalence reached in actual runs (viz. the maximum exceeds 0.7% individual runs in <xref rid="RSIF20210648F3" ref-type="fig">figure 3</xref><italic toggle="yes">a</italic>–<italic toggle="yes">c,</italic> while it is between 0.4% and 0.5% for the red curves in <xref rid="RSIF20210648F3" ref-type="fig">figure 3</xref><italic toggle="yes">d</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">e</italic>) because the mean values take into account the fact a proportion 1/<italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sub>0</sub> of the runs go extinct within the first several weeks [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>].</p></list-item></list></p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3b">
                <label>3.2<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <title>Multivariant simulations</title>
                <p>We carried out a series of multivariant simulations with <italic toggle="yes">J</italic> = 4 (i.e. 16 variants can emerge) in a population of size <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 50 000. We compared the scenarios of cascading cross-immunity with <italic toggle="yes">c</italic> = 0.8 (<xref rid="RSIF20210648M2x1" ref-type="disp-formula">equation 2.1</xref>) and transmission rates the same for all variants (<xref rid="RSIF20210648F4" ref-type="fig">figure 4</xref><italic toggle="yes">a</italic>) with the same cascading cross-immunity as in <xref rid="RSIF20210648F4" ref-type="fig">figure 4</xref><italic toggle="yes">a</italic>, but now we allowed transmission to increase by 20% for each mutation difference between variant <italic toggle="yes">j</italic> and variant 0 (equation (<xref rid="RSIF20210648M2x1" ref-type="disp-formula">2.1</xref>); <italic toggle="yes">β</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub> = 0.3, <italic toggle="yes">j</italic> = 0, …, 15, <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM37"><mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> and <italic toggle="yes">β</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub>, <italic toggle="yes">j</italic> = 1, …, 15, determined using equation (<xref rid="RSIF20210648M2x4" ref-type="disp-formula">2.4</xref>)). Finally, we compared the scenario of cascading cross-immunity with that of escaping cross-immunity for the case <italic toggle="yes">c</italic> = 0.8 (<xref rid="RSIF20210648M2x2" ref-type="disp-formula">equation 2.2</xref>) and obtained the results provide in <xref rid="RSIF20210648F4" ref-type="fig">figure 4</xref><italic toggle="yes">c</italic>. The severity of each scenario is encapsulated in the total death statistic over the course of the 2-year simulation.
<fig position="float" id="RSIF20210648F4"><label>Figure 4<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label><caption><p>Total daily incidence (Δ<italic toggle="yes">I</italic> +: purple) and variant-specific prevalence (<italic toggle="yes">I</italic>: red) for a 16-variant epidemic in a population of size <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 50 000 (for other parameter values see <xref rid="RSIF20210648TB2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>) are plotted over a 2-year period for the three cases: (<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>) cascade cross-immunity <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM38"><mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> (i.e. all <italic toggle="yes">β</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub> = 0.3, <italic toggle="yes">j</italic> = 0, …, 15), (<italic toggle="yes">b</italic>) cascade cross-immunity <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM39"><mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> and (<italic toggle="yes">c</italic>) escape cross-immunity (in the two latter cases <italic toggle="yes">β</italic><sub>0</sub> = 0.3, <italic toggle="yes">β</italic><sub>15</sub> = 0.622 and <italic toggle="yes">β</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub>, <italic toggle="yes">j</italic> = 1, …, 14, determined using equation (<xref rid="RSIF20210648M2x4" ref-type="disp-formula">2.4</xref>)). Variant number and corresponding binary representation as labelled in red for dominant or co-dominant variants (incidence at some point greater than 50 individuals per day) and grey for minor variants (incidence always less than 50 over the 2-year simulation). The order of emergence of dominant or co-dominant variants is labelled in green. Note that each panel has its own vertical scale but all plots are over 730 days (even in cases where the horizontal axis label go to 750).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsif20210648f04" position="float"/></fig></p>
                <p>Our primary observations comparing the results plotted in <xref rid="RSIF20210648F4" ref-type="fig">figure 4</xref><italic toggle="yes">a</italic>–<italic toggle="yes">c</italic> and other runs (not shown here) of the same scenarios using different runtime seeds, are the following:
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>—<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>In all three cases the initial variant, by construction, is 0 ≡ (0, 0, 0, 0). In our three scenarios, this variant was followed by chance by the emergence of variant 8 ≡ (1, 0, 0, 0), but this is common to all three scenarios because they use the same sequence of pseudo random numbers in their simulations. Using different runtime seeds, however, leads variants other than variant 8 emerging to replace variant 0. Thus, the mutant identity (i.e. its binary representation) of the variant to first emerge is somewhat random, but it is going to be influenced by having different transmission values for each variant (scenarios (<italic toggle="yes">b</italic>) and (<italic toggle="yes">c</italic>)), as well as the possibility of an idealized escape mutation (scenario (<italic toggle="yes">c</italic>)).</p></list-item><list-item><label>—<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>We expect variants that have an idealized escape mutation to emerge early, as is the case in scenario (c) in which variants 8–15 have the idealized escape mutation. In particular, in <xref rid="RSIF20210648F4" ref-type="fig">figure 4</xref><italic toggle="yes">c</italic>, we see that the second to fourth variants to emerge all have the idealized escape mutation (i.e. variant 8 then 14 and then 15), and finally variant 6 ≡ (0, 1, 1, 0) emerges because of the cross-immunity between all variants with the idealized escape mutation finally comes into play.</p></list-item><list-item><label>—<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>When <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic> &gt; 0, the variants with the higher values of <italic toggle="yes">β</italic> come to dominate, though they take time to emerge. In our cascading cross-immunity case with <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM40"><mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, the most transmissible of these (variant 15 ≡ (1, 1, 1, 1)) had yet to emerge within the simulated 2-year period. The existence of the idealized escape mutation, however, does facilitate the emergence of variant 15 at the beginning of the second year (<xref rid="RSIF20210648F4" ref-type="fig">figure 4</xref><italic toggle="yes">c</italic>). Another run of this scenario (runtime seed = 1; results not shown here) has variant 15 emerging very early (around day 120). Furthermore, due to the effects of cross-immunity, this variant was replaced by variant 11 ≡ (1, 0, 1, 1) around days 450–500. Variant 15, however, as result of waning and cross-immunity effects, reemerges again around day 600, with variant 11 declining over the last three months of the second year.</p></list-item></list></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3c">
                <label>3.3<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <title>Vaccination rollout</title>
                <sec id="s3c1">
                  <label>3.3.1<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                  <title>Single valency vaccinations</title>
                  <p>As illustrations of potential issues associated with the design and implementation of vaccination programs, we first considered vaccinating individuals in a population of 100 000 subject to an epidemic involving a single variant of the pathogen. We note that in a population of <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 100 000 individuals, a vaccination rate of <italic toggle="yes">v</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) = 0.001 involves vaccinating an average of 100 individuals per day with daily variation following a binomial distribution (i.e. a standard deviation of just under 10 individuals per day).</p>
                  <p>Rollout of our vaccination program began on day 366 after the start of the outbreak and ran for 2 years beyond that to day 1100 (<xref rid="RSIF20210648F5" ref-type="fig">figure 5</xref>). Such scenarios place us within the context of the COVID-19 epidemic because vaccinations were only available from around the second year onwards. In our first two scenarios, we selected individuals, respectively, at rates 0.1% (<italic toggle="yes">v</italic> = 0.001) and 0.2% (<italic toggle="yes">v</italic> = 0.002) of the population each day (<xref rid="RSIF20210648F5" ref-type="fig">figure 5</xref><italic toggle="yes">a</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">b</italic>). Only individuals who had not been previously vaccinated were selected, but selection was otherwise random.
<fig position="float" id="RSIF20210648F5"><label>Figure 5<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label><caption><p>Incidence (Δ<italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sup>+</sup>: purple) is plotted over 3 years for the baseline run (parameters given in <xref rid="RSIF20210648TB1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref> with <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = 100 000) for the cases where vaccination rates <italic toggle="yes">v</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) (indicated by blue lines) are applied during the second and third years only to individuals not previously vaccinated but otherwise selected at random (for clarification, the average number of individuals vaccinated each day is 100<italic toggle="yes">v</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>)% with variation following a binomial distribution). Our first two simulations involve vaccination rollout programs in a single variant epidemic at vaccination rates (<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>) <italic toggle="yes">v</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) = 0.001 and (<italic toggle="yes">b</italic>) <italic toggle="yes">v</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) = 0.002 (respectively, 0.1% and 0.2%) of individuals not previously vaccinated, but otherwise chosen at random. Our second two simulations involve vaccination rollout programs in a 16-variant epidemic, both at vaccination rates <italic toggle="yes">v</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) = 0.002, involving (<italic toggle="yes">c</italic>) individuals not previously vaccinated and (<italic toggle="yes">d</italic>) a bivalent adaptive vaccination program in which previously vaccinated individuals could be vaccinated again with a new valency vaccine, as described in the text.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsif20210648f05" position="float"/></fig></p>
                  <p>Additionally, we simulated a 16-variant scenario in which individuals were vaccinated at against variant 0 at rate <italic toggle="yes">v</italic> = 0.002 (<xref rid="RSIF20210648F5" ref-type="fig">figure 5</xref><italic toggle="yes">c</italic>). Again, individuals were selected at random from the set of those who had not been previously vaccinated. By vaccinating individuals against variant 0, some immunity was conferred against variants 1–7 through cross-immunity relationships according to the Escaping <bold>C</bold> case with cross-immunity parameter <italic toggle="yes">c</italic> = 0.8 (<xref rid="RSIF20210648M2x2" ref-type="disp-formula">equation 2.2</xref>). In this scenario, variants 8–15 contain the idealized escape mutation.</p>
                  <p>Our focal question with regard to the first two scenarios was: What vaccination level is needed to extinguish the epidemic in the population encompassed by the vaccination rollouts for the populations concerned? From these two simulations (<xref rid="RSIF20210648F5" ref-type="fig">figure 5</xref><italic toggle="yes">a</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">b</italic>), we see that vaccination rate <italic toggle="yes">v</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) = 0.001 was insufficient to eliminate the pathogen from the population, while <italic toggle="yes">v</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) = 0.002 was able to eliminate the pathogen within 10 months from the start of the vaccination rollout. Furthermore, in the first of these simulations (<xref rid="RSIF20210648F5" ref-type="fig">figure 5</xref><italic toggle="yes">a</italic>), we see a resurgence of incidence in year three, which implies that the effects of waning immunity in this case are essentially ‘outrunning the vaccination rate.’</p>
                  <p>Our focal question with regard to a comparison of scenarios two and three (<xref rid="RSIF20210648F5" ref-type="fig">figure 5</xref><italic toggle="yes">b</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">c</italic>) was: does the vaccination rate <italic toggle="yes">v</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) = 0.002, which was able to exterminate the outbreak in the 1-variant case, remain able to exterminate the outbreak in the 16-variant case when an idealized escape mutation is involved? The answer to this question from the observed incidence curve (<xref rid="RSIF20210648F5" ref-type="fig">figure 5</xref><italic toggle="yes">c</italic>) is a resounding no. In fact, the total death rate over the 3-year period rose from 0.13% of the population (1336 individuals) to 0.42% of the population (4235 individuals).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s3c2">
                  <label>3.3.2<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                  <title>Adaptive bivalent vaccinations</title>
                  <p>With the emergence of new variants, the possibility exists to modify vaccines to contain or induce the production of antigens that directly target the variant in question (i.e. rather than through cross-immunity that arises when a related variant is the direct target) [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Furthermore, it is possible for vaccines to be multivalent in terms of directly targeting more than one variant at time [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. In our third vaccination scenario, a univalent vaccine applied at a rate <italic toggle="yes">v</italic> = 0.002 failed to bring a multivariant epidemic under control. Thus we were motivated to explore a scenario to see what would happen with a bivalent vaccine that was implemented adaptively in the sense of its two valencies following the two dominant variants.</p>
                  <p>In the specific vaccination rollout program that we employed in our fourth simulation, we did not account for logistical, production and variant monitoring constraints. Such constraints, of course, exist and vary across locations and populations: in real applications, they need to be taken into account. The program we employed assumes that we are able to alter the valency of the vaccination used every 15 days, based on an ability to identify the two variants that are most prevalent at each of these successive 15-day-apart observation points (from day 365 to day 1085, which is the start of the last 15-day period ending just prior to the start of day 1100). If only one variant had an incidence exceeding 9 individuals on an observation day, then the vaccination applied over the next 15-day interval was monovalent for the dominant variant, otherwise it was bivalent for the two variants that had the highest incidence on that observation day.</p>
                  <p>As with the non-adaptive vaccination rollouts, individuals were selected at random from a pool that had previously not been vaccinated with the particular valency-specific vaccine (either bivalent or monovalent). However, in the bivalent vaccine case, if an individual had previously been vaccinated to only one of the two variants defining the latest vaccine, then these individuals were incorporated into the vaccination pool from which individuals were randomly selected for vaccination. If such individuals were selected then the start of the waning time relating to the previous vaccination was reset to start anew. Thus, with this program, it is possible for individuals to be vaccinated more than once.</p>
                  <p>The results of this simulation are depicted in <xref rid="RSIF20210648F5" ref-type="fig">figure 5</xref><italic toggle="yes">d</italic>, where we see that this vaccination program is much more effective in preventing deaths than the monovalent variant 0 program applied to the same 16-variant epidemic at the same vaccination rate in <xref rid="RSIF20210648F5" ref-type="fig">figure 5</xref><italic toggle="yes">c</italic> (total deaths are 4235 in the former versus 2145 in the latter case). The valencies of the vaccine applied during each new 15-day period are listed in <xref rid="RSIF20210648TB4" ref-type="table">table 4</xref>. We note that the monovalent case involves considerably fewer vaccinations because of the ‘no revaccination with the same vaccine’ restriction in our rollout program. In particular, over 2 years of vaccinating at a 0.2% rate per day, all individuals are vaccinated in the case of <xref rid="RSIF20210648F5" ref-type="fig">figure 5</xref><italic toggle="yes">c</italic> by day 859, while in the case of <xref rid="RSIF20210648F5" ref-type="fig">figure 5</xref><italic toggle="yes">d</italic> revaccinations kept occurring as individuals who have not previously been vaccinated to one of the focal variants were revaccinated. Even in this adaptive rollout, however, the epidemic was only substantially lowered rather than completely extinguished. The latter event for the set of parameters used in our simulation requires a somewhat higher vaccination rate than 0.2% per day; or, perhaps it requires lower rates of waning immunity, higher cross-immunity rates, or the lack of an idealized escape mutation. All of these effects can be demonstrated through the selection of appropriate parameter values, but the specifics are only relevant when the model is applied in a real-world situation.
<table-wrap position="float" id="RSIF20210648TB4"><label>Table 4<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label><caption><p>Valency of adaptive vaccination over the interval 365 to 1100 days.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">time (days)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">valency</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(365, 470)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(9, 14)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(470, 530)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(13, 14)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(530, 680)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(13, 15)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(680, 740)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(15)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(740, 905)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(10, 15)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(905, 1025)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(10, 12)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1025, 1070)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(12, 15)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(1070, 1100)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">(15)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s4">
              <label>4<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>The amount of structure and data needed in complex biological systems’ models depends on the questions that these models have been formulated to address [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="RSIF20210648C14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. In this paper, we steered away from making specific predictions—because universal solutions are not always locally applicable. Rather, we focused on gaining insights into incidence patterns that can be expected when contacts are adaptive rather than fixed, multiple variants may emerge (typically sequentially over time), and open versus adaptive uni- and multivalent vaccination programs are implemented to try to eliminate local pandemics. Analyses that incorporate more complexity in the hopes of attaining greater realism, such as adding heterogeneity related to age and spatial structures, as well as behavioural and social groups, require data that are specific to a local population (town, city, county or small country, etc.). Such elaborations are only worth incorporating when the study relates to a real world system supported by adequate data (the latter related to the complexity of the question that needs to be addressed, as discussed elsewhere [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]).</p>
              <p>In the future, we hope to release versions of our RAMP that include both demographic (e.g. age, job, or state-of-health categories) and spatial structures (e.g.using metapopulations/network formulations). We stress, however, that the number of metapopulation nodes and demographic categories leads to a quadratic proliferation of parameters because transmission modifications by demographic-category pairs and metapopulation-nodal pairs need to be included through the elements of mixing matrices [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="RSIF20210648C43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>].</p>
              <p>Beyond these elaborations, structure can be added to address other salient issues. One such issue would be to obtain a better understanding of the role informational delays may play in producing the type of incidence waves that have been observed over the course of the COVID-19 pandemic (and as we have modelled in [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]). Such delays would lead to contact rates containing a time-lag rather than depending only on current prevalence levels. We might also spend more time deconstructing the relative importance of such time delays versus the emergence of more transmissible variants in accounting for these waves.</p>
              <p>Beyond gaining a deeper understanding of some of the mechanisms responsible for the incidence patterns observed among local epidemics of the COVID-19 pandemic, a second and primary purpose of our paper is to present our M-SEIR RAMP as a platform that others may use to address issues of concern to them in formulating policies to manage local COVID-19 epidemics. This also has the advantage of providing an exemplar of our novel RAMP concept and the methods we used to construct it. At this time, the primary value of our M-SEIR RAMP itself may be in testing various vaccination strategies as they relate to variant emergence [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Clearly, such applications would require more specific variant-related information on the comparative transmissibility <italic toggle="yes">β</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub>, virulence <italic toggle="yes">α</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub>, shedding (<inline-formula><mml:math id="IM41"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>ζ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>), environmental persistence (<inline-formula><mml:math id="IM42"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>η</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>) and within- host replication rates (<italic toggle="yes">λ</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub>) of newly emerging variants.</p>
              <p>Equally important, though, in evaluating the impacts of vaccination strategies on local epidemics is obtaining variant-specific immunity and cross-immunity data. This includes waning rates, which we have not made variant specific. Our model, however, could be generalized to include variant-specific waning rates represented by the parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM43"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">half</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula> (electronic supplementary material, equation (A.6)). It also includes information for characterization of the elements <italic toggle="yes">c</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">j</italic>ℓ</sub> of the cross-immunity matrix <bold>C</bold> (i.e. a generalization that renders equation (<xref rid="RSIF20210648M2x1" ref-type="disp-formula">2.1</xref>) redundant). Models are sorely needed to explore multivariant dynamics, particularly the epidemiological properties regarding shedding, environmental persistence, transmission, mutation and within-host replication rates. These processes, acting together, determine the relative success of different variants and their actual impact on the severity of epidemics and the nature of vaccination programs needed to suppress them.</p>
              <p>Making our model both location- and variant-specific could be undertaken using methods, such as appropriate complexity modelling [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="RSIF20210648C14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], designed to enhance the relevance of models. Furthermore, in some cases, it may be useful to add spatial or age-structure information to our M-SEIR or include a contact network [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], which itself may contain spatial or refined class category (e.g. age or work categories) information. In addition, our current implementation represents variant differences in terms of <italic toggle="yes">J</italic> loci with two alleles (denoted by 0 and 1, respectively) at each locus. A more realistic representation of the genetic basis of variant differences may involve genetic representations in which several alleles are possible at each locus. Furthermore, the loci themselves may represent relevant molecular structures such as epitopes.</p>
              <p>An advantage of our RAMP design features is that they provide a framework for elaborating or simplifying model details in the pursuit of different questions at various points in a pandemic. For example, suppose we are interested in pursuing inferences regarding the drivers of variant evolution at various stages of the pandemic. We may first want to address questions relating to pandemic behaviour, driven by mutations that increase transmissibility. This is what actually happened with the appearance of the SARS‐CoV‐2 D614G and the alpha variants. A year or so into the pandemic, however, we may then want to explore processes that give rise to immunity-escaping variants. This, again, is what happened in reality. Our RAMP formulation gives us the flexibility to change the model part way through a pandemic. In particular, we can then test which among a set of alternative reinfection processes is most likely to produce an escape mutation once reinfection begins to occur on a substantial scale. By configuring model drivers so that we first have a relatively simple evolutionary process and then switch to more complex evolutionary processes, our RAMP design facilitates comparing several competing explanations of observed patterns of variant emergence at different stages of a pandemic.</p>
              <p>Although cross-immunity and immune waning are entangled in our immunity modifier functions (i.e. <italic toggle="yes">ϕ</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ij</italic></sub>; see electronic supplementary material, equation (A.8)), cross-neutralization data can be used to estimate the cross and waning immunity parameters using appropriate methods [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Such data are becoming more widely available through the application of improved serological and genetic methods [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="RSIF20210648C47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,<xref rid="RSIF20210648C48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Variant and cross neutralizing studies bring up a much neglected issue, which is the effect of dose (number of pathogens involved in the initial infection, also known as viral load) on the severity of the infection. Furthermore, dose affects both the probability of host invasion (in the context of transmission), as well as mutational rates once host invasion has occurred. Effective dose differs from the questions of the number of vaccine doses (typically one versus two) versus the antigen or virus-like particle load in each dose [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. In the context of vaccination, both these issues and the technology used to produce the vaccine [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] may well have an impact on waning immunity rates and cross-immunity values. Thus, the parameter values used in the model should ultimately be vaccine-specific, once vaccine-specific waning data have been obtained.</p>
              <p>In the coming years, as we obtain more information on the nature of waning and cross-immunity to different variants of SARS-CoV-2, not to mention the vaccines as well, it will become more apparent to us whether or not COVID-19 will settle into global endemicity [<xref rid="RSIF20210648C32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="RSIF20210648C50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] and require periodic vaccinations to combat new variants, as they arise over time. If this is the case, then constant vigilance and a well-designed vaccination program with respect to vaccinating the young and implementing booster vaccinations with appropriate variant-valency will become the order of the day. Additionally, we anticipate extending our M-SEIR RAMP to include RAMs designed to compute the optimal time to administer vaccine booster shots of the same or different variant valencies. Implementation of these RAMs can play a decisive role in the rational design of effective and efficient COVID-19 vaccination programs worldwide. The need for efficacy is made apparent from the fact that our simulations suggest that it may be harder than currently anticipated to eliminate COVID-19 using non-adaptive vaccination programs.</p>
              <p>Finally, our M-SEIR RAMP, with its RAMs, driver scripts and ability to be integrated with R and other software platforms and a JavaScript simulation driver window, provides the first example of a new concept in model implementation that facilitates model sharing and easy modification by users other than the original developers. We believe such platforms can come to play an important role not only in disease modelling, but in all fields of research that rely on models for comprehensive analyses of the behaviour of systems of interest.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgements</title>
              <p>We thank the reviewers for comments that helped improve this paper.</p>
            </ack>
            <sec id="s5">
              <title>Ethics</title>
              <p>W.M.G. and R.S. are two of three owners of Numerus Inc., which is responsible for developing and maintaining the RAMP presented in this study.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s6">
              <title>Data accessibility</title>
              <p>This article has no additional data.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s7">
              <title>Authors' contributions</title>
              <p>J.S.K. and C.P.S. initiated the project, provided feedback on early drafts and participated in discussions. W.M.G. designed and formulated the M-SEIR IBM model, drafted the manuscript, ran simulations and produced the figures. R.S. designed and built the RAMP platform and wrote the code and informational text. L.L.V. checked all the mathematical equations and code. Both R.S. and L.L.V. contributed to the structure of the manuscript. All authors contributed to editing and adding text as needed.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s8">
              <title>Competing interests</title>
              <p>W.M.G. and R.S. are two of three owners of Numerus Inc., which is responsible for developing and maintaining the RAMP presented in this study.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s9">
              <title>Funding</title>
              <p>This work was funded in part by NSF grant no. 2032264 (PI: W.M.G.).</p>
            </sec>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C1">
                <label>1<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kermack</surname><given-names>WO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McKendrick</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>1927</year><article-title>A contribution to the mathematical theory of epidemics</article-title>. <source>Proc. R. Soc. Lond. A</source><volume><bold>115</bold></volume>, <fpage>700</fpage>-<lpage>721</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspa.1927.0118</pub-id>)</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C2">
                <label>2<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hethcote</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2000</year><article-title>The mathematics of infectious diseases</article-title>. <source>SIAM Rev.</source><volume><bold>42</bold></volume>, <fpage>599</fpage>-<lpage>653</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1137/S0036144500371907</pub-id>)</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C3">
                <label>3<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Koelle</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cobey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grenfell</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pascual</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2006</year><article-title>Epochal evolution shapes the phylodynamics of interpandemic influenza A (H<sub>3</sub>N<sub>2</sub>) in humans</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume><bold>314</bold></volume>, <fpage>1898</fpage><lpage>1903</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1132745</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17185596</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C4">
                <label>4<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gilchrist</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2002</year><article-title>Modeling host–parasite coevolution: a nested approach based on mechanistic models</article-title>. <source>J. Theor. Biol.</source><volume><bold>218</bold></volume>, <fpage>289</fpage>-<lpage>308</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/jtbi.2002.3076</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12381431</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C5">
                <label>5<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Balcan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gonçalves</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ramasco</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Colizza</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vespignani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2010</year><article-title>Modeling the spatial spread of infectious diseases: the global epidemic and mobility computational model</article-title>. <source>J. Comput. Sci.</source><volume><bold>1</bold></volume>, <fpage>132</fpage>-<lpage>145</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jocs.2010.07.002</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21415939</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C6">
                <label>6<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Keeling</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>1999</year><article-title>The effects of local spatial structure on epidemiological invasions</article-title>. <source>Proc. R. Soc. Lond. B</source><volume><bold>266</bold></volume>, <fpage>859</fpage>-<lpage>867</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.1999.0716</pub-id>)</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C7">
                <label>7<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Keeling</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eames</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2005</year><article-title>Networks and epidemic models</article-title>. <source>J. R. Soc. Interface</source><volume><bold>2</bold></volume>, <fpage>295</fpage>-<lpage>307</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsif.2005.0051</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16849187</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C8">
                <label>8<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beauchemin</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perelson</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2009</year><article-title>Agent-based modeling of host–pathogen systems: the successes and challenges</article-title>. <source>Inf. Sci.</source><volume><bold>179</bold></volume>, <fpage>1379</fpage>-<lpage>1389</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ins.2008.11.012</pub-id>)</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C9">
                <label>9<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cuevas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2020</year><article-title>An agent-based model to evaluate the COVID-19 transmission risks in facilities</article-title>. <source>Comput. Biol. Med.</source><volume><bold>121</bold></volume>, <fpage>103827</fpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.compbiomed.2020.103827</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32568667</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C10">
                <label>10<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rambaut</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McCrone</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pybus</surname><given-names>OG</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2020</year><article-title>A dynamic nomenclature proposal for SARS-CoV-2 lineages to assist genomic epidemiology</article-title>. <source>Nat. Microbiol.</source><volume><bold>5</bold></volume>, <fpage>1403</fpage>-<lpage>1407</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41564-020-0770-5</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32669681</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C11">
                <label>11<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Koopman</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Getz</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2021</year><article-title>Modeling the population effects of escape mutations in SARS-CoV-2 to guide vaccination strategies</article-title>. <source>Epidemics</source><volume><bold>36</bold></volume>, <fpage>100484</fpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.epidem.2021.100484</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34375814</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C12">
                <label>12<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Aslaner</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aslaner</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gökçek</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Benli</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yıldız</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2021</year><article-title>The effect of chronic diseases, age and gender on morbidity and mortality of COVID-19 infection</article-title>. <source>Iran. J. Public Health</source><volume><bold>50</bold></volume>, <fpage>721</fpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18502/ijph.v50i4.5996</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34183921</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C13">
                <label>13<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Getz</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mgbara</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2019</year><article-title>Adequacy of SEIR models when epidemics have spatial structure: Ebola in Sierra Leone</article-title>. <source>Phil. Trans. R. Soc. B</source><volume><bold>374</bold></volume>, <fpage>20180282</fpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2018.0282</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31056043</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C14">
                <label>14<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eppinga</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Passalacqua</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Getz</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2016</year><article-title>Appropriate complexity landscape modeling</article-title>. <source>Earth Sci. Rev.</source><volume><bold>160</bold></volume>, <fpage>111</fpage>-<lpage>130</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.earscirev.2016.06.016</pub-id>)</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C15">
                <label>15<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Getz</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vissat</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Horvitz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2021</year><article-title>A versatile web app for identifying the drivers of COVID-19 epidemics</article-title>. <source>J. Transl. Med.</source><volume><bold>19</bold></volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>20</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12967-021-02736-2</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33397399</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C16">
                <label>16<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rahimi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gandomi</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2021</year><article-title>A review on COVID-19 forecasting models</article-title>. <source>Neural Comput. Appl.</source>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>11</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C17">
                <label>17<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chretien</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>George</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shaman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chitale</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2014</year><article-title>Influenza forecasting in human populations: a scoping review</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source><volume><bold>9</bold></volume>, <fpage>e94130</fpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0094130</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24714027</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C18">
                <label>18<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Getz</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></string-name></person-group><italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic><year>2015</year><article-title>Tactics and strategies for managing Ebola outbreaks and the salience of immunization</article-title>. <source>Comput. Math. Methods Med.</source><volume><bold>2015</bold></volume>, <fpage>736507</fpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2015/736507</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25755674</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C19">
                <label>19<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>PZ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bobrovitz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Premji</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koopmans</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fisman</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>FX</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2021</year><article-title>Heterogeneity in transmissibility and shedding SARS-CoV-2 via droplets and aerosols</article-title>. <source>eLife</source><volume><bold>10</bold></volume>, <fpage>e65774</fpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.65774</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33861198</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C20">
                <label>20<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>van Doremalen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name></person-group><italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic><year>2020</year><article-title>Aerosol and surface stability of SARS-CoV-2 as compared with SARS-CoV-1</article-title>. <source>N. Engl. J. Med.</source><volume><bold>382</bold></volume>, <fpage>1564</fpage>-<lpage>1567</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMc2004973</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32182409</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C21">
                <label>21<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Maginnis</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2018</year><article-title>Virus–receptor interactions: the key to cellular invasion</article-title>. <source>J. Mol. Biol.</source><volume><bold>430</bold></volume>, <fpage>2590</fpage>-<lpage>2611</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmb.2018.06.024</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29924965</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C22">
                <label>22<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Challen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brooks-Pollock</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Read</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dyson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tsaneva-Atanasova</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Danon</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2021</year><article-title>Risk of mortality in patients infected with SARS-CoV-2 variant of concern 202012/1: matched cohort study</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source><volume><bold>372</bold></volume>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.n579</pub-id>)</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C23">
                <label>23<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sariol</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perlman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2020</year><article-title>Lessons for COVID-19 immunity from other coronavirus infections</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source><volume><bold>53</bold></volume>, <fpage>248</fpage>-<lpage>263</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2020.07.005</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32717182</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C24">
                <label>24<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Eguia</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stevens-Ayers</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kelnhofer-Millevolte</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Greninger</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Englund</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boeckh</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2021</year><article-title>A human coronavirus evolves antigenically to escape antibody immunity</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog.</source><volume><bold>17</bold></volume>, <fpage>e1009453</fpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1009453</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33831132</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C25">
                <label>25<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Alizon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luciani</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Regoes</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2011</year><article-title>Epidemiological and clinical consequences of within-host evolution</article-title>. <source>Trends Microbiol.</source><volume><bold>19</bold></volume>, <fpage>24</fpage>-<lpage>32</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tim.2010.09.005</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21055948</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C26">
                <label>26<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Fenichel</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></string-name></person-group><italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic><year>2011</year><article-title>Adaptive human behavior in epidemiological models</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><volume><bold>108</bold></volume>, <fpage>6306</fpage>-<lpage>6311</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1011250108</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21444809</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C27">
                <label>27<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="std"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gozzi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bajardi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perra</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2021</year><comment>The importance of non-pharmaceutical interventions during the COVID-19 vaccine rollout. <italic toggle="yes">PLOS Comp. Biol.</italic>
<bold>17</bold>, e1009346. (</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1009346</pub-id>)</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C28">
                <label>28<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group><italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic><year>2021</year><article-title>Status report on COVID-19 vaccines development</article-title>. <source>Curr. Infect. Dis. Rep.</source><volume><bold>23</bold></volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>12</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11908-021-00752-3</pub-id>)</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C29">
                <label>29<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jefferies</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kraaijeveld</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2011</year><article-title>Risk of red queen dynamics in pneumococcal vaccine strategy</article-title>. <source>Trends Microbiol.</source><volume><bold>19</bold></volume>, <fpage>377</fpage>-<lpage>381</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tim.2011.06.001</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21763141</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C30">
                <label>30<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Willem</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Verelst</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bilcke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hens</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beutels</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2017</year><article-title>Lessons from a decade of individual-based models for infectious disease transmission: a systematic review (2006–2015)</article-title>. <source>BMC Infect. Dis.</source><volume><bold>17</bold></volume>, <fpage>612</fpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-017-2699-8</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28893198</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C31">
                <label>31<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chowell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sattenspiel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bansal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Viboud</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2016</year><article-title>Mathematical models to characterize early epidemic growth: a review</article-title>. <source>Phys. Life Rev.</source><volume><bold>18</bold></volume>, <fpage>66</fpage>-<lpage>97</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plrev.2016.07.005</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27451336</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C32">
                <label>32<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lavine</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bjornstad</surname><given-names>ON</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Antia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2021</year><article-title>Immunological characteristics govern the transition of COVID-19 to endemicity</article-title>. <source>Science</source><volume><bold>371</bold></volume>, <fpage>741</fpage>-<lpage>745</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abe6522</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33436525</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C33">
                <label>33<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Koyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weeraratne</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Snowdon</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Parida</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2020</year><article-title>Emergence of drift variants that may affect COVID-19 vaccine development and antibody treatment</article-title>. <source>Pathogens</source><volume><bold>9</bold></volume>, <fpage>324</fpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/pathogens9050324</pub-id>)</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C34">
                <label>34<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Getz</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lloyd-Smith</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2006</year><article-title>Basic methods for modeling the invasion and spread of contagious diseases</article-title>. <source>DIMACS Ser. Discrete Math. Theor. Comput. Sci.</source><volume><bold>71</bold></volume>, <fpage>87</fpage>-<lpage>109</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1090/dimacs/071</pub-id>)</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C35">
                <label>35<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>McCallum</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barlow</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hone</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2001</year><article-title>How should pathogen transmission be modelled?</article-title><source>Trends Ecol. Evol.</source><volume><bold>16</bold></volume>, <fpage>295</fpage>-<lpage>300</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0169-5347(01)02144-9</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11369107</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C36">
                <label>36<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>May</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>1982</year><article-title>Coevolution of hosts and parasites</article-title>. <source>Parasitology</source><volume><bold>85</bold></volume>, <fpage>411</fpage>-<lpage>426</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0031182000055360</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6755367</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C37">
                <label>37<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Getz</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Muellerklein</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tallam</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2018</year><article-title>Modeling epidemics: a primer and numerus model builder implementation</article-title>. <source>Epidemics</source><volume><bold>25</bold></volume>, <fpage>9</fpage>-<lpage>19</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.epidem.2018.06.001</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30017895</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C38">
                <label>38<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Getz</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lyons</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sippl-Swezey</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2015</year><article-title>Panmictic and clonal evolution on a single patchy resource produces polymorphic foraging guilds</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source><volume><bold>10</bold></volume>, <fpage>e0133732</fpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0133732</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26274613</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C39">
                <label>39<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hussein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Toraih</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Elshazli</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fawzy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Houghton</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tatum</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Killackey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kandil</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duchesne</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2021</year><article-title>Meta-analysis on serial intervals and reproductive rates for SARS-CoV-2</article-title>. <source>Ann. Surg.</source><volume><bold>273</bold></volume>, <fpage>416</fpage>-<lpage>423</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/SLA.0000000000004400</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33214421</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C40">
                <label>40<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khosrawipour</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kocbach</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ichii</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bania</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khosrawipour</surname><given-names>V</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2021</year><article-title>Evaluating the massive underreporting and undertesting of COVID-19 cases in multiple global epicenters</article-title>. <source>Pulmonology</source><volume><bold>27</bold></volume>, <fpage>110</fpage>-<lpage>115</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pulmoe.2020.05.015</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32540223</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C41">
                <label>41<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Karlinsky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kobak</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2021</year><article-title>Tracking excess mortality across countries during the COVID-19 pandemic with the world mortality dataset</article-title>. <source>eLife</source><volume><bold>10</bold></volume>, <fpage>e69336</fpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.69336</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34190045</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C42">
                <label>42<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hartfield</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alizon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2013</year><article-title>Introducing the outbreak threshold in epidemiology</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog.</source><volume><bold>9</bold></volume>, <fpage>e1003277</fpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1003277</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23785276</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C43">
                <label>43<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Del Valle</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hyman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hethcote</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Eubank</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2007</year><article-title>Mixing patterns between age groups in social networks</article-title>. <source>Soc. Netw.</source><volume><bold>29</bold></volume>, <fpage>539</fpage>-<lpage>554</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.socnet.2007.04.005</pub-id>)</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C44">
                <label>44<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="std"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Getz</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vissat</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Salter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2020</year><comment>A contact-explicit COVID-19 epidemic and response assessment model. <italic toggle="yes">medRxiv</italic></comment>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2020.07.16.20155812</pub-id>)</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C45">
                <label>45<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Greaney</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name></person-group><italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic><year>2021</year><article-title>Complete mapping of mutations to the SARS-CoV-2 spike receptor-binding domain that escape antibody recognition</article-title>. <source>Cell Host Microbe</source><volume><bold>29</bold></volume>, <fpage>44</fpage>-<lpage>57</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2020.11.007</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33259788</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C46">
                <label>46<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Funk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>King</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2020</year><article-title>Choices and trade-offs in inference with infectious disease models</article-title>. <source>Epidemics</source><volume><bold>30</bold></volume>, <fpage>100383</fpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.epidem.2019.100383</pub-id>)</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C47">
                <label>47<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Suthar</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></string-name></person-group><italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic><year>2020</year><article-title>Rapid generation of neutralizing antibody responses in COVID-19 patients</article-title>. <source>Cell Rep. Med.</source><volume><bold>1</bold></volume>, <fpage>100040</fpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.xcrm.2020.100040</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32835303</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C48">
                <label>48<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Muruato</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fontes-Garfias</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garcia-Blanco</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Menachery</surname><given-names>VD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2020</year><article-title>A high-throughput neutralizing antibody assay for COVID-19 diagnosis and vaccine evaluation</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun.</source><volume><bold>11</bold></volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>6</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-17892-0</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31911652</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C49">
                <label>49<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jeyanathan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Afkhami</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smaill</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lichty</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2020</year><article-title>Immunological considerations for COVID-19 vaccine strategies</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Immunol.</source><volume><bold>20</bold></volume>, <fpage>615</fpage>-<lpage>632</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41577-020-00434-6</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32887954</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSIF20210648C50">
                <label>50<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tkachenko</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maslov</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Elbanna</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weiner</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goldenfeld</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2021</year><article-title>Time-dependent heterogeneity leads to transient suppression of the COVID-19 epidemic, not herd immunity</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><volume><bold>118</bold></volume>, <fpage>e2015972118</fpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2015972118</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33833080</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
