<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-03-11T00:50:14Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8375363" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8375363</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-08-19</datestamp>
        <setSpec>lrhwp</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.xsd" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Lancet Reg Health West Pac</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Lancet Reg Health West Pac</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>The Lancet Regional Health: Western Pacific</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2666-6065</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC8375363</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8375363</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">8375363</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34426804</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2666-6065(21)00165-6</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lanwpc.2021.100256</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100256</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Research Paper</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>COVID-19 vaccine strategies for Aotearoa New Zealand: a mathematical modelling study</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0001">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Nguyen</surname>
                    <given-names>Trung</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                  <xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">#</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0002">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Adnan</surname>
                    <given-names>Mehnaz</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                  <xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">#</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0003">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Nguyen</surname>
                    <given-names>Binh P</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">2</xref>
                  <xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">#</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0004">
                  <name>
                    <surname>de Ligt</surname>
                    <given-names>Joep</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0005">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Geoghegan</surname>
                    <given-names>Jemma L</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0006">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Dean</surname>
                    <given-names>Richard</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MSc</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0007">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Jefferies</surname>
                    <given-names>Sarah</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0008">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Baker</surname>
                    <given-names>Michael G</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MBChB</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">4</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0009">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Seah</surname>
                    <given-names>Winston KG</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>DrEng</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">5</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0010">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Sporle</surname>
                    <given-names>Andrew A</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MA(Hons)</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff0006" ref-type="aff">6</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0011">
                  <name>
                    <surname>French</surname>
                    <given-names>Nigel Peter</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff0007" ref-type="aff">7</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0012">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Murdoch</surname>
                    <given-names>David R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>MD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff0008" ref-type="aff">8</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0013">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Welch</surname>
                    <given-names>David</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <xref rid="aff0009" ref-type="aff">9</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0014">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Simpson</surname>
                    <given-names>Colin R</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <degrees>PhD</degrees>
                  <email>colin.simpson@vuw.ac.nz</email>
                  <xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">10</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff0011" ref-type="aff">11</xref>
                  <xref rid="cor0001" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label>Institute of Environmental Science and Research, New Zealand</aff>
                <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label>School of Mathematics and Statistics, Victoria University of Wellington, New Zealand</aff>
                <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label>Department of Microbiology and Immunology, University of Otago, New Zealand and Institute of Environmental Science and Research, New Zealand</aff>
                <aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label>Department of Public Health, University of Otago, New Zealand</aff>
                <aff id="aff0005"><label>5</label>School of Engineering and Computer Science, Victoria University of Wellington, New Zealand</aff>
                <aff id="aff0006"><label>6</label>Department of Statistics, The University of Auckland, New Zealand and iNZight Analytics Ltd</aff>
                <aff id="aff0007"><label>7</label>School of Veterinary Science, Massey University, New Zealand</aff>
                <aff id="aff0008"><label>8</label>Department of Pathology and Biomedical Science, University of Otago, New Zealand</aff>
                <aff id="aff0009"><label>9</label>School of Computer Science, The University of Auckland, New Zealand</aff>
                <aff id="aff0010"><label>10</label>School of Health, Wellington Faculty of Health, Victoria University of Wellington, Wellington, New Zealand</aff>
                <aff id="aff0011"><label>11</label>Usher Institute, The University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, United Kingdom</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor0001"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author: Prof. Colin R Simpson PhD, School of Health, Wellington Faculty of Health, Victoria University of Wellington, Wellington, New Zealand and Usher Institute, The University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, United Kingdom <email>colin.simpson@vuw.ac.nz</email></corresp>
                <fn id="fn1">
                  <label>#</label>
                  <p id="notep0001">These authors contributed equally</p>
                </fn>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>19</day>
                <month>8</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.-->
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <month>10</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>19</day>
                <month>8</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>15</volume>
              <elocation-id>100256</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>5</day>
                  <month>5</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>15</day>
                  <month>7</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>29</day>
                  <month>7</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2021 The Author(s). Published by Elsevier Ltd.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
                <copyright-holder/>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="abs0001">
                <title>Summary</title>
                <p><bold>Background:</bold> COVID-19 elimination measures, including border closures have been applied in New Zealand. We have modelled the potential effect of vaccination programmes for opening borders.</p>
                <p><bold>Methods:</bold> We used a deterministic age-stratified Susceptible, Exposed, Infectious, Recovered (SEIR) model. We minimised spread by varying the age-stratified vaccine allocation to find the minimum herd immunity requirements (the effective reproduction number R<sub>eff</sub>&lt;1 with closed borders) under various vaccine effectiveness (VE) scenarios and R<sub>0</sub> values. We ran two-year open-border simulations for two vaccine strategies: minimising R<sub>eff</sub> and targeting high-risk groups.</p>
                <p><bold>Findings:</bold> Targeting of high-risk groups will result in lower hospitalisations and deaths in most scenarios. Reaching the herd immunity threshold (HIT) with a vaccine of 90% VE against disease and 80% VE against infection requires at least 86•5% total population uptake for R<sub>0</sub>=4•5 (with high vaccination coverage for 30–49-year-olds) and 98•1% uptake for R<sub>0</sub>=6. In a two-year open-border scenario with 10 overseas cases daily and 90% total population vaccine uptake (including 0–15 year olds) with the same vaccine, the strategy of targeting high-risk groups is close to achieving HIT, with an estimated 11,400 total hospitalisations (peak 324 active and 36 new daily cases in hospitals), and 1,030 total deaths.</p>
                <p><bold>Interpretation:</bold> Targeting high-risk groups for vaccination will result in fewer hospitalisations and deaths with open borders compared to targeting reduced transmission. With a highly effective vaccine and a high total uptake, opening borders will result in increasing cases, hospitalisations, and deaths. Other public health and social measures will still be required as part of an effective pandemic response.</p>
                <p><bold>Funding:</bold> This project was funded by the Health Research Council [20/1018].</p>
                <p>
                  <bold>Research in context</bold>
                </p>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group id="keys0001">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>SARS-CoV-2</kwd>
                <kwd>COVID-19</kwd>
                <kwd>Vaccination</kwd>
                <kwd>Modelling</kwd>
                <kwd>Elimination</kwd>
                <kwd>Herd immunity threshold</kwd>
                <kwd>Vaccine effectiveness</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="sec0001">
              <title>Evidence before this study</title>
              <p id="para0002">We searched PubMed, medRxiv and SSRN for modelling studies using the term “COVID-19 vaccine AND model AND New Zealand”. We found one study by Bubar et al. which investigated age-related vaccine allocations to minimise the total deaths for countries without community transmission where total vaccination supply was limited to 50% of the population and found that direct vaccination of adults aged over 60 years nearly always reduced mortality. Moore et al. predicted a reproduction number of 1•58 after implementing vaccination in the UK and highlighted the risks of early relaxation of non-pharmaceutical interventions. Sandmann et al. also considered, in a 10-year simulation, the economic impact in the UK and suggested that with COVID-19 vaccination, small outbreaks could continue.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0002">
              <title>Added value of this study</title>
              <p id="para0003">To our knowledge, this is the first detailed COVID-19 vaccination programme modelling for Aotearoa New Zealand, a country with closed borders and a COVID-19 elimination strategy. We forecast the effect of strategies of minimising disease spread in the community and prioritisation of high-risk age groups. We modelled different vaccination programme strategies for the following health outcomes: number of cases, hospitalisations, and deaths over two years with open borders.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0003">
              <title>Implications of all the available evidence</title>
              <p id="para0004">To achieve the herd immunity threshold (HIT) (where R<sub>0</sub>=4•5), and limit community transmission (e.g. sporadic outbreaks) once borders are opened, a vaccine that has a vaccine effectiveness of 90% for disease prevention and 80% for infection reduction will require high vaccination coverage for 30–49-year-olds, and at least 86•5% total population uptake. A number of possible scenarios were modelled including where 10 overseas cases are introduced daily with open-borders and 90% total population vaccine uptake with a vaccine with VE of 90% for disease prevention and 80% for infection reduction, and prioritisation of high-risk groups for vaccination. In the two-year simulation, this scenario was forecasted to have 11,400 total hospitalisations (peak 324 active and 36 new daily cases in hospitals), and 1,030 total deaths. Where 0–11 year olds are not vaccinated and total population uptake is 80% (the maximum uptake is 84•9% and HIT is not achieved) there is an estimated 37,700 total hospitalisations (peak 2,980 active and 343 new daily cases in hospitals), and 3,120 total deaths. Other non-pharmaceutical interventions will still be required to sustain the pandemic response. These findings can support policy makers in New Zealand (including the Ministry of Health) to inform their vaccination programme and is generalisable to other countries with closed borders and elimination strategies to ensure optimal vaccination programmes.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0004">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p id="para0005">COVID-19 has caused widespread morbidity and more than 4•0 million deaths globally as of July 9<sup>th</sup>, 2021<xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> with extensive social and economic consequences.<xref rid="bib0002" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> To prevent COVID-19 outbreaks, New Zealand (NZ) adopted an early elimination strategy with non-pharmaceutical interventions, referred to as public health and social measures (PHSMs) in this paper.<xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0004" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref></p>
              <p id="para0006">PHSMs, such as border controls, lockdown measures, quarantine, and comprehensive testing, surveillance, and contact tracing, have led to the elimination of COVID-19 transmission in NZ, but there are expectations that NZ will begin to reopen its border once the vaccination programme has progressed. Opening borders without strict isolation will continuously introduce COVID-19 to the community. The NZ government is undertaking a vaccination programme<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> to protect NZ communities. Vaccination modelling can help anticipate potential public health outcomes based on different vaccine effectiveness (VE) reported in clinical trials<xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> and ‘real-world’ studies,<xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref> and vaccination programme strategies.<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> Estimates of the minimal vaccine coverage for herd-immunity with vaccines of different effectiveness, for instance, is needed. Vaccine allocation strategies should also take into account the potential ranges of VE in disease prevention (70–95%) and infection reduction (30–90%) from the first available vaccines including BNT162b2, mRNA-1273, and ChAdOx1 (AZD1222) vaccines.<xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref></p>
              <p id="para0007">The aim of this study was therefore to provide age-related optimisation and simulation results that can be used to design optimal vaccine programmes; including: i. achievement of HIT and, ii. if borders are open and cases of COVID-19 are introduced to the NZ community, minimisation of COVID-19 cases, hospitalisations and deaths. These include strategies to ensure maximum protection for Māori and Pasifika populations, who are at higher risk for hospitalisation and death from COVID-19.<xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref></p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0005">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <p id="para0008">We extended an age-stratified Susceptible, Exposed, Infectious, Recovered (SEIR) model<xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> with a presymptomatic phase to include vaccinated compartments (Supplemental Figure S1). The whole population is divided into eight 10-year age groups G={0–9,10–19,20–29…,60–69,70+}.</p>
              <p id="para0009">We assume that a vaccine has three effects: <italic>e<sub>i</sub></italic> is the reduction of infection in vaccinated people (i.e. susceptibility to infection), <italic>e<sub>d</sub></italic> is the VE for disease prevention (the default concept of VE and commonly used clinical endpoint in vaccine efficacy trials), and the third effect is reduction of infectiousness. The vaccine effect on infection reduces the susceptibility of vaccinated people by a factor <italic>e<sub>i</sub></italic> compared with unvaccinated people. Thus, if the susceptibility of an unimmunised person in an age group <italic>i</italic> is <italic>u<sub>i</sub></italic>, the susceptibility of a vaccinated person in the same age group is expected to be <inline-formula><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. <italic>e<sub>i</sub></italic> has a direct influence on the viral transmission. Likewise, the probability of developing clinical disease in vaccinated infected cases in age group <italic>i</italic> is <inline-formula><mml:math id="M2" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <italic>ρ<sub>i</sub></italic> is the probability of having clinical disease in unvaccinated infected cases. <italic>e<sub>d</sub></italic> is, thus, the effect of the vaccine on preventing disease in vaccinated individuals and corresponds to the reported vaccine efficacy and effectiveness.<xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref> The effect of the vaccine on the reduction of infectiousness reduces the probability of spreading SARS-CoV-2 in vaccinated individuals. A detailed description of the model can be found in the Supplementary Appendix S1.</p>
              <p id="para0010">In addition to <italic>e<sub>i</sub></italic>, another effect of vaccines that contributes to the change of the effective reproduction number R<sub>eff</sub> is the reduction of infectiousness in vaccinated infections.<xref rid="bib0017" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> This parameter is dependent on the reduction of viral shedding and/or symptoms (e.g., coughing and sneezing). In our model, it is considered that the reduction of infectiousness is a result of the reduction of clinical disease in vaccinated infections and the parameter <italic>f</italic> (Supplemental Table S1). This dependency is different from considering a constant reduction of infectiousness across all age groups, where different rates of symptom reduction does not influence the reduction of infectiousness in vaccinated infections. This model enables us to model the effect of <italic>e<sub>d</sub></italic> on the overall transmission (R<sub>eff</sub>) while analysing the vaccine effect on reducing infection (<italic>e<sub>i</sub></italic>).</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0006">
              <title>Model assumptions</title>
              <p id="para0011">Model assumptions included: i. For open-border modelling the behaviour of New Zealanders is as observed prior to Alert level 1 (without PHSMs). The average duration from illness onset to isolation without any intervention is 7•2 days;<xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> ii. age group sizes are constant in the open-border modelling; iii. infected, vaccinated people, without disease, have the same spreading capability as the infected asymptomatic/paucisymptomatic cases without vaccination; iv. the effectively immunised people, against either infection or disease, stay immunised with the same protection effect for the whole simulation period if they do not get re-infected. This can be interpreted as the waning vaccination effect (in the vaccinated group) being balanced by the reinforcement of the vaccination process during the simulation period. This assumption is to separate other effects from the vaccine distribution; v. vaccines are as effective for children and teenagers (age below 16) as they are for other tested age groups; vi. Māori and Pasifika populations have the same contact matrix as the whole of NZ.<xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> This assumption is, however, likely to underestimate the actual contact frequencies in this population<xref rid="bib0019" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> as Māori and Pasifika people live in larger households, have larger social networks (inter-dependent households, family, church etc), have a higher proportion of the population that are young, as well as a greater likelihood of being in high exposure risk occupations;<xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref> and vii. death rates (total rate and age-specific rates) are unchanged even when the active COVID-19 hospitalisations exceeds available NZ hospital capacity.<xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref></p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0007">
              <title>Data</title>
              <p id="para0012">We used COVID-19 case data reported in EpiSurv<xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref> from February 26<sup>th</sup> 2020 (when the first case was reported) to October 21<sup>st</sup>, 2020. COVID-19 hospitalisation rates for all age groups were inferred from recorded hospitalised cases in the national notifiable disease surveillance system, EpiSurv.<xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref> We assumed that Māori and Pasifika populations have twice the hospitalisation rates estimated from EpiSurv based on previous evidence.<xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> We used the estimated age-stratified infection fatality rates modelled by Verity et al.<xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> as the age-stratified death rates for the whole of NZ, and the rates modelled by Steyn et al.<xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> as the age-stratified death rates for Māori and Pasifika populations. We used the age distribution of imported cases as recorded in EpiSurv<xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref> as the age distribution of imported cases in the model (70.6% were aged 20-59 years). The susceptibility and clinical rates of COVID-19 for different ages were calculated using data from an age-stratified model published by Davies et al.<xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> A list of parameters with their source is shown in Supplemental Table S1.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0008">
              <title>Strategies and scenarios</title>
              <sec id="sec0009">
                <title>Vaccine effectiveness</title>
                <p id="para0013">We investigated vaccine scenarios that only one vaccine is used for the whole population regarding the NZ vaccine plan.<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> We analysed varying effects of the vaccine by introducing a parameter for the effectiveness on disease prevention, <italic>e</italic><sub><italic>d</italic></sub>, and a parameter for the effectiveness on infection reduction, <italic>e<sub>i</sub></italic>. We looked at minimum vaccine effectiveness with different uptake levels (from 60% to 100% coverage of total population) required to achieve HIT (R<sub>eff</sub>&lt;1) given the R<sub>0</sub> values of 2•5, 4•5, and 6.</p>
                <p id="para0014">We modelled VE (of disease prevention) in the range of 70–95%. VE of infection reduction is normally smaller than VE of disease prevention. Thus, the range of VE for infection reduction was 30% to 90% and was no greater than VE of disease prevention in all scenarios. Hereinafter, the effects of a vaccine with VE of disease prevention (<italic>e<sub>d</sub></italic>) and VE of infection reduction (<italic>e<sub>i</sub></italic>) is shortened to <italic>e<sub>d</sub></italic>/<italic>e<sub>i</sub></italic>% effectiveness for convenience. For instance, a vaccine with 95/70% effectiveness has 95% effectiveness for disease prevention and 70% effectiveness for infection reduction. The effectiveness of a vaccine is considered “uniform” when their effectiveness is equal across age groups, while the effectiveness is called “varied” when the vaccine effectiveness is reduced in older age groups. The current vaccination strategy in NZ focuses on two dose vaccination, rather than maximising the number of administrations of first dose. The second dose is administered at least 21 days after the first dose.<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0010">
                <title>Vaccine strategies with closed borders</title>
                <p id="para0015">In this study, we compared two vaccine strategies, where each could be implemented through one of the following optimisation criteria: (1) minimising the effective reproduction number or the spreading rate; and (2) minimising disease in the total high-risk population (risk for severe disease and deaths). The first strategy minimises the leading eigenvalue of the next generation matrix (i.e. R<sub>eff</sub>) or the spreading rate. This strategy requires minimum requirements for vaccine effectiveness and the total uptake to achieve HIT. Therefore, it is used to analyse the minimum herd immunity requirements. The total high-risk population in the second strategy can be estimated as <inline-formula><mml:math id="M3" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, which are the age-stratified susceptible populations (<italic>S<sub>i</sub></italic>) weighted by their mortality rates due to COVID-19 (<italic>d<sub>i</sub></italic>). This strategy begins with vaccination in the oldest groups, followed by the younger groups, because older groups are known to have higher risks for both severe disease and death.<xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> Hereafter, two strategies are referred to as the spread-minimising/minimise R<sub>eff</sub> strategy and the high-risk (group) targeting strategy respectively. A third strategy that balances between these two strategies is included in Supplemental Appendix S2.</p>
                <p id="para0016">Both strategies are assumed to be implemented with closed borders until a certain uptake level is reached, i.e. from 60 to 100% total population coverage (<xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). A vaccination uptake of 80–90% of the NZ population requires vaccinating individuals aged under 16 and a higher rate of vaccination than being achieved in other countries. In the United Kingdom, Israel, and Canada,<xref rid="bib0026" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> around 60% of total populations have been vaccinated with more than 95% in older age groups.<fig id="fig0001"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Pre-transmission vaccination process. Note: A level of uptake (60–100% total population) has been reached before opening borders.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0001">Figure 1:</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p>
                <p id="para0017">We assumed the following constraints on all vaccine strategies: i. each age group is vaccinated at least 20%, except for the 70+ year olds with minimum 80% vaccine coverage. ii. the maximum coverage for each age group is 90% for variants with lower R<sub>0</sub> values (2–3•5) and 100% for variants with higher R<sub>0</sub> values (4•5–6). The range of the higher R<sub>0</sub> values corresponds to the early estimates of R<sub>0</sub> values for the variants of concern (4•5–6).</p>
                <p id="para0018">To compare these strategies, we ran two-year simulations of two vaccine strategies with open borders, where a continuous vaccination process is assumed to mitigate any potential waning effect of the vaccine (<xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). We assumed there is a constant ten daily imported cases that become part of the community, which are equivalent to a total of 7,300 imported cases. As part of a sensitivity analysis, we also modelled on 100 daily imported cases (73,000 total). Imported cases are assumed to be unvaccinated. Comparison criteria include total COVID-19 deaths, total community cases, peak active cases, total hospitalisations, and peak active hospitalised cases (peak hospitalisations). The measures relating to hospitalisations and deaths include a predicted 444 total hospitalised and 84 deaths from 7,300 imported cases (Supplemental Appendix S2). As vaccination has not been approved for 0–15 year olds in New Zealand,<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> we carried out a sensitivity analysis where uptake was 0% for 0–9 year olds and the vaccine coverage of 10–19 year olds is assumed to have a maximum level of 35% as the subgroup of 16–19 year olds contribute nearly 40% to the group of 10–19 year olds.<xref rid="bib0027" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> We also limited our analysis to 0–11 year olds (as clinical trials have yet to release findings). For this analysis, the vaccine coverage of 10–19 year olds is therefore assumed to have a maximum level of 70% as the subgroup of 12–19 year olds contribute about 79% to the group of 10–19 year olds.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0011">
              <title>Ethics and permissions</title>
              <p id="para0019">The study protocol was approved by the Health and Disability Ethics Committee, New Zealand, under the protocol number 20/NTB/156.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0012">
              <title>Role of the funding source</title>
              <p id="para0020">The sponsors of the study had no role in study design, data collection, data analysis, data interpretation, or the writing of this report.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0013">
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="sec0014">
                <title>Minimum herd immunity requirements</title>
                <p id="para0021"><xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> (A-B) and <xref rid="fig0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref> (A-D) show minimum herd immunity requirements for two vaccine strategies at multiple uptake levels given the R<sub>0</sub> value is in the range of 4.5–6 and 2–3.5 where there is a minimum 80% vaccine uptake for high risk groups. Reaching the HIT with a vaccine of 90/80% effectiveness requires at least 86.5% total population uptake for R<sub>0</sub>=4.5 and 98.1% uptake for R<sub>0</sub>=6 with high vaccination coverage for 30–49-year-olds, i.e. the spread-minimising strategy. With the same vaccine and the high-risk targeting strategy, reaching HIT requires 92% and 99.2% total population uptake levels for R<sub>0</sub>=4.5 and 6 respectively. With 90% total population coverage with a vaccine of 90% VE for disease prevention, a minimum 76% VE of infection reduction for R<sub>0</sub>=4.5 and 86% VE of infection reduction for R<sub>0</sub>=6 is required (using the spread-minimising strategy). For 80% population vaccine coverage, a VE of 87% for infection reduction is needed. For all VE scenarios (<xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Figures 2</xref>, <xref rid="fig0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, Supplemental Appendix S3), the spread-minimising strategy has the minimum requirements of VE for HIT among vaccine strategies given the same uptake levels although it may not be optimal for protecting the whole population from the risk of hospitalisations and deaths. Vaccinating the age groups 30–39 and 40–49 can minimise the initial effective reproduction numbers (given a limited number of doses), while 60+ and 0–9 are the age groups that contribute the least to the reduction of the effective reproduction number and the achievement of HIT.<fig id="fig0002"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Vaccine effectiveness and New Zealand population vaccine uptake requirements for herd immunity threshold. Note: The minimal vaccine effectiveness on infection reduction and disease prevention for the herd immunity threshold at multiple vaccine uptake levels: (A) R<sub>0</sub>=4•5 and (B) R<sub>0</sub>=6. The spread-minimising strategy (i.e. minimise R<sub>eff</sub>) offers lower requirements of vaccine effectiveness (on both effects) than the high-risk targeting strategy given the same uptake levels. Both effects are considered equal across age groups in this analysis. As the vaccine effectiveness on infection reduction is expected to be not greater than the vaccine effectiveness on disease prevention, all herd immunity lines are limited to the bottom half of the plot (divided by the black line).</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0002">Figure 2:</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0015">
                <title>Open border modelling results</title>
                <p id="para0022">The differences in vaccine allocation of the investigated strategies can be found in <xref rid="fig0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>. The spread-minimising strategy (minimise R<sub>eff</sub>) in this figure has enabled HIT at 80% total population coverage. Probable scenarios of VE and vaccine uptake levels in a two-year simulation of the model can be found in <xref rid="tbl0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> (open borders, ten cases daily introduced to the community and R<sub>0</sub>=4.5). Further vaccine scenarios for the whole of NZ can be found in Supplemental Tables S2–8.<fig id="fig0003"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Age-stratified allocations for two strategies with a vaccine of 95/90% uniform effectiveness and 80% coverage (A), and their minimum herd-immunity allocations (R0=4•5) (B). Note: Illustration of vaccine allocations for two strategies (i.e. minimising R<sub>eff</sub> and prioritising high-risk groups). A – shows 80% coverage with 95% (uniform) effectiveness on disease prevention and 90% (uniform) of infection reduction. B – shows the minimal age-stratified allocations required for HIT by the corresponding strategies. The high-risk targeting strategy requires more than 80% coverage (∼90•5%) to achieve HIT, while the spread-minimising strategy needs less vaccine uptake for HIT (78•2% total coverage). For R<sub>0</sub>=6.0 near complete coverage for all age groups is required to achieve the herd-immunity threshold.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0003">Figure 3:</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Comparison of cases, hospitalisations, and deaths in New Zealand population (R<sub>0</sub>=4•5) – 10 imported cases per day with open borders or 7,300 total imported cases with two-year open borders</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0005">Table 1:</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td valign="top">Vaccine scenarios (<italic>e<sub>d</sub></italic>/<italic>e<sub>i</sub></italic> &amp; uptake)</td><td valign="top">Vaccine strategies</td><td valign="top">Peak active cases</td><td valign="top">Total community cases</td><td valign="top">Peak hosps.</td><td valign="top">Total hosps.</td><td valign="top">Total deaths</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/90% uniform – 100% coverage</td><td valign="top">n/a</td><td valign="top">133</td><td valign="top">5,010</td><td valign="top">7</td><td valign="top">587</td><td valign="top">64</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/90% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">217</td><td valign="top">12,100</td><td valign="top">15</td><td valign="top">1,170</td><td valign="top">173</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">1,380</td><td valign="top">80,400</td><td valign="top">34</td><td valign="top">1,950</td><td valign="top">145</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">hybrid</td><td valign="top">270</td><td valign="top">16,800</td><td valign="top">10</td><td valign="top">814</td><td valign="top">77</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/90% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">1,090</td><td valign="top">75,700</td><td valign="top">78</td><td valign="top">5,210</td><td valign="top">863</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">66,700</td><td valign="top">821,000</td><td valign="top">1,530</td><td valign="top">17,400</td><td valign="top">947</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">hybrid</td><td valign="top">1,950</td><td valign="top">127,000</td><td valign="top">123</td><td valign="top">7,490</td><td valign="top">1,150</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/90% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">46,500</td><td valign="top">974,000</td><td valign="top">2,910</td><td valign="top">55,200</td><td valign="top">8,140</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">70% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">163,000</td><td valign="top">1,500,000</td><td valign="top">3,640</td><td valign="top">31,700</td><td valign="top">1,710</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/80% uniform – 100% coverage</td><td valign="top">n/a</td><td valign="top">272</td><td valign="top">18,100</td><td valign="top">9</td><td valign="top">708</td><td valign="top">76</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/80% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">584</td><td valign="top">43,500</td><td valign="top">29</td><td valign="top">2,120</td><td valign="top">333</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">7,050</td><td valign="top">318,000</td><td valign="top">127</td><td valign="top">5,130</td><td valign="top">383</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">hybrid</td><td valign="top">803</td><td valign="top">60,100</td><td valign="top">28</td><td valign="top">2,010</td><td valign="top">261</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/80% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">16,600</td><td valign="top">673,000</td><td valign="top">908</td><td valign="top">32,200</td><td valign="top">5,440</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">110,000</td><td valign="top">1,360,000</td><td valign="top">2,050</td><td valign="top">22,800</td><td valign="top">1,400</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/80% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">122,000</td><td valign="top">1,790,000</td><td valign="top">5,840</td><td valign="top">75,400</td><td valign="top">11,100</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">70% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">240,000</td><td valign="top">2,140,000</td><td valign="top">4,480</td><td valign="top">36,900</td><td valign="top">2,190</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/70% uniform – 100% coverage</td><td valign="top">n/a</td><td valign="top">1,560</td><td valign="top">119,000</td><td valign="top">24</td><td valign="top">1,630</td><td valign="top">168</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/70% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">14,600</td><td valign="top">734,000</td><td valign="top">459</td><td valign="top">19,600</td><td valign="top">3,210</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">42,600</td><td valign="top">1,180,000</td><td valign="top">575</td><td valign="top">13,700</td><td valign="top">1,130</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/70% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">91,900</td><td valign="top">1,820,000</td><td valign="top">3,560</td><td valign="top">60,100</td><td valign="top">9,910</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">188,000</td><td valign="top">2,200,000</td><td valign="top">2,800</td><td valign="top">28,900</td><td valign="top">1,960</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/70% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">236,000</td><td valign="top">2,650,000</td><td valign="top">8,970</td><td valign="top">87,900</td><td valign="top">12,900</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">70% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">341,000</td><td valign="top">2,830,000</td><td valign="top">5,330</td><td valign="top">40,400</td><td valign="top">2,530</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/60% uniform – 100% coverage</td><td valign="top">n/a</td><td valign="top">59,500</td><td valign="top">1,590,000</td><td valign="top">561</td><td valign="top">12,700</td><td valign="top">1,330</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/60% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">119,000</td><td valign="top">2,190,000</td><td valign="top">2,500</td><td valign="top">39,300</td><td valign="top">6,260</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">146,000</td><td valign="top">2,340,000</td><td valign="top">1,540</td><td valign="top">21,200</td><td valign="top">1,870</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/60% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">221,000</td><td valign="top">2,800,000</td><td valign="top">6,670</td><td valign="top">72,400</td><td valign="top">11,900</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">303,000</td><td valign="top">2,990,000</td><td valign="top">3,670</td><td valign="top">32,300</td><td valign="top">2,300</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/60% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">370,000</td><td valign="top">3,330,000</td><td valign="top">11,700</td><td valign="top">92,600</td><td valign="top">13,700</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">70% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">455,000</td><td valign="top">3,390,000</td><td valign="top">6,060</td><td valign="top">41,600</td><td valign="top">2,670</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90/80% uniform – 100% coverage</td><td valign="top">n/a</td><td valign="top">337</td><td valign="top">23,200</td><td valign="top">15</td><td valign="top">1,140</td><td valign="top">120</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90/80% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">918</td><td valign="top">67,500</td><td valign="top">54</td><td valign="top">3,750</td><td valign="top">559</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">11,100</td><td valign="top">439,000</td><td valign="top">324</td><td valign="top">11,400</td><td valign="top">1,030</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"/><td valign="top">hybrid</td><td valign="top">1,470</td><td valign="top">105,000</td><td valign="top">71</td><td valign="top">4,640</td><td valign="top">609</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90/80% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">29,200</td><td valign="top">928,000</td><td valign="top">1,780</td><td valign="top">50,100</td><td valign="top">7,890</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">122,000</td><td valign="top">1,500,000</td><td valign="top">3,430</td><td valign="top">38,800</td><td valign="top">3,170</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90/80% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">145,000</td><td valign="top">1,960,000</td><td valign="top">7,770</td><td valign="top">94,400</td><td valign="top">13,200</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">70% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">259,000</td><td valign="top">2,260,000</td><td valign="top">7,020</td><td valign="top">58,600</td><td valign="top">4,590</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90/70% uniform – 100% coverage</td><td valign="top">n/a</td><td valign="top">5,170</td><td valign="top">329,000</td><td valign="top">130</td><td valign="top">7,060</td><td valign="top">720</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90/70% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">34,000</td><td valign="top">1,200,000</td><td valign="top">1,310</td><td valign="top">39,700</td><td valign="top">5,810</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">63,100</td><td valign="top">1,490,000</td><td valign="top">1,480</td><td valign="top">30,100</td><td valign="top">2,880</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90/70% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">121,000</td><td valign="top">2,080,000</td><td valign="top">5,400</td><td valign="top">80,600</td><td valign="top">12,200</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">212,000</td><td valign="top">2,390,000</td><td valign="top">4,910</td><td valign="top">49,900</td><td valign="top">4,320</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90/70% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">267,000</td><td valign="top">2,810,000</td><td valign="top">11,400</td><td valign="top">107,000</td><td valign="top">15,000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">70% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">366,000</td><td valign="top">2,950,000</td><td valign="top">8,400</td><td valign="top">63,800</td><td valign="top">5,220</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90/60% uniform – 100% coverage</td><td valign="top">n/a</td><td valign="top">93,700</td><td valign="top">1,940,000</td><td valign="top">1,740</td><td valign="top">30,600</td><td valign="top">3,260</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90/60% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">157,000</td><td valign="top">2,460,000</td><td valign="top">4,430</td><td valign="top">59,900</td><td valign="top">8,590</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">183,000</td><td valign="top">2,590,000</td><td valign="top">3,400</td><td valign="top">41,700</td><td valign="top">4,150</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90/60% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">262,000</td><td valign="top">3,000,000</td><td valign="top">8,900</td><td valign="top">89,400</td><td valign="top">13,300</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">335,000</td><td valign="top">3,140,000</td><td valign="top">6,420</td><td valign="top">54,400</td><td valign="top">4,860</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90/60% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">404,000</td><td valign="top">3,440,000</td><td valign="top">14,700</td><td valign="top">113,000</td><td valign="top">15,800</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">70% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">483,000</td><td valign="top">3,490,000</td><td valign="top">9,460</td><td valign="top">64,400</td><td valign="top">5,380</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80/70% uniform – 100% coverage</td><td valign="top">n/a</td><td valign="top">41,800</td><td valign="top">1,310,000</td><td valign="top">2,000</td><td valign="top">55,000</td><td valign="top">5,780</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80/70% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">95,100</td><td valign="top">1,930,000</td><td valign="top">5,170</td><td valign="top">93,500</td><td valign="top">11,900</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">122,000</td><td valign="top">2,090,000</td><td valign="top">5,340</td><td valign="top">81,600</td><td valign="top">8,510</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80/70% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">190,000</td><td valign="top">2,560,000</td><td valign="top">10,800</td><td valign="top">131,000</td><td valign="top">17,500</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">268,000</td><td valign="top">2,770,000</td><td valign="top">11,000</td><td valign="top">105,000</td><td valign="top">10,600</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80/70% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">333,000</td><td valign="top">3,100,000</td><td valign="top">18,000</td><td valign="top">156,000</td><td valign="top">20,000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">70% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">419,000</td><td valign="top">3,190,000</td><td valign="top">16,200</td><td valign="top">119,000</td><td valign="top">11,800</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80/60% uniform – 100% coverage</td><td valign="top">n/a</td><td valign="top">175,000</td><td valign="top">2,510,000</td><td valign="top">6,290</td><td valign="top">79,400</td><td valign="top">8,690</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80/60% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">244,000</td><td valign="top">2,930,000</td><td valign="top">9,990</td><td valign="top">107,000</td><td valign="top">13,600</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">265,000</td><td valign="top">3,000,000</td><td valign="top">9,130</td><td valign="top">92,600</td><td valign="top">9,940</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80/60% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">340,000</td><td valign="top">3,300,000</td><td valign="top">15,500</td><td valign="top">138,000</td><td valign="top">18,600</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">406,000</td><td valign="top">3,420,000</td><td valign="top">13,600</td><td valign="top">106,000</td><td valign="top">10,900</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80/60% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">475,000</td><td valign="top">3,650,000</td><td valign="top">21,500</td><td valign="top">155,000</td><td valign="top">20,200</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">70% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">543,000</td><td valign="top">3,680,000</td><td valign="top">17,600</td><td valign="top">115,000</td><td valign="top">11,600</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">70/60% uniform – 100% coverage</td><td valign="top">n/a</td><td valign="top">266,000</td><td valign="top">2,940,000</td><td valign="top">13,900</td><td valign="top">141,000</td><td valign="top">15,800</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">70/60% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">336,000</td><td valign="top">3,280,000</td><td valign="top">18,300</td><td valign="top">165,000</td><td valign="top">20,100</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">354,000</td><td valign="top">3,330,000</td><td valign="top">17,600</td><td valign="top">154,000</td><td valign="top">17,100</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">70/60% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">426,000</td><td valign="top">3,570,000</td><td valign="top">23,700</td><td valign="top">187,000</td><td valign="top">23,600</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">483,000</td><td valign="top">3,660,000</td><td valign="top">22,900</td><td valign="top">166,000</td><td valign="top">18,100</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">70/50% uniform – 100% coverage</td><td valign="top">n/a</td><td valign="top">421,000</td><td valign="top">3,520,000</td><td valign="top">17,500</td><td valign="top">136,000</td><td valign="top">15,600</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">70/50% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">491,000</td><td valign="top">3,780,000</td><td valign="top">21,400</td><td valign="top">154,000</td><td valign="top">19,000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">503,000</td><td valign="top">3,800,000</td><td valign="top">20,200</td><td valign="top">144,000</td><td valign="top">16,300</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90/80%: age 50+70/60%: younger 80% coverage</td><td valign="top">dual vaccine</td><td valign="top">175,000</td><td valign="top">2,180,000</td><td valign="top">8,410</td><td valign="top">95,300</td><td valign="top">12,000</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="spara006"><p>Peak active and total community cases do not include imported cases. All measures related to hospitalisations and deaths (in all scenarios) include imported cases, which are equivalent to the expectations of 444 total hospitalisations and 49•6 total deaths.</p></fn><fn id="spara007"><p>Note: Forecasts for a two-year simulation. <italic>e<sub>d</sub></italic> is VE of disease prevention. <italic>e<sub>i</sub></italic> is VE of infection reduction. The total community cases include vaccinated cases, who are less likely to develop symptoms, need hospitalisation or die than unvaccinated individuals. A scenario of “95/90% uniform, 80% coverage” means that the vaccine has uniform effects across age groups with 95% disease prevention and 90% infection reduction, and the uptake is 80% coverage of total population. HIT is not achievable in the third and fourth scenarios, where the vaccine has poor effectiveness on infection reduction. The last scenario has 80% vaccine uptake when two vaccines are available. The “dual vaccines'' strategy reused the vaccine allocation from the high-risk (group) targeting strategy. This dual strategy allocated a vaccine with lower effectiveness 70/60% for the five younger age groups and the 90/80% vaccine for the three oldest groups (aged 50 and over). Targeted vaccine strategies: (minimise R<sub>eff</sub>) Targeting of younger (socialised) age groups to minimise R<sub>eff</sub>; (high-risk) Groups susceptible to hospitalisation and death. Results are rounded to the third significant number. The lowest values that are at least 10% lower than other corresponding numbers of the same scenarios are in bold.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
                <p id="para0023">The spread-minimising strategy (i.e. minimise R<sub>eff</sub>) resulted in the smallest peak and total community cases in all scenarios (assuming the vaccine can reduce infection <italic>e<sub>t</sub></italic> &gt; 0). The strategy which targeted high-risk groups yielded the fewest hospitalisations (active or total) and total deaths in the majority of modelled scenarios (<xref rid="tbl0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). For the high-risk group targeting strategy, a high total vaccine uptake is required that is enough to also cover young adults to achieve better outcomes in general. For instance, in a scenario with R<sub>0</sub>=4.5 and a vaccine having a VE of 90/70% and 90% population uptake, the high-risk group targeting strategy was forecasted to have the lowest number of deaths and total hospitalisations, i.e. 2,880 vs 5,810 fatalities and 30,100 vs 39,700 hospitalisations (peak active hospitalisations 1,480 vs. 1,310) respectively, and more community cases than the spread-minimising strategy, i.e. a total of 1,490,000 vs. 1,200,000 cases (peak active community cases 63,100 vs. 34,000). Where the R<sub>0</sub> value is 6 and 90% total population uptake with the same vaccine, modelling the high-risk group targeting strategy resulted in lower hospitalisations and deaths but higher cases than the spread-minimising strategy, i.e. 6,100 vs. 11,700 deaths, 59,600 vs. 82,600 hospitalisations (peak active 5,960 vs. 7,320), 2,860,000 vs. 2,750,000 cases (peak active community cases 253,000 vs. 213,000).</p>
                <p id="para0024">A dual vaccine approach has been investigated where the vaccine distribution follows the high-risk targeting strategy (<xref rid="tbl0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). All groups aged 50 and over are allocated with a vaccine of 90/80% effectiveness and the rest are allocated with a vaccine of lower 70/50% effectiveness. The outcomes of this scenario are 2,180,000 cases (peak active 175,000 cases), 95,300 hospitalisations (peak active 8,410 in hospital), and total 12,000 fatalities. These numbers are in between the corresponding outcomes of two scenarios using either one of the two vaccines.</p>
                <p id="para0025">We have modelled vaccine scenarios of immunesenescence with a 50% reduction in effectiveness (for both disease prevention and infection reduction) in people aged 60 and over (Supplemental Table S9). We also analysed the sensitivity of the results on the assumed average daily imported cases and the synthetic contact matrix<xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> in Supplemental Appendix S4. Customised vaccine strategies and open-border modelling results for Māori and Pasifika populations are provided in Supplemental Appendix S5.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0016">
              <title>Vaccination excluding youngest age-groups</title>
              <p id="para0026">Where vaccination is not allocated to the 0–15 year olds<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> or the 0–11 year olds, the maximum attainable total population vaccine coverage is 79.8% or 84.9%. At a high R<sub>0</sub> value of 4.5 or higher, these maximum total coverage levels are not enough to achieve HIT. Therefore, opening borders without vaccinating the under-12 group or the under-16 group were predicted to result in a large number of cases, hospitalisations, and deaths (<xref rid="tbl0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> and Supplemental Table S2). For instance, where 0–11 year olds are not vaccinated and R<sub>0</sub>=4.5 (<xref rid="tbl0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), the high-risk targeting strategy with a high uptake level 80% (over the maximum 84.9%) and a vaccine of 90/80% effectiveness was predicted to have lower deaths and total hospitalisations and more community cases, i.e. 3,120 vs. 5,850 deaths, 37,700 vs. 44,100 hospitalisations (peak 2,980 vs 2,630), 1,480,000 vs 1,180,000 cases (peak 107,000 vs 62,700).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Comparison of cases, hospitalisations and deaths when vaccination is not allocated to the 0–11 year olds (R<sub>0</sub>=4•5) – 10 imported cases per day with two-year open borders</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0006">Table 2:</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td valign="top">Vaccine scenarios (<italic>e<sub>d</sub></italic>/<italic>e<sub>i</sub></italic>, uptake, &amp; R<sub>0</sub>)</td><td valign="top">Vaccine strategies</td><td valign="top">Peak active cases</td><td valign="top">Total community cases</td><td valign="top">Peak hosps.</td><td valign="top">Total hosps.</td><td valign="top">Total deaths</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/90% uniform – 84•9% coverage</td><td valign="top">n/a</td><td valign="top">17,900</td><td valign="top">413,000</td><td valign="top">388</td><td valign="top">8,310</td><td valign="top">513</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/90% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">23,400</td><td valign="top">511,000</td><td valign="top">918</td><td valign="top">18,300</td><td valign="top">2,500</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">50,600</td><td valign="top">783,000</td><td valign="top">1,140</td><td valign="top">16,100</td><td valign="top">909</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/90% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">64,100</td><td valign="top">1,050,000</td><td valign="top">3,510</td><td valign="top">52,400</td><td valign="top">8,070</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">70% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">157,000</td><td valign="top">1,490,000</td><td valign="top">3,490</td><td valign="top">31,100</td><td valign="top">1,690</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/90% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">179,000</td><td valign="top">1,860,000</td><td valign="top">10,000</td><td valign="top">95,900</td><td valign="top">12,500</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">60% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">310,000</td><td valign="top">2,180,000</td><td valign="top">7,860</td><td valign="top">53,800</td><td valign="top">2,680</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/90% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">361,000</td><td valign="top">2,570,000</td><td valign="top">19,500</td><td valign="top">133,000</td><td valign="top">15,500</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">50% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">508,000</td><td valign="top">2,790,000</td><td valign="top">15,300</td><td valign="top">84,800</td><td valign="top">3,980</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/80% uniform – 84•9% coverage</td><td valign="top">n/a</td><td valign="top">39,000</td><td valign="top">826,000</td><td valign="top">695</td><td valign="top">13,100</td><td valign="top">894</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/80% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">51,000</td><td valign="top">1,010,000</td><td valign="top">1,690</td><td valign="top">29,300</td><td valign="top">4,110</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">93,500</td><td valign="top">1,330,000</td><td valign="top">1,710</td><td valign="top">21,700</td><td valign="top">1,370</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/80% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">128,000</td><td valign="top">1,780,000</td><td valign="top">5,700</td><td valign="top">70,000</td><td valign="top">10,600</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">70% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">232,000</td><td valign="top">2,130,000</td><td valign="top">4,290</td><td valign="top">36,400</td><td valign="top">2,150</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/80% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">279,000</td><td valign="top">2,560,000</td><td valign="top">13,100</td><td valign="top">108,000</td><td valign="top">14,100</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">60% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">403,000</td><td valign="top">2,780,000</td><td valign="top">8,750</td><td valign="top">57,200</td><td valign="top">3,010</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/80% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">466,000</td><td valign="top">3,150,000</td><td valign="top">22,000</td><td valign="top">139,000</td><td valign="top">16,400</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">50% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">604,000</td><td valign="top">3,300,000</td><td valign="top">16,000</td><td valign="top">85,700</td><td valign="top">4,080</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/70% uniform – 84•9% coverage</td><td valign="top">n/a</td><td valign="top">99,200</td><td valign="top">1,730,000</td><td valign="top">1,390</td><td valign="top">21,000</td><td valign="top">1,590</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/70% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">122,000</td><td valign="top">1,960,000</td><td valign="top">3,200</td><td valign="top">44,100</td><td valign="top">6,300</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">174,000</td><td valign="top">2,180,000</td><td valign="top">2,540</td><td valign="top">28,100</td><td valign="top">1,950</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/70% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">233,000</td><td valign="top">2,630,000</td><td valign="top">8,400</td><td valign="top">82,700</td><td valign="top">12,500</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">70% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">331,000</td><td valign="top">2,830,000</td><td valign="top">5,130</td><td valign="top">40,100</td><td valign="top">2,510</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/70% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">399,000</td><td valign="top">3,220,000</td><td valign="top">15,700</td><td valign="top">114,000</td><td valign="top">15,000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">60% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">506,000</td><td valign="top">3,320,000</td><td valign="top">9,500</td><td valign="top">58,500</td><td valign="top">3,150</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">95/70% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">576,000</td><td valign="top">3,640,000</td><td valign="top">24,100</td><td valign="top">141,000</td><td valign="top">16,800</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">50% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">698,000</td><td valign="top">3,720,000</td><td valign="top">16,600</td><td valign="top">85,200</td><td valign="top">4,030</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90/80% uniform – 84•9% coverage</td><td valign="top">n/a</td><td valign="top">47,900</td><td valign="top">973,000</td><td valign="top">1,360</td><td valign="top">24,700</td><td valign="top">2,140</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90/80% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">62,700</td><td valign="top">1,180,000</td><td valign="top">2,630</td><td valign="top">44,100</td><td valign="top">5,850</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">107,000</td><td valign="top">1,480,000</td><td valign="top">2,980</td><td valign="top">37,700</td><td valign="top">3,120</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90/80% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">148,000</td><td valign="top">1,950,000</td><td valign="top">7,550</td><td valign="top">89,200</td><td valign="top">12,800</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">70% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">250,000</td><td valign="top">2,250,000</td><td valign="top">6,750</td><td valign="top">58,000</td><td valign="top">4,580</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90/80% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">303,000</td><td valign="top">2,680,000</td><td valign="top">15,700</td><td valign="top">128,000</td><td valign="top">16,200</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">60% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">422,000</td><td valign="top">2,860,000</td><td valign="top">12,200</td><td valign="top">81,700</td><td valign="top">5,930</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90/70% uniform - 84•9% coverage</td><td valign="top">n/a</td><td valign="top">123,000</td><td valign="top">1,980,000</td><td valign="top">2,860</td><td valign="top">40,300</td><td valign="top">3,690</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90/70% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">148,000</td><td valign="top">2,190,000</td><td valign="top">5,020</td><td valign="top">64,900</td><td valign="top">8,660</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">199,000</td><td valign="top">2,380,000</td><td valign="top">4,580</td><td valign="top">49,200</td><td valign="top">4,310</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90/70% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">262,000</td><td valign="top">2,800,000</td><td valign="top">10,900</td><td valign="top">104,000</td><td valign="top">14,700</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">70% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">356,000</td><td valign="top">2,960,000</td><td valign="top">8,140</td><td valign="top">63,500</td><td valign="top">5,220</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">90/70% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">426,000</td><td valign="top">3,320,000</td><td valign="top">18,700</td><td valign="top">134,000</td><td valign="top">17,100</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">60% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">529,000</td><td valign="top">3,400,000</td><td valign="top">13,200</td><td valign="top">82,700</td><td valign="top">6,130</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80/70% uniform – 84•9% coverage</td><td valign="top">n/a</td><td valign="top">184,000</td><td valign="top">2,460,000</td><td valign="top">7,790</td><td valign="top">93,900</td><td valign="top">9,670</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80/70% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">213,000</td><td valign="top">2,640,000</td><td valign="top">10,500</td><td valign="top">118,000</td><td valign="top">14,600</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">258,000</td><td valign="top">2,770,000</td><td valign="top">10,600</td><td valign="top">104,000</td><td valign="top">10,600</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80/70% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">327,000</td><td valign="top">3,100,000</td><td valign="top">17,300</td><td valign="top">152,000</td><td valign="top">19,700</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">70% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">411,000</td><td valign="top">3,210,000</td><td valign="top">15,900</td><td valign="top">120,000</td><td valign="top">11,800</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80/70% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">483,000</td><td valign="top">3,510,000</td><td valign="top">25,600</td><td valign="top">178,000</td><td valign="top">21,800</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">60% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">576,000</td><td valign="top">3,560,000</td><td valign="top">22,000</td><td valign="top">137,000</td><td valign="top">13,000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80/60% uniform – 84•9% coverage</td><td valign="top">n/a</td><td valign="top">328,000</td><td valign="top">3,240,000</td><td valign="top">11,100</td><td valign="top">99,500</td><td valign="top">10,500</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80/60% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">358,000</td><td valign="top">3,360,000</td><td valign="top">14,400</td><td valign="top">124,000</td><td valign="top">15,500</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">398,000</td><td valign="top">3,430,000</td><td valign="top">13,200</td><td valign="top">106,000</td><td valign="top">11,000</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80/60% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">468,000</td><td valign="top">3,660,000</td><td valign="top">20,700</td><td valign="top">152,000</td><td valign="top">20,100</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">70% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">537,000</td><td valign="top">3,710,000</td><td valign="top">17,400</td><td valign="top">116,000</td><td valign="top">11,600</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">80/60% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">610,000</td><td valign="top">3,920,000</td><td valign="top">27,900</td><td valign="top">173,000</td><td valign="top">21,600</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">60% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">683,000</td><td valign="top">3,930,000</td><td valign="top">22,500</td><td valign="top">130,000</td><td valign="top">12,300</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">70/50% uniform – 84•9% coverage</td><td valign="top">n/a</td><td valign="top">555,000</td><td valign="top">3,920,000</td><td valign="top">21,900</td><td valign="top">148,000</td><td valign="top">16,700</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">70/50% uniform</td><td valign="top">minimise R<sub>eff</sub></td><td valign="top">671,000</td><td valign="top">4,160,000</td><td valign="top">31,200</td><td valign="top">189,000</td><td valign="top">24,300</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">70% coverage</td><td valign="top">high-risk</td><td valign="top">717,000</td><td valign="top">4,160,000</td><td valign="top">27,500</td><td valign="top">159,000</td><td valign="top">17,400</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Note: NZ's vaccination plan has not included vaccinating 0–11 year olds.<sup>5</sup> The total population coverage is therefore no more than 84•9% (other age groups have a maximum coverage of 100%).<sup>27</sup> At the maximum total coverage (84•9%), both vaccine strategies become identical.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              <p id="para0027">At a lower R<sub>0</sub> value of 2.5 (<xref rid="fig0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref> and Supplemental Figures S5-6), the achievement of HIT will require a minimum VE against infection of 61% for excluding 0–15 year olds and 73% for excluding 0–11 year olds with the limits of 76.4% and 71.8% respectively (maximum 90% coverage for each age group). The open border modelling outcomes have higher numbers of cases, hospitalisations, and deaths in almost all scenarios and vaccine strategies compared with vaccinating all age groups.<fig id="fig0004"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Vaccine effectiveness and New Zealand population vaccine uptake requirements for the herd immunity threshold at lower R0 values. Note: The minimal vaccine effectiveness on infection reduction and disease prevention for HIT at multiple vaccine uptake levels: (A) R<sub>0</sub>=2; (B) R<sub>0</sub>=2•5; (C) R<sub>0</sub>=3; and (D) R<sub>0</sub>=3•5. The maximum vaccine coverage in each age group is 90%.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0004">Figure 4:</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig></p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0017">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p id="para0028">Reaching HIT will prevent widespread community outbreaks and, as a result, vulnerable populations will have a greater chance of protection from severe disease. A long-term lockdown may only postpone future outbreaks if a high level of immunity (by vaccination or natural immunity) is not targeted. Achieving HIT through vaccination in New Zealand while borders are closed will require an effective vaccine that can reduce infection, and high national vaccine uptake. Achievement of HIT without vaccinating the youngest age groups will require a vaccine with higher VE against infection. In an open border scenario with the relaxation of PHSMs and a highly effective vaccine for both disease prevention and infection reduction, targeting high-risk groups (including Māori and Pasifika) and achieving a high national uptake level, e.g. 80%, will result in a relatively low number of forecasted COVID-19 hospitalisations and deaths by international comparisons.<xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref> Where the vaccine has lower VE for infection reduction, more COVID-19 cases, hospitalisations and deaths are likely.</p>
              <p id="para0029">A strategy to achieve HIT will ensure limited community transmission (e.g. sporadic outbreaks) once borders are opened but would require a vaccine with a minimum 87% VE for infection reduction (where R<sub>0</sub>=4.5) and a high vaccine coverage rate of 80% total population. This estimated VE for infection reduction is higher than the 85% effectiveness for preventing infections that was predicted to result in a reproduction number of 1.58 in the UK. This study did not however account for further reduced viral shedding from vaccinated individuals, reducing onward transmission.<xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref></p>
              <p id="para0030">Although, HIT is potentially possible e.g. with recent evidence of the BNT162b2 vaccine’s effect against infection,<xref rid="bib0029" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref> it is also possible that emerging effectiveness challenges against new virus variants will necessitate a shift in focus away from herd immunity strategies to protection of at-risk individuals against severe disease.<xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref> Although the range of estimated VE used in this study are plausible, in particular for the mRNA vaccines licensed in NZ,<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> the lower bounds of VE may need to be extended in the presence of variants of concern.<xref rid="bib0031" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref></p>
              <p id="para0031">Comparisons of our forecast peaks (with 80% uptake, and 95% VE for disease and 70% for infection) with other countries who had widespread community transmission during the first waves of disease (with no available vaccination) can be made. Scotland has a broadly comparable population size but higher population density (e.g. Scotland, UK, 5.4m vs. 5.1m population, 19.0/km<sup>2</sup> vs. 67.2/km<sup>2</sup>). Variants of concern with high R<sub>0</sub> values such as Alpha <xref rid="bib0032" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref> and Delta variants,<xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref> were dominant in Scotland in Spring 2021. In an open border scenario, our NZ model for R<sub>0</sub>=4.5, where a vaccine of 90/80% effectiveness is not allowed for individuals aged under 16, has estimated a peak of 355 new daily hospitalisations (3,090 peak active hospitalised cases) vs. 92 peak daily hospitalisations found during the ongoing wave in Scotland (from June until July 2021), and a higher peak of daily cases 14,800 (including asymptomatic cases, 110,000 peak active cases) vs. 3,930 found in Scotland with 64.7% two-dose vaccine coverage and 88.1% first-dose vaccine coverage of all people aged 18 and over.<xref rid="bib0034" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref> The numbers hospitalisations and deaths for NZ will be higher as this includes 7,300 unvaccinated imported cases.</p>
              <p id="para0032">Several studies have addressed COVID-19 vaccination strategies. Bubar et al.<xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref> compared five vaccine strategies that allocate vaccine doses on ‘under 20’, ‘adults 20–49’, ‘adults 20+’, ‘adults 60+’, and ‘all ages’ in terms of the reduction of deaths and infections. This study focused on the initial phase of vaccination, modelling a total vaccine uptake of no more than 50% of the population and applying non-pharmaceutical interventions to reduce the spreading rate. Moore et al. predicted 96,700 deaths (51,800–173,200) if interventions are removed after vaccination with a vaccine that could prevent 85% infections.<xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref> Sandmann et al. used an age-structured transmission and economic model to estimate the economic impact of vaccination for the UK in a ten-year simulation.<xref rid="bib0036" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref> This study suggested that vaccination could add substantial health and economic value and population-wide physical distancing might not be justifiable.</p>
              <p id="para0033">Compared with other models used for vaccination studies, the SEIR model used in this study provides a model with fewer assumptions for the same disease dynamics. By grouping individuals of the same disease phase into a compartment, this SEIR model approach only requires transitions among phases instead of requiring numerous rules representing all the disease phases that are used in agent-based models. Although agent-based models have been used to apply a number of assumptions which are useful for understanding the effect of multiple public health interventions, they have limitations due to being computationally demanding.<xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref> For instance, agent-based models do not integrate age groups, but use averages for the whole population, whereas we know that vaccine distribution across age groups is unlikely to be uniform.<xref rid="bib0038" ref-type="bibr"><sup>38</sup></xref> The required uptake levels for HIT are subject to an estimated basic reproduction number R<sub>0</sub> of COVID-19 in NZ, national priorities and consideration to protect health and social care workers and the most clinically susceptible groups. While the R<sub>0</sub> value for NZ has not been reliably estimated, its actual value is also probably dependent on seasonality.<xref rid="bib0039" ref-type="bibr"><sup>39</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr"><sup>40</sup></xref> Moreover, R<sub>0</sub> is likely to increase with the emergence of the new virus strains.<xref rid="bib0041" ref-type="bibr"><sup>41</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib0042" ref-type="bibr"><sup>42</sup></xref> To consider possible increases in R<sub>0</sub>, a strength of this study is that we also investigated herd immunity requirements for higher R<sub>0</sub> values (4.5 and 6). These R<sub>0</sub> values could be the potential reproduction number of new variants. However, this study does not include changing R<sub>0</sub> values over time (with the introduction of new variants of concern). Rather R<sub>0</sub> values are fixed for the two-year period. Another strength of this work is that the model can be calibrated when more accurate parameter values are available. There is uncertainty with new variants of concern. Model parameters, such as R<sub>0</sub>, latent/infectious periods, and age-structured mortality rates may therefore vary. However, further parameters can be added to the model once evidence of new parameters emerges.</p>
              <p id="para0034">The safe opening of borders in NZ will be dependent on a vaccine that has high effectiveness against both COVID-19 disease and viral transmission. A limitation of our study is that there is still some uncertainty regarding the vaccine effectiveness against transmission. Therefore, modelling strategies and scenarios and forecasting their potential impact on the NZ population with more accurate assumptions (including infection reduction and waning vaccine immunity) needs further investigation. A further limitation is uncertainty around the potential number of imported cases in particular if travel is restricted from regions with high numbers of cases. There is also uncertainty regarding immunesenescence and our assumption of uniform effectiveness across age groups may not hold, although we have modelled vaccine scenarios with a reduction in effectiveness (for both disease prevention and infection reduction) in people aged 60 and over. The targeting of high-risk groups (in an open border scenario), in this case, may not yield the lower total deaths in many scenarios as the disease prevention effect is now lower. This is in contrast to another modelling study which found that, in the event of low effectiveness amongst older adults and no more than 50% uptake level, the advantage of prioritising all adults or adults 20–49 vs. adults 60+ was small.<xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref></p>
              <p id="para0035">This work provides data on a range of vaccine scenarios and strategies to inform NZ vaccine planning.<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> While research to estimate vaccine effectiveness for reducing severe outcomes and infection is underway, a 70% VE against infection is predicted to be the minimum required to achieve HIT for NZ with an R<sub>0</sub>=4.5 and 95% total vaccine coverage. As NZ's vaccination plan has not yet included those aged 0–15 years for vaccination,<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> achievement of HIT without vaccinating this group may be impossible, especially if the imported cases are Alpha or Delta variants of concern.<xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref> Thus, to help reduce cases, hospitalisations, and deaths, other public health interventions will be required to manage the public health response.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0018">
              <title>Contributors</title>
              <p id="para0036">CRS, MA, BN, JdL, JG, SJ, MB, WS, AS, NF, DM and DW conceived this study. All commented on the paper, oversaw the analysis and edited the final manuscript. TN, MA, BN and CS led the writing of the paper. TN, RD, MA cleaned and analysed the data. All authors contributed to the study design. All authors contributed to drafting the paper and revised the manuscript for important intellectual content. All authors gave final approval of the version to be published.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec0019">
              <title>Declaration of interests</title>
              <p id="para0037">DM is a member of COVID-19 Vaccine Strategy Taskforce, NZ Government; COVID-19 Vaccine Strategy Scientific and Technical Advisory Group, NZ Government; Advisory Group, Vaccine Alliance Aotearoa New Zealand (VAANZ); COVID-19 Expert Advisory Network, NZ Ministry of Health; and an independent member of the Clinical Trials Steering Committee, University of Oxford COVID-19 Vaccine trials. CRS received COVID-19 related grant funding from the NZ Health Research Council, NZ Ministry of Business, Innovation and Employment, Chief Scientist Office Scotland, UK National Institute for Health Research and UK Medical Research Council. JdL, NF and TN received COVID-19 related grant funding from the NZ Health Research Council, and NZ Ministry of Business, Innovation and Employment. BN and DW received COVID-19 related grant funding from the NZ Health Research Council. DW received grant funding from the Ministry of Business, Innovation and Employment as part of the Te Pūnaha Matatini COVID-19 Modelling Programme. SJ received COVID-19 related grant funding from the NZ Ministry of Business, Innovation and Employment. SJ and JdL's institute (ESR) received funding from the New Zealand Ministry of Health to undertake national infectious disease surveillance.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="COI-statement">
              <title>Declaration of Competing Interest</title>
              <p id="para0033a">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list id="cebibl1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="bib0001">
                <label>1</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0001">World Health Organization. Coronavirus Disease (COVID-19) Dashboard. 2020. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://covid19.who.int/(accessed" id="interref0001">https://covid19.who.int/(accessed</ext-link> 11 July 2021).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0002">
                <label>2</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0002">Tom S, Gregorius S, Chris M. Economic impacts of COVID-19 containment measures: Reserve Bank of New Zealand, 2020.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0003">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0003">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jefferies</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>French</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gilkison</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Graham</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hope</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Marshall</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>COVID-19 in New Zealand and the impact of the national response: a descriptive epidemiological study</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet Public Health</source>
                  <volume>5</volume>
                  <issue>11</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <comment>e612-e23</comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0004">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0004">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baker</surname>
                      <given-names>MG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wilson</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Anglemyer</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Successful Elimination of Covid-19 Transmission in New Zealand</article-title>
                  <source>N Engl J Med</source>
                  <volume>383</volume>
                  <issue>8</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>e56</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32767891</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0005">
                <label>5</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0005">Ministry of Health New Zealand. COVID-19: Vaccines. 2021. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.health.govt.nz/our-work/diseases-and-conditions/covid-19-novel-coronavirus/covid-19-vaccines" id="interref0002">https://www.health.govt.nz/our-work/diseases-and-conditions/covid-19-novel-coronavirus/covid-19-vaccines</ext-link> (accessed 27 April 2021).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0006">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0006">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Polack</surname>
                      <given-names>FP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thomas</surname>
                      <given-names>SJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kitchin</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Absalon</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gurtman</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lockhart</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Safety and Efficacy of the BNT162b2 mRNA Covid-19 Vaccine</article-title>
                  <source>N Engl J Med</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0007">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0007">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dagan</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Barda</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kepten</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Miron</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Perchik</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Katz</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>BNT162b2 mRNA Covid-19 Vaccine in a Nationwide Mass Vaccination Setting</article-title>
                  <source>N Engl J Med</source>
                  <volume>384</volume>
                  <issue>15</issue>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <fpage>1412</fpage>
                  <lpage>1423</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33626250</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0008">
                <label>8</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0001f">Menni C, Klaser K, May A, Polidori L, Capdevila J, Louca P, et al. Vaccine side-effects and SARS-CoV-2 infection after vaccination in users of the COVID Symptom Study app in the UK: a prospective observational study. Lancet Infect Dis.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0009">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0009">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hall</surname>
                      <given-names>VJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Foulkes</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Charlett</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Atti</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Monk</surname>
                      <given-names>EJM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Simmons</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>SARS-CoV-2 infection rates of antibody-positive compared with antibody-negative health-care workers in England: a large, multicentre, prospective cohort study (SIREN)</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet</source>
                  <volume>397</volume>
                  <issue>10283</issue>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <fpage>1459</fpage>
                  <lpage>1469</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33844963</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0010">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0010">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vasileiou</surname>
                      <given-names>E</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Simpson</surname>
                      <given-names>CR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shi</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kerr</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Agrawal</surname>
                      <given-names>U</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Akbari</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Interim findings from first-dose mass COVID-19 vaccination roll-out and COVID-19 hospital admissions in Scotland: a national prospective cohort study</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet</source>
                  <volume>397</volume>
                  <issue>10285</issue>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <fpage>1646</fpage>
                  <lpage>1657</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33901420</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0011">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0011">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abu-Raddad</surname>
                      <given-names>LJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chemaitelly</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Butt</surname>
                      <given-names>AA.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effectiveness of the BNT162b2 Covid-19 Vaccine against the B.1.1.7 and B.1.351 Variants</article-title>
                  <source>N Engl J Med</source>
                  <volume>385</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <fpage>187</fpage>
                  <lpage>189</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33951357</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0012">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0012">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baden</surname>
                      <given-names>LR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>El Sahly</surname>
                      <given-names>HM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Essink</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kotloff</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Frey</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Novak</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Efficacy and Safety of the mRNA-1273 SARS-CoV-2 Vaccine</article-title>
                  <source>N Engl J Med</source>
                  <volume>384</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>403</fpage>
                  <lpage>416</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33378609</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0013">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0013">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ramasamy</surname>
                      <given-names>MN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Minassian</surname>
                      <given-names>AM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ewer</surname>
                      <given-names>KJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Flaxman</surname>
                      <given-names>AL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Folegatti</surname>
                      <given-names>PM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Owens</surname>
                      <given-names>DR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Safety and immunogenicity of ChAdOx1 nCoV-19 vaccine administered in a prime-boost regimen in young and old adults (COV002): a single-blind, randomised, controlled, phase 2/3 trial</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0014">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0014">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Steyn</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Binny</surname>
                      <given-names>RN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hannah</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hendy</surname>
                      <given-names>SC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>James</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kukutai</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Estimated inequities in COVID-19 infection fatality rates by ethnicity for Aotearoa New Zealand</article-title>
                  <source>N Z Med J</source>
                  <volume>133</volume>
                  <issue>1521</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>12</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0015">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0015">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Steyn</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Binny</surname>
                      <given-names>RN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hannah</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hendy</surname>
                      <given-names>SC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>James</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lustig</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Māori and Pacific People in New Zealand have higher risk of hospitalisation for COVID-19</article-title>
                  <source>medRxiv</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <comment>2020.12.25.20248427</comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0016">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0016">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davies</surname>
                      <given-names>NG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Klepac</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Prem</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jit</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eggo</surname>
                      <given-names>RM.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Age-dependent effects in the transmission and control of COVID-19 epidemics</article-title>
                  <source>Nat Med</source>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <issue>8</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1205</fpage>
                  <lpage>1211</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32546824</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0017">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0017">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lipsitch</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dean</surname>
                      <given-names>NE.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Understanding COVID-19 vaccine efficacy</article-title>
                  <source>Science</source>
                  <volume>370</volume>
                  <issue>6518</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>763</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33087460</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0018">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0018">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Prem</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>van Zandvoort</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Klepac</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eggo</surname>
                      <given-names>RM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davies</surname>
                      <given-names>NG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cook</surname>
                      <given-names>AR</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Projecting contact matrices in 177 geographical regions: an update and comparison with empirical data for the COVID-19 era</article-title>
                  <source>medRxiv</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <comment>2020.07.22.20159772</comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0019">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0019">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>Compass Research Centre. International Social Survey Programme (ISSP)</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>Social Networks - New Zealand Survey. COMPASS Research Centre</part-title>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <publisher-name>University of Auckland: Auckland</publisher-name>
                  <publisher-loc>New Zealand</publisher-loc>
                  <comment>2018</comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0020">
                <label>20</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0020">Stats NZ Tatauranga Aotearoa. Living in a crowded house: Exploring the ethnicity and well-being of people in crowded households, 2018.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0021">
                <label>21</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0021">Ministry of Health New Zealand. Ventilators and ICU bed capacity, 2020.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0022">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0022">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>The Institute of Environmental Science and Research</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>EpiSurv, New Zealand notifiable disease surveillance database</part-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://surv.esr.cri.nz/episurv/" id="interref0003">https://surv.esr.cri.nz/episurv/</ext-link> (accessed 11 November)</comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0023">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0023">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Verity</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Okell</surname>
                      <given-names>LC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dorigatti</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Winskill</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Whittaker</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Imai</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Estimates of the severity of coronavirus disease 2019: a model-based analysis</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>
                  <volume>20</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>669</fpage>
                  <lpage>677</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32240634</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0024">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0024">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rossella</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Caterina</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>David</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nikki</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Salvatore</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Similarity in Case Fatality Rates (CFR) of COVID-19/SARS-COV-2 in Italy and China</article-title>
                  <source>J Infect Dev Ctries</source>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <issue>02</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0025">
                <label>25</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0025">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jordan</surname>
                      <given-names>RE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Adab</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cheng</surname>
                      <given-names>KK.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Covid-19: risk factors for severe disease and death</article-title>
                  <source>BMJ</source>
                  <volume>368</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>m1198</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32217618</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0026">
                <label>26</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0026">Our World in Data. Coronavirus (COVID-19) Vaccinations. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ourworldindata.org/covid-vaccinations" id="interref0004">https://ourworldindata.org/covid-vaccinations</ext-link> (accessed 12 July 2021).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0027">
                <label>27</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0027">Stats NZ Tatauranga Aotearoa. New Zealand Population Estimates. 2020.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0028">
                <label>28</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0028">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Moore</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hill</surname>
                      <given-names>EM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tildesley</surname>
                      <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dyson</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Keeling</surname>
                      <given-names>MJ.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Vaccination and non-pharmaceutical interventions for COVID-19: a mathematical modelling study</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0029">
                <label>29</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0029">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Amit</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Regev-Yochay</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Afek</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kreiss</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leshem</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Early rate reductions of SARS-CoV-2 infection and COVID-19 in BNT162b2 vaccine recipients</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet</source>
                  <volume>397</volume>
                  <issue>10277</issue>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <fpage>875</fpage>
                  <lpage>877</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0030">
                <label>30</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0030">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mahase</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Covid-19: South Africa pauses use of Oxford vaccine after study casts doubt on efficacy against variant</article-title>
                  <source>BMJ</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <fpage>372</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0031">
                <label>31</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0031">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Madhi</surname>
                      <given-names>SA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baillie</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cutland</surname>
                      <given-names>CL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Voysey</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Koen</surname>
                      <given-names>AL</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fairlie</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Efficacy of the ChAdOx1 nCoV-19 Covid-19 Vaccine against the B.1.351 Variant</article-title>
                  <source>N Engl J Med</source>
                  <volume>384</volume>
                  <issue>20</issue>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <fpage>1885</fpage>
                  <lpage>1898</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33725432</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0032">
                <label>32</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0032">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Campbell</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Archer</surname>
                      <given-names>B</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Laurenson-Schafer</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jinnai</surname>
                      <given-names>Y</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Konings</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Batra</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Increased transmissibility and global spread of SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern as at June 2021</article-title>
                  <source>Eurosurveillance</source>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <issue>24</issue>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2100509</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0033">
                <label>33</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0033">Public Health England (PHE). SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern and variants under investigation in England: technical briefing 15, 2021.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0034">
                <label>34</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0034">Public Health Scotland. COVID-19 in Scotland. https://public.tableau.com/profile/phs.covid.19#!/vizhome/COVID-19DailyDashboard_15960160643010/Overview (accessed 12 July 2021).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0035">
                <label>35</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0035">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bubar</surname>
                      <given-names>KM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reinholt</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kissler</surname>
                      <given-names>SM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lipsitch</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cobey</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Grad</surname>
                      <given-names>YH</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Model-informed COVID-19 vaccine prioritization strategies by age and serostatus</article-title>
                  <source>Science</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0036">
                <label>36</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0036">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sandmann</surname>
                      <given-names>FG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davies</surname>
                      <given-names>NG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vassall</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Edmunds</surname>
                      <given-names>WJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jit</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sun</surname>
                      <given-names>FY</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The potential health and economic value of SARS-CoV-2 vaccination alongside physical distancing in the UK: a transmission model-based future scenario analysis and economic evaluation</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0037">
                <label>37</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0037">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Blakely</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thompson</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bablani</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Andersen</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ouakrim</surname>
                      <given-names>DA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Carvalho</surname>
                      <given-names>N</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Determining the optimal COVID-19 policy response using agent-based modelling linked to health and cost modelling: Case study for Victoria</article-title>
                  <source>Australia. <italic>medRxiv</italic></source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <comment>2021.01.11.21249630</comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0038">
                <label>38</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0038">Israel Ministry of Health. The Dashboard. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://datadashboard.health.gov.il/COVID-19/general" id="interref0005">https://datadashboard.health.gov.il/COVID-19/general</ext-link> (accessed 20 June 2021).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0039">
                <label>39</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0039">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mecenas</surname>
                      <given-names>P</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>RTdRM</surname>
                      <given-names>Bastos</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vallinoto</surname>
                      <given-names>ACR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Normando</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Effects of temperature and humidity on the spread of COVID-19: A systematic review</article-title>
                  <source>PLoS One</source>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <issue>9</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <comment>e0238339-e</comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0040">
                <label>40</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0040">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Audi</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>AlIbrahim</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kaddoura</surname>
                      <given-names>M</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hijazi</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yassine</surname>
                      <given-names>HM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zaraket</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Seasonality of Respiratory Viral Infections: Will COVID-19 Follow Suit?</article-title>
                  <source>Front Public Health</source>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <issue>576</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0041">
                <label>41</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0041">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kemp</surname>
                      <given-names>S</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Harvey</surname>
                      <given-names>W</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Datir</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Collier</surname>
                      <given-names>D</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ferreira</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Carabelli</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Recurrent emergence and transmission of a SARS-CoV-2 Spike deletion ΔH69/V70</article-title>
                  <source>bioRxiv</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0042">
                <label>42</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0042">Public Health England (PHE). Investigation of SARS-CoV-2 variants of concern: technical briefings, 2020.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
            <sec id="sec0013a" sec-type="supplementary-material">
              <label>Appendix</label>
              <title>Supplementary materials</title>
              <p id="para0020a">
                <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ecom0001a">
                  <media xlink:href="mmc1.docx">
                    <alt-text>Image, application 1</alt-text>
                  </media>
                </supplementary-material>
              </p>
            </sec>
            <ack id="ack0001">
              <sec id="sec0020">
                <title>Acknowledgments</title>
                <p id="para0038">This work was funded by the New Zealand Health Research Council (20/1018). We like to thank Te Pūnaha Matatini for providing an independent review of this work.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0021">
                <title>Data sharing</title>
                <p id="para0039">All code used in this study will be made publicly available. The data used in this study are sensitive and will not be made publicly available.</p>
              </sec>
            </ack>
            <fn-group>
              <fn id="sec0012a" fn-type="supplementary-material">
                <p id="para0002a">Supplementary material associated with this article can be found, in the online version, at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.lanwpc.2021.100256" id="interref0001a">doi:10.1016/j.lanwpc.2021.100256</ext-link>.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
