<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-03-11T00:49:11Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8426770" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8426770</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-09-24</datestamp>
        <setSpec>iranjphealth</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Iran J Public Health</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Iran J Public Health</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJPH</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">IJPH</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Iranian Journal of Public Health</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">2251-6085</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2251-6093</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Tehran University of Medical Sciences</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC8426770</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8426770</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">8426770</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34568179</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18502/ijph.v50i7.6630</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IJPH-50-1405</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Prediction of Mumps Incidence Trend in China Based on Difference Grey Model and Artificial Neural Network Learning</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Jia</surname>
                    <given-names>Jin</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Liu</surname>
                    <given-names>Mingming</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF2">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Xue</surname>
                    <given-names>Zhigang</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Wang</surname>
                    <given-names>Zhe</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Pan</surname>
                    <given-names>Yu</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF3">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="C1">
                    <sup>*</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="AFF1"><label>1.</label>Information Center, The First Affiliated Hospital of Harbin Medical University, Harbin 150001, P.R. China</aff>
                <aff id="AFF2"><label>2.</label>Clinical Laboratory, The First Affiliated Hospital of Harbin Medical University, Harbin 150001, P.R. China</aff>
                <aff id="AFF3"><label>3.</label>Medical Department, The First Affiliated Hospital of Harbin Medical University, Harbin 150001, P.R. China</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="C1"><label>*</label><bold>Corresponding Author:</bold> Email:<email>ppphhh6789@163.com</email></corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <month>7</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>50</volume>
              <issue>7</issue>
              <fpage>1405</fpage>
              <lpage>1415</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>18</day>
                  <month>7</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>21</day>
                  <month>9</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>Copyright © 2021 Jia et al. Published by Tehran University of Medical Sciences</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>). Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <sec>
                  <title>Background:</title>
                  <p>We aimed to compare the prediction efficiency of back propagation (BP) network and grey model (GM) (1.1) for mumps infectious diseases and compare the application effect of the two models.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Methods:</title>
                  <p>By calculating the average incidence rate of mumps in January 2014 –2016, we conducted the modeling of the BP time series, GM (1,1) grey model and the combination models of them, and predicted the incidence rate in June 2016 in comparison with the actual one. We compared the quarterly incidence rate to test the two prediction models, and compared the advantages and disadvantages of these models.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Results:</title>
                  <p>R value of BP model was 68.45%, for GM (1,1) was 58.49%, and for combined forecasting model was 86.95%. We used the principal component analysis clustering method to control the samples, and found that the samples were close to the population mean. We found that the GM (1.1) model was more suitable for the prediction of mumps infection mode. We carried out dimension reduction analysis on the model data, and the accuracy of the data after dimension reduction is within the range of Da. For the discrete degree of the data in the combined model, matlab pipeline was used to verify the reliability of the data and results. By calculation after manifold optimization small error probability was <italic>P</italic>=0.875 and semi mean relative error 2.43%.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Conclusion:</title>
                  <p>BP, GM (1,1) is a better method for modeling the epidemic trend of mumps in China, but the efficiency of prediction is not as high as the combination of them.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>Mumps</kwd>
                <kwd>Back propagation network</kwd>
                <kwd>Grey model</kwd>
                <kwd>China</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Mumps is a common respiratory infectious disease in children. It is caused by the virus and spreads through the respiratory tract; in the case of non-immunization, it is a periodic epidemic; winter and spring are the peak season of the disease; children are the host; the virus antigen type is single, relatively stable without mutation; there are safe and effective vaccines for prevention (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). If the immunization strategy is appropriate, coupled with active epidemiological and laboratory monitoring, it can be eliminated or even eliminated (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>–<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>).</p>
              <p>The common prediction methods of infectious diseases are:
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Qualitative prediction ① epidemic control chart method: seasonal epidemic or periodic epidemic; ② ratio figure method: infectious diseases with normal distribution of incidence; ③ Delphi method: to provide reference;</p></list-item><list-item><p>Quantitative prediction ① time series prediction model grey model: short-term prediction for diseases with stable epidemic factors B ∽ J model (ARIMA): Suitable for non-stationary time series with n &lt; 50, it is a high-precision short-term prediction model. ② multi factor model: Multiple regression model, neural network model;</p></list-item><list-item><p>Comprehensive prediction method (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Transmission dynamics needs certain data to determine parameters (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Due to the particularity of mumps, some parameters are difficult to determine, for example, it is difficult to calculate the quantity. Therefore, due to the limited original data, it is difficult to make high-precision prediction or prediction at all, it is difficult to predict and control mumps (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>–<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>).</p></list-item></list>
</p>
              <p>How to make a breakthrough in theory and find a better method is an urgent work to be solved (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Grey theory can effectively deal with the system with significant uncertainty and few data, and find out the rules of data from the disordered and limited discrete data, the basic principle of the grey prediction model is to determine the best fitting curve through the point group generated by the accumulation of the original sequence (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>–<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Some work has been done on the prediction of mumps with cm (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>) grey model. In this paper, a new method based on Back propagation (BP) neural network and GM (1,1) is proposed, This model overcomes the shortcoming of large sample data required by the conventional BP neural network. It not only takes advantage of the advantages of less sample data required by GM (1,1) grey model and high short-term prediction accuracy, but also has the advantages of parallel calculation, strong fault tolerance and strong adaptive ability of BP neural network. About one third of the world’s population has a history of mumps infection (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>).</p>
              <p>In recent years, artificial neural network has been applied to medical research field and achieved good results. In this paper, BP neural network and grey theory are applied to the prediction of mumps infectious diseases, and through the establishment of prediction model, the feasibility of BP neural network and grey theory in forecasting epidemic infectious diseases is compared. BP neural network is composed of input layer, hidden layer, output layer and the connection between neurons in each layer. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>, BP algorithm divides the learning process of the network into two alternating processes: Forward propagation and back propagation (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>).</p>
              <fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                <label>Fig. 1:</label>
                <caption>
                  <p>The architecture of simple Deep Neural Networks</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="IJPH-50-1405-g001"/>
              </fig>
              <p>If the sum of squares of forward propagation output error fails to reach the expected precision, the weights and thresholds of neurons in each layer are corrected along the negative gradient direction of the error, and so on, until the total square error of the network reaches the expected accuracy.</p>
              <p>In this study, we compared the quarterly incidence rate to test the two prediction models, and compared the advantages and disadvantages of the two models.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="methods">
              <title>Methods</title>
              <sec sec-type="methods">
                <title>Data sources</title>
                <p>The epidemic data of mumps in China were from China disease monitoring information report management system (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.chinacdc.cn/jkzt/crb/xcrxjb/201810/t20181017_195160.html">http://www.chinacdc.cn/jkzt/crb/xcrxjb/201810/t20181017_195160.html</ext-link>). Demographic data from the annual demographic report of the National Health and Health Commission s <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nhc.gov.cn/">http://www.nhc.gov.cn/</ext-link>.
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>Included subjects: ① literature on the effect of MUV vaccination on mumps prevention in China (excluding Hong Kong, Macao Special Administrative Region and Taiwan); ② the research design method was not limited, and the mumps antibody was detected before and after immunization for Chinese children (&lt; 15 years old); ③ the detection methods were hemaggluti-nation inhibition (HI) test or enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay) (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) antibody positive conversion, including antibody negative before immunization, antibody positive after immunization, or antibody titer ≥ 4-fold increase after immunization.</p></list-item><list-item><p>exclusion criteria: ① animal experiment research; ② molecular biology research; ③ foreign research; ④ pharmacological research, <italic>Construction of BP network model</italic></p></list-item></list>
</p>
                <p>The BP network model was mainly composed of input layer, hidden layer and output layer. The number of hidden layers adopted the following formula: <inline-formula><mml:math id="m1"><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mtext>L</mml:mtext><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, which L is the number of hidden layers, H is the number of input layers, M is the number of output layers, and α is a constant of 1–10. It can be seen that the value of hidden layer L is 2–11, and the best hidden layer is selected according to the training results. The transfer function between neurons in the hidden layer was Tansig type; the transfer function in the output layer was Purelin type. Through a lot of experiments, this paper finally determines that the hidden layer is 5, which is a three-layer neural network with 1-5-1 topology (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>).</p>
                <sec>
                  <title>GM (1,1) model construction</title>
                  <p>In GM (1,1) modeling, the original data was assumed to be Xo (<italic>i</italic>) = [<italic>x
</italic><italic><sub>
o
</sub></italic> (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>), <italic>x
</italic><italic><sub>
o
</sub></italic> (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>), <italic>x
</italic><italic><sub>
o
</sub></italic> (<italic>n</italic>)]. In order to overcome the strong randomness of the original data, the original data is processed by 1−AGO in the prediction, that is, <italic>x
</italic><italic><sub>
1
</sub></italic> (t) = <italic>x
</italic><italic><sub>
1
</sub></italic> (t−1) + x<sub>0</sub> (t). According to the relevant assumptions of grey theory, the time response equation can be obtained. After the parameter vector is calculated, it can be substituted into the formula to get the prediction model. The grey model is actually an accumulation generated number model, so it needs to be reduced after the prediction value is obtained.</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Prediction model construction</title>
                <sec>
                  <title>Build BP network to predict mumps epidemic</title>
                  <p>Based on Jan 2014 to Jan 2016, the time of each month was the input layer, and the incidence rate of each month is output based on the observation BP network prediction model. Jan 2014 to Jan 2016 was selected as the input layer parameter of training samples every month, and then Jan 2016 to Apr 2019 was selected as the input layer parameter of each prediction sample. The incidence rate of each month was output layer. The input and output layers were normalized as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>Build the grey theory model to predict the mumps epidemic</title>
                  <p>The G (1,1) model of mumps could be calculated by the above method on Jan. 12th, 2013, as shown in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p>
                  <table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                    <label>Table 1:</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>GM (1,1) model for mumps epidemic prediction</p>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <thead>
                        <tr>
                          <th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <bold>
                              <italic>Disease species</italic>
                            </bold>
                          </th>
                          <th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                            <bold>
                              <italic>GM(1.1)</italic>
                            </bold>
                          </th>
                        </tr>
                      </thead>
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incidence rate of male mumps</td>
                          <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>
x̂
</italic><sub>
1
</sub>
(
<italic>
t
</italic>
+ 1
) = 9.42
<italic>
e
</italic><sup>
0.00528
</sup><italic><sup>
t
</sup></italic>
− 9.36</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incidence rate of female mumps</td>
                          <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>
x̂
</italic><sub>
1
</sub>
(
<italic>
t
</italic>
+ 1
) = −13.758
<italic>
e
</italic><sup>
−0.0032
</sup><italic><sup>
t
</sup></italic>
+ 13.798</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                  </table-wrap>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec sec-type="methods">
                <title>Statistical analysis</title>
                <p>The time series of DPS755 and BP neural network were used to establish the prediction model of mumps data and combined forecasting models were established on average daily incidence rate. Incidence rate of January 2016 to April 2019 was predicted and compared with actual situation. BP time series, GM (1,1) and combination prediction model were analyzed using dps7.05 software. Spss19.0 (Chicago, IL, USA) was used to calculate correlation coefficient.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="results">
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec>
                <title>Epidemic situation of mumps</title>
                <p>From Jan, 2016 to Apr, 2018, 430 thousands cases of mumps infectious diseases were reported in China, of which 150000 cases were in 2016; 150000 in 2017 and 120000 in 2018, and the total number of people in 2016–2018 was 137 million, with a total incidence rate of 312.93/100,000..</p>
              </sec>
              <sec sec-type="methods">
                <title>Two-dimensional clustering feature analysis of two methods</title>
                <p>Feature selection tests, combined with different original sequence features and topology (network) features, could obtain higher accuracy, sensitivity, and specificity. The accuracy rate of the network attribute feature (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>) was 84.43%, and the sensitivity and specificity were close to 78.24% and 90% respectively. We observed that the standardized and filtered network features (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>) had the highest accuracy (84.76%), a sensitivity of 77.77%, and a specificity of 91.71%. Among the main sequence features, BP and GM performed well and could be followed up for testing, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2C</xref>.</p>
                <fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Fig. 2:</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Error function optimization after two-dimensional clustering of two groups of models (A). Scatter diagram of OPLS-DA scores of BP model to GM model, (B). Results of BP model ‘s replacement test for opls-da model of GM model, (C). BP model to GM model’s binary permutation optimization function difference screening volcanic map</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="IJPH-50-1405-g002"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Time distribution</title>
                <p>From the time distribution, the incidence rate showed a decreasing trend. The median monthly incidence rate in Jan 2016–Apr 2018 was 29.90/10,000,000, and the median daily incidence rate was 0.96/100,000.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Grey model (GM 1,1) for predicting the incidence rate of mumps in China</title>
                <p>The mumps data from 2016 to 2018 in China predicted by grey model was taken as the original sequence <italic>x</italic><sub>
0
</sub>
, and the cumulative generation sequence x and the adjacent mean equal weight generation sequence were calculated according to the formula in the method. The prediction results are showed in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>. R value was 58.49%.</p>
                <fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Fig. 3:</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Fitting diagram of GM (1,1) model prediction results. The predicted value of the autocorrelation function of mumps incidence in China is red, and the actual value is black</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="IJPH-50-1405-g003"/>
                </fig>
                <table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 2:</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Incidence rate of mumps GM (1,1) model fitting results</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>
                            <italic>Time</italic>
                          </bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>
                            <italic>Sequential</italic>
                          </bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>
                            <italic>Incidence rate</italic>
                          </bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>
                            <italic>Predicted value</italic>
                          </bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>
                            <italic>Residual</italic>
                          </bold>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201601–201603</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.5</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.5</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201604–201607</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.9</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.9</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201608–201610</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.6</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.8</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.8</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201611–201701</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.9</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.2</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.7</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201702–201704</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.6</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.2</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201705–201707</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.4</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.3</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201708–201710</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.6</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.9</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201711–201801</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.9</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.9</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201802–201804</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.5</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.8</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.3</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Prediction of incidence rate of mumps in China by BP network</title>
                <p>Based on the data of the incidence rate of mumps in China in 2016–2018 (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>), the BP algorithm was applied to predict the incidence rate of mumps in 2018–2019. The process was implemented by Matlab software and R value was 68.45%. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref> shows that the BP prediction method was closer to the real value.</p>
                <fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Fig. 4:</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Fitting diagram of BP network prediction results. The predicted value of the autocorrelation function of mumps incidence in China is red, and the actual value is black</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="IJPH-50-1405-g004"/>
                </fig>
                <table-wrap id="T3" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 3:</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Incidence rate of mumps BP model fitting results</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>
                            <italic>Time</italic>
                          </bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>
                            <italic>Sequential</italic>
                          </bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>
                            <italic>Incidence rate</italic>
                          </bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>
                            <italic>Predicted value</italic>
                          </bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>
                            <italic>Residual</italic>
                          </bold>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201601–201603</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.5</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.7</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−7.8</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201604–201607</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.9</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.5</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201608–201610</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.6</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.6</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201611–201701</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.9</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.1</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.8</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201702–201704</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.6</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.3</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−6.3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201705–201707</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.4</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.6</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−10.8</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201708–201710</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.6</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.2</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.4</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201711–201801</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.9</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.5</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.4</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201802–201804</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.5</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.6</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.1</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Prediction of incidence rate of mumps in China by 4.3 combination model</title>
                <p>The grey neural network combination model prediction results revealed R value as 86.95%. <xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> was grey neural network combination model prediction result fitting graph. The results in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref> illustrated that the fitting degree of BP was significantly higher than that of GM in the range of adaptive orbit prediction values.</p>
                <fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Fig. 5:</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Grey neural network combination model prediction result fitting graph</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="IJPH-50-1405-g005"/>
                </fig>
                <table-wrap id="T4" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 4:</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Grey neural network combination model prediction result fitting graph</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>
                            <italic>Time</italic>
                          </bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>
                            <italic>Sequential</italic>
                          </bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>
                            <italic>Incidence rate</italic>
                          </bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>
                            <italic>Predicted value</italic>
                          </bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>
                            <italic>Residual</italic>
                          </bold>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201601–201603</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.5</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.5</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201604–201607</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.9</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.9</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201608–201610</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.6</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.5</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201611–201701</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.9</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.2</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201702–201704</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.6</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.2</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201705–201707</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.4</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81.3</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.1</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201708–201710</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.6</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79.2</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201711–201801</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.9</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.9</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201802–201804</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.5</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.5</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Comparison of BP, GM(1.1) and combination model of BP and GM</title>
                <p>According to the GM time series model, BP model and their joint fitting and verification, the fitting degree of the two joint models was 92.34%, which was the highest (<xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>).</p>
                <table-wrap id="T5" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Table 5:</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Comparison of three main model parameters</p>
                  </caption>
                  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                    <thead>
                      <tr>
                        <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>
                            <italic>Simulation name</italic>
                          </bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>
                            <italic>Fit simulation fit (%)</italic>
                          </bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>
                            <italic>r</italic>
                          </bold>
                        </th>
                        <th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                          <bold>
                            <italic>Sum of squares of validation model residuals</italic>
                          </bold>
                        </th>
                      </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GM</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.15</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5234.55</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BP</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.81</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3482.34</td>
                      </tr>
                      <tr>
                        <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Combination</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.34</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86</td>
                        <td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2905.2</td>
                      </tr>
                    </tbody>
                  </table>
                </table-wrap>
              </sec>
              <sec>
                <title>Discrete neural network model with self-feedback in system</title>
                <p>The combined forecasting model was obtained based on GRNN by running the program in MATLAB. The weight coefficients of GM (1,1) model with residual correction and ARIMA (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,0, <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>) * (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, 0) 2 model changed with time in the combined forecasting model based on GRNN. Due to the black box principle of neural network, the specific formula of the combined model could not be obtained. β=1/2, α
<sub>
12
</sub>
= −1, α
<sub>
13
</sub>
=−1.</p>
                <p>Obviously sin’ (0) =1, arctan’ (0) = 3, sin “(0) = arctan” (0) = 0, sin “(0) =−1 &lt;0, arctan” (0). Derived from if D makes α
<sub>
21
</sub>
= 0.50, easy to get DD + if makes 0.49 easy If D = end &lt;D, then (0.0,0) is gradually stable. If a21 = 0.51, easy to get D = such as&gt; D: then (0,0, 0) is gradually divergent. There was a periodic solution branched from (0,0, 0). The above conclusions are verified in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>. It could been seen all the prediction models were in the appropriate threshold range, and the comparison results were credible.</p>
                <fig id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float">
                  <label>Fig. 6:</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Trajectory of fitting function x1, x2, x3 when sin “(0) = 0.50</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="IJPH-50-1405-g006"/>
                </fig>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="discussion">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>Based on the incidence rate of mumps in China, we used grey system theory to establish the model and predict the incidence rate of mumps. The posterior difference ratio was C-0.26, small error probability (P) was equal to 0.875 and semi mean relative error was 2.43%, which showed that the model had good accuracy grade, the prediction result was ideal, and the extrapolation result was credible.</p>
              <p>The incidence rate of mumps in China continues to decline with an average annual rate of 2.83%. We analyzed the following reasons might be related: 1. with the implementation of the national infectious disease prevention and control plan, the incidence rate of tuberculosis in the whole country is decreasing gradually. 2. Since the strategy of infectious disease control has been carried out in China, we have focused on the detection and treatment of patients with mumps, and strengthened cooperation in medical treatment and prevention. Changes are closely related to time. But when predicting the incidence of infectious diseases in a one-dimensional time series, due to the different application conditions of different models, the prediction models fitted to the same infectious disease are also different, so the accuracy of fitting in different models is also different.</p>
              <p>In this study, both BP network and GM (1,1) time series models were used to predict the incidence of mumps in China from 2016 to 2018 to compare the accuracy of BP network model and GM (1,1) model in predicting the incidence of infectious diseases (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). The BP neural network was trained with the predicted value as the input and the original data as the expected value, and the corresponding weights and thresholds were obtained. It could be predicted that the incidence rate of tuberculosis in China would continue to decrease year by year in the next few years. This was also the result of implementing the measures to prevent mumps in China (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). In view of the difficulty in establishing the transmission dynamics of mumps disease, a combined model based on GM (1,1) grey model and BP neural network model was proposed in this paper.</p>
              <p>It not only took advantage of the advantages of grey theory, such as less original data, simple principle, high short-term prediction accuracy, but also has the advantages of parallel calculation and strong adaptive ability of neural network. The combined model of grey model and BP neural network model could predict the number of mumps, which was better than the single GM (1,1) grey model, and could be used for the prediction of mumps. When the grey GM (1,1) model was used to predict, the sample size was small, and the randomness of the time series data was weakened by the ashing of the original data, but the prediction result was not good for the volatility fitting of the actual data. The advantage of grey model was that it could contain the comprehensive effect of multiple factors that affected the occurrence and development of disease in time variables. The prediction result of the grey model was a grey differential equation, which had a good prediction effect for the data with little volatility. However, when the data with large volatility were encountered, the prediction effect was not good. Grey model GM (1,1) had a good short-term prediction effect on incidence rate of mumps, and new information was needed for long-term prediction.</p>
              <p>BP network model could reflect the volatility of the original data in the prediction, but its result was very random, and the model parameter setting had a great influence on the result (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Different parameters made different convergence speed of the network, and there might be the phenomenon that the prediction result had a large deviation or even no result. Theoretically, if the excitation function of the output layer was a linear function, then the BP network model could approach to any continuous function grey neural network combination model and had the advantages of grey model and neural network model (5, 13, 14). The prediction result could reflect the volatility of the original data well, and also weakened the randomness of the data. It was suitable for prediction problems in medical application.</p>
              <p>The incidence of infectious diseases was affected by natural factors such as climate and geography, and the social factors such as living conditions, occupation, and social system. Therefore, the incidence rate fluctuated greatly and was difficult to predict. A single prediction method usually considers one aspect of the data, so there was a big error between the prediction results and the actual values. The combination model combined the advantages of the two models in a reasonable way, and the prediction results of the model were closer to the measured values. In this paper, the incidence rate of mumps in China was taken as an example, and the results were analyzed by combination model prediction. The combination model of grey neural network had good prediction effect and could be extended to other prediction problems in medical field.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="conclusion">
              <title>Conclusion</title>
              <p>The incidence rate of mumps in GM (1,1) and the error rate of external preprocessing can be reduced. Therefore, grey correlation analysis and principal component analysis are used to identify the factors. Then, GM is used to predict the rate of error. According to the data predicted by the experiment, when mumps is modeled by grey prediction and rolling grey prediction, the incidence of mumps is low. We can improve the accuracy of the external prediction of the unemployment rate. We can use grey prediction to do research. We can use GM (1,1) as far as possible, and the grey correlation factor of GM (1, n) is best combined with its joint degree analysis. However, the external prediction part of GM (1, n) can predict too many periods, or the value of 5 can be trained with the theory of neural like or other related categories, because of the influence error of rolling factor prediction, instead of substituting a normal 0.5, in that way the result may be better.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec>
              <title>Ethical considerations</title>
              <p>Ethical issues (including plagiarism, informed consent, misconduct, data fabrication and/or falsification, double publication and/or submission, redundancy, etc.) have been completely observed by the authors.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgements</title>
              <p>No funding was received in this study.</p>
            </ack>
            <fn-group>
              <fn fn-type="COI-statement">
                <p>
                  <bold>Conflict of interest</bold>
                </p>
                <p>The authors declare that there is no conflict of interest.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="B1">
                <label>1.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>ZL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>[Nondestructive detection of total nitrogen content in leaves of Santalum album based on ST-PCA-BP neural network.]</article-title>. <source>Ying Yong Sheng Tai Xue Bao</source>, <volume>29</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1551</fpage>–<lpage>1558</lpage>. [In Chinese].<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29797888</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B2">
                <label>2.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>The Sustainable Development Assessment of Reservoir Resettlement Based on a BP Neural Network</article-title>. <source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source>,<volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>146</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B3">
                <label>3.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Competing Endogenous RNA Network Analysis Reveals Pivotal ceRNAs in Adrenocortical Carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Front Endocrinol (Lausanne)</source>,<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>301</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31156552</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B4">
                <label>4.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>A new gene regulatory network model based on BP algorithm for interrogating differentially expressed genes of Sea Urchin</article-title>. <source>Springerplus</source>, <volume>5</volume> (<issue>1</issue>): <fpage>1911</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27867818</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B5">
                <label>5.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lyu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>BP neural network prediction model for suicide attempt among Chinese rural residents</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord</source>,<volume>246</volume>:<fpage>465</fpage>–<lpage>473</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30599370</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B6">
                <label>6.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>A Lung Sound Category Recognition Method Based on Wavelet Decomposition and BP Neural Network</article-title>. <source>Int J Biol Sci</source>, <volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>195</fpage>–<lpage>207</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30662359</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B7">
                <label>7.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>A Novel Neural Network Model for Blood Pressure Estimation Using Photoplethesmography without Electrocardiogram</article-title>. <source>J Healthc Eng</source>, <volume>2018</volume>:<fpage>7804243</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29707186</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B8">
                <label>8.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>A Structure-Adaptive Hybrid RBF-BP Classifier with an Optimized Learning Strategy</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>,<volume>11</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>e0164719</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27792737</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B9">
                <label>9.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belyaletdinova</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitrofanova</surname><given-names>IV</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozlovskaya</surname><given-names>LI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Cases of aseptic meningitis after vaccination against mumps in Russia (2009–2019)</article-title>. <source>Public Health</source>, <volume>186</volume>:<fpage>8</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32736309</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B10">
                <label>10.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamidi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zarrineh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Es-Haghi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Rapid and sensitive determination of neomycin and kanamycin in measles, mumps, and rubella vaccine via high-performance liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry using modified super-paramagnetic Fe3O4 nanospheres</article-title>. <source>J Chromatogr A</source>, <volume>1625</volume>:<fpage>461343</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32709308</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B11">
                <label>11.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Roles of Sialic Acid, AXL, and MER Receptor Tyro-sine Kinases in Mumps Virus Infection of Mouse Sertoli and Leydig Cells</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>,<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1292</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32695074</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B12">
                <label>12.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McPherson</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ringness</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Mumps Cases Disproportionately Affecting Persons Living with HIV Infection and Men Who Have Sex with Men - Chicago, Illinois, 2018</article-title>. <source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source>, <volume>69</volume>(<issue>28</issue>):<fpage>909</fpage>–<lpage>912</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32673295</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B13">
                <label>13.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Filippi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Patrizi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabattini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Pity-riasis lichenoides triggered by measles-mumps-rubella vaccine injection</article-title>. <source>J Dtsch Dermatol Ges</source>, <volume>18</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>758</fpage>–<lpage>760</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B14">
                <label>14.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Grenfell</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Mina</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Waning immunity and re-emergence of measles and mumps in the vaccine era</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Virol</source>, <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>48</fpage>–<lpage>54</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32634672</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B15">
                <label>15.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salehzadeh</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Vachon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabourin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Vertically tapered waveguide spot size converters fabricated via a linewidth controlled grey tone lithography for InP-based photonic integrated circuits</article-title>. <source>Opt Express</source>, <volume>28</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>23523</fpage>–<lpage>23533</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32752347</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B16">
                <label>16.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>[Grey model prediction of occupational diseases in Changsha]</article-title>. <source>Zhonghua Lao Dong Wei Sheng Zhi Ye Bing Za Zhi</source>,<volume>38</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>508</fpage>–<lpage>511</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32746571</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B17">
                <label>17.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lawson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Suppiah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rota</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>In vitro inhibition of mumps virus replication by favipiravir (T-705)</article-title>. <source>Antiviral Res</source>,<volume>180</volume>:<fpage>104849</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32553844</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B18">
                <label>18.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>An adaptive Kalman filtering algorithm based on back-propagation (BP) neural network applied for simultaneously detection of exhaled CO and N2O</article-title>. <source>Spectrochim Acta A Mol Biomol Spectrosc</source>, <volume>223</volume>:<fpage>117332</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31288168</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B19">
                <label>19.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>[Study on Risk Assessment Model of in Vitro Diagnostic Reagent Adverse Events Based on BP Neural Network]</article-title>. <source>Zhongguo Yi Liao Qi Xie Za Zhi</source>,<volume>43</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>136</fpage>–<lpage>139</lpage>. [In Chinese].<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30977615</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B20">
                <label>20.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zha</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Effects of meteorological factors on the incidence of mumps and models for prediction, China</article-title>. <source>BMC Infect Dis</source>,<volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>468</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32615923</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B21">
                <label>21.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>De Gascun</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Presence of low mumps-specific IgG in oral fluids is associated with high mumps viral loads</article-title>. <source>J Clin Virol</source>, <volume>129</volume>:<fpage>104517</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32629188</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
