<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-03-11T00:45:52Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8687493" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8687493</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-12-29</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rsbmt</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Rev Soc Bras Med Trop</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Rev Soc Bras Med Trop</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">rsbmt</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Revista da Sociedade Brasileira de Medicina Tropical</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0037-8682</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1678-9849</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Medicina Tropical - SBMT</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC8687493</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8687493</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">8687493</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34932762</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/0037-8682-0339-2021</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="other">00662</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Short Communication</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Seropositivity for Chagas disease in blood donors from the state of Alagoas, Northeastern Brazil: an 11-year time series study</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5056-4048</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Abreu</surname>
                    <given-names>Sílvia Letícia da Conceição</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9962-6537</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Bezerra-Santos</surname>
                    <given-names>Márcio</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2959-1484</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Damasceno</surname>
                    <given-names>Flávia Silva</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
                    <sup>4</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
              </contrib-group>
              <aff id="aff1"><label>1</label> Universidade Estadual de Alagoas, Especialização em Doenças Parasitárias e Meio Ambiente, Santana do Ipanema, AL, Brasil. </aff>
              <aff id="aff2"><label>2</label> Universidade Federal de Sergipe, Hospital Universitário, Aracaju, SE, Brasil. </aff>
              <aff id="aff3"><label>3</label> Universidade Federal de Sergipe, Departamento de morfologia, Aracaju, SE, Brasil.</aff>
              <aff id="aff4"><label>4</label> Universidade de São Paulo, Instituto de Ciências Biomédicas, Departamento de Parasitologia, São Paulo, SP, Brasil. </aff>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="c1"><bold><italic toggle="yes">Corresponding author:</italic></bold> Dr. Flávia Silva Damasceno. <bold>e-mail:</bold>
<email>flaviasdamasceno@gmail.com</email>
</corresp>
                <fn fn-type="con" id="fn1">
                  <p><bold>Authors’ contribution:</bold> SLCA: Conceptualization, formal analysis, writing-original draft. MBS: Formal analysis, visualization, writing-review and editing. FSD: Conceptualization, formal analysis, supervision, validation, visualization, writing-original draft, writing-review and editing.</p>
                </fn>
                <fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="fn2">
                  <p><bold>Conflict of Interest:</bold> The authors declare that there is no conflict of interest.</p>
                </fn>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic">
                <day>17</day>
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic">
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>54</volume>
              <elocation-id>e0339-2021</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>13</day>
                  <month>7</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>08</day>
                  <month>10</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <title>Abstract </title>
                <sec>
                  <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
                  <p> Chagas disease can be transmitted by blood transfusion. Herein, we assessed the seropositivity for Chagas disease in blood donors from Alagoas, during 2010-2020. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>METHODS</title>
                  <p> Data were requested from the Alagoas blood center. Time trend analysis was performed using a joinpoint regression model. </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>RESULTS</title>
                  <p> Seropositivity rate during the study period was 0.35%, which decreased from 2014 to 2020, (annual percentage change, APC = -29.38; <italic toggle="yes">p-</italic>value &lt;0.05), while the total number of tests performed remained stable (APC = 6.5). </p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                  <title>CONCLUSIONS</title>
                  <p> Despite the drop in the seropositivity for Chagas infection in donors, it is imperative to maintain the screening of donors for the epidemiological control.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <title>Keywords:</title>
                <kwd>Chagas disease</kwd>
                <kwd>Blood donors</kwd>
                <kwd>Transfusional transmission disease</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <counts>
                <fig-count count="1"/>
                <table-count count="1"/>
                <equation-count count="0"/>
                <ref-count count="15"/>
              </counts>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <p>Chagas disease (CD), also known as American trypanosomiasis, is caused by the protozoan parasite <italic toggle="yes">Trypanosoma cruzi</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">T. cruzi</italic>). The World Health Organization (WHO) estimates that 7 million people are affected by CD causing nearly 12,000 deaths annually. The disease is endemic in Latin American countries and the southwestern region of the United States<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref>. Although CD cases mainly occur on the American continent, the geographical distribution of the disease is worldwide due to the migration of people from endemic to non-endemic areas. As a result, it is estimated that 70 million people worldwide are at risk of infection<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>.</p>
            <p>Clinically, CD demonstrates both acute and chronic phases. The acute phase, occurring shortly after infection and commonly being asymptomatic, is characterized by the presence of parasites in the bloodstream with an absence of detectable specific antibodies. In contrast, the chronic phase is characterized by low concentration of parasites in the bloodstream and the presence of specific anti-<italic toggle="yes">T. cruzi</italic> IgG antibodies. During the chronic phase, most patients are asymptomatic throughout life; however, some patients experience symptoms, such as megaviceras and heart failure<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>. Importantly, most cases of CD are diagnosed in the chronic phase when the patients present symptoms, while the absence of or unspecific symptoms results in difficulty of diagnosis in the acute phase. Nonetheless, in Brazil, only acute cases of CD are reported to public health services.</p>
            <p>The main form of transmission of <italic toggle="yes">T. cruzi</italic> in endemic areas is via insect vectors, specifically bedbugs of the subfamily Triatominae. Additionally, CD can be transmitted through ingestion of contaminated food, congenitally through pregnancy or during childbirth, via organ transplantation, during blood transfusion from an infected donor, or laboratory accidents<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>. </p>
            <p>Transfusion transmission of <italic toggle="yes">T. cruzi</italic> was first confirmed in the 1950s<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> and was considered a relevant public health problem, leading to the implementation of a serological test for CD in blood banks in Brazil and other countries. The implementation of serological testing for CD gradually increased in the last decades, with the exception of some countries. Despite conducting serological tests for CD on donated blood, the risk of transfusion transmission is still present in Brazil. Recently, Santos et al. described that 0.31% of the acute CD cases notified in Brazil, in the two last decades, had transfusion as the probable route of infection<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>. Unfortunately, scientific articles relating to CD positivity rates of blood donated in Brazil are scarce in the articles database. In the Northeast Region, we can find these data only from the states of Ceará, Pernambuco, and Piauí, all of which demonstrate the occurrence of CD seropositive individuals among blood donors<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref>
<sup>-</sup>
<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>. However, no information is available regarding CD seropositivity rates among blood donors in Alagoas. More importantly, there have been no cases of CD notified by the disease notification system of the Brazilian Ministry of Health<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> in the last decade in Alagoas. Meanwhile, according to the Brazilian mortality information system<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref>, the annual average of deaths from CD in the same period was approximately 100 per year. This lack of information makes it difficult to plan health policies to prevent and control CD in Alagoas. </p>
            <p>Considering the lack of information on CD in the State of Alagoas, the objective of the current study was to assess the rate of seropositivity for CD in blood donors in this endemic region of Northeast Brazil between 2010 and 2020. </p>
            <p>We carried out a time series study on data related to the total number of tests performed in the period between 2010 to 2020 in order to assess CD in blood samples and the number of seropositive tests to IgG anti-<italic toggle="yes">T. cruzi</italic> antibody. Data were requested from the Alagoas blood center, HEMOAL. This institution attends blood donors from urban and rural areas of the entire state of Alagoas, Northeastern Region of Brazil. Traditionally, HEMOAL utilized enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) as a diagnostic method to identify IgG anti-<italic toggle="yes">T. cruzi</italic> in blood samples. However, since 2013, the institution has relied on the chemiluminescence technique. Absolute and relative frequencies were calculated using Microsoft Excel (2017) software. </p>
            <p>Additionally, we assessed time trends contained within the data using the joinpoint regression model (segmented linear regression). The annual percentage change (APC) and its respective 95% confidence interval (95% CI) were calculated for each segmented period. Thereby, significant positive values of APC (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value &lt;0.05) indicate increasing trends over time, while significant negative APC values indicate a decreasing trend. Similarly, APC values that were not significantly different between time periods indicate a stationary trend<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref>. Moreover, when a time trend had inflection points and more than one APC, we calculated the average annual percentage change (AAPC) for the entire period. Time trends were considered statistically significant when the APC or AAPC had a <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value &lt;0.05 and was accompanied by a 95% CI that did not include a zero value. We used the Joinpoint Regression Program, version 4.5.0 (National Cancer Institute, Maryland, USA) for the analysis. </p>
            <p>A total of 322,060 blood tests for CD were performed by HEMOAL between 2010 and 2020, while 1,142 (0.35%) of these tests were positive for IgG anti-<italic toggle="yes">T.cruzi</italic> antibodies. Analyzing the total number of CD tests performed, a stable trend was observed between 2010 and 2020 (APC = 1.85) (<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>A and <xref rid="t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Likewise, a stable trend over time was identified for positive tests for IgG anti-<italic toggle="yes">T. cruzi</italic> antibodies between 2010 and 2014 (APC = 6.5). However, a decreasing trend was observed from 2014 to 2020 (APC = -29.38*, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value &lt;0.05) (<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>B and <xref rid="t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Similarly, a decreasing trend was seen when considering positive tests for IgG anti-<italic toggle="yes">T. cruzi</italic> antibodies over the entire time period (2010 = 148; 2020 = 23), (AAPC = -16.8; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value &lt;0.05). </p>
            <p>
              <fig position="float" id="f1">
                <label>FIGURE 1:</label>
                <caption>
                  <title><bold>Joinpoint temporal trend evaluation of seropositive tests for Chagas disease in the state of Alagoas, Northeastern Brazil, between 2010 and 2020.</bold> Temporal trend analysis of: <bold>(A)</bold> Total number of anti-<italic toggle="yes">T. cruzi</italic> tests performed by Alagoas blood center - HEMOAL. <bold>(B)</bold> Positive tests for IgG anti-<italic toggle="yes">T. cruzi</italic>. <bold>(C)</bold> Positivity rate for IgG anti-<italic toggle="yes">T. cruzi</italic>. APC: Annual Percent Change. *<italic toggle="yes">p-value</italic> &lt;0.05.</title>
                </caption>
                <graphic xlink:href="1678-9849-rsbmt-54-e0339-2021-gf1" position="float"/>
              </fig>
            </p>
            <p>
              <table-wrap position="float" id="t1">
                <label>TABLE 1:</label>
                <caption>
                  <title>Temporal trends in the positivity rate for anti-<italic toggle="yes">T. cruzi</italic> and number of tests performed by HEMOAL, state of Alagoas, Northeast Brazil, between 2010 and 2020.</title>
                </caption>
                <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                  <colgroup span="1">
                    <col span="1"/>
                    <col span="1"/>
                    <col span="1"/>
                    <col span="4"/>
                    <col span="3"/>
                  </colgroup>
                  <thead>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables </th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                      <th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1">Segmented Period </th>
                      <th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Total Period </th>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2010</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2020</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Period</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">APC<sup>a</sup> (*<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt;0.05)</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trend</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAPC<sup>b</sup> (*<italic toggle="yes">p</italic> &lt;0.05)</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95% CI</th>
                      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trend</th>
                    </tr>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Tests Performed for Anti-<italic toggle="yes">T. cruzi</italic> (n)</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24,886</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29,300</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2007-2016</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.5, 4.3</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stable</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">--</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Positive Tests for Anti-<italic toggle="yes">T. cruzi</italic> (n)</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">148</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2010-2014</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.5</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-23, 47.2</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stable</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-16.8*</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-30.4, -0.5</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Decreasing</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014-2020</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-29.38*</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-47.8, -4.5</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Decreasing</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
                        <bold>Positivity Rate for Anti-<italic toggle="yes">T. cruzi</italic> (%)</bold>
                      </td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2010-2014</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-1.56</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-24.1, 27.6</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stable</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-18.3*</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-31.5, -2.5</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Decreasing</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014-2020</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-27.87*</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-47.9, -0.2</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Decreasing</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td>
                    </tr>
                  </tbody>
                </table>
                <table-wrap-foot>
                  <fn id="TFN1">
                    <p><sup>a</sup>Annual Percent Change; <sup>b</sup>Annual Average Percent Change; n = number of samples; *Indicates that the APC or AAPC is significantly different from zero at the alpha = 0.05 level.</p>
                  </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot>
              </table-wrap>
            </p>
            <p>In addition, we calculated the percentage of positive tests for CD related to the total number of tests performed in the analyzed period. As expected, the joinpoint analysis showed the same temporal profile regarding positivity rates for IgG anti-<italic toggle="yes">T. cruzi</italic>, corroborating the stable trend identified in the period from 2010 to 2014 (APC = -1.56) and the decreasing trend over time observed between 2014 and 2020 (APC = -27.87*; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value &lt;0.05). Similarly, there is a decreasing trend when considering the entire period of time analyzed (2010 = 0.59%; 2020 = 0.07%; AAPC = -18.3; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value &lt;0.05) (<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>C and <xref rid="t1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). </p>
            <p>To our knowledge, this is the first study that addresses CD in blood donors from the state of Alagoas, an endemic area in Northeastern Brazil. Herein, we demonstrate that 0.35% of the blood donors in Alagoas were positive for IgG anti-<italic toggle="yes">T. cruzi</italic> antibody between 2010 and 2020. The WHO considers CD as a neglected tropical disease that mainly affects low-income populations worldwide, with the largest number of cases in Latin America<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref>. Considering our findings and that Alagoas has the lowest Brazilian Human Development Index (HDI = 0.683)<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref>, we speculate that CD transmission persists in this state, mostly in municipalities with high social vulnerability.</p>
            <p>Remarkably, vector transmission is the most important route of CD transmission in endemic areas. However, other transmission routes remain important in both endemic and non-endemic areas, such as transfusional transmission. The transfusional transmission of CD was first confirmed in the 1950s<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref>; this method of transmission occurs when a blood bank provides blood for transfusion supplied by a donor infected with <italic toggle="yes">T. cruzi</italic>. Currently, Brazilian blood centers control blood bags to avoid CD transmission. Nevertheless, more than half-century after the implementation of anti-<italic toggle="yes">T. cruzi</italic> tests in blood banks, the risk of CD transmitted by blood transfusion are still reported in Brazil. In the last two decades, 0.31% of the notified acute CD cases in Brazil, had transfusion as the probable route of infection<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref>. </p>
            <p>In this study, we demonstrate that the positivity rate for CD among blood donors in Alagoas was 0.35%. This value is similar to the data reported from the State of Ceará (0.33% in 2015)<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref>; while being less than the positivity rate reported in the State of Piauí from 2004 to 2013 (1%)<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref>; and greater than in the Pernambuco State from 2002 to 2007 (0.17%)<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref>. The WHO estimate of the seropositivity rate in blood donors from Brazil in 2010 was 0.18%<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref>, while our results show the seropositive rate in Alagoas is two-fold more than that. </p>
            <p>Despite the positive tests for CD observed among blood donors between 2010 and 2020, surprisingly, there were no cases of CD notified in Alagoas by the DATASUS during this same period; meanwhile, approximately 100 deaths were notified to be caused by CD annually in this state<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref>
<sup>,</sup>
<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref>. We highlight that, in general, blood donors consist of people who feel healthy, without fever or discomfort, which suggest that the seropositive blood donors were in the later acute phase or asymptomatic chronic phase of CD when donating. Moreover, once a blood donor is diagnosed with CD or any other transmissible illness, they are prevented from donating blood again<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref>. Therefore, even with the definitive control of the transmission of the infection in the state of Alagoas, since the asymptomatic carrier of the infection has harbored the parasite for several decades, and blood donation in the country can be done up to 70 years of age, the occurrence of infected donors could continue for years; thus, requiring the maintenance of control measures. </p>
            <p>Our data demonstrate that, despite the decreasing trend of seropositive tests, it remains necessary to carry out these tests on all the donated blood before it is used for transfusion in order to prevent the transmission of CD via blood or blood products. </p>
            <p>Our study presented some limitations; it was not possible to access data related to sex, age, socioeconomic characteristics, the municipality of blood donor residence, and donor characteristics related to number of donations. </p>
            <p>Regardless of the decreasing trend in the positivity rate for IgG anti-<italic toggle="yes">T. cruzi</italic> antibodies in blood donors, our data suggest that transfusional transmission of CD continues to be a risk, which justifies the need to maintain the testing of samples of the donated blood in the state of Alagoas. </p>
            <sec>
              <title>ETHICAL STATEMENT</title>
              <p>We only used secondary data; thus, the project does not need to be submitted to the ethics and research committee. The databank used in the study does not allow identification of patients.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title>
              <p>We would like to thank the Alagoas blood center - HEMOAL, for providing the data used in this study. Without this information, this work would not have been possible. </p>
            </ack>
            <fn-group>
              <fn fn-type="supported-by" id="fn3">
                <p><bold>Financial Support:</bold> This work had no financial support. </p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
            <ref-list>
              <title>REFERENCES</title>
              <ref id="B1">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rodriguez</surname>
                      <given-names>F</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Luna</surname>
                      <given-names>BS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Calderon</surname>
                      <given-names>O</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Manriquez-Roman</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Amezcua-Winter</surname>
                      <given-names>K</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cedillo</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Surveillance of Trypanosoma cruzi infection in Triatomine vectors, feral dogs and cats, and wild animals in and around El Paso county, Texas, and New Mexico</article-title>
                  <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <elocation-id>e0009147</elocation-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33600455</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B2">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lidani</surname>
                      <given-names>KCF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Andrade</surname>
                      <given-names>FA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bavia</surname>
                      <given-names>L</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Damasceno</surname>
                      <given-names>FS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Beltrame</surname>
                      <given-names>MH</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Messias-Reason</surname>
                      <given-names>IJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Chagas disease: From discovery to a worldwide health problem</article-title>
                  <source>J Phys Oceanogr</source>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <volume>49</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>13</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B3">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>WHO</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Chagas disease (also known as American trypanosomiasis)</source>
                  <comment>Chagas Disease Fact Sheets</comment>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <date-in-citation content-type="access-date" iso-8601-date="2021-04-01">2021 Apr 1</date-in-citation>
                  <fpage>p. 6</fpage>
                  <lpage>p. 6</lpage>
                  <comment>Available from: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/chagas-disease-(american-trypanosomiasis)" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/chagas-disease-(american-trypanosomiasis)</ext-link>
</comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B4">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pérez-Molina</surname>
                      <given-names>JA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Molina</surname>
                      <given-names>I</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Chagas disease</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>391</volume>
                  <issue>10115</issue>
                  <fpage>82</fpage>
                  <lpage>94</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28673423</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B5">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Santos</surname>
                      <given-names>EF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Silva</surname>
                      <given-names>ÂAO</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leony</surname>
                      <given-names>LM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Freitas</surname>
                      <given-names>NEM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Daltro</surname>
                      <given-names>RT</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Regis-Silva</surname>
                      <given-names>CG</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Acute chagas disease in brazil from 2001 to 2018: A nationwide spatiotemporal analysis</article-title>
                  <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <issue>8</issue>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>16</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B6">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Freitas</surname>
                      <given-names>JLP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Biancalana</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>AmatoNeto</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nussenzweig</surname>
                      <given-names>V</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sonntag</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Barreto</surname>
                      <given-names>JG</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Primeiras verificações de transmissão acidental da moléstia de Chagas ao homem por transfusão de sangue</article-title>
                  <source>Rev Paul Med</source>
                  <year>1952</year>
                  <volume>40</volume>
                  <fpage>36</fpage>
                  <lpage>40</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14942150</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B7">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Santana</surname>
                      <given-names>MP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Souza-Santos</surname>
                      <given-names>R</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>De Almeida</surname>
                      <given-names>AS</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Prevalência da doença de chagas entre doadores de sangue do estado do Piauí, Brasil, no período de 2004 a 2013</article-title>
                  <source>Cad Saude Publica</source>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <volume>34</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>15</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B8">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Melo</surname>
                      <given-names>AS</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lorena</surname>
                      <given-names>VMB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Moraes</surname>
                      <given-names>AB</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pinto</surname>
                      <given-names>MBA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leão</surname>
                      <given-names>SC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Soares</surname>
                      <given-names>AKA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Prevalência de infecção chagásica em doadores de sangue no estado de Pernambuco, Brasil</article-title>
                  <source>Rev Bras Hematol Hemoter</source>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <volume>31</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>69</fpage>
                  <lpage>73</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B9">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Costa</surname>
                      <given-names>AC da</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rocha</surname>
                      <given-names>EA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Silva</surname>
                      <given-names>JD da</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fidalgo ASO de</surname>
                      <given-names>BV</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nunes</surname>
                      <given-names>FMM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Viana</surname>
                      <given-names>CEM</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Prevalência da Infecção pelo Trypanosoma cruzi em Doadores de Sangue</article-title>
                  <source>Arq Bras Cardiol</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>115</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <fpage>1082</fpage>
                  <lpage>1091</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33470305</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="database">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>DATASUS. Brasil, Ministério da Saúde</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Banco de dados do Sistema Único de Saúde-DATASUS</source>
                  <date-in-citation content-type="access-date" iso-8601-date="2021-04-05">2021 Apr 5</date-in-citation>
                  <comment>Available from: <ext-link xlink:href="http://www.datasus.gov.br" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.datasus.gov.br</ext-link>
</comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="database">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>SIM. Brasil, Ministerio da Saúde</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Banco de dados do Sistema de Informações de Mortalidade (SIM)</source>
                  <date-in-citation content-type="access-date" iso-8601-date="2021-04-05">2021 Apr 5</date-in-citation>
                  <comment>Available from: <ext-link xlink:href="http://tabnet.datasus.gov.br/cgi/deftohtm.exe?sim/cnv/obt10al.def" ext-link-type="uri">http://tabnet.datasus.gov.br/cgi/deftohtm.exe?sim/cnv/obt10al.def</ext-link>
</comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Antunes</surname>
                      <given-names>JLF</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cardoso</surname>
                      <given-names>MRA</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Using time series analysis in epidemiological studies</article-title>
                  <source>Epidemiol Serv Saúde</source>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <volume>24</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>565</fpage>
                  <lpage>576</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B13">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>IBGE</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Instituto Brasileiro de Geografia e Estatística - Brasil, Alagoas, Panorama</source>
                  <ext-link xlink:href="https://cidades.ibge.gov.br/brasil/al/panorama" ext-link-type="uri">https://cidades.ibge.gov.br/brasil/al/panorama</ext-link>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dias</surname>
                      <given-names>JCP</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ramos</surname>
                      <given-names>AN</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gontijo</surname>
                      <given-names>ED</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Luquetti</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shikanai-Yasuda</surname>
                      <given-names>MA</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Coura</surname>
                      <given-names>JR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Aspectos Gerais da Epidemiologia da Doença de Chagas com Especial Atenção ao Brasil</article-title>
                  <source>Epidemiol e Serv Saude</source>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <volume>25</volume>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
                  <lpage>86</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="B15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dias</surname>
                      <given-names>JCP</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Doença de Chagas e transfusão de sangue no Brasil: Vigilância e desafios</article-title>
                  <source>Rev Bras Hematol Hemoter</source>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <volume>28</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <fpage>83</fpage>
                  <lpage>84</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
