<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-03-11T00:53:15Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8164697" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8164697</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-06-01</datestamp>
        <setSpec>idr</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Infect Drug Resist</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Infect Drug Resist</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">idr</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">idr</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Infection and Drug Resistance</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1178-6973</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC8164697</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8164697</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">8164697</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34079304</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">299704</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IDR.S299704</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Original Research</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Forecasting the Tuberculosis Incidence Using a Novel Ensemble Empirical Mode Decomposition-Based Data-Driven Hybrid Model in Tibet, China</article-title>
                <alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Li et al</alt-title>
                <alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Li et al</alt-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Li</surname>
                    <given-names>Jizhen</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Li</surname>
                    <given-names>Yuhong</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0002">
                    <sup>2</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ye</surname>
                    <given-names>Ming</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0003">
                    <sup>3</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Yao</surname>
                    <given-names>Sanqiao</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Yu</surname>
                    <given-names>Chongchong</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Wang</surname>
                    <given-names>Lei</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0004">
                    <sup>4</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7334-8679</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Wu</surname>
                    <given-names>Weidong</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Wang</surname>
                    <given-names>Yongbin</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff0001">
                    <sup>1</sup>
                  </xref>
                  <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="an0001"/>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="aff0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Epidemiology and Health Statistics, School of Public Health, Xinxiang Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Xinxiang</addr-line>, <addr-line>Henan Province</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
                <aff id="aff0002"><label>2</label><institution>National Center for Tuberculosis Control and Prevention, China Center for Disease Control and Prevention</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
                <aff id="aff0003"><label>3</label><institution>Preventive Medicine Clinic, Xinxiang Center for Disease Control and Prevention</institution>, <addr-line>Xinxiang</addr-line>, <addr-line>Henan Province</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country></aff>
                <aff id="aff0004"><label>4</label><institution>Center for Musculoskeletal Surgery, Charité–Universitätsmedizin Berlin, Corporate Member of Freie Universität Berlin, Humboldt–Universität Zu Berlin and Berlin Institute of Health</institution>, <addr-line>Berlin</addr-line>, <country>Germany</country></aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="an0001">Correspondence: Yongbin Wang <institution>Department of Epidemiology and Health Statistics, School of Public Health, Xinxiang Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Xinxiang</addr-line>, <addr-line>Henan Province</addr-line>, <addr-line>453000</addr-line>, <country>People’s Republic of China</country> Email wybwho@163.com</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>25</day>
                <month>5</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>14</volume>
              <fpage>1941</fpage>
              <lpage>1955</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>29</day>
                  <month>12</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>14</day>
                  <month>4</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2021 Li et al.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
                <copyright-holder>Li et al.</copyright-holder>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract>
                <sec id="s2001">
                  <title>Objective</title>
                  <p>The purpose of this study is to develop a novel data-driven hybrid model by fusing ensemble empirical mode decomposition (EEMD), seasonal autoregressive integrated moving average (SARIMA), with nonlinear autoregressive artificial neural network (NARNN), called EEMD-ARIMA-NARNN model, to assess and forecast the epidemic patterns of TB in Tibet.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s2002">
                  <title>Methods</title>
                  <p>The TB incidence from January 2006 to December 2017 was obtained, and then the time series was partitioned into training subsamples (from January 2006 to December 2016) and testing subsamples (from January to December 2017). Among them, the training set was used to develop the EEMD-SARIMA-NARNN combined model, whereas the testing set was used to validate the forecasting performance of the model. Whilst the forecasting accuracy level of this novel method was compared with the basic SARIMA model, basic NARNN model, error-trend-seasonal (ETS) model, and traditional SARIMA-NARNN mixture model.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s2003">
                  <title>Results</title>
                  <p>By comparing the accuracy level of the forecasting measurements including root-mean-square error, mean absolute deviation, mean error rate, mean absolute percentage error, and root-mean-square percentage error, it was shown that the EEMD-SARIMA-NARNN combined method produced lower error rates than the others. The descriptive statistics suggested that TB was a seasonal disease, peaking in late winter and early spring and a trough in autumn and early winter, and the TB epidemic indicated a drastic increase by a factor of 1.7 from 2006 to 2017 in Tibet, with average annual percentage change of 5.8 (95% confidence intervals: 3.5–8.1).</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s2004">
                  <title>Conclusion</title>
                  <p>This novel data-driven hybrid method can better consider both linear and nonlinear components in the TB incidence than the others used in this study, which is of great help to estimate and forecast the future epidemic trends of TB in Tibet. Besides, under present trends, strict precautionary measures are required to reduce the spread of TB in Tibet.</p>
                </sec>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group kwd-group-type="author">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>tuberculosis</kwd>
                <kwd>incidence rate</kwd>
                <kwd>time series analysis</kwd>
                <kwd>statistical models</kwd>
                <kwd>forecasting</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <counts>
                <fig-count count="4"/>
                <table-count count="10"/>
                <ref-count count="67"/>
                <page-count count="15"/>
              </counts>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec sec-type="intro" id="s0001">
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Tuberculosis (TB) is a chronic communicable disease caused by the bacillus <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic>, it is a major cause of ill-health, ranking among the 10 leading causes of morbidity and mortality globally.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> The WHO estimated that about 10.0 million people developed TB in 2019 around the globe.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Furthermore, there were an estimated 1.4 million deaths associated with TB in 2019, leading to an annual approximately 1.8% and 2.8% reductions between 2015 and 2019 in the incidence and death rates, respectively, worldwide.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Currently, the global case notifications were mainly reported from 30 high TB burden countries, accounting for around 87% of the worldwide totals.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Of them, ranking the third is China, where the proportion of the reported cases reaches 8.4% in the world.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Moreover, China also has the second share (14%) of the global burden of drug-resistant TB in 2019, despite progress in cutting TB incidence with an average annual percent change of 3.2% between 1990 and 2017.<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> However, recent years have been witnessing a risk of resurgence in the TB incidence in some regions in China, attributable to climate change, alcohol use disorders, diabetes, HIV infection, smoking, and undernourishment, which have suppressed the progress of the end TB strategy with a target of 90% and 95% reductions in the TB incidence and death rates, respectively, in the period 2015–2035.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> To accelerate progress towards such an ambitious goal, accurately estimating and forecasting the past, current, and future epidemic trends of TB play a pivotal role in forming the targeted prevention and control measures and in adjusting the present interventions.</p>
              <p>There is a large volume of studies forecasting the epidemiological trends of communicable diseases using different statistical techniques, such as the seasonal autoregressive integrated moving average (SARIMA) method,<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> exponential smoothing method,<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> generalized regression neural network (GRNN) method,<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> nonlinear autoregressive neural network (NARNN) method,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> backpropagation neural network (BPNN) method,<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> multivariate linear regression method,<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> and Elman and Jordan recurrent neural networks.<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Among them, the most frequently used linear method is the SARIMA model,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12–15</xref> whereas the nonlinear method is the NARNN model.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> However, there are various factors affecting and limiting the epidemiological patterns of diseases.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> For this reason, the epidemics of communicable diseases are often characterized by linear and nonlinear patterns.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> However, the above-mentioned statistical techniques are often insufficient to capture either tendencies or randomness in the time series, which may limit the generalization of the findings from the mentioned models. Therefore, to improve the prediction accuracy and reliability, an alternative approach is expected to be customized for use with both the above two traits included in the object series. Inspired by such an idea, many studies have adopted a hybrid technique comprising a linear model and a nonlinear model to yield more accurate prediction by integrating each model’s superiority.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></p>
              <p>Over the last years, wavelet analysis has become a popular method capable of decomposing the data into different high-scale and low-frequency components (linear trait) and low-scale and high-frequency components (nonlinear trait) particularly when target series shows complex nonstationary and nonlinear characteristics.<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> More recently, a new wavelet analysis approach-ensemble empirical mode decomposition (EEMD) was developed by adding noise to overcome the mode mixing disadvantage of the traditional empirical mode decomposition (EMD).<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Importantly, different from the most commonly used discrete wavelet transform techniques that may generate different decomposition results since they are required to predetermine basis functions,<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref> EEMD is a self-adaptive, intuitive, direct, and empirical decomposition method for the nonstationary and nonlinear time series.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Considering the superiority of the EEMD technique in decomposing the data and the worsening epidemic trends of TB in Tibet with the highest TB morbidity in China in the past years,<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> we thus proposed a novel forecasting method (designated as EEMD-SARIMA-NARNN hybrid method) by integrating the SARIMA and NARNN models based on the EEMD technique to capture both the tendencies and randomness in the time series simultaneously. Specifically, the EEMD technique was first applied to decompose the TB incidence series into several Intrinsic Mode Functions (IMFs) components representing the different nonlinear parts of the data and a residue component denoting the tendency of the data. Second, using the NARNN and SARIMA methods to model the IMFs and residue components, respectively. Finally, the forecasting values from the IMFs and residue components were aggregated as the predicted results from the EEMD-SARIMA-NARNN hybrid technique. By doing so, the linear and nonlinear parts contained in the TB incidence series can be considered by this data-driven mixture method simultaneously. Whilst we also compared the fitted and predicted results from the basic SARIMA model, basic NARNN model, and the traditional SARIMA-NARNN mixture model with that from our proposed novel hybrid method to judge the forecasting performance of this novel data-driven method.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s0002">
              <title>Materials and Methods</title>
              <sec id="s0002-s2001">
                <title>Study Area and Data Source</title>
                <p>Tibet is located in the southwest of the People’s Republic of China. It is one of the five ethnic autonomous regions in China, and its average elevation is above 4000 m, known as the “roof of the world”. Tibet covers 1228.4 km<sup>2</sup>. At the end of 2019, the resident population was 3.506 million.</p>
                <p>The monthly incident cases between January 2006 and December 2017 reported to the Center for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) were taken from the National Notifiable Infectious Disease Surveillance System (NNIDSS), and the population data during the same period from the Bureau of statistics of Tibet Autonomous Region (<underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tjj.xizang.gov.cn/">http://tjj.xizang.gov.cn/</ext-link></underline>). A total of 144 observations across 12 years were aggregated. Generally, it is required to use preferably 100 observations or more to develop object models so that a reliable and stable result is obtained.<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> Therefore, the observations used in this research were partitioned into two parts including a training dataset comprising 132 observations (from January 2006 to December 2016) and a testing dataset comprising 12 observations (from January to December 2017).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s0002-s2002">
                <title>Ethics Approval and Consent to Participate</title>
                <p>The study protocol was approved by the study institutional review board of the Xinxiang Medical University (No: XYLL-2019,072), and consent is not needed for this study since we only collected the reported monthly TB cases publicly available without the detailed individual information.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s0002-s2003">
                <title>A New Hybrid Model of EEMD-SARIMA-NARNN</title>
                <sec id="s0002-s2003-s3001">
                  <title>EEMD Technique</title>
                  <p>In the past, albeit EMD technique shows remarkable superiority in signal analysis, particularly for the data produced in noisy nonlinear and non-stationary processes, there are two major weaknesses including the edge-effects and mode-mixing,<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> especially for the mode-mixing disadvantage, which not only results in the mixing of different scale vibration modes but can even cause the loss of the physical meaning of each IMFs.<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> The EEMD method was thus developed based on the EMD algorithm to overcome the barriers of the original technique.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> In the EEMD approach, it uses a powerful method of ensemble mean to improve the accuracy of measurements.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> Namely, it defines the actual individual IMFs components as the average of an ensemble of experiments, each IMF component is composed of the signal and noise of finite-amplitude.<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> The decomposition procedure of the EEMD approach can be in the form as below.</p>
                  <p>Initially, add white noise w(<italic>t</italic>) to the given time series <italic>x</italic>(<italic>t</italic>), and the obtained new series can be expressed as
<disp-formula-group><disp-formula id="m0001"><label>(1)</label><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="IDR-14-1941-e0001.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$$X(t)\, = \,x(t) + w(t)$$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></disp-formula></disp-formula-group></p>
                  <p>Secondly, decompose the produced series into IMFs with the help of the EMD algorithm.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, repeat the above two steps using various white noise series, the resulting results were added to the original series each time.</p>
                  <p>Finally, average the ensemble of the corresponding IMFs generated by the EMD decomposition technique.</p>
                  <p>In the process of decomposition, the numbers of the ensemble and the amplitude of the added white noise play a pivotal role in the obtained final results.<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> Fortunately, a well-demonstrated statistical rule helps to determine these two key parameters<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>:<disp-formula-group><disp-formula id="m0002"><label>(2)</label><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="IDR-14-1941-e0002.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><tex-math id="M2">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$${\varepsilon _n}\, = \,{\varepsilon \over N}$$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></disp-formula></disp-formula-group></p>
                  <p>where <italic>N</italic> represents the numbers of the ensemble, <inline-formula id="ilm0001"><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="IDR-14-1941-e0003.jpg"/><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$$\varepsilon $$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></inline-formula> is the amplitude of the added white noise, and<inline-formula id="ilm0002"><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="IDR-14-1941-e0004.jpg"/><tex-math id="M4">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$${\varepsilon _n}\,$$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></inline-formula>signifies the standard deviation of the error. Prior studies have found that the parameter settings with the ensemble numbers of 100 and the amplitude of added white noise of 0.2 times standard deviation can generate a satisfactory result.<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s0002-s2004">
                <title>EEMD-SARIMA-NARNN Hybrid Model</title>
                <p>To this end that makes full use of the possible linear and nonlinear information contained in the target series, inspired by the idea of “decomposition and ensemble” of the EEMD technique and the powerful ability to extract nonlinear information of the NARNN model,<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> the EEMD-SARIMA-NARNN hybrid model was thus proposed (<underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=299704.docx">Figure S1</ext-link></underline>). In this project, the time series of TB morbidity was decomposed into different IMFs subseries and residue terms. Then, each of IMFs subseries was predicted using a suitable NARNN model, while the residue term was forecasted with an appropriate SARIMA model. As such, the final results can be derived by integrating the resulting values of the SARIMA model with the counterparts of the NARNN approaches. By doing so, the hybrid model can then attain a capacity that unearths all possible components included in the data. The specified equation of a SARIMA-NARNN combined model can be written as
<disp-formula-group><disp-formula id="m0003"><label>(3)</label><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="IDR-14-1941-e0005.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$$IM{F_t}\, = \,\sum\limits_{i = 1}^N {(f(IMF(t -1), \cdots } ,IM{F_1}(t - d) + \Lambda \, + (f(IM{F_N}(t -1){\rm{,}} \cdots {\rm{,}}IM{F_N}(t - d)$$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></disp-formula></disp-formula-group>
<disp-formula-group><disp-formula id="m0004"><label>(4)</label><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="IDR-14-1941-e0006.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><tex-math id="M6">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$$\mathop y\limits^\^ \, = \,\mathop a\limits^\^ {\,_t} + \,IM{F_t}$$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></disp-formula></disp-formula-group></p>
                <p>where <inline-formula id="ilm0003"><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="IDR-14-1941-e0007.jpg"/><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$$\mathop y\limits^\^ $$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></inline-formula> represents the estimates using the proposed hybrid method,<inline-formula id="ilm0004"><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="IDR-14-1941-e0008.jpg"/><tex-math id="M8">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$$\,\mathop a\limits^\^ {\,_t}$$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></inline-formula> is the estimates of residue terms using the SARIMA method,<inline-formula id="ilm0005"><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="IDR-14-1941-e0009.jpg"/><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$$\,\mathop e\limits^\^ {\,_t}$$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></inline-formula> refers to the estimates of IMFs subseries using the NARNN method.</p>
                <p>Furthermore, the SARIMA method, NARNN method, and traditional SARIMA-NARNN method were created according to the steps described in supplementary material.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s0002-s2005">
                <title>Statistical Analysis</title>
                <p>The TB epidemic trends and changes were measured with average annual percentage change (AAPC) based on the joinpoint regression program (Version 4.8.0.1). The basic SARIMA method was constructed with R software (version 3.4.3, R Development Core Team, Vienna, Austria), and the EEMD, basic NARNN, SARIMA-NARNN, and EEMD-SARIMA-NARNN methods were developed using MATLAB software (Version R2014a, MathWorks, Natick, MA, USA). The Lagrangian Multiplier (LM) method was used to test the conditional heteroskedastic behavior and volatility (ARCH effect) of the residual series from the selected four models.<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref> The root-mean-square error (RMSE), mean absolute deviation (MAD), mean error rate (MER), mean absolute percentage error (MAPE), and root-mean-square percentage error (RMSPE) were chosen to assess the predictive accuracy levels among models. The lower the indices’ values are, the better the models are.
<disp-formula-group><disp-formula id="m0005"><label>(5)</label><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="IDR-14-1941-e0010.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><tex-math id="M10">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$${\rm{RMSE}}\,{\rm{ = }}\,\sqrt {{1 \over N}} \,\sum\limits_{i = 1}^N {({X_i}} \, - \,{\mathop X\limits^\^ _i}{)^2}$$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></disp-formula></disp-formula-group>
<disp-formula-group><disp-formula id="m0006"><label>(6)</label><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="IDR-14-1941-e0011.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$${\rm{MAD = }}\,{1 \over N}\,\sum\limits_{i = 1}^N {{{\left| {{X_i}\,\, - \,{{\mathop X\limits^\^ }_i}} \right|}_{}}} $$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></disp-formula></disp-formula-group>
<disp-formula-group><disp-formula id="m0007"><label>(7)</label><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="IDR-14-1941-e0012.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><tex-math id="M12">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$${\rm{MER = }}\,{{{1 \over N}\,\sum\limits_{i = 1}^N {{{\left| {{X_i}\,\, - \,{{\mathop X\limits^\^ }_i}} \right|}_{}}} } \over {\overline {{X_i}} }}$$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></disp-formula></disp-formula-group>
<disp-formula-group><disp-formula id="m0008"><label>(8)</label><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="IDR-14-1941-e0013.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><tex-math id="M13">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$${\rm{MAPE = }}{{\rm{1}} \over {\rm{N}}}\,\sum\limits_{{\rm{i = 1}}}^{\rm{N}} {{{\left| {{{\rm{X}}_{\rm{i}}}\,\,{\rm{ - }}\,{{\mathop {\rm{X}}\limits^{\rm{\^}} }_{\rm{i}}}} \right|} \over {{{\rm{X}}_{\rm{i}}}}}} \,{\rm{ \times }}\,{\rm{100}}$$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></disp-formula></disp-formula-group>
<disp-formula-group><disp-formula id="m0009"><label>(9)</label><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="IDR-14-1941-e0014.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><tex-math id="M14">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$${\rm{RMSPE}}\,{\rm{ = }}\,\sqrt {{{\rm{1}} \over {\rm{N}}}} \,\sum\limits_{{\rm{i = 1}}}^{\rm{N}} {{{{{{\rm{(}}{{\rm{X}}_{\rm{i}}}{\rm{ - }}\,{{\mathop {\rm{X}}\limits^{\rm{\^}} }_{\rm{i}}}{\rm{)}}}^{\rm{2}}}} \over {{{\rm{X}}_{\rm{i}}}}}\,\,} \,$$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></disp-formula></disp-formula-group></p>
                <p>where <italic>X<sub>i</sub></italic> signifies the observed TB values,<inline-formula id="ilm0006"><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="IDR-14-1941-e0015.jpg"/><tex-math id="M15">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$$\mathop {{X_i}}\limits^\^ $$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></inline-formula>is the estimates using the chosen approaches,<inline-formula id="ilm0007"><alternatives><inline-graphic xlink:href="IDR-14-1941-e0016.jpg"/><tex-math id="M16">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{wasysym}
\usepackage[substack]{amsmath}
\usepackage{amsfonts}
\usepackage{amssymb}
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage[mathscr]{eucal}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\DeclareFontFamily{T1}{linotext}{}
\DeclareFontShape{T1}{linotext}{m}{n} {linotext }{}
\DeclareSymbolFont{linotext}{T1}{linotext}{m}{n}
\DeclareSymbolFontAlphabet{\mathLINOTEXT}{linotext}
\begin{document}
$$\mathop {\overline {{X_i}} }\limits^{} $$
\end{document}</tex-math></alternatives></inline-formula>refers to the mean of all the observed TB values, and <italic>N</italic> stands for the number of simulations and forecasts.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s0003">
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="s0003-s2001">
                <title>Descriptive Analysis</title>
                <p>During the period 2006–2017, the reported TB cases totaled 45,025 with notified 3753 cases annually, leading to annualized and monthly incidence rates of 121.9 and 10.2 per 100,000 persons, respectively. As illustrated in <underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=299704.docx">Figure S2</ext-link></underline>, when the seasonal-trend decomposition procedure based on Loess (STL) technique was applied to the TB morbidity series, it was found that the TB epidemic showed a drastic increase by a factor of 1.7 from 2006 to 2017, with AAPC=5.8 (95% confidence intervals: 3.5–8.1; Z=5.8, <italic>P</italic>&lt;0.001) (<underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=299704.docx">Figure S3</ext-link></underline>). The highest TB morbidity rate was noted in 2017 (152.0 cases per 100,000 people), it has increased 2.4-fold compared with 2008 when the morbidity rate was lowest (64.7 cases per 100,000 people). Besides, it was observed that the TB morbidity had notable seasonal effects, with a peak occurred in January until August, especially in January and March, and a trough in September until December, particularly in December (<underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=299704.docx">Figures S2</ext-link></underline> and <underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=299704.docx">S4</ext-link></underline>).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s0003-s2002">
                <title>The Best-Fitting SARIMA Method</title>
                <p>The original TB incidence series showed a unit root (ADF=−1.3, <italic>P</italic>=0.2) and marked seasonal effects (<underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=299704.docx">Figure S2</ext-link></underline>), indicating a nonstationary series, and thus seasonally differencing once to remove the seasonal variation of the data. By doing so, the differenced data met the prerequisite of the SARIMA model development, being stationary (ADF=−3.4, <italic>P</italic>=0.001). Afterward, by plotting the ACF and PACF graphs for the stationary series, the autocorrelations at lags 1, 2, and 3 and partial autocorrelations at lags 1 and 2 were found to touch the significance levels (<underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=299704.docx">Figure S5</ext-link></underline>), and we observed that the values of the key parameters (p, q, P, and Q) of SARIMA model exceeded 2, the model’s parameter suggested no statistical significance, and thereby we selected several plausible models with the key parameters were between 0 and 2. <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> demonstrates that the SARIMA(2,0,0)(2,1,0)<sub>12</sub> model seems to provide adequate modeling for the object series since this model presented the lowest values of performance indices (AIC=409.2, CAIC=409.7, and BIC=423.2) among the possible nine models, and statistical test of the estimated parameters for this method was indicated significantly different (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Moreover, both the Ljung–Box Q test and LM test showed a <italic>P</italic>-value greater than 0.05 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1A</xref>, <underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=299704.docx">Tables S1</ext-link></underline> and <underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=299704.docx">S2</ext-link></underline>), suggesting that the residuals behaved like white noise and the ARCH effect had been removed from the residuals. The above tests mean that the SARIMA(2,0,0)(2,1,0)<sub>12</sub> model is appropriate for describing this time series. Therefore, this model is taken as the best.<table-wrap id="t0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The Identified Nine Plausible SARIMA Methods and Their Information Criteria</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Models</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AIC</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAIC</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">BIC</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Log-Likelihood</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SARIMA(2,0,0)(2,1,0)<sub>12</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">409.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">409.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">423.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−199.61</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SARIMA(1,0,2)(2,1,0)<sub>12</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">410.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">410.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">426.73</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−199.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SARIMA(1,0,1)(2,1,0)<sub>12</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">411.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">412.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">425.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−200.92</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SARIMA(0,0,2)(2,1,0)<sub>12</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">440.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">440.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">454.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−215.21</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SARIMA(2,0,1)(2,1,0)<sub>12</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">410.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">411.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">427.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−199.35</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SARIMA(2,0,1)(0,1,1)<sub>12</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">415.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">416.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">429.78</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−202.92</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SARIMA(2,0,1)(0,1,2)<sub>12</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">416.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">416.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">432.90</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−202.09</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SARIMA(2,0,0)(1,1,1)<sub>12</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">415.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">415.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">429.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−202.53</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SARIMA(2,0,0)(1,1,0)<sub>12</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">432.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">433.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">443.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−212.40</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: SARIMA, seasonal autoregressive integrated moving average method; AIC, Akaike’s Information Criterion; BIC, Bayesian Information Criterion.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="t0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Statistical Test of the Estimated Parameters for the Optimal SARIMA (2,0,0)(2,1,0)<sub>12</sub> Method</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimates</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard Error</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>t</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.519</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.089</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.831</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.329</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.092</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.576</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SAR1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.736</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.086</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−8.558</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SAR2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.526</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.089</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−5.910</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0002"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: SARIMA, seasonal autoregressive integrated moving average method; AR1, autoregressive method at lag 1; AR2, autoregressive method at lag 2; SAR1, seasonal autoregressive method at lag 1; SAR2, seasonal autoregressive method at lag 2.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig id="f0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Estimated autocorrelogram and partial autocorrelogram of the residual sequence to forecast the TB epidemic patterns using (A) SARIMA model, (B) basic NARNN model, (C) traditional SARIMA-NARNN hybrid model, and (D) novel EEMD-SARIMA-NARNN hybrid model. As seen, the estimated autocorrelations and partial autocorrelations of the errors from the different models almost fell into the 95% confidence intervals (CIs) with few exceptions, such as the autocorrelations at lags 15 and 19 and partial autocorrelations at lags 15 in (A), and autocorrelations and partial autocorrelations at lag 11 in (D), these are also reasonable because higher-order autocorrelations and partial autocorrelations easily exceed the 95 CIs by chance.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="IDR-14-1941-g0001"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s0003-s2003">
                <title>The Best-Fitting NARNN Method</title>
                <p>As described in previous studies, the ANNs models with hidden units between 10 and 20 and feedback delays between 3 and 7 can often provide a satisfactory prediction and ease overfitting to a certain degree.<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33–37</xref> Therefore, we trained a series of networks with the mentioned-above ranges of hidden units and feedback delays by trial and error so that a preferred model was discovered. By doing so, the NARNN (16, 6) model with 16 hidden units and 6 feedback delays tended to be indicated the optimal in that this network structure produced the lowest MSE values in the training (0.6), validation (4.5), and testing (3.8), and all R values were greater than 0.8 in the training (1.0), validation (0.8), testing (0.8), and the whole data (0.9) (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> and <underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=299704.docx">Figure S6</ext-link></underline>). Also, as shown in <underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=299704.docx">Figure S7</ext-link></underline>, the modeling results of this model agreed pretty well with the observed values as most of the errors were between −1 and 1. Additionally, the Ljung–Box Q and LM-test statistics for the residual sequence yielded by this model showed a <italic>P</italic>-value greater than 0.05 (<underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=299704.docx">Tables S1</ext-link></underline> and <underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=299704.docx">S2</ext-link></underline>), and the sample autocorrelation and partial autocorrelation for the in-sample forecast errors at different lags failed to exceed the significance bounds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1B</xref>), implying that the in-sample forecast errors showed a white noise and no ARCH effect. Thus, we are confident that the NARNN (16, 6) model was considered optimal in this study.<table-wrap id="t0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>The Estimated Parameters of the Optimal NARNN Models for the Original Series and Decomposed Series Using the EEMD Method</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Target<break/>Components</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Hidden Units</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Delays</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">MSE</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">R</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Training</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Validation</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Testing</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Training</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Validation</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Testing</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Original series</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.648</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.531</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.760</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.973</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.842</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.848</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.944</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Residuals of<break/>SARIMA model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.537</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.110</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.287</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.806</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.714</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.607</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.715</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IMF1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.124</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.885</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.806</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.967</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.799</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.827</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.911</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IMF2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.052</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.101</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.226</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.992</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.979</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.971</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.988</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IMF3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IMF4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IMF5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">IMF6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0003"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: SARIMA, seasonal autoregressive integrated moving average method; NARNN, nonlinear autoregressive artificial neural network.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s0003-s2004">
                <title>The Best-Fitting Traditional SARIMA-NARNN Mixture Method</title>
                <p>In the process of constructing the traditional SARIMA-NARNN method, the residual series from the SARIMA model was utilized to train the best NARNN model. Similarly, we found that the NARNN (19, 6) method with 19 hidden units and 6 feedback delays appeared to be abundant for modeling the object series via repeated modeling as this model had a relatively great R-value and a relatively low MSR value in the training, validation, and testing data (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). Further, we investigated the residual series from the SARIMA(2,0,0)(2,1,0)<sub>12</sub>-NARNN (16, 6) mixture model using the Ljung–Box Q and LM tests, showing that this residual series belonged to a white noise series and also no ARCH effect was noted in the residuals (<underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=299704.docx">Tables S1</ext-link></underline> and <underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=299704.docx">S2</ext-link></underline>). Besides, the sample autocorrelations and partial autocorrelations for the in-sample forecast errors inside the 95% uncertainty bounds also indicated that the errors met the assumption of uncorrelatedness (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1C</xref>). Thereby, the SARIMA(2,0,0)(2,1,0)<sub>12</sub>-NARNN (16, 6) mixture model is considered the best-performing in this work.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s0003-s2005">
                <title>The Best-Fitting Novel EEMD-SARIMA-NARNN Mixture Method</title>
                <p>The EEMD technique was employed to decompose the TB morbidity series. As listed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0002">Figure 2</xref>, the original series was decomposed into six different IMFs subseries and a residue term. Subsequently, the residue term was modeled using the SARIMA method and the IMFs terms were modeled with different NARNN methods, and the resulting results showed that the SARIMA (1,2,0)(1,0,1)<sub>12</sub> method was the most suitable for modeling the residue term and NARNN(17, 5), NARNN(16, 5), NARNN(15, 5), NARNN(16, 6), NARNN(14, 4), and NARNN(14, 5) models were taken to be the best methods for modeling the IMF1~IMF6 subseries (<xref rid="t0003" ref-type="table">Tables 3</xref>–<xref rid="t0004" ref-type="table">4</xref>), respectively, and the diagnostic test results for the best SARIMA model and different NARNN models are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0003">Figure 3</xref> and <underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=299704.docx">S8</ext-link></underline>-<underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=299704.docx">S14</ext-link></underline>. Further checking results for the residuals from the new EEMD-SARIMA-NARNN mixture method are given in <underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=299704.docx">Tables S1-S2</ext-link></underline> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1D</xref>. The <italic>P</italic>-values for LM and Ljung–Box Q tests were greater than 0.05 (<underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=299704.docx">Tables S1</ext-link></underline>-<underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=299704.docx">S2</ext-link></underline>), suggesting that there was no ARCH effect in the errors and there was little evidence of non-zero autocorrelations in the in-sample forecast errors at various lags, which could also be verified by the ACF and PACF plots as the sample autocorrelations and partial autocorrelations at different lags almost fell into the 95% significance bounds (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0001">Figure 1D</xref>). The above results intimated that this new data-driven mixture model can capture the short-term dependencies of the data and is adequate for forecasting the data.<table-wrap id="t0004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Statistical Test of the Estimated Parameters for the Optimal SARIMA (1,2,0)(1,0,1)<sub>12</sub> Method</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variables</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Estimates</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standard Error</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>t</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AR1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">578.647</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SAR1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.984</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.493</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SMA1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.692</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.152</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.564</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0004"><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: SARIMA, seasonal autoregressive integrated moving average method; AR1, autoregressive method at lag 1; SAR1, seasonal autoregressive method at lag 1; SMA1, seasonal moving average method at lag 1.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig id="f0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Intrinsic mode functions (IMFs) and residue components of the original TB incidence series using the EEMD.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="IDR-14-1941-g0002"/></fig><fig id="f0003" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Estimated autocorrelogram of the residual sequence to forecast the six intrinsic mode functions (IMFs) decomposed by the EEMD method using the SARIMA-NARNN hybrid model. (<bold>A</bold>) IMF1, (<bold>B</bold>) IMF2, (<bold>C</bold>) IMF3, (<bold>D</bold>) IMF4, (<bold>E</bold>) IMF5, and (<bold>F</bold>) IMF6. For the estimated autocorrelations of the residual series from the different IMFs, all of them are inside of the 95 CIs except for the one at lag zero, meaning that there is no correlated serial in the residuals of the best-fitting SARIMA-NARNN hybrid model. Thereby, there appears to be adequate and reasonable for forecasting upcoming epidemiological trends using these best-fitting models.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="IDR-14-1941-g0003"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s0003-s2006">
                <title>Assessing the Predictive Accuracy Levels Among Models</title>
                <p>We used the preferred individual models to predict the testing data, and then comparing the predictive accuracy levels among models from two aspects of the training and forecasting horizons based on five measures including RMSE, MAD, MER, MAPE, and RMSPE. The comparative results showed that our proposed EEMD-SARIMA-NARNN mixture model produced lower values of the above five measures compared with other methods used in this study both in training and forecasting horizons (<xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). Likewise, visible in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f0004">Figure 4</xref>, it makes sense that this new mixture technique can better capture the temporal dependency structure of the TB incidence series than the others.<table-wrap id="t0005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Comparisons of the Fitted and Forecasted Accuracy Levels Among the Optimal Four Methods</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="1">Models</th><th colspan="5" rowspan="1">Simulated Part</th><th colspan="5" rowspan="1">Predicted Part</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAD</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAPE</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">RMSE</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MER</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">RMSPE</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAD</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAPE</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">RMSE</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">MER</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">RMSPE</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SARIMA model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.977</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.222</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.216</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.702</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.444</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.486</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.658</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.114</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.805</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NARNN model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.770</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.301</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.170</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.078</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.258</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.183</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.335</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.309</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.093</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.101</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SARIMA-NARNN hybrid model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.648</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.634</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.856</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.066</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.155</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.443</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.281</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.803</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.114</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.143</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">EEMD-SARIMA-NARNN hybrid model</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.438</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.814</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.669</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.045</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.141</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.965</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.958</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.133</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.076</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.096</td></tr><tr><td colspan="11" rowspan="1"><bold>Reduced percentage</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D vs A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.169</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.280</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.984</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.782</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.172</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.716</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.665</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.333</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.477</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D vs B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.117</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.606</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.821</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.308</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.349</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.428</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.751</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.445</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.280</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.950</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">D vs C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.407</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.079</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.846</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.818</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.032</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.125</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.457</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.160</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.333</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.867</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0005"><p><bold>Notes</bold>: A refers to the SARIMA method, B takes for the NARNN method, C signifies the traditional SARIMA-NARNN mixture method, D is the novel EEMD-SARIMA-NARNN mixture method.</p><p><bold>Abbreviations</bold>: SARIMA, seasonal autoregressive integrated moving average method; EEMD, ensemble empirical mode decomposition; NARNN, nonlinear autoregressive artificial neural network; MAD, mean absolute deviation; MAPE, mean absolute percentage error; RMSE, root-mean-square error; MER, mean error rate; RMSPE, root-mean-square percentage error.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig id="f0004" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Time series plot showing the comparative results between original observations and fitted and predicted values using the selected best-fitting (<bold>A</bold>) SARIMA model, (<bold>B</bold>) NARNN model, (<bold>C</bold>) traditional SARIMA-NARNN hybrid model, and (<bold>D</bold>) novel EEMD-SARIMA-NARNN hybrid model (The curve at the left of the vertical black dotted line represents the fitted values, whereas the curve at the right denotes the forecasted values). As shown, the produced curve from the EEMD-SARIMA-NARNN hybrid model is closer to the actual both in the fitted and predicted aspects compared with the curves from the other models.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="IDR-14-1941-g0004"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s0004">
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>Accurately estimating the epidemics of infectious diseases acts as a basis for the decision-making process and the rational allocation of limited health resources under dynamic demand.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> The importance and originality of this work are that it creates a novel and more effective forecasting model for TB incidence series prediction by integrating the linear characteristics of a SARIMA method and nonlinear characteristics of the NARNN model based on the EEMD technique. By comparing the performance indicators of this novel model comprising RMSE, MAD, MER, MAPE, and RMSPE with the basic SARIMA model, basic NARNN model, and the traditional SARIMA-NARNN mixture model, it was observed that this new data-driven hybrid model showed better superiority than the others both in the fitted and predicted aspects. Often, the MAPE value is considered a useful measure to assess the forecasting accuracy of a model, with a value less than 10% indicating a highly accurate forecast, and a value less than 20% suggesting a good approximation to the observed values.<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref> Exhilaratingly, our proposed novel hybrid technique provided a highly accurate forecast for the TB morbidity series as the MAPE showed a value less than 10% both in the simulated and predicted horizons, which further reinforces the usefulness of our proposed new method as a helpful forecasting tool. Also, we used the TB incidence data in Qinghai province to provide an external validation for the predictive ability of our proposed hybrid method,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>
<underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=299704.docx">Tables S3</ext-link></underline>-<underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=299704.docx">S5</ext-link></underline> and <underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=299704.docx">Figures S15</ext-link></underline>-<underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=299704.docx">S16</ext-link></underline> exhibit the resulting results, suggesting a same finding as our current work that the EEMD-SARIMA-NARNN mixture method produces more accurate approximation to the TB incidence data in Qinghai. Besides, recent work of our research group indicates that the error-trend-seasonal (ETS) model can also accurately estimate and forecast the epidemic patterns of TB incidence,<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> and thus we further compared the mimic and predicted abilities between our proposed hybrid technique and ETS model. The modeling results displayed that the ETS(A,AD,A) model is supposed to be considered the preferred (<underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=299704.docx">Tables S6</ext-link></underline>-<underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=299704.docx">S7</ext-link></underline>). Similarly, visible in <underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/get_supplementary_file.php?f=299704.docx">Table S8</ext-link></underline>, the EEMD-SARIMA-NARNN hybrid technique also significantly outperforms the optimal ETS model. Therefore, this novel data-driven hybrid technique can be recommended as an effective and valuable tool in analyzing and estimating the temporal trends of the TB incidence in Tibet. Moreover, although the SARIMA model, NARNN model, ETS model, and SARIMA-NARNN mixture model produced a relatively low predictive performance relative to our proposed hybrid technique, they are also shown to have a good potential to model the TB epidemics because they gave a MAPE value less than 20% both in the mimic and predictive aspects, this is in good agreement with prior researches that used the above common models to analyze the temporal patterns of other infectious diseases (eg COVID-19,<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> typhoid and paratyphoid fevers,<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> schistosomiasis,<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> and hand-foot-mouth disease<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). Also, our proposed hybrid model can be used to estimate the current intervention effects for TB, if this model estimates a significantly higher incidence than the actual, meaning that the current interventions play an important role. Otherwise, additional or optimized measures are essential, such as optimization of the current tools, the pursuit of universal health coverage and social protection, the introduction of new vaccine and new prophylaxis, and the increase of the funding for TB.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></p>
              <p>The SARIMA model has been recommended as a versatile tool for estimating and forecasting time series with marked seasonality and periodicity, and for a non-stationary time series, after differencing or making a transformation with logarithm or square root, this model can also be used and can achieve satisfactory forecasting. For instance, Chen et al developed a SARIMA method to estimate the epidemiological trends of the influenza incidence, they found that the SARIMA(0,1,0) (0,1,2)<sub>12</sub> method showed a MAPE value of 10.597% for predicting the influenza incidence in the urban area of Shenyang, and the SARIMA(1,1,1) (1,1,0)<sub>12</sub> method had a MAPE value of 19.414% in the rural area.<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref> Gao et al observed that the SARIMA(0,1,7)(1,0,1)<sub>12</sub> method displayed a good performance for forecasting the cumulative incidences of typhoid (MAPE=13.257%) and paratyphoid fevers (MAPE=19.501%).<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref> Although the SARIMA model displays a good forecasting performance, it cannot describe the nonlinear information included in the TB morbidity in that this model assumes that there is a linear link between successive values of the time series.<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> However, different from the SARIMA model, the dynamic NARNN method has been deemed as a promising alternative to address any nonlinear issue without any constraints because of its short-run memory function besides the common properties of static BPNN and GRNN.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> Thereby, researchers developed the traditional SARIMA-NARNN mixture model to take advantage of each method’s potentials, and yet recent studies found that such a conventional combined mode may fail to model seasonal or trend variations effectively based on the unpreprocessed time series as the conventional model may not capture the linear and nonlinear components reasonably well,<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> namely, the conventional hybrid models do not necessarily overmatch their individual predictions.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> Also, as evidenced by our and other work, the traditional SARIMA-NARNN or other conventional mixture models (such as SARIMA-BPNN and SARIMA-GRNN) cannot offer a performance improvement over the basic NARNN and ETS methods on the testing data.<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47–49</xref> For this reason, our proposed data-driven hybrid model is more reasonably customized for forecasting the different components via decomposing the target series into different linear and nonlinear traits based on the EEMD method. As expected, this hybrid technique is shown to be mechanically more robust and accurate for forecasting the TB incidence in Tibet compared with the others. Given its superiority and the low-cost data collection, this data-driven EEMD-SARIMA-NARNN combined technique seems to be transferable to analyze the epidemiological trends of the TB incidence in other regions or other types of infectious diseases, even of all-time series data, whereas much work is still required to investigate its efficiency and usefulness. Besides, of note, some new advanced deep mining methods (such as long short-term memory neural network (LSTM) and convolutional neural network (CNN)) have currently been applied to predict the dengue cases,<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref> daily land surface temperature,<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> and ICD-9 codes of medical records,<xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref> and these studies suggested that the LSTM and CNN also showed high accuracy for forecasting the target series. Therefore, further work is supposed to compare the forecasting ability between our proposed combined method and the above deep mining methods.</p>
              <p>In this work, we discovered that the TB morbidity exhibited marked seasonal variations, predominantly peaking in late winter and early spring and a trough in autumn and early winter. Such a seasonal pattern is similar to previous findings from across China and most of the southwest regions of China (such as Qinghai, Xizang, and Yunnan),<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref> along with the results obtained in Japan and Spain.<xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> A preceding review to examine the seasonal variability based on 12 studies also supports further evidence that the peak patterns of TB are predominantly seen during the spring and summer seasons.<xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref> And yet in disagreement with that in Eastern Cape, the United States, Korea, Mongolia, northern India, and Kuwait.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56–58</xref> In this study, an interesting finding is that the TB incidence series in Tibet displayed a primarily exclusive semi-annual seasonal pattern with longer high-risk seasons from January until August and low-risk seasons from September until December per year, which is inconsistent with those observed in earlier studies.<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref> Seemingly, various factors are related to the mechanisms underlying TB high-risk seasonal behavior. Firstly, Tibet, as a famous tourist city, attracts hundreds of thousands of persons every year, with tourists being over 40 million in 2019.<xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref> Among them, the persons touring during the TB high-risk months approximately accounting for most of them. Large-scale population movements may drive the transmission of TB,<xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref> which is also in keeping with the temporal patterns present in the high-risk months in the spatial-temporal sequence. Secondly, current studies have shown that meteorological parameters may play a pivotal role in the spread of TB.<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref> A study found that the TB incidence showed a decreased trend with the increases in temperature and precipitation in Qinghai.<xref rid="cit0062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref> Another study suggested that wind speed is positively correlated with the TB incidence in Jinghong city of Yunnan.<xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref> The climate of Tibet is characterized by low pressure, strong wind, heavy rainfall, and relatively low temperature (annual mean temperature is 8°C), this climate type may increase the likelihood of contracting TB in the high-risk seasons as people tend to move indoors or crowded spaces for carrying out their activities and work.<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> Thirdly, it is thought that vitamin D levels may be closely associated with the seasonal variation of TB, this is mediated through the elevated risk of activation of latent TB because of late winter nadirs in vitamin D levels.<xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref> The reduced sunshine in winter causes vitamin D deficiency, which further influences the potential of macrophages to kill the <italic>bacillus Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> in vitro.<xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,<xref rid="cit0063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref> Fourthly, Lunar New Year, the foremost festival in China, may also play an important role in the seasonal peak patterns of TB since this festival is followed by the largest scale collective on the Tibet migrates, particularly in January and February per year. Given that there is an incubation of around 4–8 weeks from infection to medical diagnosis,<xref rid="cit0064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref> this is wholly in agreement with the maximum peak in March. Besides, it can be seen that there are lower reported cases in February than in January and March. This is derived from the fact that people do not tend to seek medical advice during the Lunar New Year period. Finally, in recent years, more and more activities involving the knowledge-attitude-behavior and new control modes of TB were implemented on World Tuberculosis Day in Tibet, which can enhance public awareness of TB and they are more willing to access healthcare. Besides, an investigation into other factors driving the seasonal variation should go on.</p>
              <p>In contrast with the fact that the TB morbidity is falling per year at the rates of about 1.6% and 3% since 2005 in the world and China, respectively,<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> the TB incidence was demonstrated to display a rapidly increasing trend in Tibet, with AAPC=5.8 from 2006 to 2017. To achieve the 2035 target of the End TB Strategy for 90% reductions in the TB incidence compared with 2015, the WHO estimates that the downtrend in the TB incidence requires to be accelerated at the rates of around 5% by 2020, 10% by 2025, and 17% between 2025 and 2035 globally.<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="cit0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref> The current epidemic patterns of TB in Tibet has been an extremely daunting challenge for reaching the aim of a world free of TB during different periods.<xref rid="cit0065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref> Many reasons may be responsible for such an increasing trend in the TB epidemics in Tibet. Firstly, TB is an infectious disease of poverty; Tibet has poor essential health-care services and low socio-economic conditions, with the GDP ranking the last among 31 provinces and municipalities of China in 2019,<xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref> which may be the most important trigger for the rapid rise in the TB incidence. Secondly, local meteorological and environmental factors may also be important contributors. Thirdly, Buddhist monks and nuns that account for a significant proportion of the population in Tibet have poor health-care knowledge and they frequently undertake their religious activities in relatively small temples, irrespective of the time of the year, which facilitates the continued transmission among people.<xref rid="cit0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref> Fourthly, in recent years, the laboratory equipment and testing ability are continuously improved, and new techniques and methods of molecular biology detection and rapid diagnosis are popularized to improve the level of patient discovery in Tibet. Fifthly, around 80% of TB patients in Tibet had been resident in farming and pastoral areas,<xref rid="cit0066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref> and many TB patients do not know that they can be examined and treated free of charge. Faced with the catastrophic costs for TB patients and their households, they often choose not to access healthcare, which further helps the spreading of TB among people. Finally, a study showed that the public awareness of core information on TB prevention and treatment was only 34%, significantly lower than the national average level (57.0%),<xref rid="cit0067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref> such a low public awareness may be a contributory factor in relation to the elevated TB incidence in Tibet. Besides, some other reasons (such as alcohol use disorders, diabetes, HIV infection, smoking, and undernourishment) may also play a role. Confronted with such a worsening tendency, some additional or comprehensive intervention strategies must be taken to combat TB in Tibet.</p>
              <p>The present study was subject to some potential weaknesses. Firstly, the time series of the TB incidence was derived from a passive monitoring system, and therefore the underreporting may be inevitable. Secondly, we only used a dataset spanning 12 years to construct the models and some detailed information (such as sex and age) of the TB cases cannot be extracted, which limits further sensitivity analysis for our model. Thirdly, there is currently still in the absence of a guidance to determine the suitable key parameters of ANNs (such as hidden units and feedback delays). In applications, a series of experiments need to be performed by trial and error until the best performance indices are detected. Fourthly, incorporating potential influencing factors of TB into the EEMD-SARIMA-NARNN method may favor the improvement of the forecasting performance, and yet this failed to be done in our work. Fifthly, whether this novel mixture method can also achieve a high-accuracy prediction for other infectious diseases or time series, further research should be undertaken to explore its potential use. Finally, in applications, the newly reported TB cases should be added into the model in time to make sure of its forecasting accuracy level.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s0005">
              <title>Conclusions</title>
              <p>Our proposed novel data-driven EEMD-SARIMA-NARNN hybrid method can better capture the dynamic dependence characteristics of the TB incidence in Tibet compared with the basic SARIMA model, basic NARNN model, ETS model, and traditional SARIMA-NARNN combined method, which can be recommended as a helpful and instrumental policy-supportive tool for planning the health-care resources ahead of time and directing the intensity and type of current interventions required to end the TB epidemic. Besides, considering the ongoing increases in TB cases, some additional or comprehensive intervention strategies must be taken to combat TB in Tibet.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgments</title>
              <p>We appreciate the Chinese CDC for providing the monthly number of TB cases. This project was supported by the Innovation and Entrepreneurship Training Project for University Students of Henan Province (S202010472007) and Xinxiang Medical University (XYXSKYZ201932) and the Key Scientific Research Project of Universities in Henan (21A330004).</p>
            </ack>
            <sec id="s0006">
              <title>Data Sharing Statement</title>
              <p>All the data supporting the findings of the work are contained within the study.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s0007">
              <title>Author Contributions</title>
              <p>All authors made substantial contributions to conception and design, acquisition of data, or analysis and interpretation of data; took part in drafting the article or revising it critically for important intellectual content; agreed to submit to the current journal; gave final approval of the version to be published; and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s0008" sec-type="COI-statement">
              <title>Disclosure</title>
              <p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</p>
            </sec>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="cit0001">
                <label>1.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>ZQ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>HQ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Comparing the performance of time series models with or without meteorological factors in predicting incident pulmonary tuberculosis in eastern China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infect Dis Poverty</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>151</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40249-020-00771-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33148337</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0002">
                <label>2.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="web"><collab>WHO</collab>. <article-title>Global tuberculosis report 2020</article-title>. <comment>Available from</comment>: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://apps.who.int/iris/handle/10665/336069">https://apps.who.int/iris/handle/10665/336069</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>12</month><day>25</day>, 2020</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0003">
                <label>3.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shangguan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Epidemic trends of tuberculosis in China from 1990 to 2017: evidence from the global Burden of Disease Study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infect Drug Resist</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>1663</fpage>–<lpage>1672</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/idr.s249698</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32606817</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0004">
                <label>4.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Secular seasonality and trend forecasting of tuberculosis incidence rate in China using the advanced error-trend-seasonal framework</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infect Drug Resist</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>733</fpage>–<lpage>747</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IDR.S238225</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32184635</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0005">
                <label>5.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Temporal trends analysis of tuberculosis morbidity in mainland China from 1997 to 2025 using a new SARIMA-NARNNX hybrid model</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ Open</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>e024409</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2018-024409</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0006">
                <label>6.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Application of a hybrid model in predicting the incidence of tuberculosis in a Chinese population</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infect Drug Resist</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>1011</fpage>–<lpage>1020</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/idr.s190418</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31118707</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0007">
                <label>7.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YQ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Analysis and predication of tuberculosis registration rates in Henan Province, China: an exponential smoothing model study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infect Dis Poverty</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>123</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40249-020-00742-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32867846</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0008">
                <label>8.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>ZZ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Comparison of autoregressive integrated moving average model and generalised regression neural network model for prediction of haemorrhagic fever with renal syndrome in China: a time-series study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ Open</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e025773</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2018-025773</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0009">
                <label>9.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Adeboye</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Akinwumi</surname><given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>James</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ruffin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Seasonality and trend forecasting of tuberculosis prevalence data in Eastern Cape, South Africa, using a hybrid model</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>757</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph13080757</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0010">
                <label>10.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Applications and comparisons of four time series models in epidemiological surveillance data</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>e88075</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0088075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24505382</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0011">
                <label>11.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>An</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Time series analysis of human brucellosis in mainland China by using Elman and Jordan recurrent neural networks</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Infect Dis</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>414</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-019-4028-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31088391</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0012">
                <label>12.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>An advanced data-driven hybrid model of SARIMA-NNNAR for tuberculosis incidence time series forecasting in Qinghai Province, China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infect Drug Resist</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>867</fpage>–<lpage>880</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IDR.S232854</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32273731</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0013">
                <label>13.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Time-series modelling and forecasting of hand, foot and mouth disease cases in China from 2008 to 2018</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epidemiol Infect</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>147</volume>:<fpage>e82</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S095026881800362X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30868999</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0014">
                <label>14.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>RX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Time series analysis and forecasting of chlamydia trachomatis incidence using surveillance data from 2008 to 2019 in Shenzhen, China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epidemiol Infect</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>148</volume>:<fpage>e76</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/s0950268820000680</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32178748</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0015">
                <label>15.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Forecasting the incidence of acute haemorrhagic conjunctivitis in Chongqing: a time series analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epidemiol Infect</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>148</volume>:<fpage>e193</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S095026882000182X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32807257</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0016">
                <label>16.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Hybrid methodology for tuberculosis incidence time-series forecasting based on ARIMA and a NAR neural network</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epidemiol Infect</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>145</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1118</fpage>–<lpage>1129</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0950268816003216</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28115032</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0017">
                <label>17.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association of public health interventions with the epidemiology of the COVID-19 outbreak in Wuhan, China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JAMA</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>323</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>1915</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2020.6130</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32275295</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0018">
                <label>18.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Association between ambient air pollution and elevated risk of tuberculosis development</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infect Drug Resist</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>3835</fpage>–<lpage>3847</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IDR.S227823</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31827330</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0019">
                <label>19.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Taskaya-Temizel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Casey</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A comparative study of autoregressive neural network hybrids</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Neural Net</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>5–6</issue>):<fpage>781</fpage>–<lpage>789</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neunet.2005.06.003</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0020">
                <label>20.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gui</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hybrid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Model for annual runoff time series forecasting using Elman neural network with ensemble empirical mode decomposition</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Water-Sui</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>416</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/w10040416</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0021">
                <label>21.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>XM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Time-series analysis of tuberculosis from 2005 to 2017 in China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epidemiol Infect</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>146</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>935</fpage>–<lpage>939</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0950268818001115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29708082</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0022">
                <label>22.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Deb</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chakrabarty</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A wavelet based hybrid SARIMA-ETS model to forecast electricity consumption</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Elect J Appl Statistical Anal</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>408</fpage>–<lpage>430</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0023">
                <label>23.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Ensemble empirical mode decomposition: a noise-assisted data analysis method</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Adv Adapt Data Anal</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>01</volume>(<issue>01</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>41</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1142/s1793536909000047</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0024">
                <label>24.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A new view of nonlinear water waves: the Hilbert spectrum</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Annu Rev Fluid Mech</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>417</fpage>–<lpage>457</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0025">
                <label>25.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zuo</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Spatiotemporal characteristics and the epidemiology of tuberculosis in China from 2004 to 2017 by the nationwide surveillance system</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1284</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-020-09331-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32843011</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0026">
                <label>26.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Bartholomew</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Box</surname><given-names>GEP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Time Series Analysis: Forecasting and Control</italic></source>. <edition>5th</edition> ed. <publisher-loc>Hoboken, New Jersey</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name>; <year>2015</year>:<fpage>14</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0027">
                <label>27.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Suganthan</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Amaratunga</surname><given-names>GAJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Empirical mode decomposition based ensemble deep learning for load demand time series forecasting</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Appl Soft Comput</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>246</fpage>–<lpage>255</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0028">
                <label>28.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Data-driven model for daily land surface temperature forecasting using long short-term memory neural network based on ensemble empirical mode decomposition</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1032</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph15051032</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0029">
                <label>29.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A hybrid model for PM2.5 forecasting based on ensemble empirical mode decomposition and a general regression neural network</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Total Environ</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>496</volume>:<fpage>264</fpage>–<lpage>274</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2014.07.051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25089688</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0030">
                <label>30.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jian</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>RX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Performance enhancement of ensemble empirical mode decomposition</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mech Syst Signal Process</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<page-range>P.2104–2123</page-range>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0031">
                <label>31.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chau</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Improving forecasting accuracy of annual runoff time series using ARIMA based on EEMD decomposition</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Water Resources Manage</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>2655</fpage>–<lpage>2675</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0032">
                <label>32.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Time series analysis of temporal trends in hemorrhagic fever with renal syndrome morbidity rate in China from 2005 to 2019</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>9609</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-66758-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32541833</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0033">
                <label>33.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Forecasting the seasonality and trend of pulmonary tuberculosis in Jiangsu Province of China using advanced statistical time-series analyses</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infect Drug Resist</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>2311</fpage>–<lpage>2322</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/idr.s207809</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31440067</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0034">
                <label>34.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Oshodi</surname><given-names>OS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Forecasting construction output: a comparison of artificial neural network and Box-Jenkins model</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eng Construction Arch Manage</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>302</fpage>–<lpage>322</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0035">
                <label>35.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Maleki</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nasseri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Aminabad</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hadi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Comparison of ARIMA and NNAR models for forecasting water treatment plant’s influent characteristics</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Ksce J Civil Eng</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0036">
                <label>36.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Thoplan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Simple v/s sophisticated methods of forecasting for Mauritius monthly tourist arrival data</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Stat Appl</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>223</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5923/j.statistics.20140405.01</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0037">
                <label>37.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Using a hybrid model to forecast the prevalence of schistosomiasis in humans</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>355</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph13040355</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27023573</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0038">
                <label>38.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pao</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Forecasting energy consumption in Taiwan using hybrid nonlinear models</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Energy</italic></source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1438</fpage>–<lpage>1446</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.energy.2009.04.026</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0039">
                <label>39.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Saba</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Elsheikh</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Forecasting the prevalence of COVID-19 outbreak in Egypt using nonlinear autoregressive artificial neural networks</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Process Saf Environ Protection</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>141</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psep.2020.05.029</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0040">
                <label>40.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Time series analysis of cumulative incidences of typhoid and paratyphoid fevers in China using both Grey and SARIMA models</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>e0241217</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0241217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33112899</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0041">
                <label>41.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>LX</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Comparative study of SARIMA and NARX models in predicting the incidence of schistosomiasis in China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mathematical Biosci Eng</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>2266</fpage>–<lpage>2276</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3934/mbe.2019112</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0042">
                <label>42.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Application of a new hybrid model with seasonal auto-regressive integrated moving average (ARIMA) and nonlinear auto-regressive neural network (NARNN) in forecasting incidence cases of HFMD in Shenzhen, China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e98241</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0098241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24893000</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0043">
                <label>43.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leng</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Epidemiological features and time-series analysis of influenza incidence in urban and rural areas of Shenyang, China, 2010-2018</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epidemiol Infect</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>148</volume>:<fpage>e29</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0950268820000151</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32054544</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0044">
                <label>44.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Development and evaluation of a deep learning approach for modeling seasonality and trends in hand-foot-mouth disease incidence in mainland China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>8046</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-44469-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31142826</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0045">
                <label>45.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nury</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hasan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alam</surname><given-names>MJB</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Comparative study of wavelet-ARIMA and wavelet-ANN models for temperature time series data in northeastern Bangladesh</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J King Saud Univ</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>47</fpage>–<lpage>61</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0046">
                <label>46.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>ZM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Neural network forecasting for seasonal and trend time series</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Oper Res</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<fpage>501</fpage>–<lpage>514</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0047">
                <label>47.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Time series model for forecasting the number of new admission inpatients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Med Inform Decis Mak</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>39</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12911-018-0616-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29907102</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0048">
                <label>48.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>A new hybrid model using an autoregressive integrated moving average and a generalized regression neural network for the incidence of tuberculosis in Heng County, China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Trop Med Hyg</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>97</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>799</fpage>–<lpage>805</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.16-0648</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28820678</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0049">
                <label>49.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>An</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Comparison of two hybrid models for forecasting the incidence of hemorrhagic fever with renal syndrome in Jiangsu Province, China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>e0135492</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0135492</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26270814</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0050">
                <label>50.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Forecast of dengue cases in 20 Chinese cities based on the deep learning method</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Environ Res Public Health</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>2</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph17020453</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0051">
                <label>51.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Singaravelan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Applying convolutional neural networks to predict the ICD-9 codes of medical records</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sensors (Basel, Switzerland)</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>24</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/s20247116</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0052">
                <label>52.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wubuli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Upur</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wushouer</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Seasonality of active tuberculosis notification from 2005 to 2014 in Xinjiang, China</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>e0180226</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0180226</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28678873</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0053">
                <label>53.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sumi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Time-series analysis of geographically specific monthly number of newly registered cases of active tuberculosis in Japan</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e0213856</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0213856</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30883581</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0054">
                <label>54.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rios</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A statistical analysis of the seasonality in pulmonary tuberculosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur J Epidemiol</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>483</fpage>–<lpage>488</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/a:1007653329972</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10997837</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0055">
                <label>55.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fares</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Seasonality of tuberculosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Glob Infect Dis</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>46</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0974-777X.77296</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21572609</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0056">
                <label>56.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Willis</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Winston</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heilig</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cain</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mac Kenzie</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Seasonality of tuberculosis in the United States, 1993-2008</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Infect Dis</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1553</fpage>–<lpage>1560</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cid/cis235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22474225</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0057">
                <label>57.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bae</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Seasonality of tuberculosis in the Republic of Korea, 2006-2016</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Epidemiol Health</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>e2018051</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4178/epih.e2018051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30486553</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0058">
                <label>58.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Thorpe</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Frieden</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Laserson</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khatri</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Seasonality of tuberculosis in India: is it real and what does it tell us?</article-title><source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>364</volume>(<issue>9445</issue>):<fpage>1613</fpage>–<lpage>1614</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0140-6736(04)17316-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15519633</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0059">
                <label>59.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="web"><collab>Tibet Autonomous Region Department of Tourism Development</collab>. <comment>Available from:</comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lyfzt.xizang.gov.cn/">http://lyfzt.xizang.gov.cn/</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>12</month><day>25</day>, 2020</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0060">
                <label>60.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Males, ages ≥ 45 years, businessperson, floating population, and rural residents may be considered high-risk groups for tuberculosis infection in Guangzhou, China: a review of 136,394 tb confirmed cases</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Rev Inst Med Trop Sao Paulo</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>366</fpage>–<lpage>368</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/s0036-46652013000500013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24037294</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0061">
                <label>61.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>He</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The influence of meteorological factors on tuberculosis incidence in Southwest China from 2006 to 2015</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>10053</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-28426-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29968800</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0062">
                <label>62.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>HX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Spatial transmission and meteorological determinants of tuberculosis incidence in Qinghai Province, China: a spatial clustering panel analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infect Dis Poverty</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>45</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40249-016-0139-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27251154</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0063">
                <label>63.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ganmaa</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Uyanga</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Vitamin D supplements for prevention of tuberculosis infection and disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">N Engl J Med</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>383</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>359</fpage>–<lpage>368</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1915176</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32706534</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0064">
                <label>64.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Using the Kulldorff’s scan statistical analysis to detect spatio-temporal clusters of tuberculosis in Qinghai Province, China, 2009-2016</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Infect Dis</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>578</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-017-2643-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28826399</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0065">
                <label>65.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="web"><collab>WHO</collab>. <article-title>The End TB Strategy</article-title>. <year>2014</year>. <comment>Available from:</comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://wwwwhoint/tb/End_TB_brochurepdf">https://wwwwhoint/tb/End_TB_brochurepdf</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>12</month><day>25</day>, 2020</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0066">
                <label>66.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="web"><collab>Bureau of statistics of Tibet Autonomous Region</collab>. <article-title>Statistical Yearbook of Tibet 2020</article-title>. <comment>Available from</comment>:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tjj.xizang.gov.cn/">http://tjj.xizang.gov.cn/</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>12</month><day>25</day>, 2020</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="cit0067">
                <label>67.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Sorangza. A survey of the knowledge of core information on tuberculosis prevention and control in Tibet Autonomous Region</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">World Latest Med Inf</italic></source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>73</issue>):<fpage>217</fpage>–<lpage>219</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
