<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-03-11T00:50:21Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8362659" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8362659</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-08-15</datestamp>
        <setSpec>pheelsevier</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.xsd" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sustain Cities Soc</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sustain Cities Soc</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Sustainable Cities and Society</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">2210-6707</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2210-6715</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Elsevier Ltd.</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC8362659</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8362659</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">8362659</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34414067</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2210-6707(21)00530-8</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scs.2021.103254</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">103254</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Discovering optimal strategies for mitigating COVID-19 spread using machine learning: Experience from Asia</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0001">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Pan</surname>
                    <given-names>Yue</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0002">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Zhang</surname>
                    <given-names>Limao</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
                  <xref rid="cor0001" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0003">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Yan</surname>
                    <given-names>Zhenzhen</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff0003" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0004">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Lwin</surname>
                    <given-names>May O.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff0004" ref-type="aff">d</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0005">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Skibniewski</surname>
                    <given-names>Miroslaw J.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">e</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff0006" ref-type="aff">f</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff0007" ref-type="aff">g</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="aff0001"><label>a</label>School of Civil and Environmental Engineering, Nanyang Technological University, 50 Nanyang Avenue, 639798, Singapore</aff>
                <aff id="aff0002"><label>b</label>Shanghai Key Laboratory for Digital Maintenance of Buildings and Infrastructure, Department of Civil Engineering, Shanghai Jiao Tong University, 800 Dongchuan Road, Shanghai, China</aff>
                <aff id="aff0003"><label>c</label>School of Physical and Mathematical Sciences, Nanyang Technological University, 21 Nanyang Link, Singapore 637371, Singapore</aff>
                <aff id="aff0004"><label>d</label>Wee Kim Wee School of Communication and Information, Nanyang Technological University, 31 Nanyang Link, WKWSCI Bldg, 637718, Singapore</aff>
                <aff id="aff0005"><label>e</label>Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering, University of Maryland, College Park, 9 MD 20742-3021, USA</aff>
                <aff id="aff0006"><label>f</label>Chaoyang University of Technology, Taichung 4413310, Taiwan</aff>
                <aff id="aff0007"><label>g</label>Polish Academy of Sciences, Institute for Theoretical and Applied Informatics, 44-100 Gliwice, Poland</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor0001"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author.</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>13</day>
                <month>8</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.-->
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <month>12</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>13</day>
                <month>8</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>75</volume>
              <fpage>103254</fpage>
              <lpage>103254</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>4</day>
                  <month>3</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>28</day>
                  <month>7</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>10</day>
                  <month>8</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2021 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
                <copyright-holder>Elsevier Ltd</copyright-holder>
                <license>
                  <license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="abs0002">
                <p>To inform data-driven decisions in fighting the global pandemic caused by COVID-19, this research develops a spatiotemporal analysis framework under the combination of an ensemble model (random forest regression) and a multi-objective optimization algorithm (NSGA-II). It has been verified for four Asian countries, including Japan, South Korea, Pakistan, and Nepal. Accordingly, we can gain some valuable experience to better understand the disease evolution, forecast the prevalence of the disease, which can provide sustainable evidence to guide further intervention and management. Random forest with a proper rolling time-window can learn the combined effects of environmental and social factors to accurately predict the daily growth of confirmed cases and daily death rate on a national scale, which is followed by NSGA-II to find a range of Pareto optimal solutions for ensuring the minimization of the infection rate and mortality at the same time. Experimental results demonstrate that the predictive model can alert the local government in advance, allowing the accused time to put forward relevant measures. The temperature in the category of environment and the stringency index belonging to the social factor are identified as the top 2 important features to exert a greater impact on the virus transmission. Moreover, optimal solutions provide references to design the best control strategies towards pandemic containment and prevention that can accommodate the country-specific circumstance, which are possible to decrease the two objectives by more than 95%. In particular, appropriate adjustment of social-related features needs to take priority over others, since it can bring about at least 1.47% average improvement of two objectives compared to environmental factors.</p>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group id="keys0001">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>COVID-19</kwd>
                <kwd>Random forest regression</kwd>
                <kwd>Feature importance analysis</kwd>
                <kwd>Multi-objective optimization</kwd>
                <kwd>Sustainability</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="sec0001">
              <label>1</label>
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p id="para0006">Since the first confirmed case of the novel coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) reported at the end of December 2019 in Wuhan, Hubei province, China, COVID-19 has rapidly spread across more than 200 countries and territories of the world. The severe pneumonia outbreak has triggered a public health emergency of international concern, which has been announced as a global pandemic by the World Health Organization (WHO) on March 11, 2020. According to open data from the Johns Hopkins University tracker, the total confirmed cases and reported deaths globally have reached over 82 million and 1.8 million up to 31st December 2020. Notably, the genome and symptoms of COVID-19 show apparent similarity to the severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV) that occurred during 2002–2003 and Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV) firstly appeared in 2012 (<xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr">Ali &amp; Alharbi, 2020</xref>). In contrast to SARS and MERS, COVID-19 demonstrates a lower case‐fatality rate and stronger transmission capability, resulting in a larger number of infections worldwide. The mutation in the virus has led to changes in viruses' ability to cause the pandemic, which is estimated to be more transmissible than the original version. As the epidemic continues progressing, it negatively affects the resilience of the global society from every aspect of daily life, environment, economy, and others, and thus it raises urgent attention from policymakers and health planners internationally. In order to address the unprecedented challenge, the scientific evidence can be derived from the deep exploration of the dynamic evolution of COVID-19 transmission. Accordingly, potential strategies and interventions can be formulated at an early stage for limiting or even blocking the sustained propagation, contributing to reducing the infectious and mortality rates.</p>
              <p id="para0007">Apart from existing bioinformatics and medical methodologies about virus mechanism study, data science as another feasible solution has shown its advantages of battling against the pandemic (<xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">Barda, Riesel et al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">Gao, Cai et al., 2020</xref>). In this regard, a novel and convincing way is to continuously investigate the impacts of important factors especially concerning environmental and social aspects on the spread of COVID-19, resulting in data-oriented modeling and prediction to make treatment or prevention decisions (<xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">Lim, Tun et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">Lwin, Lu et al., 2020</xref>). For one thing, environmental indicators, like temperature, humidity, atmospheric pressure, wind speed, meteorological variability, air quality, and others, have been regarded as the top predictors of coronavirus illnesses (<xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">Das, Ghosh et al., 2021</xref>). They possibly play critical roles in influencing the viability, transmission, and mortality of COVID-19 (<xref rid="bib0004" ref-type="bibr">Bashir, Ma et al., 2020</xref>). As expected, the actionable environmentally-informed COVID-19 risk monitoring and prediction can meet its great potential in supporting political agendas for pandemic comprehension and response (<xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">Zaitchik, Sweijd et al., 2020</xref>). For another, when no reliable vaccines and antiviral medication is available, a feasible response plan for curbing the spread of the virus relies on a suitable combination of various government intervention strategies, such as home quarantines, social distance measures, personal protective measures, and others, which could impinge on people's behavior and daily life, including work mode, travel distance, and engagement in social activities ()<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">(Haug, Geyrhofer, Londei, &amp; Dervic, 2020)</xref>. It has been found that the speed of the region to act on outbreaks and the reduction in travel is crucial to eliminate the infectivity, transmissibility resurgence of COVID-19 (<xref rid="bib0032" ref-type="bibr">Siegenfeld &amp; Bar-Yam, 2020</xref>). Besides, strategies based on social distancing and ventilation have been emphasized broadly in limiting the spread and risk of COVID-19 ()(<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Sun &amp; Zhai, 2020</xref>). In short, the dynamic of the COVID-19 pandemic is highly associated with multiple factors from the environmental and social aspects. Most of the previous studies have paid a lot of attention to climate change, especially for the temperature and humidity, while the impact of other environmental and social factors has not been fully explored (<xref rid="bib0026" ref-type="bibr">Nakada &amp; Urban, 2020</xref>). In particular, <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">Hu et al. (2021)</xref> indicated that social environmental factors could be strongly correlated with COVID-19 death. Due to the interrelated nature of the pandemic situation with various factors, additional factors beyond the climate aspects should be considered and examined systematically, aiming to more reliably track the evolution and forecast the future trend of virus spread. Therefore, a question can be raised on how to create a realistic multivariable prediction model to accurately estimate and understand the daily infection rate and death due to COVID-19 at the nationwide scale, in order to potentially facilitate responsive and preventive actions ahead of time.</p>
              <p id="para0008">For tracking and predictive purposes, the susceptible–infectious–recovered (SIR) epidemiological model is the most basic and extensively applied to describe the dynamics of coronavirus transmission across populations. Although it is relatively easy to understand and implement only relying on three components of susceptible (S), infected (I), and removed (R) individuals, its prediction performance is limited by the assumptions, such as the well-mixed population, homogeneity of the population, exponentially distributed duration of infection, large population (<xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">Huppert &amp; Katriel, 2013</xref>). In other words, the SIR model has difficulty in adapting to changeable external conditions, which is insufficient to handle the COVID-19 epidemic/pandemic development in the nature of complexity and nonlinearity. For this reason, machine learning invovling complex mathematical calculations has been employed as a reliable alternative to provide more accurate time-series forecasting, which can seek nonlinear relations in a set of input variables to discover the hidden patterns by learning the increasing availability of historical data (<xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Pan &amp; Zhang, 2021</xref>). It is believed that big data practice based on machine learning models is helpful to intelligently and dynamically support decision-making for fighting against COVID-19 towards compiling the sustainable development goal (<xref rid="bib0029" ref-type="bibr">Rahman, Zaman et al., 2020</xref>). Recent research reveals that machine learning-based methods can make full use of spatio-temporal data to achieve more promising results with the superiority of adaptive learning, trend-based recalibration, and great flexibility, contributing to fully understanding the current situations and predicting future trends about COVID-19 (<xref rid="bib0002" ref-type="bibr">Bansal, Padappayil et al., 2020</xref>). For example, <xref rid="bib0038" ref-type="bibr">Yeşilkanat (2020)</xref> adopted random forest to predict the daily cases of COVID-19 reaching R2 above 0.845, which was proven useful in estimating and map the spatio-temporal distribution of COVID-19 outbreak. <xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Malki et al. (2020)</xref> built several state-of-the-art machine learning models, including k neighbors regressor, random forest, decision tree, support vector machine, and others, to learn features about climatic conditions for studying the spreading rate of COVID-19, which validated that weather variables were more relevant to the accurate prediction of mortality rate and thus these variables required more attention. <xref rid="bib0041" ref-type="bibr">Zhan et al. (2021)</xref> developed a hybrid machine learning model of random-forest-bagging broad learning system to forecast the COVID-19 trend and compare the prediction performance with other popular than machine learning algorithms, which verified that random forest had great robustness and was flexible in feature importance analysis. According to the above-mentioned studies, it is worth noting that an ensemble learning-based model named random forest composed of several decision trees has shown outstanding performance in estimating the daily number of confirmed COVID-19 cases.</p>
              <p id="para0009">From the advent of COVID-19, most studies mainly put efforts on building the intelligent model for predicting the pandemic trend and investigating the contribution of different factors to the virus spread for a single country or a state (<xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">Maiti, Zhang et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">Mansour, Al Kindi et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bib0031" ref-type="bibr">Sannigrahi, Pilla et al., 2020</xref>). However, a challenge arises that it is impossible to directly inform preparedness response strategies under the combination of ideal socio-environmental conditions from the prediction. As reviewed, there has been limited research on applying optimization algorithms to the constructed machine learning model that provides the relationship between inputs and outputs. The possible cause might be the considerably high degree of complexity and uncertainty arising from multiple influential factors and their complicated impact on the transmission dynamics of COVID-19. It is observed that simulation of the dynamic pandemic behavior is nonlinear and time-variant in nature, which can be regarded as a multi-objective prediction and optimization problem (<xref rid="bib0034" ref-type="bibr">Thakur, 2020</xref>). Therefore, another research gap to be narrowed is to seek the optimal setting of environmental and social factors for depressing together the growth of the confirmed cases and deaths as much as possible in the targeted region. For this concern, we intend to incorporate the random forest regression model with certain optimization algorithms in the area of single or multicriteria decision-making. To be more specific, single-objective optimization determines the best solution to reach the maximum/minimum of the single objective function, while the multi-objective optimization search for a Pareto front representing a set of optimal trade-off solutions to handle conflicting objectives simultaneously. As a result, knowledge from the optimum solutions offers clear insights into the complex nature of the COVID-19 outbreak, which provides decision-makers with the profile of the influential factors that can satisfy the desired requirements. Accordingly, mixed and suitable control measures can be designed to combat the pandemic.</p>
              <p id="para0010">Since the COVID-19 pandemic has placed humanity at extremely high health and social risk, this research aims to seek novel solutions based on data science in pursuit of reducing the COVID-19 severity and dissemination. It paves a new way to control the ongoing pandemic COVID-19 for promoting sustainable societies. We concentrate on the following two specific objectives: one is from the view of prediction by developing a machine learning-based prediction model with the proper lead-time to forecast the daily growth rate and mortality rate of COVID-19 towards possible circumstances in the next few days; the other is from the view of optimization by optimizing the established model for the determination of optimal control and preventive strategies. That is to say, the research offers an opportunity to fully mine the valuable information behind the large amount of accumulated data related to environmental and social dimensions. Results from the spatiotemporal analysis are expected to provide insights to policymakers for putting forward early preparations and preventive measures. In this regard, there are three main research questions to be answered: (1) How to build the machine learning model to characterize the dynamics of COVID-19 cases and return convincing predictions about its evolution trend; (2) How to explain the tree-based predictor and precisely measure the critical roles of various factors in impacting the disease prevalence; (3) How to perform optimization to reasonably reveal the optimal environmental and social conditions for minimizing the growth of confirmed cases and deaths.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0002">
              <label>2</label>
              <title>Data and method</title>
              <sec id="sec0003">
                <label>2.1</label>
                <title>Framework of the proposed method</title>
                <p id="para0011">For two goals of prediction and prevention, the proposed approach is executed based on three major steps, including dataset preparation, COVID-19 predictor creation, and optimal strategy formulation, which has been visualized in <xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>
. At first, a high-quality dataset is carefully prepared, which incorporates a large number of continuous features from several public datasets. The scope of features that we have employed is broad, covering the environmental and social categories to describe the spatial dynamic of COVID-19. Secondly, random forest regression is trained on the prepared dataset to model the non-linear relationship between the input influential factors and the targeted objective, aiming to conduct the time-series prediction. As a result, it can return the promising estimation of the daily increase about the COVID-19 confirmed cases and deaths within 95% CI at the country level. In particular, hyper-parameters of the model are fine-tuned by the PSO algorithm to ensure high prediction accuracy. For better interpretability of the random forest model, MDI and SHAP-based feature important measures are calculated to numerically infer the effects of socio-environmental factors on the outcomes. Thirdly, a multi-objective optimization algorithm is applied to the prediction model to minimize two objectives about the growth rate and death rate simultaneously. As a result. it can yield Pareto fronts as the optimal solution for determining the effective control strategies under ideal settings of decision variables. Several single objective optimization algorithms are also carried out to minimize each objective separately. In the end, the full understanding of the data analysis results assists governments in decision-making efforts to reduce COVID-19 risk for harmonizing the goal of sustainable development, which can decrease dependence on subjective judgment.<fig id="fig0001"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Framework of the proposed method for investigating COVID-19 spread.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0001">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0004">
                <label>2.2</label>
                <title>Data preparation</title>
                <p id="para0012">To begin with, the preparation of the machine model training is to collect a comprehensive dataset. As reviewed, the dependency of COVID-19 on environmental and social factors has been verified. In order to gain a more full understanding of the epidemiology of COVID-19, we can therefore rely on the daily growth of confirmed cases and deaths along with related factors potentially impacting the virus spread. All the desired information is available on the following four open sources: (1) The confirmed and death cases per day in each country are continuously recorded by the Center for Systems Science and Engineering (CSSE) at Johns Hopkins University (<xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Hopkins, 2020</xref>). (2) The environmental data, including the air pollutant species and meteorological characteristics, is collected from the world air quality index project (<xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">WAQI, 2020</xref>). (3) Social Distancing Stringency Index and Policy Indicators are obtained via the Oxford Covid Government Response Tracker (OxCGRT) (<xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">Hale, Webster et al., 2020</xref>), which aggregate scores to quantify the extent of government responses. (4) The travel popularity data is summarized in the Google Community Mobility Reports (<xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Google 2020</xref>), as a reflection of the citizens’ movement trends over time by geography. In subsequence, data from the above-mentioned disparate sources can be systematically merged into a single repository. Since it is found that multiple data sources in combination can demonstrate a strong ability in representing an event or domain of interest (<xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">Samuelsen, Chen et al., 2019</xref>), our prepared dataset with data integration will have implications for predicting the potential cases and explore the influence from the socio-environmental aspects. In addition, we focus on the COVID-19 transmission country-wise, including Japan, Korea, Pakistan, and Nepal, during the period of Feb 15, 2020 – Nov 27, 2020. Detailed description of the prepared dataset has been provided in <xref rid="tbl0001" ref-type="table">Tables 1</xref>
and <xref rid="tbl0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>
.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of features in Japan and Korea datasets.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0011">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Category</th><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Feature description</th><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Variable</th><th colspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Japan</th><th colspan="2" align="left" valign="top">South Korea</th><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr><tr><th valign="top">Mean (SD)</th><th valign="top">[Min, Max]</th><th valign="top">Mean (Sd)</th><th valign="top">[Min, Max]</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="11" align="left" valign="top">Environment</td><td valign="top">Carbon monoxide (CO) (mg/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td valign="top">x1</td><td valign="top">2.99 (0.50)</td><td valign="top">[1.95, 4.58]</td><td valign="top">4.83 (0.72)</td><td valign="top">[3.03, 7.63]</td><td valign="top">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Relative humidity (%)</td><td valign="top">x2</td><td valign="top">70.40 (10.80)</td><td valign="top">[24.8, 91.58]</td><td valign="top">72.08 (15.22)</td><td valign="top">[38.17, 97.67]</td><td valign="top">0.021</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Nitrogen dioxide (NO<sub>2</sub>) (μg/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td valign="top">x3</td><td valign="top">6.25 (2.09)</td><td valign="top">[3.04, 16.15]</td><td valign="top">13.15 (5.08)</td><td valign="top">[5.32, 34.60]</td><td valign="top">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Ozone (O<sub>3</sub>) (μg/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td valign="top">x4</td><td valign="top">25.25 (7.61)</td><td valign="top">[8.98, 51.44]</td><td valign="top">24.80 (10.44)</td><td valign="top">[5.75,49.15]</td><td valign="top">0.014</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Particulate matter with aerodynamic diameter ≤10 μm (PM<sub>10</sub>) (μm/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td valign="top">x5</td><td valign="top">13.39 (5.16)</td><td valign="top">[6.29, 39.48]</td><td valign="top">27.57 (10.44)</td><td valign="top">[6.17, 55.00]</td><td valign="top">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Particulate matter with aerodynamic diameter ≤2.5 μm (PM<sub>2.5</sub>) (μm/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td valign="top">x6</td><td valign="top">38.11 (11.91)</td><td valign="top">[18.23, 84.35]</td><td valign="top">56.61 (18.89)</td><td valign="top">[13.00,115.33]</td><td valign="top">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Pressure (hPa)</td><td valign="top">x7</td><td valign="top">1008.66 (5.93)</td><td valign="top">[993.98, 1032.90]</td><td valign="top">1013.87 (7.17)</td><td valign="top">[991.00, 1032.00]</td><td valign="top">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Sulfur dioxide (SO<sub>2</sub>) (μg/m<sup>3</sup>)</td><td valign="top">x8</td><td valign="top">2.51 (0.41)</td><td valign="top">[1.83, 5.16]</td><td valign="top">4.72 (0.50)</td><td valign="top">[3.60, 6.40]</td><td valign="top">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Temperature ( °C)</td><td valign="top">x9</td><td valign="top">18.77 (6.39)</td><td valign="top">[4.27, 29.65]</td><td valign="top">16.97 (6.49)</td><td valign="top">[1.03, 28.48]</td><td valign="top">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Wind gust (m/s)</td><td valign="top">x10</td><td valign="top">6.33 (2.32)</td><td valign="top">[2.47, 15.90]</td><td valign="top">9.32 (1.45)</td><td valign="top">[1.50, 15.40]</td><td valign="top">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Wind speed (m/s)</td><td valign="top">x11</td><td valign="top">2.77 (0.75)</td><td valign="top">[1.58, 8.47]</td><td valign="top">2.40 (0.86)</td><td valign="top">[1.08, 6.32]</td><td valign="top">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="7" align="left" valign="top">Social</td><td valign="top">Stringency index</td><td valign="top">x12</td><td valign="top">36.05 (6.75)</td><td valign="top">[19.44, 47.22]</td><td valign="top">51.73 (10.51)</td><td valign="top">[31.48, 82.41]</td><td valign="top">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Change of people in retail and recreation (%)</td><td valign="top">x13</td><td valign="top">−13.23 (10.97)</td><td valign="top">[−48, 21]</td><td valign="top">−11.72 (9.74)</td><td valign="top">[−45, 15]</td><td valign="top">0.131</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Change of people in grocery and pharmacy (%)</td><td valign="top">x14</td><td valign="top">0.24 (4.08)</td><td valign="top">[−15, 14]</td><td valign="top">6.06 (10.00)</td><td valign="top">[−18, 73]</td><td valign="top">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Change of people in parks (%)</td><td valign="top">x15</td><td valign="top">−1.25 (16.50)</td><td valign="top">[−52, 76]</td><td valign="top">30.79 (27.71)</td><td valign="top">[−38, 158]</td><td valign="top">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Change of people in transit stations (%)</td><td valign="top">x16</td><td valign="top">−25.67 (12.75)</td><td valign="top">[−69, 2]</td><td valign="top">−8.55 (9.24)</td><td valign="top">[−36, 16]</td><td valign="top">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Change of people in workplaces (%)</td><td valign="top">x17</td><td valign="top">−14.49 (13.13)</td><td valign="top">[−73, 4]</td><td valign="top">−6.89 (11.16)</td><td valign="top">[−81, 3]</td><td valign="top">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Change of people in residential (%)</td><td valign="top">x18</td><td valign="top">7.12 (4.73)</td><td valign="top">[0, 30]</td><td valign="top">3.84 (3.48)</td><td valign="top">[−2, 17]</td><td valign="top">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Note: SD, min, max are the abbreviation of the standard deviation, the minimum, and the maximum, respectively. <italic>P</italic>-value for the 18 continuous variables is calculated by the Wilcoxon signed ranks test.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Characteristics of features in Pakistan and Nepal datasets.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0012">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Category</th><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Feature description</th><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Variable</th><th colspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Pakistan</th><th colspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Nepal</th><th rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top"><italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr><tr><th valign="top">Mean (Sd)</th><th valign="top">[Min, Max]</th><th valign="top">Mean (Sd)</th><th valign="top">[Min, Max]</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="5" align="left" valign="top">Environment</td><td valign="top">Relative humidity (%)</td><td valign="top">x1</td><td valign="top">58.10 (10.18)</td><td valign="top">[36.375,84.875]</td><td valign="top">82.03 (12.21)</td><td valign="top">[44.033, 100]</td><td valign="top">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Particulate matter with aerodynamic diameter ≤2.5 μm (PM2.5) (μm/m3)</td><td valign="top">x2</td><td valign="top">112.25 (36.31)</td><td valign="top">[46.333,253.25]</td><td valign="top">79.04 (41.01)</td><td valign="top">[16.5, 181]</td><td valign="top">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Pressure (hPa)</td><td valign="top">x3</td><td valign="top">1006.21 (6.60)</td><td valign="top">[957.025,1023.35]</td><td valign="top">958.90 (40.75)</td><td valign="top">[890.35,1021]</td><td valign="top">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Temperature ( °C)</td><td valign="top">x4</td><td valign="top">25.90 (5.48)</td><td valign="top">[13.625, 35.867]</td><td valign="top">20.03 (3.69)</td><td valign="top">[11.067,35,567]</td><td valign="top">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Wind speed (m/s)</td><td valign="top">x5</td><td valign="top">3.02 (0.82)</td><td valign="top">[1.5,5.2]</td><td valign="top">1.14 (0.40)</td><td valign="top">[0.5667,2.45]</td><td valign="top">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="7" align="left" valign="top">Social</td><td valign="top">Stringency index</td><td valign="top">x6</td><td valign="top">61.71 (20.86)</td><td valign="top">[11.11,96.3]</td><td valign="top">75.77 (23.17)</td><td valign="top">[16,67,96.3]</td><td valign="top">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Change of people in retail and recreation (%)</td><td valign="top">x7</td><td valign="top">−22.40 (22.78)</td><td valign="top">[−73,12]</td><td valign="top">−42.09 (24.14)</td><td valign="top">[−79,7]</td><td valign="top">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Change of people in grocery and pharmacy (%)</td><td valign="top">x8</td><td valign="top">−8.49 (22.71)</td><td valign="top">[−58,31]</td><td valign="top">−26.22 (24.61)</td><td valign="top">[−70,18]</td><td valign="top">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Change of people in parks (%)</td><td valign="top">x9</td><td valign="top">−5.79 (16.21)</td><td valign="top">[−46,30]</td><td valign="top">−26.11 (17.23)</td><td valign="top">[−57,14]</td><td valign="top">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Change of people in transit stations (%)</td><td valign="top">x10</td><td valign="top">−16.81 (21.78)</td><td valign="top">[−65,20]</td><td valign="top">−35.30 (24.33)</td><td valign="top">[−74,10]</td><td valign="top">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Change of people in workplaces (%)</td><td valign="top">x11</td><td valign="top">−20.60 (18.42)</td><td valign="top">[−70,6]</td><td valign="top">−32.68 (22.56)</td><td valign="top">[−74,12]</td><td valign="top">&lt;0.001</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Change of people in residential (%)</td><td valign="top">x12</td><td valign="top">7.84 (6.65)</td><td valign="top">[−1,25]</td><td valign="top">13.22 (7.15)</td><td valign="top">[−2,28]</td><td valign="top">&lt;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Note: SD, min, max are the abbreviation of the standard deviation, the minimum, and the maximum, respectively. <italic>P</italic>-value for the 12 continuous variables is calculated by the Wilcoxon signed ranks test.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0005">
                <label>2.3</label>
                <title>Random forest model development and evaluation</title>
                <p id="para0013">Due to the powerful capability of returning considerably accurate and robust predictions, a machine learning algorithm named random forest (RF) (<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">Breiman, 2001</xref>) is adopted in this research for establishing a non-linear regression model. Random forest, known as an ensemble of decision trees, occurs with the combination of multiple weak decision trees that are easily implemented and interpreted (<xref rid="bib0027" ref-type="bibr">Pan, Zhang et al., 2020</xref>). That is to say, RF with the notion of an ensemble forms a strong learner to demonstrate a much better approximation to the ground truth. To be more specific, RF begins with the bootstrap resampling technique, which makes random sampling from the original training data. After the random sample with replacement, subsets of the training data in the same size are generated. It should be noted that around 36.8% of the data is left out for the validation purpose in one bootstrap resampling, which is called out-of-bag (OOB) samples. Then, each bootstrapped training set is responsible for building an unpruned decision tree, which learns a limited number of features that are randomly selected from all alternatives. Finally, the overall prediction of random forest can be determined based on the aggregation of results from multiple base estimators by averaging.</p>
                <p id="para0014">Notably, hyper-parameter tunning can be the key to build an optimal random forest model with the goal of minimizing the error difference between the actual and predicted, which exerts a direct effect on the model performance. However, the task of hyper-parameter optimization is not straightforward, since parameters cannot be directly learned from data. To address the issue, we carry out a prevalent optimization technique named particle metaheuristic algorithm (PSO) in 3-fold cross-validation, and thus the hyper-parameters of random forest can be determined in an automatic process. To ensure a promising performance, the hyper-parameters of the random forest, which are unable to be directly learned from data, are automatically determined by a prevalent optimization technique named particle metaheuristic algorithm (PSO) in 3-fold cross-validation. PSO in the family of the evolutionary algorithm has been proven useful in efficiently finding near-optimal or optimal solutions in large configuration space in a set of public datasets (<xref rid="bib0037" ref-type="bibr">Yang &amp; Shami, 2020</xref>). In short, the superiority of PSO lies in its fast convergence rate and easy implementation under relatively low computational complexity. A brief introduction of PSO is given in the part of single-objective and multi-objective optimization. Herein, four important hyper-parameters are chosen to be tuned for well-fitting the random forest model into the prepared COVID-19 dataset, including the number of trees in the forest, the maximum depth of the tree to grow, the minimum number of data to split an internal node, and the minimum number of data to gain a leaf node. In the end, three common metrics in <xref rid="eqn0001" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (1)</xref> – (3), namely the mean squared error (MSE), mean absolute error (MAE), and mean absolute percentage error (MAPE), are adopted to figure out the optimal hyper-parameter configuration and evaluate the model performance.<disp-formula id="eqn0001"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="eqn0002"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M2" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.33em"/><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="eqn0003"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M3" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where <italic>N</italic> is the total number of data points, <italic>y<sub>p,i</sub></italic> and <italic>y<sub>a,i</sub></italic> are the predictive value and actual value, respectively. The smaller value of MSE, MAE, and MAPE indicates the better prediction performance.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0006">
                <label>2.4</label>
                <title>Feature importance measurement</title>
                <p id="para0015">Based upon the machine learning model, more investigation is required to examine the cause-effect between the COVID-19 spread and a series of factors to consider. For this purpose, two methods of feature importance calculation are deployed in this research to assign the importance scores to input features for quantifying their contribution to the model's decision. The first one is a popular tree feature attribution approach known as mean decrease impurity (MDI), which is a built-in important score in the scikit-learn package for the random forest regression. Calculation of impurity-based feature importance largely depends on features selected for splitting, aiming to reach the goal to explore how much each feature decreases the weighted impurity in a tree that is measured by the variance reduction using MSE. If a variable used for node splitting can largely decrease the impurity, it is fair to assume that it acts as an important feature to define the predictions. As given in <xref rid="eqn0004" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (4)</xref> (<xref rid="bib0019" ref-type="bibr">Louppe, Wehenkel et al., 2013</xref>), the impurity importance of variable <italic>x<sub>i</sub></italic> is calculated by summing up all the impurity decrease of all nodes <italic>m</italic> where the targeted variable <italic>x<sub>i</sub></italic> is adopted, which is then averaged by the total number of trees <italic>N</italic> in the forest. Accordingly, features can be ranked and the higher score indicates the higher importance of the feature. Although the impurity-based feature importance is commonly used and computationally efficient, it prefers features with high cardinality to be the important ones.<disp-formula id="eqn0004"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="M4" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mstyle mathvariant="normal"><mml:mi>Δ</mml:mi></mml:mstyle><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where <italic>N</italic> is the total number of trees, <italic>p</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) stands for the proportion of samples that can reach them, and <italic>v</italic>(<italic>s<sub>t</sub></italic>) represents the variable to split <italic>s<sub>t</sub></italic>.</p>
                <p id="para0016">A new type of explanation for tree-based machine learning models is called the TreeSHAP (Shapley Additive exPlanation), which is basically evolved from the classic game-theoretic Shapley values. It can better improve the interpretability of the predictive tree ensemble model from two aspects. For one thing, Shapley values defined in <xref rid="eqn0004" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (4)</xref> can measure the impacts of features on the model as a whole and recognize the most influential features (<xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Lundberg, Erion et al., 2018</xref>). In other words, the importance value is assigned to each feature, allowing for a reliable explanation to the model behavior. However, the computation of <xref rid="eqn0005" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (5)</xref> is not a straightforward task especially in the intractable models with multiple trees and features, which hinders its practical use. As an efficient solution, a modified algorithm for fast SHAP value estimation has been introduced in the paper (<xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Lundberg, Erion et al., 2018</xref>) to exponentially lower the computational complexity of <xref rid="eqn0005" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (5)</xref> from <italic>O</italic>(<italic>TL2<sup>M</sup></italic>) to <italic>O</italic>(<italic>TLD<sup>2</sup></italic>), where <italic>T</italic> is the number of trees in the tree ensemble model, <italic>L</italic> is the maximum number of leaves in a tree, <italic>M</italic> is the number of features, and <italic>D</italic> is the maximum depth of a tree. For another, the SHAP interaction index, as an extension of SHAP values, can directly capture the pairwise interaction effects between local features on the model's prediction, which can be obtained from <xref rid="eqn0006" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (6)</xref> to generate a matrix of feature attribution (<xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Lundberg, Erion et al., 2020</xref>). This can be explained as the difference between the SHAP value of the <italic>i</italic>th feature when the <italic>j</italic>th feature is presented or not.<disp-formula id="eqn0005"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="M5" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>⊆</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∖</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">{</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>!</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>!</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo>!</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>∪</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">{</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">}</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where <italic>f</italic> is a specific prediction, <italic>M</italic> is the number of input features, and <italic>S</italic> denotes a subset of features to be conditioned on, which does not contain the <italic>i</italic>th feature.<disp-formula id="eqn0006"><label>(6)</label><mml:math id="M6" altimg="si6.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>⊆</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="script">M</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>!</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>!</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>!</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>∇</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mtext>when</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>≠</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="eqn0007"><label>(7)</label><mml:math id="M7" altimg="si7.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>∇</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>∪</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>∪</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">{</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>∪</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">{</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mtext>When</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>≠</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M8" altimg="si8.svg"><mml:mi mathvariant="script">M</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> denotes the subsets of all <italic>M</italic> input features. It should be noted that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M9" altimg="si9.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, since the SHAP interaction index of the <italic>i</italic>th and <italic>j</italic>th feature can be equally split between each feature.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0007">
                <label>2.5</label>
                <title>Single-objective and multi-objective optimization</title>
                <p id="para0017">Noticeably, the determination of optimal COVID-19 control solutions in a data-driven manner can be considered as a single or multi-objective optimization problem. The ultimate goal of proper optimization algorithms is minimizing the rate of increase in COVID-19 confirmed cases or deaths or both of them. In particular, these targeted objectives are closely associated with various influential features, and their complicated relationships have been mathematically modeled by machine learning. In consequence, a reasonable profile of variables of interest can be provided, which is believed to benefit epidemic management and prevention.</p>
                <p id="para0018">For the single-objective optimization, three typical methods belonging to the family of meta-heuristic optimization techniques are deployed in this research, namely genetic algorithm (GA), particle metaheuristic algorithm (PSO), and biased random key genetic algorithm (BRKGA). They all own the powerful ability of performing a global search over the promising regions to address non-convex problems <xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">Pan &amp; Zhang, 2021</xref>; <xref rid="bib0036" ref-type="bibr">Yan, Gao et al., 2018</xref>). The main procedure of the three algorithms is presented below: (1) In GA (<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Gen &amp; Lin, 2007</xref>), a fitness function, which is the objective function defined by the random forest regression model herein, is employed to assess the performance of individuals in the current generation. The desired individuals that are deemed to have better survival capability and adaptability will have more chances to survive and produce the next generation based on operators of selection, crossover, and mutation. The above-mentioned process will repeat several times until the termination criterion is satisfied. As a result, the best individual which GA is convergent to symbolizes the global optima. (2) In BRKGA (<xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Gonçalves &amp; Resende, 2011</xref>), a solution of the combinatorial optimization problem is encoded by a vector of randomly generated numbers named the random keys in the range [0,1]. To take the place of evolutionary operators, a decoder is designed to take the random keys as inputs to produce a discrete solution. Solutions are ranked by the fitness calculation and partitioned into the elite and non-elite ones. Later, one parent is always chosen from the elite solutions, while the other is selected from the non-elite. Based on the parameterized uniform crossover, the two parent solutions can be combined for generating the offspring. (3) In PSO (<xref rid="bib0017" ref-type="bibr">Kennedy &amp; Eberhart, 1995</xref>), its obvious distinction from GA is that it does not implement any evolutionary operators termed crossover and mutation. PSO carries out the search using a swarm of particles. The velocity of a particle is regarded as the potential solution, which is greatly influenced by the personnel best and global best locations. At each iteration, the velocity and the position of the particle can be updated by <xref rid="eqn0008" ref-type="disp-formula">Eqs. (8)</xref> and (<xref rid="eqn0009" ref-type="disp-formula">(9)</xref> to drive the particle towards the desired locations.<disp-formula id="eqn0008"><label>(8)</label><mml:math id="M10" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="eqn0009"><label>(9)</label><mml:math id="M11" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where <italic>w</italic> is the inertia weight, <italic>v<sub>id</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>) and <italic>x<sub>id</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>) are the <italic>d</italic>th coordinates of <italic>i</italic>th particle's velocity and position at the <italic>t</italic>th iteration, respectively. <italic>p</italic>
<sub>id</sub>(t) and <italic>g</italic>
<sub>id</sub>(t) are the <italic>d</italic>th coordinates of <italic>i</italic>th particle's local best and global best value. <italic>c<sub>1</sub></italic> can <italic>c<sub>2</sub></italic> are constant to balance exploiting <italic>p<sub>id</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>) and <italic>g<sub>id</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>). <italic>r<sub>1</sub></italic> and <italic>r<sub>2</sub></italic> are two random values between 0 and 1.</p>
                <p id="para0019">For the multi-objective optimization, a popular evolutionary algorithm called the non-dominated sorting genetic algorithm (NSGA-II) is adopted, which obeys the general procedure of GA with a modified mating and survival selection. There are three special characteristics involved in NSGA-II, namely fast non-dominated sorting approach, fast crowded distance estimation procedure, and simple crowded comparison operator, which are conducive to guarantee computational efficiency and population diversity (<xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">Deb, Pratap et al., 2002</xref>). The general steps of NSGA-II are given below (<xref rid="bib0039" ref-type="bibr">Yusoff, Ngadiman et al., 2011</xref>). To begin with, individuals in the population are sorted according to the non-domination criteria and assigned the crowding distance value. For producing the next generation, three critical operators are applied, which are the binary tournament selection under the crowd comparison-operator, simulated binary crossover, and polynomial mutation. Next, a combination of the obtained offspring population and the current generation is created to ensure elitism, from which several solutions can be chosen by the non-dominated sorting to form the next generation. In other words, the next generation is continuously filled by each front until its size is larger than the current population size. After several iterations, the last generation can approximate the Pareto front on behalf of a representative set of trade-off optimal solutions to the defined problem.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0008">
              <label>3</label>
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="sec0009">
                <label>3.1</label>
                <title>Baseline characteristics of the prepared dataset</title>
                <p id="para0020">The COVID-19 pandemic has brought unprecedented health and economic crisis to the world, which unfortunately weakens the sustainability and resilience in both developed and developing countries. To make a comprehensive prediction and optimization in this research, we obtain access to COVID-19-related data of two developed countries in East Asia and two developing countries in South Asia (Pakistan and Nepal) from February 15, 2020 to November 27, 2020. Thus, there are four prepared datasets for the four targeted countries, and each dataset owns 287 lines of valid records to describe the condition during the study period. For one thing, Japan and South Korea are taken as two typical developed countries, which are the first ones to confront the novel coronavirus beyond China. Both of them have taken suitable measures and policies to well control the disease and prevent the massive outbreaks that have hit the United States and some parts of Europe. Lessons learned from them are possible to lead the global recovery efforts. For another, Pakistan and Nepal are two representatives of developing countries under relatively poor economic conditions. The location of the four countries has been visualized in the map of <xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>
a, along with their accumulated number of COVID-19 confirmed cases and death cases by November 27, 2020. Observably, Pakistan and Nepal have reported the largest number of confirmed cases, which are around 11.76 and 6.8 times more than South Korea. To some extent, the COVID-19 outbreak tends to put the relatively less developed countries at higher health risk mainly due to the lack of sufficient economic resources, advanced medical technology, and far-reaching government responses for risk mitigation.<fig id="fig0002"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Real and predicted conditions of the COVID-19 confirmed cases and death cases in Japan, South Korea, Pakistan, and Nepal by November 27, 2020: (a) A map about the four targeted countries. (b) and (c) Comparison of the ground truth and prediction about the daily growth rate of the confirmed cases and the daily death rate. Similarly, (d) and (e) are the comparison for South Korea. (f) and (g) are the comparison for Pakistan. (h) and (i) are the comparison for Nepal. In (b)-(i), the orange line indicates the ground truth, the blue line represents the corresponding predictions, and the blue band around the blue line stands for the 95% CI with the 95% certain to contain the population mean.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0002">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="para0021">Different kinds of features affecting the COVID-19 spread country-wise are gathered mainly from the environmental and social perspectives, as listed in <xref rid="tbl0001" ref-type="table">Tables 1</xref> and <xref rid="tbl0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>. To be more specific, environmental features are composed of the meteorological variables (i.e., the daily average of relative humanity, pressure, temperature, wind gust, and wind speed) and air pollutant variables (i.e., mean concentrations of CO, NO<sub>2</sub>, O<sub>3</sub>, PM<sub>10</sub>, PM<sub>2.5</sub>, and SO<sub>2</sub>). Social features also incorporate two categories of information. One is the stringency index to quantify the level of government responses between 0 (low strictness) to 100 (high strictness). The other is the Google mobility index in the form of a positive or negative percentage to reflect changes in people's movement affected by the governmental policy implementation, which is measured by comparing with the medium value from the period of January 3, 2020 – February 6, 2020 as the baseline. Due to data availability, datasets of Japan and Korea own 18 features in total, which has 6 more features than the resting datasets for Pakistan and Nepal. The difference lies in the additional 5 features about the concentration of air pollutants (including CO, NO<sub>2</sub>, O<sub>3</sub>, pm10, SO<sub>2</sub>) and 1 feature regarding wind gust.</p>
                <p id="para0022">To provide insights into conditions of the environment, social, and pandemic evolution across four targeted countries, <xref rid="tbl0001" ref-type="table">Tables 1</xref> and <xref rid="tbl0002" ref-type="table">2</xref> outline the statistical characteristics of features in terms of mean value, standard deviation, and upper and lower bound. All the prepared features are in the numerical type, which are valuable information for describing the patterns in pandemic evolution over time. Besides, the Wilcoxon rank-sum test, a nonparametric version of the two-sample <italic>t</italic>-test under the assumption of independence and equal variance in two populations, is carried out in <xref rid="tbl0001" ref-type="table">Tables 1</xref> and <xref rid="tbl0002" ref-type="table">2</xref> to statistically examine the difference from the observations between pairs of Japan and Korea, Pakistan and Nepal. Almost all the <italic>P</italic>-value is less than 0.05, except for the variable x13 in <xref rid="tbl0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. It means that although the pairs of countries are proximal to each other, there is a significant difference in both the environmental and social aspects, which can be highlighted as the major contributors to the varying degree of COVID-19 negative effects across countries. The selected features are weakly correlational to the output variables calculated by the Pearson correlation coefficient in Supplementary Figure 1. Later, the random forest can flexibly learn these prepared data to fit different functions for different countries. All these features will act as the decision variables in the single-objective or multi-objective optimization task.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0010">
                <label>3.2</label>
                <title>Random forest model performance</title>
                <p id="para0023">For the purpose of predictive controlling and prevention, these influential features described in <xref rid="tbl0001" ref-type="table">Tables 1</xref> and <xref rid="tbl0002" ref-type="table">2</xref> can then be fed into the appropriate machine learning model to return reliable predictions about the future trend. Herein, two random forest regression models are built for each country to capture the complex dynamics of COVID-19 spread, resulting in accurate predictions on the daily growth rate of COVID-19 confirmed cases and death cases. The hyper-parameters of models are tuned by the optimization technique called PSO in 3-fold cross-validation to further guarantee the promising and stabilize model performance. The developed models optimized by PSO can always quickly reach the slightly smaller MSE and MAE than the traditional grid search method (Supplementary Table 1), and thus PSO is a reasonable choice for fine-tuning parameters of models in this research.</p>
                <p id="para0024">Besides, it is worth noting that a rolling time-window in the size of <italic>n</italic> days is designed in random forest regression to model and predict the target objectives over time. That is to say, the increase rate on the current day is estimated based on the number of consecutive observations within the window of the previous <italic>n</italic> days. To exhibit the effects of the rolling time-window, its alternative size is set as 3, 5, and 7 days for several comparative experiments. In particular, a window of suitable size significantly enhances the model performance in Japan and South Korea datasets, as can be seen in Supplementary Table 1. For instance, the MSE value from the prediction on the South Korea growth rate of confirmed cases experiences an 82.96% decrease (drop from 2.53×10<sup>−2</sup> to 4.31×10<sup>−3</sup>) when the window size is widened from 3 days to 7 days. Similarly, the Japan dataset also benefits a lot from the fixed number <italic>n</italic> of previous data, where the MSE value gradually declines from the model with a 3-day rolling time-window to the 7-day one reaching a 26.33% and 59.69% improvement in the estimation of growth rate and death rate, respectively. It is experimentally proved that the model's performance is also sensitive to the selection of the window size. The COVID-19 evolution in Japan and South Korea gains a pretty clear weekly trend.</p>
                <p id="para0025"><xref rid="tbl0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> lists the most optimal set of hyper-parameter configurations and the rolling time-window, which are adopted to build the best predictive models for learning the collected data. Also, we have made attempts to compute variance and find a 95% confidence interval (CI) of the generated predictions. The defined range of values supports a reliable estimation of uncertainty from the random forest regression. The model performance after 3-fold cross-validation is demonstrated in <xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>(b) – (i), where the predicted value under 95 CI is plotted with the actual trend reflecting the daily increase rate of confirmed cases and deaths for a clear comparison. Observably, there is a high level of agreement between the ground truth and the predicted value in all eight figures. The great discrepancy is more likely to appear in the first fifty days in Japan, Korea, and Pakistan and the second fifty-day interval in Nepal mainly due to the unpredictably high and sudden increase of COVID-19 transmission during this period. On the contrary, the remaining days see a great fitting and the predicted rate can even be slightly higher than the actual data to manifest a relatively conservative estimate of the model. <xref rid="tbl0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> measured the performance of the model with the optimal parameters by MSE, MAE, and MAPE. It turns out that MSE and MAE are small enough in all conditions, highlighting the great reliability and generalization of the developed model. For the two prediction purposes, models in the Japan dataset achieve the most accurate results under the lowest MSE of 3.51×10<sup>−4</sup> (95% CI: 2.41×10<sup>−4</sup>–4.62×10<sup>−4</sup>) and 2.12×10<sup>−3</sup> (95% CI: 6.67×10<sup>−4</sup>–3.56×10<sup>−3</sup>), and the lowest MAE of 2.12×10<sup>−3</sup> (95% CI: 9.45×10<sup>−3</sup>–1.30×10<sup>−2</sup>) and 1.89×10<sup>−2</sup> (95% CI: 1.39×10<sup>−2</sup>–2.38×10<sup>−2</sup>), probably because of the smaller outlier value in Japan than other countries. Through comparison with other relevant studies, it can be found that the prediction performance of our model is better. In terms of MAPE value for model evaluation, experiment result based on the random forest from <xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Malki, Atlam et al., (2020)</xref> for predicting confirmed cases globally was 3.313, and the improved adaptive network-based fuzzy inference system (CESBAS-ANFIS) from <xref rid="bib0042" ref-type="bibr">Zivkovic, Bacanin et al., (2021)</xref> for predicting confirmed cases in China was 4.08. As for our established model in this case, the MAPE value is in the range of 0.593 and 2.416, which is significantly lower than the above-mentioned studies. Particularly, Japan and Nepal demonstrate a higher prediction accuracy, whose MAPE value for the growth rate and death rate can be all below 1.0. Overall, both <xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> and <xref rid="tbl0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> reveal the success of the random forest-based model in forecasting the growth of infections and mortality in the near future under acceptable prediction error, which can play a valuable role in perceiving the potential risk at an early phase. To further validate the prediction performance of random forest, we compare it with another popular machine learning algorithm named support vector machine (SVM), as shown in Supplementary Table 2. As a more detailed explanation, it reveals that random forest can bring an improvement of 10.2%, 38.6%, 23.3%, 24.3% in terms of MAE in predicting the growth rate and an improvement of 31.7%, 30.2%, 32.1%, 22.8% in terms of MAE in predicting the death rate for Japan, South Korea, Pakistan, and Nepal, respectively.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Performance evaluation of the established random forest regression models with the optimal parameters.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0013">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top">Country</th><th valign="top">Prediction</th><th valign="top">Optimal parameter</th><th valign="top">MSE (95% CI)</th><th valign="top">MAE (95% CI)</th><th valign="top">MAPE</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Japan</td><td valign="top">Growth rate</td><td valign="top"><italic>n</italic> = 14, <italic>d</italic> = 21, <italic>s</italic> = 8, <italic>l</italic> = 2, <italic>w</italic> = 7</td><td valign="top">3.51×10<sup>−4</sup><break/>(2.41×10<sup>−4</sup>–4.62×10<sup>−4</sup>)</td><td valign="top">1.12×10<sup>−2</sup><break/>(9.45×10<sup>−3</sup>–1.30×10<sup>−2</sup>)</td><td valign="top">0.763</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Death rate</td><td valign="top"><italic>n</italic> = 24, <italic>d</italic> = 31, <italic>s</italic> = 6, <italic>l</italic> = 10, <italic>w</italic> = 7</td><td valign="top">2.12×10<sup>−3</sup><break/>(6.67×10<sup>−4</sup>–3.56×10<sup>−3</sup>)</td><td valign="top">1.89×10<sup>−2</sup><break/>(1.39×10<sup>−2</sup>–2.38×10<sup>−2</sup>)</td><td valign="top">0.366</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">South Korea</td><td valign="top">Growth rate</td><td valign="top"><italic>n</italic> = 38, <italic>d</italic> = 35, <italic>s</italic> = 15, <italic>l</italic> = 1, <italic>w</italic> = 7</td><td valign="top">4.31×10<sup>−3</sup><break/>(0.00–9.87×10<sup>−3</sup>)</td><td valign="top">1.73×10<sup>−2</sup><break/>(9.79×10<sup>−3</sup>–2.47×10<sup>−2</sup>)</td><td valign="top">1.371</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Death rate</td><td valign="top"><italic>n</italic> = 29, <italic>d</italic> = 18, <italic>s</italic> = 8, <italic>l</italic> = 14, <italic>w</italic> = 7</td><td valign="top">1.62×10<sup>−2</sup><break/>(0.00–4.31×10<sup>−2</sup>)</td><td valign="top">3.07×10<sup>−2</sup><break/>(1.61×10<sup>−2</sup>–4.52×10<sup>−2</sup>)</td><td valign="top">1.895</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Pakistan</td><td valign="top">Growth rate</td><td valign="top"><italic>n</italic> = 20, <italic>d</italic> = 15, <italic>s</italic> = 2, <italic>l</italic> = 8, <italic>w</italic> = 3</td><td valign="top">2.63×10<sup>−2</sup><break/>(5.17×10<sup>−3</sup>–4.75×10<sup>−2</sup>)</td><td valign="top">5.57×10<sup>−2</sup><break/>(3.83×10<sup>−2</sup>–7.40×10<sup>−2</sup>)</td><td valign="top">2.416</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Death rate</td><td valign="top"><italic>n</italic> = 48, <italic>d</italic> = 38, <italic>s</italic> = 11, <italic>l</italic> = 7, <italic>w</italic> = 3</td><td valign="top">7.12×10<sup>−3</sup><break/>(0.00–1.46×10<sup>−2</sup>)</td><td valign="top">2.95×10<sup>−2</sup><break/>(2.02×10<sup>−2</sup>–3.87×10<sup>−2</sup>)</td><td valign="top">2.070</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Nepal</td><td valign="top">Growth rate</td><td valign="top"><italic>n</italic> = 25, <italic>d</italic> = 17, <italic>s</italic> = 8, <italic>l</italic> = 10, <italic>w</italic> = 3</td><td valign="top">1.03×10<sup>−2</sup><break/>(2.08×10<sup>−3</sup>–1.85×10<sup>−2</sup>)</td><td valign="top">4.03×10<sup>−2</sup><break/>(2.94×10<sup>−2</sup>–5.12×10<sup>−2</sup>)</td><td valign="top">0.746</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Death rate</td><td valign="top"><italic>n</italic> = 25, <italic>d</italic> = 31, <italic>s</italic> = 13, <italic>l</italic> = 7, <italic>w</italic> = 3</td><td valign="top">8.75×10<sup>−3</sup><break/>(2.18×10<sup>−4</sup>–1.73×10<sup>−3</sup>)</td><td valign="top">3.33×10<sup>−2</sup><break/>(2.30×10<sup>−2</sup>–4.35×10<sup>−2</sup>)</td><td valign="top">0.593</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Note: <italic>n</italic> is the number of trees in the forest in the range [5, 50]. <italic>d</italic> is the maximum depth of the tree to grow in the range [5, 50]. <italic>s</italic> is the minimum number of data to split an internal node in the range [2, 50]. <italic>l</italic> is the minimum number of data to gain a leaf node in the range [1, 20]. <italic>w</italic> is the size of the rolling time-window defined by the integer {3, 5, 7}.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0011">
                <label>3.3</label>
                <title>Feature importance analysis</title>
                <p id="para0026">To better understand the inner workings behind the random forest, the importance of prepared features is measured and ranked by two different approaches (an impurity-based method and a SHAP-based method). The potential influence features ranked at the top can be assumed to have greater predictive power. Since a <italic>n</italic>-day rolling time-window is added to predict the successive daily increase rate based upon its past <italic>n</italic> values, multiple lagged features with values at the prior time steps can be generated from the time series data. That is to say, each feature in Japan and South Korea datasets will be transformed into 7 lagged features due to the window width of 7, while datasets of Pakistan and Nepal own the 3 lagged features. In view of the number of total lagged features used for model training, <xref rid="fig0003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>
highlights the top 20 features with the highest importance for Japan and Korea and the top 10 important features for Pakistan and Nepal.<fig id="fig0003"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Summary of the top 20 or top 10 important features in all the eight models for predicting the increase rate of confirmed cases or the death cases. The numeral above each line represents the number of times a certain feature will appear in the top list. The feature importance in (a) and (c) is measured by the mean decrease impurity MDI, while (b) and (d) are based on the TreeSHAP.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0003">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="para0027">It can be assumed all features summarized in <xref rid="fig0003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> can contribute more to the accuracy of the prediction model, and thus they deserve more investigation. Observably, both the impurity-based score and SHAP value reveal that features representing the temperature (x9 in Japan and South Korea, x4 in Pakistan and Nepal) and stringency index (x12 in Japan and South Korea, x6 in Pakistan and Nepal) tend to appear more frequently in the top 20 or top 10 important feature list. In other words, temperature from the environmental category and stringency index belonging to the social category can be reasonably perceived as the two most influential and relevant features of the growth rate and death rate apart from Nepal. Especially for Japan and South Korea, the two identified features take up even over 40% among the top 20 important features in the two prediction purposes. With regard to the environmental factors, it is found that the relative humidity (x12 in Japan and South Korea, x6 in Pakistan and Nepal) performs as the second most important, since the number of times it turns up in the top list is followed by the feature of temperature. Besides, it can be seen that the degree of contribution from the environmental and social variables is diametrically opposite in the pairwise countries of Japan and South Korea, Pakistan, and Nepal. More specifically, there are more than 12 features concerning the environmental aspects in the top 20 list for the Japan dataset, indicating that environmental factors play a leading role in impacting the prediction performance. Conversely, social-related features accounting for more than 77.78% of all 20 top features will take over the prediction in the South Korea dataset. A similar situation can be seen in Pakistan and Nepal. Therefore, it is of necessity to take both the categories of environment and society into account, aiming to ensure the development of a generalized and robust prediction model for the monitoring and controlling of COVID-19.</p>
                <p id="para0028">Next, we take two random forest models of Japan as an example for model interpretability. The top 20 most important features captured by the SHAP value of the tree ensembles have been provided in <xref rid="fig0004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>, <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>
, which are deeply analyzed as follows. As for the explanation of the growth rate model, it can be seen in <xref rid="fig0004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>a and b that all the top 3 features are about temperature, which are followed by two social features representing the change of people in workplaces. The main difference between <xref rid="fig0004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>a and b is that <xref rid="fig0004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>b with the individualized feature attribution can succinctly show the positive or negative effects of the features on the prediction. From <xref rid="fig0004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>b, it is observed that the three highest-magnitude effects come from temperature about the previous 3 to 5 days. When the temperature drops smoothly, the daily growth rate of confirmed cases has an increasing tendency. There is a long trail on the right, indicating that the extremely low temperature is very possible to raise the risk of accelerating virus spread. Noticeably, all the seven records of temperature within the 7-day rolling window are incorporated in the top 20 list, meaning that temperature from the whole of the last week will pose a combined and significant effect in the growth prediction. <xref rid="fig0004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>c reveals that the relationship between temperature at the previous 7 days and the targeted output of the model is considerably complex, which is neither approximately linear nor monotonic. Besides, the influence of temperature on the predicted growth rate may differ for the strictness of policies. When Japan enforces its strongest measures above the value of 40, low temperature will not exert too many negative impacts on disease control. <xref rid="fig0004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>d provides an intuitive visualization of the interaction in the two variables of interest. It shows that the higher temperature and higher level of government response are more likely to correspond to a lower growth rate of daily confirmed cases. An increase of either of the two independent variables can have positive effects in slowing down the growth.<fig id="fig0004"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Feature importance analysis by SHAP values in the baseline model of growth rate in Japan: (a) A bar chart of the absolute mean SHAP values, where the top 20 features are sorted in a descending order according to their importance for the model outcome calculated by SHAP values. The feature label x<italic>n</italic>_d<italic>i</italic> means the feature x<italic>n</italic> about the <italic>i</italic>th day within the rolling time-window. (b) SHAP summary plot of the top 20 features, where each point in a line stands for the value of a feature attribution and is colored by the value of a feature. The x-axis displays the range of effects from a certain feature associated with the model outcome. (c) SHAP dependence plot with interaction visualization of the interaction between the temperature and stringency index from the first day of the rolling time-window. The higher SHAP value for the temperature at the previous seven days on the y-axis indicates the larger growth rate or death rate because of this feature. The gray histogram is the data distribution of the SHAP value. (d) A partial dependence plot to visualize the marginal effect of two given features that are the temperature and stringency index from the first day of the rolling time-window towards the targeted output. The average prediction is based on the change of two input variables (the temperature and stringency index from the first day of the rolling time-window) and the fix of other variables.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0004">Fig. 4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig0005"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Feature importance analysis by SHAP values in the baseline model of death rate in Japan: (a) A bar chart of the absolute mean SHAP values for the top 20 features. (b) SHAP summary plot of the top 20 features. (c) SHAP dependence plot with interaction visualization of the interaction between the temperature and stringency index from the first day of the rolling time-window. (d) A partial dependence plot to visualize the marginal effect of two given features that are the temperature and stringency index from the first day of the rolling time-window towards the targeted output. The detailed explanation of the four figures is similar to <xref rid="fig0004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0005">Fig. 5</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr5_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="para0029">Similarly, the model for predicting the death rate can also be interpreted. <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>a and b turn out that the stringency index and temperature have been ranked into the top 1 and 2, whose SHAP scores are at least 0.0015 greater than other features. It suggests that these two features require special attention in estimating the variation tendency of COVID-19 deaths, which are proved to be the critical determinants for significantly affecting the occurrence of deaths. Especially for the stringency index, it makes up the largest part of the top 20 features (accounting for 25%). It is worth noting that the value of the stringency index from the past 1 – 5 days will play a greater role in the prediction task. Moreover, there is a sudden leap appears in the vertical direction of <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>c under the value of stringency index over 40. That is to say, even the fairly rigid government responses are executed, the low temperature is still an adverse factor in mitigating COVID-19, which is prone to put the patients in the country at a greater risk of dying. In particular, when the temperature decreases to the value below 10 °C, it might lead to an obvious increase in mortality, as shown in <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>d. Thus, one possible way of reducing morality is attempting to avoid too cold conditions for patients in therapy. Additionally, the feature importance of prediction models about the other three countries can be reasonably explored in the same way. Their corresponding global interpretability based on the SHAP summary plot can be found in Supplementary Figures 2 and 3.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0012">
                <label>3.4</label>
                <title>Optimal control strategies determination</title>
                <p id="para0030">A promising solution for mitigating the COVID-19 transmission is to design optimal control strategies in a data-driven manner, which characterizes a multi-objective optimization problem. To this end, the NSGA-II algorithm is implemented to search the decision space iteratively under the goal of minimizing the growth rate of confirmed cases and the death rate simultaneously. These two objectives are highly associated with environmental and social variables, which have been well fitted in the random forest regression model. All the 18 features in Japan and South Korea and the 12 features in Pakistan and Nepal are served as the decision variables. They are adjusted within the range defined by their minimal and maximal value in <xref rid="tbl0001" ref-type="table">Tables 1</xref> and <xref rid="tbl0002" ref-type="table">2</xref> to customize the optimization process. For the four targeted countries, we build four NSGA-II models according to different initialized parameters in Supplementary Table 3.</p>
                <p id="para0031">The convergence of NSGA-II in the four models has been provided in <xref rid="fig0006" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6</xref>
, which can show the effectiveness of the multi-objective optimization algorithm. It can be perceived that the four optimization models all demonstrate a good convergence performance, especially when their iterations are added up to 600, 400, 400, and 50, respectively. After the optimization process, the approximations of the Pareto frontier in <xref rid="fig0007" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>
a to d can be generated, where red points stand for a set of trade-off optimal choices found by the algorithm. Thus, several prospective solutions under the great balance of minimizing the two objectives are available to a country for implementation, which seem to be more practical than a single solution. The most optimal solution in each figure is highlighted by a blue box, which can be considered to most effectively depress the increase in both the infections and deaths among all possible solutions. This ideal point is the most proximal one to the ideal point (0, 0) under the Euclidean distance of 1.99×10<sup>−3</sup>, 1.39×10<sup>−3</sup>, 1.19×10<sup>−3</sup>, and 1.34×10<sup>−3</sup> for Japan, South Korea, Pakistan, and Nepal, respectively.<fig id="fig0006"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Convergence of the NSGA-II algorithm measured by the recently proposed running metric: (a) The Japan dataset after 800 iterations. (b) The South Korea dataset after 800 iterations. (c) The Pakistan dataset after 800 iterations. (d) The Nepal dataset after 200 iterations. It is observed that there is a significant improvement at the 600th iteration, 400th iteration, 400th iteration, and 50th iteration of the four models, respectively.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0006">Fig. 6</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr6_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig0007"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Results of the multi-objective optimization problems for minimizing the growth rate of confirmed cases together with the death rate by the NSGA-II algorithm, which are expressed by the Parato front. (a) Japan. (b) South Korea. (c) Pakistan. (d) Nepal. f1 and f2 represent the two objective functions, which are the daily growth rate of confirmed cases and the daily death rate, respectively.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0007">Fig. 7</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr7_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="para0032">To easily arrive at the most optimal solutions determined in <xref rid="fig0007" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>, <xref rid="tbl0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>
lists the relevant profiles of the decision variables. For example, if Japan follows the ideal setting of variables, its growth rate of confirmed cases and death rate are expected to dramatically drop by 94.07% and 96.42% in comparison of the mean of the corresponding 287 records in the actual situation during the study period (the average growth rate of confirmed cases: 2.85×10–2, the average death rate: 2.90×10–2). Similarly, following the setting of decision variables in <xref rid="tbl0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>, the optimum solutions for the other three countries can also drive a more than 95% decline in the increase rate of infections and deaths. Therefore, it can be concluded that such optimal combinations of variables have great application potential in better satisfying the two defined objectives of minimizing the infection rate and mortality together. Governments can refer to them as valuable guidance in the determination of the control policies that are adapted to the characteristics of a certain country. In that respect, the decision-making process for developing appropriate measures no longer largely depends on expert knowledge and subjective judgment. Taking two key features named temperature and stringency index as an example to describe the formulated strategies against COVID-19. According to <xref rid="tbl0004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>, there is no significant difference in the temperature setting in Japan (23.24 °C), South Korea (24.83 °C), and Pakistan (26.75 °C), while the temperature in Nepal is at least 7.85 °C higher than other three countries. The strictness of government responses in the four countries can be sorted as: South Korea (39.62) &gt; Japan (28.74) &gt; Nepal (27.23) &gt; Pakistan (21.90).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0004"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Value setting of decision variables to reach the most optimal solution in the four countries.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0014">Table 4</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top">Feature</th><th valign="top">Japan</th><th valign="top">South Korea</th><th valign="top">Feature</th><th valign="top">Pakistan</th><th valign="top">Nepal</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top">x1</td><td valign="top">2.52</td><td valign="top">4.64</td><td valign="top">x1</td><td valign="top">68.92</td><td valign="top">69.63</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x2</td><td valign="top">78.81</td><td valign="top">89.98</td><td valign="top">x2</td><td valign="top">102.95</td><td valign="top">85.50</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x3</td><td valign="top">3.71</td><td valign="top">12.00</td><td valign="top">x3</td><td valign="top">1002.52</td><td valign="top">974.47</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x4</td><td valign="top">34.31</td><td valign="top">42.09</td><td valign="top">x4</td><td valign="top">26.76</td><td valign="top">15.39</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x5</td><td valign="top">7.64</td><td valign="top">28.15</td><td valign="top">x5</td><td valign="top">2.33</td><td valign="top">1.79</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x6</td><td valign="top">20.21</td><td valign="top">61.90</td><td valign="top">x6</td><td valign="top">21.90</td><td valign="top">27.23</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x7</td><td valign="top">1031.76</td><td valign="top">1010.01</td><td valign="top">x7</td><td valign="top">−9.81</td><td valign="top">0.13</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x8</td><td valign="top">2.74</td><td valign="top">4.03</td><td valign="top">x8</td><td valign="top">−10.97</td><td valign="top">−12.24</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x9</td><td valign="top">23.24</td><td valign="top">24.83</td><td valign="top">x9</td><td valign="top">1.57</td><td valign="top">2.45</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x10</td><td valign="top">6.69</td><td valign="top">9.12</td><td valign="top">x10</td><td valign="top">6.35</td><td valign="top">6.40</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x11</td><td valign="top">2.96</td><td valign="top">3.11</td><td valign="top">x11</td><td valign="top">0.73</td><td valign="top">10.23</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x12</td><td valign="top">28.74</td><td valign="top">39.62</td><td valign="top">x12</td><td valign="top">−0.40</td><td valign="top">2.81</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x13</td><td valign="top">−22.52</td><td valign="top">5.78</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">x14</td><td valign="top">1.93</td><td valign="top">42.56</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">x15</td><td valign="top">−4.40</td><td valign="top">113.07</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">x16</td><td valign="top">−51.56</td><td valign="top">−7.48</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">x17</td><td valign="top">−10.66</td><td valign="top">−7.05</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr><tr><td valign="top">x18</td><td valign="top">6.68</td><td valign="top">2.74</td><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/><td valign="top"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
                <p id="para0033">Social factors associated with government actions and peoples’ travel distance are preferred in the sequence of non-pharmaceutical interventions against COVID-19. As a matter of fact, it is not a straightforward task to change all the influential factors at the same time to meet all requirements of multiple objectives. Prioritization of the control strategies is another concern. Aiming to investigate the impacts of different factors on the optimization task, another three scenarios are set up through the adjustment of different decision variables, where only the environmental factors, the social factors, and the two critical variables named temperature and stringency index are considered, separately. The Euclidean distance of the most optimal solutions to (0, 0) is calculated for evaluating the optimization performance, which is compared to the distance of original conditions under no control effort to (0, 0) to measure how much the distance is shortened after optimization. The improvement from the four scenarios has been visualized in the beanplot in <xref rid="fig0008" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>
. Based on the red line in <xref rid="fig0008" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref>, it is observed that the four scenarios under different priorities of factors in all countries can reach an average improvement of distance over 30%. The improvement of distance is mainly due to the proper adjustment of the related variables, which verifies the considerable potential of the optimization approach in effectively reducing both the confirmed cases and death tolls.<fig id="fig0008"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Beanplots about the improvement of optimal solutions through adjusting different kinds of decision variables for: (a) Japan. (b) South Korea. (c) Pakistan. (d) Nepal. As for the variable adjustment, we set four different scenarios: Scenario 1 can change all prepared variables; Scenario 2 only changes variables in the social category; Scenario 3 only changes variables in the environmental category; Scenario 4 only changes two variables named temperature and stringency index. The most optimal solution from a certain scenario is compared to the 287 original records in the dataset, and thus the individual improvement is visualized as small gray lines. Also, the estimated density about the distribution of improvement degree is summarized along with the overall average value.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0008">Fig. 8</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr8_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="para0034">A detailed explanation of <xref rid="fig0008" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref> is given below. From the scenario 1 to 4 in each country, the mean of the optimization improvement shows a decreasing trend, while the standard deviation donating the uncertainty continues to grow. To be more specific, the control action based on all variables can always lead to the best improvement in the decrease of COVID-19 spread. This kind of optimization results in a 7.20% (Japan), 10.49% (South Korea), 20.71% (Pakistan), and 6.74% (Nepal) increase of improvement compared with changing variables in the social category. Under scenarios 2 and 3 by controlling the single kind of factors, the average improvement for the two objectives is reduced from 76.55% to 69.25% (Japan), from 65.27% to 53.73% (South Korea), from 59.02% to 46.57%, and from 88.64% to 87.17%. It means that social factors may play more important roles in processing the decreased number of COVID-19 cases and deaths. Therefore, it is essential for decision-makers to give priority to social factors in formulating the optimal strategies, which can be more beneficial for epidemy intervention. For simplicity and timesaving, a reasonable choice can rely on the examination of only the temperature and stringency index. Although it seems sufficient to lower the increase rate defined in the two objective functions for most cases, its improvement is relatively weaker and unstable than others. Especially for Pakistan, the average optimization improvement from the last scenario is smaller than half of scenario 1 with all variables considered.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0013">
              <label>4</label>
              <title>Discussions</title>
              <p id="para0035">As the prerequisite of optimization, the random forest regressor eventually generates two fitted objective functions for modeling relationships between inputs and two objectives about the daily growth of confirmed cases and deaths, respectively. It is known that the goal of the NSGA-II algorithm that has been well executed is to simultaneously deal with the two objective functions. Differently, when we intend to analyze each objective function independently for simplicity, the problem can be transformed into a single-objective one to minimize either the COVID-19 patients or deaths. For performing a fair comparison, the decision variables and their corresponding value range in the single-objective optimization task are the same as those in the multi-objective optimization process based on NSGA-II.</p>
              <p id="para0036"><xref rid="fig0009" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref> presents the comparison results from one multi-objective optimization algorithm named NSGA-II and three single-objective optimization algorithms called GA, BRKGA, and PSO, where the size of each circle is proportional to the value of the minimal growth rate or death rate. Evidently, most results reveal that the single-objective optimization is likely to return a larger reduction in the unwanted cases. For example, the optimized value of growth rate in Japan, South Korea, and Nepal can significantly decline to the smallest value of 1.74×10<sup>−3</sup>, 4.12×10<sup>−3</sup>, and 3.15×10<sup>−3</sup>, respectively, using the proper single-objective methods, which is around 1.66, 1.98, and 4.09 times lower than the results from NSGA-II. That is probably because multi-objective optimization needs to seek the tradeoff between the growth rate and mortality, whereas the single-objective task is chiefly driven by the dominating contributions. This tendency appears in almost all countries, signaling that the effectiveness of single-objective optimization is independent of a certain geographical region. Besides, PSO in this case tends to perform a little worse than the other GA-based methods, resulting in a slightly larger rate of increase. The optimal values of the decision variables output by the three single-objective optimization algorithms have been listed in <xref rid="tbl0005" ref-type="table">Tables 5</xref>
and <xref rid="tbl0006" ref-type="table">6</xref>
, which can also serve as a reliable guideline for formulating government control policies. Due to the great performance of the single-objective algorithm, we can also execute it twice to the two defined objectives in sequence as an optional solution for the bi-objective problem. However, it should be noted that such a method is considerably high-cost effective compared to the multi-objective algorithm.<fig id="fig0009"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>Comparison of the optimal results from the multi-objective optimization (NSGA-II) and three single-objective optimization algorithms (GA, BRKGA, and PSO): (a) Growth rate of confirmed cases. (b) Death rate. The value of the minimized growth rate and death rate derived from these four optimization algorithms is represented by the circle size, and thus the smaller circle means a lower value. Four targeted countries are differentiated by color.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0009">Fig. 9</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr9_lrg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0005"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Ideal setting of decision variables produced by the single-objective optimization algorithm named GA, BRKGA, and PSO for the purpose of minimizing the growth rate of confirmed cases or the death rate in Japan and South Korea.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0015">Table 5</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Variable</th><th colspan="6" align="left" valign="top">Japan</th><th colspan="6" align="left" valign="top">South Korea</th></tr><tr><th colspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Model of growth rate</th><th colspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Model of death rate</th><th colspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Model of growth rate</th><th colspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Model of death rate</th></tr><tr><th valign="top">GA</th><th valign="top">BRKGA</th><th valign="top">PSO</th><th valign="top">GA</th><th valign="top">BRKGA</th><th valign="top">PSO</th><th valign="top">GA</th><th valign="top">BRKGA</th><th valign="top">PSO</th><th valign="top">GA</th><th valign="top">BRKGA</th><th valign="top">PSO</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top">x1</td><td valign="top">1.06</td><td valign="top">1.77</td><td valign="top">2.36</td><td valign="top">1.01</td><td valign="top">2.88</td><td valign="top">1.36</td><td valign="top">4.98</td><td valign="top">4.69</td><td valign="top">4.61</td><td valign="top">3.21</td><td valign="top">4.83</td><td valign="top">7.44</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x2</td><td valign="top">75.84</td><td valign="top">60.11</td><td valign="top">74.55</td><td valign="top">84.31</td><td valign="top">87.54</td><td valign="top">86.52</td><td valign="top">75.29</td><td valign="top">82.05</td><td valign="top">56.91</td><td valign="top">88.53</td><td valign="top">79.84</td><td valign="top">85.86</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x3</td><td valign="top">3.97</td><td valign="top">4.74</td><td valign="top">5.80</td><td valign="top">6.49</td><td valign="top">5.96</td><td valign="top">4.79</td><td valign="top">12.14</td><td valign="top">5.61</td><td valign="top">12.07</td><td valign="top">18.53</td><td valign="top">26.11</td><td valign="top">26.44</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x4</td><td valign="top">34.98</td><td valign="top">26.00</td><td valign="top">32.76</td><td valign="top">17.64</td><td valign="top">22.74</td><td valign="top">21.63</td><td valign="top">25.98</td><td valign="top">21.06</td><td valign="top">25.56</td><td valign="top">49.56</td><td valign="top">46.45</td><td valign="top">40.67</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x5</td><td valign="top">16.90</td><td valign="top">32.58</td><td valign="top">10.11</td><td valign="top">24.49</td><td valign="top">34.62</td><td valign="top">25.04</td><td valign="top">34.35</td><td valign="top">30.52</td><td valign="top">34.96</td><td valign="top">32.34</td><td valign="top">21.32</td><td valign="top">29.03</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x6</td><td valign="top">51.21</td><td valign="top">37.53</td><td valign="top">48.77</td><td valign="top">83.57</td><td valign="top">22.26</td><td valign="top">76.00</td><td valign="top">47.76</td><td valign="top">61.17</td><td valign="top">60.09</td><td valign="top">57.27</td><td valign="top">66.37</td><td valign="top">58.11</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x7</td><td valign="top">1017.80</td><td valign="top">1012.22</td><td valign="top">1020.52</td><td valign="top">995.73</td><td valign="top">1018.26</td><td valign="top">1013.58</td><td valign="top">1008.81</td><td valign="top">1013.32</td><td valign="top">1020.36</td><td valign="top">1001.57</td><td valign="top">1001.97</td><td valign="top">1006.37</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x8</td><td valign="top">2.74</td><td valign="top">2.55</td><td valign="top">3.83</td><td valign="top">1.75</td><td valign="top">1.16</td><td valign="top">3.15</td><td valign="top">4.44</td><td valign="top">5.36</td><td valign="top">4.44</td><td valign="top">4.87</td><td valign="top">5.52</td><td valign="top">6.70</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x9</td><td valign="top">19.58</td><td valign="top">16.73</td><td valign="top">19.95</td><td valign="top">20.14</td><td valign="top">23.50</td><td valign="top">21.15</td><td valign="top">19.33</td><td valign="top">13.82</td><td valign="top">14.08</td><td valign="top">28.58</td><td valign="top">28.53</td><td valign="top">28.99</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x10</td><td valign="top">3.21</td><td valign="top">4.38</td><td valign="top">14.62</td><td valign="top">15.29</td><td valign="top">2.12</td><td valign="top">9.05</td><td valign="top">8.76</td><td valign="top">9.27</td><td valign="top">8.76</td><td valign="top">10.06</td><td valign="top">9.26</td><td valign="top">12.32</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x11</td><td valign="top">3.05</td><td valign="top">7.93</td><td valign="top">8.86</td><td valign="top">2.91</td><td valign="top">6.42</td><td valign="top">4.57</td><td valign="top">2.11</td><td valign="top">2.41</td><td valign="top">6.44</td><td valign="top">3.41</td><td valign="top">2.56</td><td valign="top">5.82</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x12</td><td valign="top">35.53</td><td valign="top">41.36</td><td valign="top">31.43</td><td valign="top">26.74</td><td valign="top">20.59</td><td valign="top">20.68</td><td valign="top">43.84</td><td valign="top">43.76</td><td valign="top">43.03</td><td valign="top">53.18</td><td valign="top">54.66</td><td valign="top">45.90</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x13</td><td valign="top">−24.88</td><td valign="top">−23.93</td><td valign="top">−20.64</td><td valign="top">−25.16</td><td valign="top">−15.29</td><td valign="top">−12.88</td><td valign="top">14.78</td><td valign="top">−14.28</td><td valign="top">6.80</td><td valign="top">−1.19</td><td valign="top">−8.54</td><td valign="top">−4.92</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x14</td><td valign="top">2.27</td><td valign="top">2.48</td><td valign="top">−1.88</td><td valign="top">−12.84</td><td valign="top">−7.39</td><td valign="top">−0.75</td><td valign="top">37.08</td><td valign="top">28.95</td><td valign="top">33.78</td><td valign="top">10.06</td><td valign="top">26.50</td><td valign="top">4.02</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x15</td><td valign="top">−35.80</td><td valign="top">−2.42</td><td valign="top">−15.14</td><td valign="top">−19.99</td><td valign="top">−19.51</td><td valign="top">−2.87</td><td valign="top">117.33</td><td valign="top">135.95</td><td valign="top">89.95</td><td valign="top">23.22</td><td valign="top">−17.13</td><td valign="top">8.01</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x16</td><td valign="top">−37.91</td><td valign="top">−59.20</td><td valign="top">−37.90</td><td valign="top">−8.90</td><td valign="top">−8.13</td><td valign="top">−26.99</td><td valign="top">−6.35</td><td valign="top">−2.07</td><td valign="top">−3.49</td><td valign="top">−27.94</td><td valign="top">−3.28</td><td valign="top">−11.67</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x17</td><td valign="top">−18.06</td><td valign="top">−21.84</td><td valign="top">−16.66</td><td valign="top">−9.81</td><td valign="top">−6.00</td><td valign="top">−12.02</td><td valign="top">−35.12</td><td valign="top">−27.16</td><td valign="top">−14.36</td><td valign="top">1.37</td><td valign="top">1.81</td><td valign="top">0.45</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x18</td><td valign="top">7.61</td><td valign="top">10.57</td><td valign="top">10.91</td><td valign="top">15.62</td><td valign="top">1.85</td><td valign="top">18.54</td><td valign="top">5.67</td><td valign="top">5.97</td><td valign="top">5.30</td><td valign="top">1.82</td><td valign="top">1.86</td><td valign="top">5.24</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0006"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Ideal setting of decision variables produced by the single-objective optimization algorithm named GA, BRKGA, and PSO for the purpose of minimizing the growth rate of confirmed cases or the death rate in Pakistan and Nepal.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0016">Table 6</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Variable</th><th colspan="6" align="left" valign="top">Pakistan</th><th colspan="6" align="left" valign="top">Nepal</th></tr><tr><th colspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Model of growth rate</th><th colspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Model of death rate</th><th colspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Model of growth rate</th><th colspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Model of death rate</th></tr><tr><th valign="top">GA</th><th valign="top">BRKGA</th><th valign="top">PSO</th><th valign="top">GA</th><th valign="top">BRKGA</th><th valign="top">PSO</th><th valign="top">GA</th><th valign="top">BRKGA</th><th valign="top">PSO</th><th valign="top">GA</th><th valign="top">BRKGA</th><th valign="top">PSO</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top">x1</td><td valign="top">73.76</td><td valign="top">82.61</td><td valign="top">83.62</td><td valign="top">74.81</td><td valign="top">99.84</td><td valign="top">80.38</td><td valign="top">61.46</td><td valign="top">49.18</td><td valign="top">80.54</td><td valign="top">49.45</td><td valign="top">48.93</td><td valign="top">63.50</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x2</td><td valign="top">190.56</td><td valign="top">123.30</td><td valign="top">101.53</td><td valign="top">129.32</td><td valign="top">129.32</td><td valign="top">115.82</td><td valign="top">69.71</td><td valign="top">98.42</td><td valign="top">68.79</td><td valign="top">80.14</td><td valign="top">84.32</td><td valign="top">85.83</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x3</td><td valign="top">981.11</td><td valign="top">991.08</td><td valign="top">1003.95</td><td valign="top">895.70</td><td valign="top">916.46</td><td valign="top">1001.96</td><td valign="top">942.10</td><td valign="top">926.21</td><td valign="top">934.70</td><td valign="top">939.97</td><td valign="top">935.84</td><td valign="top">941.68</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x4</td><td valign="top">24.81</td><td valign="top">26.13</td><td valign="top">27.08</td><td valign="top">17.59</td><td valign="top">17.24</td><td valign="top">16.29</td><td valign="top">13.27</td><td valign="top">16.75</td><td valign="top">11.36</td><td valign="top">16.63</td><td valign="top">19.62</td><td valign="top">19.55</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x5</td><td valign="top">3.12</td><td valign="top">2.40</td><td valign="top">3.99</td><td valign="top">2.09</td><td valign="top">2.49</td><td valign="top">1.05</td><td valign="top">1.11</td><td valign="top">1.24</td><td valign="top">1.15</td><td valign="top">2.29</td><td valign="top">1.22</td><td valign="top">1.51</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x6</td><td valign="top">17.15</td><td valign="top">22.12</td><td valign="top">26.27</td><td valign="top">17.15</td><td valign="top">17.94</td><td valign="top">16.97</td><td valign="top">25.32</td><td valign="top">28.78</td><td valign="top">35.38</td><td valign="top">96.85</td><td valign="top">61.01</td><td valign="top">78.67</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x7</td><td valign="top">−4.46</td><td valign="top">−11.68</td><td valign="top">−8.22</td><td valign="top">3.89</td><td valign="top">4.21</td><td valign="top">3.30</td><td valign="top">−15.67</td><td valign="top">5.90</td><td valign="top">−1.96</td><td valign="top">−57.68</td><td valign="top">−13.55</td><td valign="top">−16.54</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x8</td><td valign="top">2.58</td><td valign="top">−2.36</td><td valign="top">−1.87</td><td valign="top">−28.33</td><td valign="top">−11.80</td><td valign="top">−12.48</td><td valign="top">−66.82</td><td valign="top">−16.14</td><td valign="top">−62.08</td><td valign="top">−51.29</td><td valign="top">−38.15</td><td valign="top">−40.32</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x9</td><td valign="top">17.43</td><td valign="top">25.63</td><td valign="top">0.15</td><td valign="top">12.63</td><td valign="top">7.51</td><td valign="top">3.12</td><td valign="top">5.78</td><td valign="top">9.02</td><td valign="top">−1.13</td><td valign="top">−46.84</td><td valign="top">−40.57</td><td valign="top">−36.04</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x10</td><td valign="top">4.92</td><td valign="top">4.62</td><td valign="top">−3.19</td><td valign="top">−7.40</td><td valign="top">−1.60</td><td valign="top">7.04</td><td valign="top">8.76</td><td valign="top">4.54</td><td valign="top">−5.91</td><td valign="top">−69.66</td><td valign="top">−62.62</td><td valign="top">−49.13</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x11</td><td valign="top">−59.22</td><td valign="top">−27.40</td><td valign="top">−16.19</td><td valign="top">1.76</td><td valign="top">7.56</td><td valign="top">6.76</td><td valign="top">8.06</td><td valign="top">−4.89</td><td valign="top">7.39</td><td valign="top">−53.67</td><td valign="top">−66.84</td><td valign="top">−2.78</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">x12</td><td valign="top">6.92</td><td valign="top">4.78</td><td valign="top">3.50</td><td valign="top">1.50</td><td valign="top">3.45</td><td valign="top">1.23</td><td valign="top">4.64</td><td valign="top">1.97</td><td valign="top">−0.37</td><td valign="top">23.58</td><td valign="top">17.97</td><td valign="top">17.24</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
              <p id="para0037">As for the multi-objective optimization solver, another superiority to notice is that it is designed to produce several optima in an approximation of the Pareto front. That is to say, the concept of domination embedded in the optimization problem can maintain diversity within a population, which can give back a choice of reasonable solutions rather than a single result. As can be seen in <xref rid="fig0007" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>a – d, there are 8, 32, 16, and 2 desired Pareto-optimal solutions for Japan, South Korea, Pakistan, and Nepal, respectively. It is believed that strategies relying on such a list of solutions can all dramatically reduce the two objectives, which imply useful suggestions for the local government. The values of the decision variables derived from optimization have been visualized in <xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10</xref>
a – r, and their corresponding descriptive statistics are summarized in Supplementary Tables 4 and 5. Clearly, each variable allows to fluctuate slightly within a proper interval due to the great feasibility and flexibility of the NSGA-II optimization in an improved decision making of controlling COVID-19 evolution countrywide. The distribution shape and statistical characteristics of a variable in four countries differ from one another. That is because optimal strategies are put forward to meet the country's own conditions. Importantly, the appropriate temperature can be set as 23.32 (IQR: [23.24, 23.62]), 22.31 (IQR: [22.37, 24.83]), 20.49 (IQR: [19.99, 20.60]), and 14.52 (IQR: [14.06, 15.39]) in Japan, South Korea, Pakistan, and Nepal, respectively. Governments of the four countries are supposed to take harsh measures at the level of 27.40 (IQR: [27.43, 28.74]), 41.31 (IQR: [39.62, 43.11]), 23.44 (IQR: [18.90, 29.95]), 25.98 (IQR: [23.54, 28.19]). Based upon the proposed optimization process, each country can therefore make the factors balance and suitable according to the characteristics of itself so as to realize the best way for controlling the disease.<fig id="fig0010"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p>A kernel density estimate (KDE) plot for the value of decision variables in the four countries that are determined by the NSGA-II optimization algorithm. (a) – (r) Optimal value setting of decision variables x1-x18 for determining suitable control strategies. It adopts the Kernel smoothing to plot value. The peak of a curve indicates the place where values are concentrated over the interval. For labels of the x-axis, the variable outside the bracket represents the feature in Japan or South Korea dataset, while the variable in the bracket is the feature in Pakistan or Nepal dataset. Japan or South Korea dataset owns six more features than the other two countries.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0010">Fig. 10</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr10_lrg"/></fig></p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0014">
              <label>5</label>
              <title>Conclusions and future works</title>
              <p id="para0038">In summary, this research attempts to develop a combinatorial application of random forest regression and single/multi-objective optimization algorithm, contributing to better curbing the COVID-19 spread for maintaining society sustainability. The practical value of our data-driven framework lies in two aspects. For one thing, it can well capture the transmission dynamics of the virus under consideration of environmental and social variables, resulting in an accurate prediction about the near future increase of COVID-19 cases and deaths in different countries. For another, it can systematically analyze and optimize the relevant factors on the targeted two objectives. Therefore, policymakers can directly refer to these discovered pieces of critical knowledge to realize early warning, preparation, and prevention for crisis control. In particular, the measures adopted over different countries are anticipated to adapt to local conditions, which could be well fitted in sustainable societies. The effectiveness and stability of the proposed approach have been verified in four countries, including Japan, South Korea, Pakistan, and Nepal. Some important lessons can be learned from these four Asia countries as follows.</p>
              <p id="para0039">As for the random forest regression, it is built based on the 3-fold cross-validation, PSO optimization, and proper rolling time-window to learn effective combinations of environment and social features, which is proven effective to exhibit high accuracy in estimating how COVID-19 will evolve nationally. Besides, the environmental factor named temperature and the social factor called stringency index measuring the response level of government are found to play the most dominant role in forecasting the COVID-19 evolution among all considered features. It appears that the relatively high temperature and tight control tend to support a favorable condition for suppressing the spread of the influenza virus. As for the multi-objective optimization process, the NSGA-II algorithm is responsible for generating several Pareto-optimal solutions along with a suitable combination and setting of critical variables that are adapted to the country-specific circumstance, which is beneficial to the disease mitigation. By following the determined profile of decision variables, we can see the considerable potential of cutting down the daily increase rate of infections and deaths in all countries by over 95% compared with the original condition. Accordingly, optimal results provide the local government with actionable suggestions for combating the pandemic. Moreover, it must be stressed that the optimal level based on the social factors is about 7.3% (Japan), 11.54% (South Korea), 12.45% (Pakistan), 1.47% (Nepal) larger than adjustment of environmental variables. That means that factors concerning the social aspect should be the prioritization of designing the control strategies.</p>
              <p id="para0040">Some future work will be performed to address the existing limitations in the current research. Firstly, we can add more variables of interest that significantly impact the pandemic evolution and perform proper preprocessing techniques on the collected raw data, aiming to pursue an improvement of the data quality and representativeness. We will also take more countries into consideration to further verify the feasibility and practicability of our proposed approach. The targeted countries will not be confined to Asia, which can be extended to other continents, like Europe, North America, and so on. As a result, a larger and more comprehensive dataset can be created to better fit the predictive model, aiming to provide deep insights into COVID-19 evolution in different countries. We can therefore easily look for coherent patterns and differences embedded in the spatial-temporal distribution among different countries in Asia or countries in different continents across the world. This discovered knowledge is meaningful to draw valuable conclusions for pandemic mitigation. Secondly, since the pandemic has negatively caused massive global economic disruptions, we can reasonably add a new objective concerning the economic impact of a country into the multi-objective optimization problem. This desired goal at the level of economy is entirely different from the current two objectives about the case and death increase, which deserves further investigation. It is necessary for the government to take effective actions to slow down the virus spread and in the meanwhile limit economic recession. Thirdly, we can strive to explore the real cause-effect rather than the statistical relationship between the inputs and outputs for a more solid analysis. The discovery and measurement of the causal association is another important question in mining complex time-series data.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="COI-statement">
              <title>Declaration of Competing Interest</title>
              <p id="para0046">None.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list id="cebibl1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="bib0001">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0001">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ali</surname>
                      <given-names>I.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alharbi</surname>
                      <given-names>O.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"COVID-19: Disease, management, treatment, and social impact"</article-title>
                  <source>Science of the Total Environment</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">138861</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0002">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0002">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bansal</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"Utility of artificial intelligence amidst the COVID 19 pandemic: A review"</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Medical Systems</source>
                  <volume>44</volume>
                  <issue>9</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>6</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0003">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0003">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Barda</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"Developing a COVID-19 mortality risk prediction model when individual-level data are not available"</article-title>
                  <source>Nature Communications</source>
                  <volume>11</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>9</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0004">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0004">Bashir, M.F. .(2020). "Correlation between climate indicators and COVID-19 pandemic in New York, USA". <italic>Science of the Total Environment</italic>: 138835.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0005">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0005">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Breiman</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"Random forests"</article-title>
                  <source>Machine learning</source>
                  <volume>45</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2001</year>
                  <fpage>5</fpage>
                  <lpage>32</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0006">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0006">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Das</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"Living environment matters: Unravelling the spatial clustering of COVID-19 hotspots in Kolkata megacity, India"</article-title>
                  <source>Sustainable Cities and Society</source>
                  <volume>65</volume>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">102577</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0007">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0007">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Deb</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"A fast and elitist multiobjective genetic algorithm: NSGA-II."</article-title>
                  <source>IEEE Transactions on Evolutionary Computation</source>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <fpage>182</fpage>
                  <lpage>197</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0008">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0008">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gao</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"Machine learning based early warning system enables accurate mortality risk prediction for COVID-19."</article-title>
                  <source>Nature Communications</source>
                  <volume>11</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>10</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0009">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0009">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gen</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lin</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>"Genetic algorithms."</part-title>
                  <source>Wiley Encyclopedia of Computer Science and Engineering</source>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>15</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0010">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0010">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gonçalves</surname>
                      <given-names>J..F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Resende</surname>
                      <given-names>M.G..</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"Biased random-key genetic algorithms for combinatorial optimization"</article-title>
                  <source>Journal of Heuristics</source>
                  <volume>17</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <fpage>487</fpage>
                  <lpage>525</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0011">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0011">Google (2020). "Google Community Mobility Reports." https://www.google.com/covid19/mobility/.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0012">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0012">Hale, T. (2020). "Oxford COVID-19 government response tracker (OxCGRT)." https://www.bsg.ox.ac.uk/research/research-projects/coronavirus-government-response-tracker.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0014">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0014">Hopkins, J. (2020). "COVID-19 Dashboard by the Center for Systems Science and Engineering (CSSE) at Johns Hopkins University (JHU)." Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University: https://www.arcgis.com/apps/opsdashboard/index.html#/bda7594740fd40299423467b40299423448e40299423469ecf40299423466.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib43">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="optIHhqSYlx4O">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Haug</surname>
                      <given-names>Nils</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Geyrhofer</surname>
                      <given-names>Lukas</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Londei</surname>
                      <given-names>Alessandro</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dervic</surname>
                      <given-names>Elma</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Ranking the effectiveness of worldwide COVID-19 government interventions</article-title>
                  <source>Nature human behaviour</source>
                  <volume>4</volume>
                  <issue>12</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1303</fpage>
                  <lpage>1312</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0015">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0015">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hu</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"The role of built and social environmental factors in Covid-19 transmission: A look at America's capital city."</article-title>
                  <source>Sustainable Cities and Society</source>
                  <volume>65</volume>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">102580</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0016">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0016">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huppert</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Katriel</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"Mathematical modelling and prediction in infectious disease epidemiology."</article-title>
                  <source>Clinical microbiology and infection</source>
                  <volume>19</volume>
                  <issue>11</issue>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <fpage>999</fpage>
                  <lpage>1005</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24266045</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0017">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0017">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kennedy</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eberhart</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>Particle swarm optimization</part-title>
                  <source>Proceedings of ICNN'95-International Conference on Neural Networks</source>
                  <year>1995</year>
                  <publisher-name>IEEE</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0018">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0018">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lim</surname>
                      <given-names>J..M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"Population anxiety and positive behaviour change during the COVID-19 epidemic: Cross-sectional surveys in Singapore, China and Italy."</article-title>
                  <source>Influenza and Other Respiratory Viruses</source>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <fpage>45</fpage>
                  <lpage>55</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32889784</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0019">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0019">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Louppe</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"Understanding variable importances in forests of randomized trees."</article-title>
                  <source>Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems</source>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <fpage>431</fpage>
                  <lpage>439</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0020">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0020">Lundberg, S..M., .(2018). "Consistent individualized feature attribution for tree ensembles." arXiv preprint arXiv:.03888.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0021">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0021">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lundberg</surname>
                      <given-names>S..M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"From local explanations to global understanding with explainable AI for trees."</article-title>
                  <source>Nature Machine Intelligence</source>
                  <volume>2</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>2522</fpage>
                  <lpage>5839</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0022">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0022">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lwin</surname>
                      <given-names>M..O.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"Global sentiments surrounding the COVID-19 pandemic on Twitter: Analysis of Twitter trends."</article-title>
                  <source>JMIR Public Health and Surveillance</source>
                  <volume>6</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>E19447</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32412418</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0023">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0023">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Maiti</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"Exploring spatiotemporal effects of the driving factors on COVID-19 incidences in the contiguous United States."</article-title>
                  <source>Sustainable Cities and Society</source>
                  <volume>68</volume>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">102784</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0024">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0024">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Malki</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"Association between weather data and COVID-19 pandemic predicting mortality rate: Machine learning approaches."</article-title>
                  <source>Chaos, Solitons &amp; Fractals</source>
                  <volume>138</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">110137</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0025">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0025">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mansour</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"Sociodemographic determinants of COVID-19 incidence rates in Oman: Geospatial modelling using multiscale geographically weighted regression (MGWR)."</article-title>
                  <source>Sustainable Cities and Society</source>
                  <volume>65</volume>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">102627</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0026">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0026">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nakada</surname>
                      <given-names>L.Y.K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Urban</surname>
                      <given-names>R.C..</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"COVID-19 pandemic: Environmental and social factors influencing the spread of SARS-CoV-2 in São Paulo, Brazil."</article-title>
                  <source>Environmental Science and Pollution Research</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>7</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0027">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0027">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pan</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"Improved Fuzzy Bayesian Network-Based Risk Analysis With Interval-Valued Fuzzy Sets and D–S Evidence Theory."</article-title>
                  <source>IEEE Transactions on Fuzzy Systems</source>
                  <volume>28</volume>
                  <issue>9</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>2063</fpage>
                  <lpage>2077</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0028">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0028">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pan</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"Roles of artificial intelligence in construction engineering and management: A critical review and future trends."</article-title>
                  <source>Automation in Construction</source>
                  <volume>122</volume>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">103517</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib45">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="optxWZEmL9dqa">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pan</surname>
                      <given-names>Yue</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>Limao</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A BIM-data mining integrated digital twin framework for advanced project management</article-title>
                  <source>Automation in Construction</source>
                  <volume>124</volume>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <fpage>103564</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0029">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0029">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rahman</surname>
                      <given-names>M..A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"Data-driven dynamic clustering framework for mitigating the adverse economic impact of Covid-19 lockdown practices."</article-title>
                  <source>Sustainable Cities and Society</source>
                  <volume>62</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">102372</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0030">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0030">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Samuelsen</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"Integrating multiple data sources for learning analytics—Review of literature."</article-title>
                  <source>Research and Practice in Technology Enhanced Learning</source>
                  <volume>14</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <fpage>11</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0031">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0031">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sannigrahi</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"Examining the association between socio-demographic composition and COVID-19 fatalities in the European region using spatial regression approach."</article-title>
                  <source>Sustainable Cities and Society</source>
                  <volume>62</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">102418</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0032">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0032">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Siegenfeld</surname>
                      <given-names>A..F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bar-Yam</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"The impact of travel and timing in eliminating COVID-19."</article-title>
                  <source>Communications Physics</source>
                  <volume>3</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>8</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0034">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0034">Thakur, N..V. (2020). Coronavirus outbreak: Multi-objective prediction and optimization. intelligent systems and methods to combat Covid-19, Springer: 19–28.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib44">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="optPShm3IzGWQ">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sun</surname>
                      <given-names>Chanjuan</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhai</surname>
                      <given-names>Zhiqiang</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The efficacy of social distance and ventilation effectiveness in preventing COVID-19 transmission</article-title>
                  <source>Sustainable Cities and Society</source>
                  <volume>62</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>102390.</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32834937</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0036">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0036">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yan</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"On the design of sparse but efficient structures in operations."</article-title>
                  <source>Management Science</source>
                  <volume>64</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <fpage>3421</fpage>
                  <lpage>3445</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0037">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0037">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shami</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"On hyperparameter optimization of machine learning algorithms: Theory and practice."</article-title>
                  <source>Neurocomputing</source>
                  <volume>415</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>295</fpage>
                  <lpage>316</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0038">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0038">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yeşilkanat</surname>
                      <given-names>C.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"Spatio-temporal estimation of the daily cases of COVID-19 in worldwide using random forest machine learning algorithm."</article-title>
                  <source>Chaos, Solitons &amp; Fractals</source>
                  <volume>140</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">110210</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0039">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0039">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yusoff</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"Overview of NSGA-II for optimizing machining process parameters."</article-title>
                  <source>Procedia Engineering</source>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <fpage>3978</fpage>
                  <lpage>3983</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0040">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0040">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zaitchik</surname>
                      <given-names>B.F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"A framework for research linking weather, climate and COVID-19."</article-title>
                  <source>Nature communications</source>
                  <volume>11</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>3</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0041">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0041">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhan</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"Random-Forest-Bagging Broad Learning System with Applications for COVID-19 Pandemic."</article-title>
                  <source>IEEE Internet of Things Journal</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0042">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0042">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zivkovic</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>"COVID-19 cases prediction by using hybrid machine learning and beetle antennae search approach."</article-title>
                  <source>Sustainable Cities and Society</source>
                  <volume>66</volume>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">102669</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0035">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="tboref0001">WAQI, (2020).The World Air Quality Index (WAQI) Project: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://aqicn.org/data-platform/covid19/verify/11c09b43b-09f12-4244-a4286f-24647e24641fa24643d24649" id="interref8001">https://aqicn.org/data-platform/covid19/verify/11c09b43b-09f12-4244-a4286f-24647e24641fa24643d24649</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
            <sec id="sec0017" sec-type="supplementary-material">
              <label>Appendix</label>
              <title>Supplementary materials</title>
              <p id="para0045a">
                <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ecom0001">
                  <media xlink:href="mmc1.docx">
                    <alt-text>Image, application 1</alt-text>
                  </media>
                </supplementary-material>
              </p>
            </sec>
            <ack id="ack0001">
              <title>Aknowledgements</title>
              <p id="para0047">This study is supported by the <funding-source id="gs0001">Ministry of Education Tier 1</funding-source> Grants, Singapore (no. 04MNP000279C120, no. 04MNP002126C120) and the Start-Up Grant at <funding-source id="gs0002"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100001475</institution-id><institution>Nanyang Technological University</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>, Singapore (no. 04INS000423C120).</p>
            </ack>
            <fn-group>
              <fn id="sec0016" fn-type="supplementary-material">
                <p id="para0006a">Supplementary material associated with this article can be found, in the online version, at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scs.2021.103254" id="interref0001">doi:10.1016/j.scs.2021.103254</ext-link>.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
