<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-03-11T00:53:57Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8119293" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8119293</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-05-14</datestamp>
        <setSpec>pheelsevier</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.xsd" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Financ Res Lett</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Financ Res Lett</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Finance Research Letters</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">1544-6123</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1544-6131</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>The Author(s). Published by Elsevier Inc.</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC8119293</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8119293</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">8119293</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34007250</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pii">S1544-6123(21)00204-X</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.frl.2021.102123</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">102123</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Optimal lockdown policy for vaccination during COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0001">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Fu</surname>
                    <given-names>Yuting</given-names>
                  </name>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0002">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Jin</surname>
                    <given-names>Hanqing</given-names>
                  </name>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0003">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Xiang</surname>
                    <given-names>Haitao</given-names>
                  </name>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0004">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Wang</surname>
                    <given-names>Ning</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="cor0001" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="aff0001">Oxford Nie Financial Big Data Laboratory, Mathematical Institute, University of Oxford, Oxford, UK</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor0001"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author.</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>14</day>
                <month>5</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.-->
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <month>3</month>
                <year>2022</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>14</day>
                <month>5</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>45</volume>
              <fpage>102123</fpage>
              <lpage>102123</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>31</day>
                  <month>1</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>21</day>
                  <month>4</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>6</day>
                  <month>5</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2021 The Author(s)</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
                <license>
                  <license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="abs0001">
                <p>As the COVID-19 spreads across the world, many nations impose lockdown measures at the early stage of the pandemic to prevent the spread of the disease. Controversy surrounds the lockdown as it is a choice between economic freedom and public health. The ultimate solution to a pandemic is to vaccinate a massive population to achieve herd immunity. However, the whole vaccination programme is a long and complicated process. The virus and the vaccine will coexist for quite a long time. How to gradually ease the lockdown based on vaccination progress is an important question, as both economic and epidemiological issues are involved. In this paper, we extend the classic SIR model to find optimal decision to balance between economy and public health in the process of vaccination rollout. The model provides an approach of vaccine value estimation. Our results provide scientific suggestion for policymakers to make important decisions on how to gradually relax the strength for the lockdown over the entire vaccination cycle.</p>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group id="keys0001">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>COVID-19</kwd>
                <kwd>Equilibrium</kwd>
                <kwd>SIR</kwd>
                <kwd>Lockdown</kwd>
                <kwd>Optimal control</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="sec0001">
              <label>1</label>
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p id="p0007">Since reaching over 100 million infections and 3 million deaths, the outbreak of Coronavirus (COVID-19) is one of the most devastating pandemics in human history. We are still in the midst of the global outbreak, which has led the world to severe economic decline and caused devastating damage to the many nations (<xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">Sułkowski, 2020</xref>). The global economy has been divided into its pre-pandemic and post-pandemic phases (<xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2020</xref>). The financial markets are significantly influenced by COVID-19 with substantially increased volatility (<xref rid="bib0004" ref-type="bibr">Albulescu, 2020</xref>) and reduced market efficiency (<xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">Wang and Wang, 2020</xref>). In an attempt to curb the spread of the disease, the governments impose a lockdown measure at the early stage of the pandemic. Without vaccination, lockdown is more effective at mitigating the effects of COVID-19 exposure than other measures like travel bans and economic stimulus packages (<xref rid="bib0019" ref-type="bibr">Narayan et al., 2020</xref>). Several countries are in and out of the lockdown many times, which has a considerable impact on financial markets. Lockdown increases stock market volatility and liquidity (<xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">Baig et al., 2020</xref>). The stringency of the lockdown has a two-way effect on the financial markets (<xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">Aggarwal et al., 2020</xref>).</p>
              <p id="p0008">Lockdown is a dilemma between economic freedom and public health. If countries do not release lockdown as soon as possible, it will lead to economic stagnation. On the other hand, several countries open too early to prevent a recession, which triggers the numerous waves of the outbreaks. Some countries have recently gone back and forth several times from lifting the ban to the reinstatement of the lockdown. For example, the UK has been through the third period to enforce a mandatory lockdown. Therefore whether and how to impose and release lockdown should take into account the public welfare and economic benefits.</p>
              <p id="p0009">The ultimate solution to a pandemic is to vaccinate massive population to achieve herd immunity. Recent research into COVID-19 and vaccine production has made significant progress. The current vaccine research has been in the development and production process. The regulators have approved a range of vaccines, and many countries are in the process of a mass vaccination rollout. Despite the expense and safety issues with vaccines (<xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">Forni and Mantovani, 2021</xref>), a successful vaccination programme is only known to be a conclusive milestone that will end the pandemic and result in a robust economic recovery. Vaccines significantly mitigate the adverse impact of previous pandemics (<xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">Gong et al., 2020</xref>). Forecasts suggest that there will be high economic costs in the absence of global vaccinations of COVID-19 (<xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">Çakmaklı et al., 2021</xref>). The vaccine is also an essential factor driving stock market prices (<xref rid="bib0002" ref-type="bibr">Acharya et al., 2020</xref>).</p>
              <p id="p0010">From an economic point of view, vaccination is possibly a powerful way to restore economic and social normality. Lockdown only slows down the spread of epidemic while vaccination prevents people from having the disease, thus free people for working and consumption. Many people assume that vaccination would protect them, and lockdown should be relaxed instantly after vaccination. However, there are billions of people in the world waiting to receive the vaccine and the production of vaccine is still limited. The whole vaccination rollout is long and complicated. In the future, we will live with the virus and the vaccine for quite some time. Considering the vaccination progress and the quarantine cost, lockdown will be gradually lifted when vaccination is available.</p>
              <p id="p0011">How to gradually ease the lockdown based on the vaccine progress is an important question as of this time. There is a need for a quantitative model to address the above question that policymakers may face in reality. We extend the classic SIR model (<xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Harko, Lobo, Mak, 2014</xref>, <xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">Kermack, McKendrick, 1927</xref>) and incorporate an equilibrium framework to study the optimal lockdown policy during the pandemic period. The model can be used to study the role of lockdown policy in the pandemic by tracking vaccination progress. Our results suggest that it is crucial to gradually relax the strength for the lockdown policy during vaccination. Our model also provides an optimal estimation on a process to release the lockdown.</p>
              <p id="p0012">Several studies have indicated that incorporating vaccination and lockdown is beneficial. <xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">Garriga et al. (2020)</xref>, <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">Alvarez et al. (2020)</xref>, <xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr">Acemoglu et al. (2020)</xref> include the vaccination in epidemiological models to study the optimal lockdown control policy. It assumes the arrival of vaccination as a Poisson process and once the vaccination is available, people get vaccination immediately. However, the second assumption is an over-simplification. In reality, due to the limited productivity and speed of vaccination rollout, it often takes not a short time to get vaccination for massive population.Different from previous works, we assume the vaccination is already available at the beginning and focus on the the impact of the vaccination on the lockdown policy.</p>
              <p id="p0013">The expenditure on the vaccine is a problem for policymakers to consider when there are various kinds of vaccines available in the market. We provide an approach for vaccine value estimation based on utility indifference. The estimation result can be a reference for policymakers to choose different vaccines. Under the parameter setting in our simulation, the estimated value of the vaccine is approximately at the middle of vaccine prices in the current market.</p>
              <p id="p0014">This paper continues as follows, in <xref rid="sec0002" ref-type="sec">Section 2</xref>, we describe the SIR-Lockdown model with vaccination. In <xref rid="sec0008" ref-type="sec">Section 3</xref>, we discuss the parameter estimation of the model. We present the numerical results of the SIR-Lockdown model with vaccination in <xref rid="sec0011" ref-type="sec">Section 4</xref>. <xref rid="sec0016" ref-type="sec">Section 5</xref> makes conclusions.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0002">
              <label>2</label>
              <title>Model</title>
              <p id="p0015">Epidemiological models have been widely studied in literature to analyse the dynamics of the pandemic (<xref rid="bib0017" ref-type="bibr">Kucharski, Russell, Diamond, Liu, Edmunds, Funk, Eggo, Sun, Jit, Munday, et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">Liu, Gayle, Wilder-Smith, Rocklöv, 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">Wang, Fu, Zhang, Shi, 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">Wu, Leung, Leung, 2020</xref>) and search for optimal lockdown policy (<xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">Alvarez, Argente, Lippi, 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">Gonzalez-Eiras, Niepelt, 2020</xref>, <xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr">Acemoglu, Chernozhukov, Werning, Whinston, 2020</xref>). However, there is less discussion on the optimal lockdown policy during vaccination, which is carried out in many countries and is hopefully the best way out of COVID-19 pandemic. In this section, we extend the canonical SIR model by including the effect of vaccine to balance the economic welfare and public health during the outbreak of COVID-19. We also introduce an estimation of vaccine value based on our model.</p>
              <sec id="sec0003">
                <label>2.1</label>
                <title>Epidemiology model</title>
                <p id="p0016">As shown in the classic SIR model (<xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">Kermack, McKendrick, 1927</xref>, <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">Hethcote, 1989</xref>), we classify people into three categories according to <xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">Harko et al. (2014)</xref>:<list list-type="simple" id="lst0002"><list-item id="lstitem0007"><label>•</label><p id="p0017">Susceptible (S) are those who have not been tested positive to the virus.</p></list-item><list-item id="lstitem0008"><label>•</label><p id="p0018">Infectious (I) are those who are tested positive to the virus;</p></list-item><list-item id="lstitem0009"><label>•</label><p id="p0019">Recovered (R) are those who have been tested positive to the virus and now recovered;</p></list-item></list>
</p>
                <p id="p0020">In a certain unit of time, we assume that all susceptible people are subjects to be infected with some probability in direct contact with infectious people, and infectious people will recover with a constant probability of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si7.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> or die with another constant probability <inline-formula><mml:math id="M2" altimg="si6.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>. All infection happens via direct contact between susceptible people and infected ones into three types of activities: purchasing and/or consumption of goods and services, working with other people, and other daily activities. Vaccination is an effective method of preventing the spread of infectious diseases.</p>
                <p id="p0021">When there is no vaccination, people become immune to the virus only through getting infected and then recovered. We now include vaccination into the SIR model, with which people can become immune by a safe vaccination.</p>
                <p id="p0022">We assume that at each unit time period, a fix amount <inline-formula><mml:math id="M3" altimg="si12.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> of susceptible people get vaccination, and hence swith to the class of recovered from the next unit time period.</p>
                <p id="p0023">We use the following equation (<xref rid="eq0001" ref-type="disp-formula">(1)</xref>, <xref rid="eq0002" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref>, <xref rid="eq0003" ref-type="disp-formula">(3)</xref>, <xref rid="eq0004" ref-type="disp-formula">(4)</xref>, <xref rid="eq0005" ref-type="disp-formula">(5)</xref>) to describe our extended SIR model for the transition among four groups, i.e., the Susceptible, the Infected, the Recover, and the Death outcome.<disp-formula id="eq0001"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M4" altimg="si15.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="eq0002"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M5" altimg="si16.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="eq0003"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M6" altimg="si17.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="eq0004"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="M7" altimg="si18.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="eq0005"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="M8" altimg="si19.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
                <p id="p0024">In this system of equations, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M9" altimg="si20.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M10" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> represents the number of people in categories of Susceptible, Infectious, Recovery and Death respectively at time <inline-formula><mml:math id="M11" altimg="si22.svg"><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. We use <inline-formula><mml:math id="M12" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to model the (average) consumption behaviour and working hours of susceptible people. Similarly we use <inline-formula><mml:math id="M13" altimg="si24.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for infectious people and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M14" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for recovered people. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M15" altimg="si26.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> in <xref rid="eq0001" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (1)</xref> models the number of newly infectious people in the time period <inline-formula><mml:math id="M16" altimg="si22.svg"><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M17" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> through direct contact between infectious and susceptible people. There are three types of direct contact, which are for consumption, for working, and for other purpose of daily life. We use 3 constant parameters to describe the contribution of the 3 types of contact in the infection rate, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M18" altimg="si28.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> for the purchasing/consuming, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M19" altimg="si29.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> for the working, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M20" altimg="si30.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> for other contact.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0004">
                <label>2.2</label>
                <title>Preference model</title>
                <p id="p0025">In this section, we introduce the preference model of the three categories of people (S,I,R)and analyse their rational behaviour in the epidemiology model.</p>
                <sec id="sec0005">
                  <label>2.2.1</label>
                  <title>Behaviour of individuals in different categories</title>
                  <p id="p0026">We study the rational behaviour of all people who maximise their own welfare by choosing proper consumption and working hours like in a normal time.<xref rid="fn0001" ref-type="fn">1</xref>
We use the following utility function to model the utility from consumption and working of an individual,<disp-formula id="eq0006"><label>(6)</label><mml:math id="M21" altimg="si31.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>ln</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M22" altimg="si32.svg"><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the consumption, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M23" altimg="si33.svg"><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the working hours. In this utility, the first term measures the utility from consumption, the second term measures the disutility from working, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M24" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the weight between this two terms.</p>
                  <p id="p0027">Denote by <inline-formula><mml:math id="M25" altimg="si34.svg"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> the average wage per hour of a person, then the labor income of an individual with working hour <inline-formula><mml:math id="M26" altimg="si33.svg"><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is <inline-formula><mml:math id="M27" altimg="si35.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">*</mml:mo><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, which will be the upper bound of the consumption, i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M28" altimg="si36.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                  <p id="p0028">The parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="M29" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is not emperially easy to estimate. We fix it by assuming that the prevailing behaviour of consumption and working are optimal. Denote by <inline-formula><mml:math id="M30" altimg="si8.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> the full working hours in a unit time before the spread of the virus, which is officially guided by the government. It is natural that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M31" altimg="si8.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is set optimally for individuals. If a person follows the full working hours <inline-formula><mml:math id="M32" altimg="si8.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> optimally, then her labor income will be <inline-formula><mml:math id="M33" altimg="si37.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Since the utility function is strictly increasing in the consumption, all labor income should be consumed up, hence the optimal consumption <inline-formula><mml:math id="M34" altimg="si38.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> should be <inline-formula><mml:math id="M35" altimg="si39.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. By the assumed optimality of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M36" altimg="si8.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, we have <inline-formula><mml:math id="M37" altimg="si40.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∂</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, by which we choose<disp-formula id="ueq0001"><mml:math id="M38" altimg="si41.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
                  <p id="p0029">Given a terminal time <inline-formula><mml:math id="M39" altimg="si42.svg"><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, the total utility of a flow of consumption and working hours <inline-formula><mml:math id="M40" altimg="si43.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>⋯</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is defined by<disp-formula id="eq0007"><label>(7)</label><mml:math id="M41" altimg="si44.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>U</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:msup><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
                  <p id="p0030">To contain the spreading of the virus, governments need to apply a lockdown policy to reduce direct contacts between people, which will impose stricter constraints on their behaviour. In this paper, we study the lockdown policy by a constraint on the ratio <inline-formula><mml:math id="M42" altimg="si45.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> of the working hour in the full working capacity, i.e., given the full working hours <inline-formula><mml:math id="M43" altimg="si8.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, the maximal working hour cannot exceed <inline-formula><mml:math id="M44" altimg="si46.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">*</mml:mo><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. We suppose the government cannot easily identify individuals into their categories so that the lockdown constraint on the working hours is the same for all people who are interested in their own total utility. We formulate the decision making problem for each category with a given lockdown policy <inline-formula><mml:math id="M45" altimg="si47.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, and then study the lockdown policy-making problem for the government. It turns out that the optimal behaviour for infected and recovered people are quite straightforward, to consume and work as much as they are allowed to do. While for susceptible people, their optimal working hour may be strictly less than being allowed to do. We summarise our this properties on these optimal behaviour (the proof is deferred to the supplementary).<list list-type="simple" id="lst0003"><list-item id="lstitem0010"><label>•</label><p id="p0031">At time <inline-formula><mml:math id="M46" altimg="si22.svg"><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> with state <inline-formula><mml:math id="M47" altimg="si48.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and the lockdown policy <inline-formula><mml:math id="M48" altimg="si49.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, the optimal behaviour <inline-formula><mml:math id="M49" altimg="si50.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for recovered people is<disp-formula id="ueq0002"><mml:math id="M50" altimg="si51.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>⋯</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p></list-item><list-item id="lstitem0011"><label>•</label><p id="p0032">Given the lockdown policy <inline-formula><mml:math id="M51" altimg="si47.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, the optimal behaviour <inline-formula><mml:math id="M52" altimg="si52.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for infectious people is<disp-formula id="eq0008"><label>(8)</label><mml:math id="M53" altimg="si53.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>⋯</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p></list-item><list-item id="lstitem0012"><label>•</label><p id="p0033">Given the lockdown policy <inline-formula><mml:math id="M54" altimg="si47.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, the optimal <inline-formula><mml:math id="M55" altimg="si54.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for susceptible people must satisfies<disp-formula id="eq0009"><label>(9)</label><mml:math id="M56" altimg="si55.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>⋯</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p></list-item></list>
</p>
                  <p id="p0034">Given the trivial optimal behaviour <inline-formula><mml:math id="M57" altimg="si56.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for infected people and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M58" altimg="si57.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for recovered people, we denote by <inline-formula><mml:math id="M59" altimg="si58.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M60" altimg="si59.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> the optimal total utility from <inline-formula><mml:math id="M61" altimg="si22.svg"><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M62" altimg="si42.svg"><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> for these two types of people respectively. For a susceptible people, since she may be infected or vaccinated, her total utility will involve the optimal total utilities of infected people and recovered people. Suppose her behaviour flow is described by <inline-formula><mml:math id="M63" altimg="si60.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, then, her total utility <inline-formula><mml:math id="M64" altimg="si61.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> should satisfy<disp-formula id="eq0010"><label>(10)</label><mml:math id="M65" altimg="si62.svg"><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mfrac><mml:msup><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>Hence the optimal behaviour for susceptible people can be formuated as<disp-formula id="eq0011"><label>(11)</label><mml:math id="M66" altimg="si63.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mtext>Maximise</mml:mtext><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>since the optimal consumption <inline-formula><mml:math id="M67" altimg="si64.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is trivially determined by the working hour <inline-formula><mml:math id="M68" altimg="si65.svg"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula>
</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="sec0006">
                  <label>2.2.2</label>
                  <title>Optimal control of the policymaker</title>
                  <p id="p0035">With the optimal behaviour in each category under a given lockdown policy <inline-formula><mml:math id="M69" altimg="si47.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, we can easily formulate the optimal policy-making problem into an optimal control problem.</p>
                  <p id="p0036">Suppose we start the lockdown problem from some time <inline-formula><mml:math id="M70" altimg="si66.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> with the contamination state <inline-formula><mml:math id="M71" altimg="si67.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> being given by <inline-formula><mml:math id="M72" altimg="si68.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M73" altimg="si69.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, then the optimal lockdown policy should be the optimal control for<disp-formula id="eq0012"><label>(12)</label><mml:math id="M74" altimg="si70.svg"><mml:munder><mml:mi>max</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo></mml:msub></mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo></mml:msub><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:msup><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M75" altimg="si71.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are the optimal consumption and working hours for people in category <inline-formula><mml:math id="M76" altimg="si72.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M77" altimg="si72.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> can be <inline-formula><mml:math id="M78" altimg="si73.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> or <inline-formula><mml:math id="M79" altimg="si74.svg"><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>), which are all determined in previous optimisation problems.</p>
                  <p id="p0037">In previous objective <inline-formula><mml:math id="M80" altimg="si75.svg"><mml:msup><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>, we remove all cases of death without any penalty. In reality, since death of disease has a strong negative impact to a household as well as to the society, regulators should not ignore any death case. We correct the previous objective by introducing a heavy penalty, and dedine the new objective<disp-formula id="eq0013"><label>(13)</label><mml:math id="M81" altimg="si76.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:msub><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:msup><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where the parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="M82" altimg="si77.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> describes how serious we are on death from the virus. In this new objective, we measure the the cost of a death by a multiple of the optimal utility for a recovered people, and the multiple <inline-formula><mml:math id="M83" altimg="si78.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> can be viewed as the severity of death in the government’s view. When <inline-formula><mml:math id="M84" altimg="si79.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M85" altimg="si80.svg"><mml:msup><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> reduces to our previous objective <inline-formula><mml:math id="M86" altimg="si75.svg"><mml:msup><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                  <p id="p0038">With this new objective, the problem for a regulator to solve is<disp-formula id="eq0014"><label>(14)</label><mml:math id="M87" altimg="si81.svg"><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:munder><mml:mi>max</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo></mml:msub></mml:munder></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo></mml:msub><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>X</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mspace width="0.28em"/><mml:mo>∀</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0007">
                <label>2.3</label>
                <title>A model application: value of vaccine</title>
                <p id="p0039">We introduce a method for value estimation of vaccination based on the proposed model. It is based on utility indifference, i.e, the aggregated expected utility of the whole population would be the same w/o the vaccination at the end of the epidemic. Then the gap between the accumulated aggregated utility w/o vaccination can be regarded as the utility of the vaccine value. Denote the value of vaccination as <inline-formula><mml:math id="M88" altimg="si82.svg"><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, the overall percentage of the population that accepted the vaccination as <inline-formula><mml:math id="M89" altimg="si83.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, accumulated aggregated utility as <inline-formula><mml:math id="M90" altimg="si84.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M91" altimg="si85.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> from start to the end of the epidemic w/o vaccination. Then by utility indifference, we have<disp-formula id="eq0015"><label>(15)</label><mml:math id="M92" altimg="si86.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>log</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
                <p id="p0040">For the utility function of vaccination, since we use <inline-formula><mml:math id="M93" altimg="si87.svg"><mml:mi>log</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> in our model as the utility function of consumption as in <xref rid="eq0006" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (6)</xref>, we also apply it here as the utility function of vaccination value. By <xref rid="eq0015" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (15)</xref>, we get the estimation of vaccine value <inline-formula><mml:math id="M94" altimg="si82.svg"><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0008">
              <label>3</label>
              <title>Solving the model</title>
              <sec id="sec0009">
                <label>3.1</label>
                <title>Solving scheme</title>
                <p id="p0041">In Problem <xref rid="eq0014" ref-type="disp-formula">(14)</xref>, or its reduced version <xref rid="eq0012" ref-type="disp-formula">(12)</xref>, the optimal decisions of individuals in all three categories are involved. Fortunately, the optimal decisions of recovered and infectious people are trivial due to our good structure of the model, which leaves us to tackle the optimal decision Problem <xref rid="eq0011" ref-type="disp-formula">(11)</xref> for susceptible people before the Problem <xref rid="eq0014" ref-type="disp-formula">(14)</xref>.</p>
                <p id="p0042">We start our solving scheme by tackling the Problem <xref rid="eq0011" ref-type="disp-formula">(11)</xref> with a given lockdown policy <inline-formula><mml:math id="M95" altimg="si47.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>. Because of the lockdown constraint, it is almost hopeless for us to get an explicit solution. We solve this optimal control problem numerically in the same was as in <xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">Eichenbaum et al. (2020)</xref>. In this approach, the optimal control at each time step is regarded as the static optimisation with two constraints from the consumption budget and the lockdown policy on the working hours, and solutions are obtained by solving the corresponding KKT condition.<xref rid="fn0002" ref-type="fn">2</xref>
</p>
                <p id="p0043">With the optimal control <inline-formula><mml:math id="M96" altimg="si89.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> as functions of the lockdown policy <inline-formula><mml:math id="M97" altimg="si47.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>·</mml:mo></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, we deal with the optimal control problem <xref rid="eq0014" ref-type="disp-formula">(14)</xref> as an optimisation over the high dimension space <inline-formula><mml:math id="M98" altimg="si90.svg"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> by the gradient-based interior-point method used in the Matlab function fmincon. Although we have no theoretical proof on the convergence of our scheme, our numerical results show the convergence of our scheme.</p>
                <p id="p0044">Parts of our code in our scheme are from <xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">Eichenbaum et al. (2020)</xref>.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0010">
                <label>3.2</label>
                <title>Model parameters</title>
                <p id="p0045">In this subsection, we specify the parameters in our model for simulation. The parameter estimation is based on COVID data in the UK. Detailed parameter estimation process refers to <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">Fu et al. (2020)</xref>
</p>
                <p id="p0046">For the simplicity of the epidemiology model, we set the starting population as 1, and all quantities for numbers of people can be regarded as the percentage of the total population at the initial time <inline-formula><mml:math id="M99" altimg="si91.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Furthermore, we set the unit time period as 1 week, which is long enough to avoid delay in recording data, and is frequent enough to show the changes of the epedemic. <xref rid="tbl0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> lists the commonly used parameters and values in our numerical experiments.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0001"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Model parameters.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0003">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top">parameter</th><th align="left" valign="top">value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M100" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M101" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.244887</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M102" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M103" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.0336</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M104" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">0.01759</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M105" altimg="si6.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">0.00233</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M106" altimg="si7.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>π</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">0.38656</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M107" altimg="si8.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">36.9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M108" altimg="si9.svg"><mml:mi>ϕ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top">0.8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M109" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M110" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>36.9</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M111" altimg="si12.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td valign="top"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M112" altimg="si13.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mn>104</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0011">
              <label>4</label>
              <title>Numerical results</title>
              <p id="p0047">In this section, we present the result of our numerical experiments under the parameter setting in <xref rid="sec0010" ref-type="sec">Section 3.2</xref>. By comparing these numerical experiments, we claim the necessity of lockdown when vaccination is available.</p>
              <p id="p0048">For every experiment presented in this section, the initial state is set as <inline-formula><mml:math id="M113" altimg="si92.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.998</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.002</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The epidemic stops when the whole population become recovered. As we set <inline-formula><mml:math id="M114" altimg="si93.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mn>104</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in simulation, it takes around 100 weeks to end the simulation without the lockdown control assuming vaccination is available. All lockdown in this section refer to the optimal lockdown that maximises the utility of the whole population defined in <xref rid="sec0002" ref-type="sec">Section 2</xref>.</p>
              <sec id="sec0012">
                <label>4.1</label>
                <title>Effect of vaccination without lockdown</title>
                <p id="p0049">First, we compare the effect of the vaccine on the development of the pandemic in the absence of lockdown. As shown in <xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>
(a) vaccination significantly reduces the infection between the susceptible and suppresses the growth of the infectious. <xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>(b) also indicates that the number of death is significantly reduced by the vaccine, which speeds up the ending of the epidemic by converting the population of susceptible to the recovered. As more people become recovered, they will not cut back their working hours and consumption, therefore the aggregated consumption increases in <xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>(c).<fig id="fig0001"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Effect of Vaccination on COVID-19 without Lockdown.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0001">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0013">
                <label>4.2</label>
                <title>Effect of optimal lockdown with vaccination</title>
                <p id="p0050">In this section we analyse the effect of optimal lockdown on the tendency of COVID-19 assuming vaccination is available. We apply the solving scheme with parameters in <xref rid="sec0008" ref-type="sec">Section 3</xref> to obtain the optimal lockdown policy as shown in <xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>
(a).<fig id="fig0002"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Effect of Optimal Lockdown on COVID-19 with Vaccination.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0002">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="p0051">It is illustrated in <xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>(b) that by restricting work hours and decreasing consumption, the optimal lockdown policy significantly reduces the risk of interaction between the susceptible and the infectious while slowing down the spread of the disease. For the recovered and infectious, optimal lockdown restricts their working hours and consumption. For the susceptible, if there is no lockdown, the susceptible would cut back their working hours and consumption to reduce their probability of becoming infectious. The optimal lockdown forces the susceptible to reduce even more of their working hours and consumption.</p>
                <p id="p0052">The optimal lockdown policies maximise the utility of the overall population with cost on consumption loss. <xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>(c) presents a clear difference between the aggregated consumption of the lockdown with no lockdown case. It is necessary to lockdown at the start of the epidemic when vaccination is available. The lockdown benefits the susceptible people and slight detriments the infectious and recovered in terms of expected utility (see <xref rid="tbl0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>
). In reality, susceptible people are not likely to be perfectly rational that maximise their utility exactly due to various reasons. For example, people may want to consume more for their mental needs during the isolation in the pandemic. In an extreme case, the susceptible being irrational that consume and work as usual time (see <xref rid="tbl0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), then the optimal lockdown becomes even more necessary in benefiting the utility of the susceptible. As the susceptible people dominate the population at the start, it is reasonable to optimise their utility in the view of policymakers to maximise the utility of the whole population.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0002"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Reduction of Expected Utility of the Susceptible (S), the Infectious (I), and the Recovered (R).</p></caption><alt-text id="at0004">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top">People Category</th><th align="left" valign="top">S</th><th align="left" valign="top">I</th><th align="left" valign="top">R</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top">Rational Susceptible With Lockdown</td><td valign="top">3.8</td><td valign="top">152</td><td valign="top">2.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Rational Susceptible Without Lockdown</td><td valign="top">10.6</td><td valign="top">149.9</td><td valign="top">0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Irrational Susceptible With Lockdown</td><td valign="top">3.8</td><td valign="top">152</td><td valign="top">2.2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Irrational Susceptible Without Lockdown</td><td valign="top">28.1</td><td valign="top">149.9</td><td valign="top">0</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
                <p id="p0053"><xref rid="tbl0003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> shows the lockdown with more severe the initial situation, i.e., the larger the infectious population, the more necessary to impose lockdown. In the extreme case that susceptible people do not cut back their working hours and consumption, the lockdown will become more effective.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0003"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Reduction of Accumulated Utility of the Susceptible (S), the Infectious (I), and the Recovered (R).</p></caption><alt-text id="at0005">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top">Initial Infectious Population</th><th align="left" valign="top">0.002</th><th align="left" valign="top">0.005</th><th align="left" valign="top">0.01</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top">Rational Susceptible</td><td valign="top">3.9</td><td valign="top">5.9</td><td valign="top">7.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Irrational Susceptible</td><td valign="top">8.7</td><td valign="top">17.2</td><td valign="top">25.4</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0014">
                <label>4.3</label>
                <title>Early/Late start of lockdown</title>
                <p id="p0054">We have shown that lockdown is appropriate at the early stage of vaccination. However, in fact, it takes time for policymakers to complete regulations for the lockdown. Here we discuss if it is necessary to lockdown in the middle of the vaccination process. We focus on the impact of the delayed lockdown on the the vaccination process.</p>
                <p id="p0055">As shown in <xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>(b) the earlier the lockdown starts, the more effective it will be. <xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>(c) implies that when optimal lockdown policy starts from week 0 or 20, there is a notable difference on aggregated consumption with the no control case. However the lockdown policy has marginal influence after week 40.</p>
                <p id="p0056">The optimal lockdown level reduces when it starts late as shown in <xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>(a). This might because with a stricter lockdown, the benefit of lockdown on the utility of susceptible will be surpassed by the detriment of the lockdown on the recovered. Also, the stricter lockdown makes the overall utility even worse with the decreasing susceptible and increasing recovered population.</p>
                <p id="p0057">The results in <xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>(c) are useful for the policymakers to access the situation and decide how and when to start or relax the lockdown policy. The working hours and consumption of the susceptible returning to normal is a sign of releasing lockdown as shown in <xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>(c). As the infectious population decreases, the probability of being infected drops. Consequently, susceptible people will become less afraid of being infected, which raises their working hours and consumption back to normality.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0015">
                <label>4.4</label>
                <title>Vaccine value estimation</title>
                <p id="p0058">In this subsection, we apply the vaccine value estimation approach in <xref rid="sec0007" ref-type="sec">Section 2.3</xref> under the parameter setting of our simulation in <xref rid="sec0010" ref-type="sec">Section 3.2</xref>. To get the vaccine value estimation by <xref rid="eq0015" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (15)</xref>, we specify how to estimate <inline-formula><mml:math id="M115" altimg="si84.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M116" altimg="si85.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> in <xref rid="eq0015" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (15)</xref> in our simulation. According to results in <xref rid="sec0012" ref-type="sec">Section 4.1</xref>, at 100th week, the epidemic ends in the case with vaccination, for which <inline-formula><mml:math id="M117" altimg="si84.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is available. However, the epidemic is far from ending in the case without vaccination. We assume the vaccination is available at week 100th that force an ending of the epidemic, the accumulated aggregated utility, in this case is an estimation of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M118" altimg="si85.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>. Then by <xref rid="eq0015" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (15)</xref> we can get the estimation of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M119" altimg="si82.svg"><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                <p id="p0059">Starting with infectious population 0.002, the estimated value of vaccine is 11.5. Our estimation is about at the middle of the available vaccine prices in the market (Table<xref rid="fn0003" ref-type="fn">3</xref>
<xref rid="tbl0004" ref-type="table">4</xref>
).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0004"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Vaccine company and price.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0006">Table 4</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top">Company</th><th align="left" valign="top">Price(<inline-formula><mml:math id="M120" altimg="si14.svg"><mml:mi>£</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top">AstraZeneca</td><td valign="top">2.2-2.9</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Johnson &amp; Johnson</td><td valign="top">7.3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Novavax</td><td valign="top">11.6</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Pfizer</td><td valign="top">15</td></tr><tr><td valign="top">Moderna</td><td valign="top">25</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
                <p id="p0060">Need to mention that the estimation of vaccine value is based on our model, which is an over-simplification of reality, for instance, the model does not include people’s saving behaviour. The estimated vaccine value can be used as a reference for policymakers in the vaccine spending.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0016">
              <label>5</label>
              <title>Conclusion</title>
              <p id="p0061">In this paper, we study the relation between vaccination and lockdown policy and address the question on how to gradually relax the strength for the lockdown when vaccination is available. We extend the canonical epidemiological model SIR to find an optimal decision making with the aim to balance between economy and public health. In the model, people in different health statuses take different decisions on their working hours and consumption to maximise their own utility, while policymakers control the lockdown rate to maximise the overall welfare. This leads to a two phases optimisation problem. The model can also provide an estimation of vaccine value. Our results show that although vaccination can effectively reduce the deaths and infections caused by the COVID-19, lockdown is still necessary at the beginning of the vaccination rollout. The larger the infectious population, the more rigorous the optimal lockdown are required during vaccination. The results provides scientific suggestions for policymakers to make decisions on when to start and release the lockdown policy during the whole vaccination cycle.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0016a">
              <title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title>
              <p id="p0061a"><bold>Yuting Fu:</bold> Data curation, Writing - original draft. <bold>Hanqing Jin:</bold> Supervision, Methodology, Writing - review &amp; editing. <bold>Haitao Xiang:</bold> Conceptualization, Methodology. <bold>Ning Wang:</bold> Supervision, Methodology, Writing - review &amp; editing.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list id="bib001">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="bib0001">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0001">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Acemoglu</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chernozhukov</surname>
                      <given-names>V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Werning</surname>
                      <given-names>I.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Whinston</surname>
                      <given-names>M.D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>Optimal Targeted Lockdowns in a Multi-Group Sir Model</part-title>
                  <source>NBER Working Paper 27102</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0002">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0002">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Acharya</surname>
                      <given-names>V.V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Johnson</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sundaresan</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zheng</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>The Value of a Cure: An Asset Pricing Perspective</part-title>
                  <source>Technical Report</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <publisher-name>National Bureau of Economic Research</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0003">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0003">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aggarwal</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nawn</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dugar</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>What caused global stock market meltdown during the covid pandemic–lockdown stringency or investor panic?</article-title>
                  <source>Finance Res. Lett.</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>101827</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0004">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0004">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Albulescu</surname>
                      <given-names>C.T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>COVID-19 and the united states financial markets’ volatility</article-title>
                  <source>Finance Res. Lett.</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>101699</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0005">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0005">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alvarez</surname>
                      <given-names>F.E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Argente</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lippi</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>A Simple Planning Problem for COVID-19 Lockdown</part-title>
                  <source>Technical Report</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <publisher-name>National Bureau of Economic Research</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0006">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0006">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baig</surname>
                      <given-names>A.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Butt</surname>
                      <given-names>H.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Haroon</surname>
                      <given-names>O.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rizvi</surname>
                      <given-names>S.A.R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Deaths, panic, lockdowns and us equity markets: the case of covid-19 pandemic</article-title>
                  <source>Finance Res. Lett.</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>101701</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0007">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0007">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Çakmaklı</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Demiralp</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kalemli-Őzcan</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yeşiltaş</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yıldırım</surname>
                      <given-names>M.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>The Economic Case for Global Vaccinations: An Epidemiological Model with International Production Networks</part-title>
                  <source>Working Paper 28395</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <publisher-name>National Bureau of Economic Research</publisher-name>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3386/w28395</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <note>
                  <p>
                    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nber.org/papers/w28395" id="intrrf0005">http://www.nber.org/papers/w28395</ext-link>
                  </p>
                </note>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0008">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0008">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eichenbaum</surname>
                      <given-names>M.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rebelo</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Trabandt</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>The Macroeconomics of Epidemics</part-title>
                  <source>Technical Report</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <publisher-name>National Bureau of Economic Research</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0009">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0009">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Forni</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mantovani</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>COVID-19 vaccines: where we stand and challenges ahead</article-title>
                  <source>Cell Death Differ.</source>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>14</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0010">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sbref0010">Fu, Y., Xiang, H., Jin, H., Wang, N., 2020. Optimal lockdown policy for COVID-19: a modelling study. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3776635" id="intrrf0006">https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3776635</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0011">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0011">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Garriga</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Manuelli</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sanghi</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>Optimal Management of an Epidemic: Lockdown, Vaccine and Value of Life</part-title>
                  <source>Technical Report</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0012">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0012">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gong</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jiang</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lu</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Pandemic and bank lending: evidence from the 2009 H1N1 pandemic</article-title>
                  <source>Finance Res. Lett.</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>101627</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0013">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0013">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gonzalez-Eiras</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Niepelt</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>On the Optimal “Lockdown” during an Epidemic</part-title>
                  <source>Technical Report</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <publisher-name>CESifo Working Paper</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0014">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0014">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Harko</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lobo</surname>
                      <given-names>F.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mak</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Exact analytical solutions of the susceptible-infected-recovered (sir) epidemic model and of the sir model with equal death and birth rates</article-title>
                  <source>Appl. Math. Comput.</source>
                  <volume>236</volume>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <fpage>184</fpage>
                  <lpage>194</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0015">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0015">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hethcote</surname>
                      <given-names>H.W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>Three basic epidemiological models</part-title>
                  <source>Applied Mathematical Ecology</source>
                  <year>1989</year>
                  <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
                  <lpage>144</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0016">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0016">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kermack</surname>
                      <given-names>W.O.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McKendrick</surname>
                      <given-names>A.G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A contribution to the mathematical theory of epidemics</article-title>
                  <source>Proc. R. Soc. London Ser.A</source>
                  <volume>115</volume>
                  <issue>772</issue>
                  <year>1927</year>
                  <fpage>700</fpage>
                  <lpage>721</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0017">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0017">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kucharski</surname>
                      <given-names>A.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Russell</surname>
                      <given-names>T.W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Diamond</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Edmunds</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Funk</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eggo</surname>
                      <given-names>R.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sun</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jit</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Munday</surname>
                      <given-names>J.D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Early dynamics of transmission and control of COVID-19: a mathematical modelling study</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet Infect. Dis.</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0018">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0018">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gayle</surname>
                      <given-names>A.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wilder-Smith</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rocklöv</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The reproductive number of COVID-19 is higher compared to sars coronavirus</article-title>
                  <source>J. Travel Med.</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0019">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0019">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Narayan</surname>
                      <given-names>P.K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Phan</surname>
                      <given-names>D.H.B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>COVID-19 lockdowns, stimulus packages, travel bans, and stock returns</article-title>
                  <source>Finance Res. Lett.</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>101732</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0020">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0020">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sułkowski</surname>
                      <given-names>Ł.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>COVID-19 pandemic; recession, virtual revolution leading to de-globalization?</article-title>
                  <source>J. Intercult. Manage.</source>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <lpage>11</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0021">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0021">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>COVID-19 and financial market efficiency: evidence from an entropy-based analysis</article-title>
                  <source>Finance Res. Lett.</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>101888</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0022">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0022">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fu</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shi</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An evaluation of mathematical models for the outbreak of COVID-19</article-title>
                  <source>Precis. Clin. Med.</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0023">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0023">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>J.T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leung</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leung</surname>
                      <given-names>G.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Nowcasting and forecasting the potential domestic and international spread of the 2019-nCoV outbreak originating in Wuhan, China: a modelling study</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet</source>
                  <volume>395</volume>
                  <issue>10225</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>689</fpage>
                  <lpage>697</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32014114</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0024">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0024">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hu</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ji</surname>
                      <given-names>Q.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Financial markets under the global pandemic of COVID-19</article-title>
                  <source>Finance Res. Lett.</source>
                  <volume>36</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>101528</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
            <sec id="sec0017" sec-type="supplementary-material">
              <label>Appendix A</label>
              <title>Supplementary materials</title>
              <p id="p0063">
                <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="ecom0001">
                  <caption>
                    <title>Supplementary Data S1</title>
                    <p>Supplementary Raw Research Data. This is open data under the CC BY license <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" id="intrrf0004">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link></p>
                  </caption>
                  <media xlink:href="mmc1.pdf">
                    <alt-text>Supplementary Data S1</alt-text>
                  </media>
                </supplementary-material>
              </p>
            </sec>
            <ack id="ack0001">
              <title>Acknowledgement</title>
              <p id="para1125">The work is supported by the Oxford NIE Financial Big Data Lab at the University of Oxford. We are grateful to research funding support from the HPCC systems and the VeChain Foundation.</p>
            </ack>
            <fn-group>
              <fn id="fn0001">
                <label>1</label>
                <p id="notep0001">We implicitly assume that the virus does not change people’s rationality and preference.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="fn0002">
                <label>2</label>
                <p id="notep0002">In fact, when we use the numerical scheme proposed in <xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">Eichenbaum et al. (2020)</xref> to our problem, the derivative used in the KKT condition is not correct due to the absence of a complicated term from the term in <xref rid="eq0010" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (10)</xref>. We decide to ignore this absence due to the following two reasons: (1) if we recover this complicated term, the calculation will be extremely complicated; (2) from real data in the COVID-19 pandemic, we know the coefficient in the third term <inline-formula><mml:math id="M121" altimg="si88.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is very close to 0, which is also observed in our numerical results.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="fn0003">
                <label>3</label>
                <p id="notep0003">Data Source: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.bmj.com/content/371/bmj.m4670" id="intrrf0001">https://www.bmj.com/content/371/bmj.m4670</ext-link><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.healthline.com/health-news/how-much-will-it-cost-to-get-a-covid-19-vaccine#How-much-each-dose-will-cost" id="intrrf0002">https://www.healthline.com/health-news/how-much-will-it-cost-to-get-a-covid-19-vaccine</ext-link></p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="sec0018" fn-type="supplementary-material">
                <p id="p0062">Supplementary material associated with this article can be found, in the online version, at doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.frl.2021.102123" id="intrrf0003">10.1016/j.frl.2021.102123</ext-link>.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
