<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-03-11T00:54:11Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8106524" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8106524</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-05-10</datestamp>
        <setSpec>pheelsevier</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Epidemics</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Epidemics</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Epidemics</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">1755-4365</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1878-0067</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>The Authors. Published by Elsevier B.V.</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC8106524</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8106524</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">8106524</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33984687</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pii">S1755-4365(21)00023-2</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.epidem.2021.100465</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100465</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Assessing the nationwide impact of COVID-19 mitigation policies on the transmission rate of SARS-CoV-2 in Brazil</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au000001">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Jorge</surname>
                    <given-names>Daniel C.P.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
                  <xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au000002">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Rodrigues</surname>
                    <given-names>Moreno S.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
                  <xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au000003">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Silva</surname>
                    <given-names>Mateus S.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
                  <xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au000004">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Cardim</surname>
                    <given-names>Luciana L.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au000005">
                  <name>
                    <surname>da Silva</surname>
                    <given-names>Nívea B.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au000006">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Silveira</surname>
                    <given-names>Ismael H.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au000007">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Silva</surname>
                    <given-names>Vivian A.F.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au000008">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Pereira</surname>
                    <given-names>Felipe A.C.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">f</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au000009">
                  <name>
                    <surname>de Azevedo</surname>
                    <given-names>Arthur R.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au000010">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Amad</surname>
                    <given-names>Alan A.S.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">g</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au000011">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Pinho</surname>
                    <given-names>Suani T.R.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au000012">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Andrade</surname>
                    <given-names>Roberto F.S.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au000013">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ramos</surname>
                    <given-names>Pablo I.P.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au000014">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Oliveira</surname>
                    <given-names>Juliane F.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff8" ref-type="aff">h</xref>
                  <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Instituto de Fısica, Universidade Federal da Bahia, Salvador, Bahia, Brazil</aff>
                <aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Fundação Oswaldo Cruz, Porto Velho, Rondônia, Brazil</aff>
                <aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Center for Data and Knowledge Integration for Health (CIDACS), Instituto Gonçalo Moniz, Fundação Oswaldo Cruz, Bahia, Brazil</aff>
                <aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Instituto de Matemática e Estatística, Universidade Federal da Bahia, Salvador, Bahia, Brazil</aff>
                <aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Instituto de Saúde Coletiva, Universidade Federal da Bahia, Salvador, Bahia, Brazil</aff>
                <aff id="aff6"><label>f</label>Instituto de Física, Universidade de São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil</aff>
                <aff id="aff7"><label>g</label>College of Engineering, Swansea University, Swansea, Wales, United Kingdom</aff>
                <aff id="aff8"><label>h</label>Centre of Mathematics of the University of Porto (CMUP), Department of Mathematics, Porto, Portugal</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author at: Center for Data and Knowledge Integration for Health (CIDACS), Instituto Gonçalo Moniz, Fundação Oswaldo Cruz, Bahia, Brazil.</corresp>
                <fn id="fn1">
                  <label>1</label>
                  <p id="d1e968">These authors contributed equally to this work and are listed in alphabetical order..</p>
                </fn>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>8</day>
                <month>5</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.-->
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <month>6</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>8</day>
                <month>5</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>35</volume>
              <fpage>100465</fpage>
              <lpage>100465</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>3</day>
                  <month>7</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>13</day>
                  <month>3</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>30</day>
                  <month>4</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2021 The Authors</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
                <license>
                  <license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="d1e974">
                <p>COVID-19 is now identified in almost all countries in the world, with poorer regions being particularly more disadvantaged to efficiently mitigate the impacts of the pandemic. In the absence of efficient therapeutics or large-scale vaccination, control strategies are currently based on non-pharmaceutical interventions, comprising changes in population behavior and governmental interventions, among which the prohibition of mass gatherings, closure of non-essential establishments, quarantine and movement restrictions. In this work we analyzed the effects of 707 governmental interventions published up to May 22, 2020, and population adherence thereof, on the dynamics of COVID-19 cases across all 27 Brazilian states, with emphasis on state capitals and remaining inland cities. A generalized SEIR (Susceptible, Exposed, Infected and Removed) model with a time-varying transmission rate (TR), that considers transmission by asymptomatic individuals, is presented. We analyze the effect of both the extent of enforced measures across Brazilian states and population movement on the changes in the TR and effective reproduction number. The social mobility reduction index, a measure of population movement, together with the stringency index, adapted to incorporate the degree of restrictions imposed by governmental regulations, were used in conjunction to quantify and compare the effects of varying degrees of policy strictness across Brazilian states. Our results show that population adherence to social distance recommendations plays an important role for the effectiveness of interventions and represents a major challenge to the control of COVID-19 in low- and middle-income countries.</p>
              </abstract>
              <abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="d1e980">
                <title>Graphical abstract</title>
                <fig id="dfig1" position="anchor">
                  <graphic xlink:href="fx1_lrg"/>
                </fig>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group id="d1e989">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>Brazil</kwd>
                <kwd>COVID-19</kwd>
                <kwd>Mathematical modeling</kwd>
                <kwd>Non-pharmaceutical interventions</kwd>
                <kwd>Public policies</kwd>
                <kwd>Transmission rate</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="sec1">
              <label>1</label>
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p id="d1e1030">COVID-19, a disease caused by the SARS-CoV-2 coronavirus, emerged in December 2019 in China and was recognized as a pandemic by the World Health Organization on March 11, 2020 (<xref rid="b58" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization, 2020</xref>). At that moment, Brazil had already confirmed 53 cases. On March 20, with 972 confirmed cases, the Brazilian Ministry of Health recognized community transmission of COVID-19 throughout the national territory, 24 days after the first confirmed case of COVID-19 was identified (<xref rid="b15" ref-type="bibr">da Saúde declara transmissão comunitária nacional, 2020</xref>). Brazil is a country with 209.5 million individuals and stark socioeconomic disparities throughout its territory. It is the largest country in South America and the fifth largest nation in the world. Accordingly, the many challenges imposed by the COVID-19 pandemic are unprecedented in this country.</p>
              <p id="d1e1044">The political-administrative organization of Brazil comprises three spheres of governance: The Union (federal government), the 27 states (including the Federal District, where the capital city, Brasilia, is located) and 5,570 municipalities. To reduce the transmission of SARS-CoV-2, federal, state and city governments implemented a series of interventions by means of government decrees (<xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">Aquino et al., 2020</xref>). This included recommendations to identify and isolate confirmed cases and contacts; to restrict unnecessary movements; to practice social distancing; to increase hygiene awareness; to follow respiratory etiquette; to wear masks in public, among others. In the absence of more intensive mitigation policies implemented by the federal government (such as lock-downs and movement restrictions), most measures were adopted by local governments (state/municipalities) (<xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">Aquino et al., 2020</xref>). However, adherence to these policies varied greatly throughout the country, and while some regions enacted more strict controls, others have been more lax.</p>
              <p id="d1e1058">The COVID-19 crisis has called attention to the importance of mathematical modeling to inform governmental policies and in quantifying the effects of the pandemic at multiple levels (<xref rid="b44" ref-type="bibr">Panovska-Griffiths, 2020</xref>). Models have been adapted to address questions such as the role of asymptomatic individuals to SARS-CoV-2 transmission chains (<xref rid="b35" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2020b</xref>), to assess the effectiveness of testing and quarantine strategies in informing economic reopening (<xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">Berger et al., 2020</xref>) and epidemic suppression by partial lockdown strategies (<xref rid="b49" ref-type="bibr">Roche et al., 2020</xref>), to quantify the needs for hospital beds under various social distancing scenarios (<xref rid="b43" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira et al., 2021</xref>, <xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr">Ferguson et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b41" ref-type="bibr">Moghadas et al., 2020</xref>), among others, eg. <xref rid="b48" ref-type="bibr">Prem et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b33" ref-type="bibr">Leung et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b57" ref-type="bibr">Weitz et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b29" ref-type="bibr">Kissler et al., 2020a</xref>. By drawing on a generalized SEIR model that simulates the dynamics of viral spread in a population entirely susceptible to the new virus, it is possible to define and estimate the transmission rate (TR) at which an infected individual will transmit the disease to a susceptible person (<xref rid="b28" ref-type="bibr">Keeling and Rohani, 2011</xref>). Therefore, the higher this rate, the greater the number of new cases in a region over time. Downward changes on the TR are expected with the implementation of mitigation policies such as non-pharmaceutical interventions (NPI), the only option to limit the spread of SARS-CoV-2 in the absence of effective therapies or vaccination with sufficient population coverage.</p>
              <p id="d1e1096">In this work, we comparatively analyze the evolution of the COVID-19 transmission rate and effective reproduction number across all 27 Brazilian states, with emphasis on state capitals and remaining inland cities, establishing links with measures of governmental restrictions (NPIs) implemented in each region together with the human behavior response, particularly the adherence to recommendations of social distancing. The varying degree of enforced policies across the country offers an opportunity to study the impacts of interventions, including their breadth and timing, on the TR of SARS-CoV-2 throughout Brazilian states. These findings can be extrapolated to similar settings in other low- and middle-income countries to drive improvements in mitigation policies against subsequent waves of SARS-CoV-2 and other potentially pandemic pathogens.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec2">
              <label>2</label>
              <title>Methodology</title>
              <sec id="d1e1103">
                <title>Data sources</title>
                <p id="d1e1106">The number of confirmed cases of COVID-19 for each Brazilian municipality, up to May 22, 2020, was obtained from the Ministry of Health of Brazil and are publicly available (<xref rid="b13" ref-type="bibr">Coronavírus, 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b25" ref-type="bibr">Io, 2020</xref>). Since the capitals of each state have different dynamics and largely concentrated COVID-19 cases in the initial wave of the epidemic (an assumption informed by previous works (<xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">Candido et al.</xref>, <xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">Candido et al., 2020</xref>)), we analyzed the transmission dynamics for each state in the following way: (1) The entire state, (2) the state capital alone; and (3) the remaining state municipalities grouped as a single place by summing up their reported cases. Throughout the text we refer to the latter as inland cities, although strictly not all of these are distant from the shore.</p>
                <p id="d1e1118">To evaluate state-wide enforced governmental measures, we collated government decrees and resolutions scattered throughout various state government gazettes and other official repositories up to May 22, 2020, since each state uses different platforms to communicate their legislation. We annotated the type of measure enforced, the implementation date, the duration and whether it was valid to the whole state or limited to specific regions (see Supplementary Material).</p>
                <p id="d1e1120">In addition to state level decrees we also collated COVID-19-related federal regulations, which affect equally all states (<xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">Bolsonaro, 2020</xref>). However, federal-level regulations did not interfere on measures enforced by state or municipalities, and most of them were later repealed. Indeed, on April 8, 2020 the Brazilian Federal Supreme Court ruled in favor of the decentralization of operations aimed at controlling COVID-19 in the country, empowering the actions of state and municipal governments (<xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">Brazilian Judicial System, 2020</xref>). The evaluation of municipal-level regulations was not performed due to the large number of Brazilian cities, a total of 5,570, each having their own system for publications of legislation, with variable degrees of update frequency and usually providing unstructured data and burdensome access options, which would make their manual processing unpractical. For this reason, in this work we only considered regulations issued by the 27 state governments, which totaled 707 decrees.</p>
                <p id="d1e1132">As a proxy of the population adherence to recommendations of social distancing, we used information from <xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">InLoco (2020)</xref>, a Brazilian technology start-up that developed an index of social mobility, which seeks to help in fight the pandemic in Brazil. Data for the index construction is obtained from the unidentified, aggregated geo-movement patterns extracted from 60 million mobile devices throughout the country. The index ranges from 0 to 100% and measures the proportion of devices from a given municipality that remained within a 450 meter radius from the location identified as home by the device. The higher the index, the greatest the population adherence to social distancing recommendations. The data is available at <xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">InLoco (2020)</xref>. Examples of other works that used the Social mobility reduction index (SMRI) can be found in <xref rid="b46" ref-type="bibr">Peixoto et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">Ajzenman et al., 2020</xref>.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="d1e1146">
                <title>Stringency index</title>
                <p id="d1e1149">To comparatively evaluate the governmental measures implemented by the Brazilian states, we constructed a stringency index, denoted by <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1152" display="inline" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mi>ι</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, similarly to that implemented in <xref rid="b52" ref-type="bibr">Thomas Hale APTP Sam Webster and Kira (2020)</xref>. To score each employed policy we adapted the methodology to the Brazilian context by taking into account the specific measures established by the different state governments and described in the Data Sources section.</p>
                <p id="d1e1160">Measures were classified into two categories: Ordinal and cumulative. Ordinal class of measures, denoted by <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1163" display="inline" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, are those in which there is a clear order on the intensity of the restriction, so that there are less possibilities of reclassification. For instance, a decree prohibiting agglomerations of more than 100 people, followed by a second decree restricting to 500 people, belong to the ordinal category, where the first is more intense than the second. Cumulative class of measures, denoted by <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1168" display="inline" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, are those with no clear order of intensity, allowing for a wide range of possibilities to classify the restriction. For instance, closure of malls and prohibition to accessing parks and beaches have no clear order to which of these measures is more intense and may lead to subjective classification.</p>
                <p id="d1e1172">Every class of measures is a collection of sub-measures depending on how each government decided to response and enforce measures. In this work we have seven classes of measures, of which four are ordered and three are cumulative, further described in Supplementary Table 1. Cancellation of public events (<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1176" display="inline" altimg="si16.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>) presents six sub-measures. Similarly, health etiquette policies (<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1187" display="inline" altimg="si24.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>) has two sub-measures.</p>
                <p id="d1e1196">The evaluation of the ordered class of measures varies from 0 (when no measure is applied) to <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1199" display="inline" altimg="si6.svg"><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> (when the most stringent sub-measure is applied), where the index <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1204" display="inline" altimg="si6.svg"><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> varies from 0 to <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1209" display="inline" altimg="si8.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, the number of sub-measures of the ordinal class of measures <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1225" display="inline" altimg="si9.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> (we similarly denote <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1235" display="inline" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, as the number of sub-measures for the cumulative class). For the cumulative class of measures, we evaluate each sub-measure as 0 if the sub-measure was not applied or 1 otherwise, so that the value of the class will be the sum of points of the sub-measures <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1250" display="inline" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>. Additionally, to take into account whether the measure was enforced for the whole state or limited to a particular region, each class has a target <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1265" display="inline" altimg="si12.svg"><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. If the measure is ordinal, then we consider <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1271" display="inline" altimg="si13.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, taking either the value 0, if the most stringent sub-measure is applied for specific areas of the state, or 1, if it is enforced for the whole state. If the measure is cumulative, and since it will be a sum of the sub-measures, then <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1291" display="inline" altimg="si14.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the sum of targets for each sub-measure <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1311" display="inline" altimg="si15.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, which again is either 0 if the sub-measure is applied to specific areas or 1 if it is applied to the whole state without exceptions. A summary of the seven measures, as well as their number of sub-measures and targets are presented in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p>
                <p id="d1e1334">
The index for the ordinal classes is given by <disp-formula id="d1e1341"><mml:math id="d1e1344" display="block" altimg="si30.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ι</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>Thus, the value of the stringency <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1402" display="inline" altimg="si31.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ι</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is the value of the most stringent measured applied, <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1418" display="inline" altimg="si6.svg"><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, normalized by the number of sub-classes, <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1423" display="inline" altimg="si8.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, multiplied by the term <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1438" display="inline" altimg="si34.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, which is 1 when the target is for the whole state or 2 otherwise (that is, the stringency <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1462" display="inline" altimg="si31.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ι</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is divided by two).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Classification of governmental responses to COVID-19 in Brazil (state-wide).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Measure adopted</th><th align="left">Type</th><th align="left">Class of measures</th><th align="left">Targeting index</th><th align="left">Number of sub-classes N</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Cancellation of public events</td><td align="left">Ordinal</td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e149" display="inline" altimg="si16.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e159" display="inline" altimg="si17.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Closure of schools/universities</td><td align="left">Ordinal</td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e181" display="inline" altimg="si18.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e191" display="inline" altimg="si19.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Home-office for governmental employees</td><td align="left">Ordinal</td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e213" display="inline" altimg="si20.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e223" display="inline" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Isolation</td><td align="left">Ordinal</td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e245" display="inline" altimg="si22.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e255" display="inline" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Closure of non-essential businesses and public activities</td><td align="left">Cumulative</td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e277" display="inline" altimg="si24.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e287" display="inline" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Transport lock</td><td align="left">Cumulative</td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e309" display="inline" altimg="si26.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e319" display="inline" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Health etiquette policies</td><td align="left">Cumulative</td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e341" display="inline" altimg="si28.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e351" display="inline" altimg="si29.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">2</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
                <p id="d1e1476">For the cumulative classes the index is defined by <disp-formula id="d1e1481"><mml:math id="d1e1484" display="block" altimg="si36.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ι</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where the sum <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1579" display="inline" altimg="si15.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> reflects the measures that were applied to the whole state, and the term <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1599" display="inline" altimg="si38.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>∕</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> evaluates the measures that were not applied for the whole state. Lastly, the whole expression is normalized by the number of sub-classes <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1644" display="inline" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                <p id="d1e1658">Therefore, the total state index <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1661" display="inline" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mi>ι</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, for a given day, will be taken as the average of the value of the classes <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1666" display="inline" altimg="si31.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ι</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1681" display="inline" altimg="si42.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ι</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, yielding <disp-formula id="d1e1699"><mml:math id="d1e1702" display="block" altimg="si43.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ι</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">×</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ι</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ι</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>Examples of these estimates are given in Supplementary Note 1.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="d1e1774">
                <title>The mathematical model</title>
                <p id="d1e1777">We generalize the usual SEIR model by separating the infectious compartment into two: Asymptomatic/non-detected and symptomatic cases, denoted by <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1780" display="inline" altimg="si44.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1790" display="inline" altimg="si56.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, respectively, following our previous modeling strategy (<xref rid="b43" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira et al., 2021</xref>). It is reasonable to consider that the compartment <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1806" display="inline" altimg="si44.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> encompasses many of the sub-notified cases since the majority of asymptomatic and mild cases are not accounted for in the official data, in spite of their important role to the SARS-CoV-2 transmission chain <xref rid="b35" ref-type="bibr">Li et al. (2020b)</xref>. The system of differential equations reads: <disp-formula-group id="d1e1823"><disp-formula id="fd1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="d1e1827" display="block" altimg="si47.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac id="mmlalignd1e1867"><mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="fd2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="d1e1893" display="block" altimg="si48.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac id="mmlalignd1e1933"><mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="fd3"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="d1e1965" display="block" altimg="si49.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow id="mmlalignd1e2010"><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="fd4"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="d1e2020" display="block" altimg="si50.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi id="mmlalignd1e2065">p</mml:mi><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="fd5"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="d1e2066" display="block" altimg="si51.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub id="mmlalignd1e2106"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></disp-formula-group> The epidemiological parameters presented in Eqs. <xref rid="fd1" ref-type="disp-formula">(1)</xref>–<xref rid="fd5" ref-type="disp-formula">(5)</xref> are described in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, along with their estimates (or search ranges, when fitted), which were informed by previous works.</p>
                <p id="d1e2126">
As described in <xref rid="b43" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira et al. (2021)</xref>, the parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2135" display="inline" altimg="si54.svg"><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, a factor associated with the infectivity of asymptomatic/non-detected infections, plays an important role on the viral transmission dynamics. As described by Eq. <xref rid="fd1" ref-type="disp-formula">(1)</xref>, it influences the non-linear term, and thus cannot be neglected from the system, unless it is assumed that the infectivity of asymptomatic individuals is equivalent to that of symptomatic cases, i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2146" display="inline" altimg="si61.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. However, several studies suggest <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2156" display="inline" altimg="si62.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref rid="b35" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2020b</xref>, <xref rid="b30" ref-type="bibr">Kissler et al., 2020b</xref>, <xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">Cheng et al., 2020</xref>), which guided our modeling choice that defined the search interval for this parameter (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Key epidemiological parameters used in the SEIR model, with their respective value (when fixed) or the search intervals used for parameter estimations, informed by the literature.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Parameter</th><th align="left">Description</th><th align="left">Search interval</th><th align="left">Fixed</th><th align="left">Reference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e394" display="inline" altimg="si52.svg"><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">Transmission rate</td><td align="left">[0,2]</td><td align="left">–</td><td align="left">(<xref rid="b35" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2020b</xref>, <xref rid="b36" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">Chowell et al., 2004</xref>, <xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">Dehning et al., 2020</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e412" display="inline" altimg="si53.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">Time of when transmission rate change</td><td align="left">Defined in the Result section</td><td align="left">–</td><td align="left">(<xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">Chowell et al., 2004</xref>, <xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">Dehning et al., 2020</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e435" display="inline" altimg="si54.svg"><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">Asymptomatic infectivity</td><td align="left">[0,0.7]</td><td align="left">–</td><td align="left">(<xref rid="b35" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2020b</xref>, <xref rid="b30" ref-type="bibr">Kissler et al., 2020b</xref>, <xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr">Ferretti et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr">Ferguson et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b40" ref-type="bibr">Mizumoto et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">Cheng et al., 2020</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e453" display="inline" altimg="si55.svg"><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">Proportion of latent (E) that proceed to <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e459" display="inline" altimg="si56.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">–</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">(<xref rid="b35" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2020b</xref>, <xref rid="b40" ref-type="bibr">Mizumoto et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b42" ref-type="bibr">Nishiura et al., 2020</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e480" display="inline" altimg="si57.svg"><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">Mean exposed period, or incubation time</td><td align="left">–</td><td align="left">1/4</td><td align="left">(<xref rid="b35" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2020b</xref>, <xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr">Ferretti et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b51" ref-type="bibr">Sanche et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b34" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2020a</xref>, <xref rid="b37" ref-type="bibr">Linton et al., 2020</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e498" display="inline" altimg="si58.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">Mean asymptomatic period</td><td align="left">–</td><td align="left">1/3.5</td><td align="left">(<xref rid="b35" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2020b</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e521" display="inline" altimg="si59.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="left">Mean symptomatic period</td><td align="left">–</td><td align="left">1/4</td><td align="left">(<xref rid="b35" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2020b</xref>, <xref rid="b36" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b31" ref-type="bibr">Kissler et al., 2020c</xref>)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
                <p id="d1e2176">Additionally, to account for variations in the TR over time, we assume that the TR <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2179" display="inline" altimg="si52.svg"><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is a function given by: <disp-formula id="fd6"><label>(6)</label><mml:math id="d1e2190" display="block" altimg="si64.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="script">H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2327" display="inline" altimg="si65.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> represent a set of points in time defining the change on the TR, <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2365" display="inline" altimg="si66.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> are TRs in the interval [<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2375" display="inline" altimg="si67.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>], and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2399" display="inline" altimg="si68.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> if <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2416" display="inline" altimg="si69.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2427" display="inline" altimg="si70.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> if <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2444" display="inline" altimg="si71.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2454" display="inline" altimg="si72.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">H</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>∕</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> if <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2475" display="inline" altimg="si73.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                <p id="d1e2484">The key novelty here is that the influence of governmental measures on social mobility and human behavior can dictate changes on the TR (<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2488" display="inline" altimg="si66.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>’s) on inferred points <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2498" display="inline" altimg="si53.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>’s. To do so, we assume that the <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2508" display="inline" altimg="si53.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>’s change in an interval search based on variations in stringency and social mobility, described previously. Additionally, to evaluate if one or more changes to the transmission rate was required, we assessed the value obtained using the Bayesian information criterion (BIC) as well as by visual evaluation of the fitted results. The visual evaluation is important since the calculation of the BIC may yield small variations when the number of parameters is increased due to the inherent noise in the data.</p>
                <p id="d1e2517">The time of changing transmission rate and the rate itself, as well as the <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2520" display="inline" altimg="si54.svg"><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> parameter are estimated using the Particle Swarm Optimization (PSO) metaheuristic. Under the PSO framework, we used maximum likelihood estimation to optimize the model to the series of daily confirmed cases for each state, capital cities and remaining inland cities up to May 22, 2020. PSO was implemented using pyswarms library version 1.1.0 for Python 3 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://python.org" id="interref2">http://python.org</ext-link>) (<xref rid="b39" ref-type="bibr">Miranda, 2018</xref>), and was executed with 150 particles through 500 iterations with cognitive parameter 0.1, social parameter 0.3, inertia parameter 0.9, evaluating five closest neighbors through Euclidean (or L2) distance metric. In addition to the point estimates obtained by the PSO method, percentile confidence intervals were also estimated for these parameters. The intervals were constructed using the weighted non-parametric bootstrap method, considering 100 replicates of the original series of new cases. Similar work to evaluate the impact of non-pharmaceutical measures on the TR and dynamic spread of the disease are presented in <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">Chowell et al., 2004</xref>, <xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">Dehning et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b19" ref-type="bibr">Flaxman et al., 2020</xref>. The parameters <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2541" display="inline" altimg="si78.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>κ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em" class="nbsp"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em" class="nbsp"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> were informed by the literature and kept fixed. The remaining estimated model parameters and search intervals were informed both by the literature and the analyses presented in this work, and are presented in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="d1e2574">
                <title>Basic and effective reproduction number</title>
                <p id="d1e2577">Based on the obtained parameter values we also evaluated the basic reproductive number <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2580" display="inline" altimg="si79.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and the effective reproductive number <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2590" display="inline" altimg="si80.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, also denoted by <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2603" display="inline" altimg="si123.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, as described in <xref rid="b43" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira et al. (2021)</xref>. The basic reproductive number <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2618" display="inline" altimg="si79.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> characterizes the disease spread during the very early time interval after it has been introduced, thus it is evaluated on the first transmission rate estimated by the model. Its expression is given by (see <xref rid="b43" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira et al., 2021</xref>, <xref rid="b56" ref-type="bibr">Wallinga and Lipsitch, 2007</xref>, <xref rid="b55" ref-type="bibr">Van den Driessche and Watmough, 2002</xref>): <disp-formula id="fd7"><label>(7)</label><mml:math id="d1e2638" display="block" altimg="si83.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
                <p id="d1e2702">We also obtain the time series of the effective reproductive number <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2705" display="inline" altimg="si80.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, which indicate the current trend of the epidemic. Details of this calculation can be found in Supplementary Note 5 of our previous work (<xref rid="b43" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira et al., 2021</xref>). By writing the infection-age structured epidemic model of our system of Eqs. <xref rid="fd1" ref-type="disp-formula">(1)</xref> to <xref rid="fd5" ref-type="disp-formula">(5)</xref> (<xref rid="b56" ref-type="bibr">Wallinga and Lipsitch, 2007</xref>, <xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr">Fraser, 2007</xref>), we obtain: <disp-formula-group id="fd8"><label>(8)</label><disp-formula id="d1e2742"><mml:math id="d1e2743" display="block" class="split" altimg="si86.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.16667em" id="mmlalignd1e2770"/><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></disp-formula-group>Eq. <xref rid="fd8" ref-type="disp-formula">(8)</xref> would be similar to the general form given by <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2864" display="inline" altimg="si87.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> only for a portion of the evaluated period, since we consider changes on time in the transmission rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2895" display="inline" altimg="si52.svg"><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and the <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2900" display="inline" altimg="si79.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> expression only takes into account the transmission rate before the first change, that is, for <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2911" display="inline" altimg="si90.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                <p id="d1e2925">Additionally, Eq. <xref rid="fd8" ref-type="disp-formula">(8)</xref> can be also given by: <disp-formula id="fd9"><label>(9)</label><mml:math id="d1e2938" display="block" altimg="si91.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">∫</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>∞</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where the numerator <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3003" display="inline" altimg="si92.svg"><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> represents daily number of new cases and the denominator corresponds to the convolution on <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3009" display="inline" altimg="si92.svg"><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3014" display="inline" altimg="si94.svg"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, that is the disease probability distribution function for the time interval between the infection of an individual and its secondary cases. The function <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3019" display="inline" altimg="si94.svg"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is derived from the differential equations of the model and receives contributions from the three compartments <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3024" display="inline" altimg="si96.svg"><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3030" display="inline" altimg="si44.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3040" display="inline" altimg="si56.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> that impact the evaluation of <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3050" display="inline" altimg="si79.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3060" display="inline" altimg="si80.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, as presented in <xref rid="b43" ref-type="bibr">Oliveira et al. (2021)</xref>. The advantage of Eq. <xref rid="fd9" ref-type="disp-formula">(9)</xref> is that it allow us to evaluate the effective reproduction number directly on the available data and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3083" display="inline" altimg="si94.svg"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, a probability distribution function that can take different shapes and makes our result more flexible to compare directly with the data, being <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3088" display="inline" altimg="si54.svg"><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> the only estimated necessary parameter used to feed equation <xref rid="fd9" ref-type="disp-formula">(9)</xref>.</p>
                <p id="d1e3097">Finally, since the data are reported as daily case counts, to calculate expression <xref rid="fd9" ref-type="disp-formula">(9)</xref>, we discretize the generation time distribution <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3104" display="inline" altimg="si94.svg"><mml:mi>g</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, such that <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3109" display="inline" altimg="si104.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, see <xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr">Fraser (2007)</xref>. Thus, <disp-formula id="fd10"><label>(10)</label><mml:math id="d1e3154" display="block" altimg="si105.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="d1e3225">
                <title>Visualization app</title>
                <p id="d1e3228">To facilitate visualizing the results of the analysis performed in this work, a web-based application was developed using R/Shiny (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://shiny.rstudio.com" id="interref3">http://shiny.rstudio.com</ext-link>). The application can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://modelingtaskforce.shinyapps.io/transmission_rate_app/" id="interref4">https://modelingtaskforce.shinyapps.io/transmission_rate_app/</ext-link>.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec3">
              <label>3</label>
              <title>Results</title>
              <sec id="d1e3241">
                <title>The entry of SARS-CoV-2 in the Brazilian states</title>
                <p id="d1e3244">Brazil had a total of 334,555 registered COVID-19 cases up to May 22, 2020. The first confirmed case of COVID-19 in Brazil occurred in the state of São Paulo, southeastern region, on February 26, 2020. Within an interval of seven to 12 days (from March 4 to March 9) the states<xref rid="fn2" ref-type="fn">2</xref>
10]Two-letter state abbreviations are as follows: AC, Acre; AL, Alagoas; AP, Amapá; AM, Amazonas; BA, Bahia; CE, Ceará; DF, Distrito Federal; ES, Espírito Santo; GO, Goiás; MA, Maranhão; MT, Mato Grosso; MS, Mato Grosso do Sul; MG, Minas Gerais; PA, Pará; PB, Paraíba; PR, Paraná; PE, Pernambuco; PI, Piauí; RJ, Rio de Janeiro; RN, Rio Grande do Norte; RS, Rio Grande do Sul; RO, Rondônia; RR, Roraima; SC, Santa Catarina; SP, São Paulo; SE, Sergipe; TO, Tocantins. of ES, DF, BA, AL, RJ and MG had confirmed cases of COVID-19. From March 10 to March 25 the disease spread to the remaining 20 Brazilian states (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>A).</p>
                <p id="d1e3260">By the moment that state authorities were unable to relate confirmed cases through chains of transmission, SARS-CoV-2 community transmission began to be declared in each region (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>A; Supplementary Table 2). Supplementary Figure 1 shows the temporal variation from the first reported case to the declaration of community transmission in the state. As depicted in Supplementary Figure 1, 40.7% (11/27) of the states took between 0 and 10 days to declare community transmission, 51.9% (14/27) took between 11 and 30 days, while only two states (Tocantins and Roraima), corresponding to 7.5%, took more than 30 days to declare community transmission. This scenario is further complicated by the delays in reporting cases. Although each state declared community transmission at some point, there are uncertainties around these dates due to delays in both the registration of cases and the communication from the local level (municipality) to state authorities, as exemplified in the states of Paraná and Roraima (<xref rid="b6" ref-type="bibr">Bittar, 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">Araújo, 2020</xref>).</p>
                <p id="d1e3272">
In the supplemental web-page (see Data availability section), we present the incidence of COVID-19 for each state, capitals and inland cities. As shown, in the early stage of the pandemic in Brazil, the North region was the most affected, accounting for the highest incidence, followed by CE and MA in the Northeastern region. Once the entry of the virus was confirmed within each state, the capitals were the most affected cities initially (<xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">Candido et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">Candido et al.</xref>), emerging as the epicenter of the epidemic in each state (see Supplementary Figures 2 and 3). Subsequently, SARS-CoV-2 disseminated throughout the inland cities with a different speed, as shown in the top panel plots of Supplementary Figures 2 and 3, where the incidence of COVID-19 is reported for the Brazilian states, capitals and inland cities.<fig id="fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>(A) A timeline of events associated with the spread of SARS-CoV-2 across the 27 Brazilian states. The dates of first registered cases are shown (red dots), followed by the moment that community transmission was declared in each state (blue dots). The dates when the TR were observed to change (<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e28" display="inline" altimg="si106.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and, when applicable, <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e48" display="inline" altimg="si107.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, are shown as triangles). The orange segments indicate the interval between the initial NPIs enforced by states and the first observed peak in stringency. Dates refer to the year 2020. (B) Estimates of <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e68" display="inline" altimg="si108.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> (and corresponding 95% confidence intervals) for each state, their capitals and remaining inland cities. Data for the Federal District (DF), the smallest Brazilian federal unit and the only one that has no municipalities, is only shown at the state-level.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="d1e3281">
                <title>Governmental measures and population adherence</title>
                <p id="d1e3284">Next, we evaluated the timing of governmental interventions on the number of cases, the breadth of these interventions as measured by the stringency index, and their effects on influencing people’s behavior, particularly adhesion to social distancing recommendations.</p>
                <p id="d1e3286">A total of 707 regulations published by the 27 Brazilian state governments were annotated according to the methods described to construct the stringency index. The first measures enforcement of the state governments were implemented between March 11 and March 24, with exception of MT that present a larger time window interval, as shown in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>A and Supplementary Table 2. The states of TO, RR, PI, PA, MT, AP, RO, MA, PB and AC adopted measures even before the first registered case. In contrast, some regions which were first affected by COVID-19 were among those that delayed the implementation of measures to contain viral spread. For instance, São Paulo adopted measures only 2 weeks after the confirmation of the first case, on March 13, the same day of community transmission declaration in the state. A similar scenario occurred in Rio de Janeiro, where the first restriction measures were only implemented in parallel to the declaration of community transmission.</p>
                <p id="d1e3292">Among the measures classified in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, strict quarantine measures (<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3300" display="inline" altimg="si22.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>O</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>), restrictions on public transportation (<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3311" display="inline" altimg="si28.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>) and mandatory use of mask (<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3323" display="inline" altimg="si28.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>) were the most weakly implemented measures enforced by the states. Such measures contributed to an average level of 14% in stringency in the studied period, and were adopted only partially in AP, BA, CE, MA and MT. Only an average of 16.9% of public transportation measures were applied in states. In the collected decrees, SP, DF and MS did not enact restrictions on public transport and PA, PB, PI, RN, GO and ES had a very low average of 4% in such measures. On the other hand, the mandatory use of masks contributed, in average, to 33% of the index, with only one state (MS) failing to enact such measures (Supplementary Table 3).</p>
                <p id="d1e3332">To assess the dynamics of implementation, continuance and lifting of NPIs by Brazilian states, <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref> shows the variation of the stringency index over time for each region relative to the number of confirmed COVID-19 deaths per 100,000 inhabitants. All states increased stringency after an incidence of 10 cases per 100k inhabitants. In addition, the states of AP, AM, RR, CE and PE displayed the highest stringency index in the last period evaluated. Of note, those states were close to reaching full occupancy of their health care systems, with more than 75% of ICU occupation (<xref rid="b45" ref-type="bibr">Paulo, 2020</xref>). These results evidenced that heightening the level of measures only when the number of cases and hospitalizations is already mounting represents a flawed strategy unable to avert the impacts of a surge of COVID-19 in healthcare demands.</p>
                <p id="d1e3343">
Variable adherence to social isolation recommendations was seen across the states, with values of the SMRI close to 30% at the beginning of March, followed by a peak to around 60% at the end of that month. This was observed in both state capitals and inland cities. The evolution of the stringency index for each state, as well as the SMRI for capitals and inland cities is presented in the lower panel plots of Supplementary Figure 2 an 3, as well as in the supplementary web-page. Used in conjunction, both measures offer a quantitative evaluation of the degree of policies enforced by Brazilian state governments, as well as their effectiveness in reducing the circulation of people, which lead to decreased contacts. Our results showed that, once the SMRI reached its maximum, it was followed by a decreasing trend even with the maintenance of measures by state governments.<fig id="fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Evolution of the governmental measures adopted for each Brazilian state with respect to COVID-19 death incidence. The figure shows the variation of the stringency index over time for each state relative to the number of confirmed death per 100,000 inhabitants The number of confirmed deaths per 100,000 population is shown in logarithmic scale on the <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e86" display="inline" altimg="si112.svg"><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>-axis.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="d1e3347">With respect to the breadth and intervention period of governmental measures, our results led to the identification of three stringency index patterns: (1) Increase-and-decrease (ID), where the stringency index increases initially, but is followed by the lifting of measures leading to its reduction (such as Santa Catarina in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>a); (2) Increase-and-steady (IS), where stringency measures reach a peak that remains constant over time (depicted by São Paulo in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>b); (3) Increase-and-increase (II), where the stringency index increases successively, probably a mechanism to cope with the accelerated growth of the epidemic in some regions (illustrated by Amapá in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>c). Seven states, all located in the North (AC, AP and AM) and Northeast (BA, CE, PE and PI), followed the II pattern, while seven states, distributed throughout the Midwest (GO, MT), South (RS, SC), Southeast (ES) and North (RO, TO) regions conform to the ID pattern (Supplementary Figure 2 and 3). The remaining 13 states (AL, DF, MA, MG, MS, PA, PB, PR, RJ, RN, RR, SE and SP), distributed in all regions, followed the IS pattern. In addition, our results indicated that the reduction of the SMRI was smaller in states that followed both IS and II patterns (median reduction of −7.55% and −5.88%, respectively), compared to states that relaxed their measures according to the ID pattern (median reduction of −9.03%) (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>d).</p>
                <p id="d1e3367">
Of note, even states that promoted relaxation of policies, such as those that followed an ID pattern, maintained an average SMRI in the last week of May corresponding to 40.1 ± 2.0%, a value higher than that corresponding to the pre-pandemic SMRI in the first week of February, corresponding to a value of 28.7 ± 1.4%.<fig id="fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Illustrative examples of a general pattern observed for the behavior of stringency measures over time in Brazil. Upper panels show COVID-19 incidence and bottom panels exhibit the social mobility reduction and the stringency indexes over time for (a) Santa Catarina (increase-and-decrease, ID), (b) São Paulo (increase-and-steady, IS) and (c) Amapá (increase-and-increase, II). The social mobility index is considered separately for capitals, inland cities and the whole state. Plots for the remaining Brazilian states are shown in Supplementary Figure 2 and 3. The average reduction in the SMRI according to the stringency pattern for all states is shown in panel d. For each category, the median is shown as a solid horizontal bar.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3_lrg"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="d1e3371">
                <title>Varying transmission rates of SARS-CoV-2 in Brazil</title>
                <p id="d1e3374">Lastly, we sought to comparatively evaluate the effects of governmental measures and population adherence to social distancing recommendations in the TR of SARS-CoV-2 throughout Brazilian states.</p>
                <p id="d1e3376">As shown earlier, states reported initial cases of COVID-19 and announced community transmission at different moments. Then, all regions reached a peak of measures implemented and corresponding SMRI on March, 2020. By evaluating these metrics in all of the 81 regions analyzed (state, capitals, inland cities), we defined the search interval for a possible first change in the transmission rate from March 13, to May 15, to include the date of the first measure enforced and the last announcement of community transmission (see <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>a). When more than one change in the TR took place, we defined the search interval to the last month of the studied period, i.e. from April 22 to May 22, 2020. More than two points of time changes were not considered in the time interval of study.</p>
                <p id="d1e3382">In Supplementary Table 4, we detail the number of days elapsed from the date of first implemented measure to the estimated date of TR change, and the variation from the first to the second (<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3386" display="inline" altimg="si113.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3396" display="inline" altimg="si114.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>) TR obtained by the SEIR model. Our results show that 26% of the states (BA, RN, DF, MG, RJ, RS and SC) presented a noticeable change in the TR up to 15 days after the implementation of the first NPI, 40.7% between 16 and 30 days, 14.8% (PA, PB, PE, PI) between 31 and 45 days and the remaining 18.5% (AC, RO, RR, AL and MS) of the states had a TR change only more than 46 days since the first implemented measure. Estimate TR changes occurred first in capitals, followed by inland cities (Supplementary Table 4).</p>
                <p id="d1e3405">The dynamic behavior post intervention can be classified into DDD, DDI, DID, IDI and III, corresponding to decrease or increase in TR in the state as a whole, capital and inland, respectively. Around 62% of the states presented a DDD behavior, that is a decrease on the TR in the state, capital and inland cities. These states had an average TR decrease higher in the capitals (−49.67%) compared to the inland cities (−40.43%). The states of AP, RO, AL and RS (14.8%) displayed a DDI pattern, with an increase in cases observed for inland cities in May, 2020. On the other hand, the states of PI and SC showed an increase of the TR in capitals and an observed decrease in both state-level and inland cities (DID pattern). AC was the only state with an IDI pattern, while the remaining states (TO, SE and MS) presented with an III pattern. However, TO and SE later resembled a DDD pattern with a second change in TR. Furthermore, all states with an increase in TR in any of its regions (state, capital or inland cities) had either an ID or IS for the stringency index (as noted in the previous subsection).</p>
                <p id="d1e3407">In <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>B we show values for the basic reproduction number for each region. The lowest values of <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3414" display="inline" altimg="si79.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> were for the regions that presented an increased TR, as showed before. For instance, TO and SE presented values of <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3424" display="inline" altimg="si116.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. This indicates the lower transmission in the early stage of the disease spread in these states. The state of MS, that also had and III pattern, and the inland cities of SC all had the following lowest values of <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3440" display="inline" altimg="si79.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> (less than 1.5). The inland cities of AC, AL, RO and RS showed values between 1.5 and 2. The remaining states that presented with a DDD pattern for the TR had <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3450" display="inline" altimg="si118.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Additionally, we can see that states that implemented the measures before the first reported case usually experienced delayed changes in the TR (after 8 April) compared to the remaining states and, with exception of AP, these states were the ones with an average lower value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3465" display="inline" altimg="si79.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> as well.</p>
                <p id="d1e3474">To conclude, changes in the TR also impacted on the effective reproduction number causing an average reduction of −56.44% in capitals and of −46.43% in inland cities, after the first TR change In <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> we show this impact for each state, their capitals and inland cities. Although a decrease in the average <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3481" display="inline" altimg="si123.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> after the first TR reduction was observed in most of the states, in none of the regions the values of <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3491" display="inline" altimg="si123.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> fell below one. Moreover, after the first TR change, the average level of <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3502" display="inline" altimg="si123.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> was equal to 1.86 in the inland cities compared to 1.53 in capitals.</p>
                <p id="d1e3511">
More details regarding the fitting of the data to the SEIR model produced in this work can be found in the supplementary web-page, for both capitals and inland cities of each state, as well as the entire state (Supplementary Figure 4). We highlight, in each plot, as vertical dashed red lines, the dates of transition from <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3516" display="inline" altimg="si113.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3526" display="inline" altimg="si114.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> (and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3536" display="inline" altimg="si114.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3547" display="inline" altimg="si127.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, when applicable) (Supplementary Figure 4B). The blue dashed and full lines represent the evolution of the epidemic with a fixed transmission rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3557" display="inline" altimg="si113.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and with both <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3567" display="inline" altimg="si113.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3577" display="inline" altimg="si114.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> (where <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3588" display="inline" altimg="si127.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is included when suitable), respectively (Supplementary Figure 4B). The effective reproductive number is also presented for each state, capitals and inland cities (Supplementary Figure 4C). The black line represents the <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3598" display="inline" altimg="si123.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> calculated with reported number of new cases; the blue dashed line represents the <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3608" display="inline" altimg="si123.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> calculated with the new number of simulated cases obtained from the model. The variation of the TR highlights the variations of the trends of the effective reproductive number. Also shown are the estimates for stringency for each region and state (Supplementary Figure 4D), the moments of changes in <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3618" display="inline" altimg="si52.svg"><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> (Supplementary Figure 4D) and the goodness-of-fit (Supplementary Figure 4F), along with tables describing all these results (Supplementary Figure 4G). Finally, post assessment for all fit performances are available to evaluate reliability of the forecasts for a 15 day-period beyond May 22.<fig id="fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Impact of measures and popular adherence on the effective reproduction number in each Brazilian state. The plot depicts the decrease of the average of <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e107" display="inline" altimg="si123.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> before and after the first TR change.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr4_lrg"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec4">
              <label>4</label>
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p id="d1e3627">In this work we evaluated the effects of non-pharmaceutical interventions and social mobility reduction patterns on the spread dynamics of SARS-CoV-2 throughout the 27 Brazilian states, by employing an underlying SEIR model to estimate the transmission rate of SARS-CoV-2. Our results show that the measures adopted, combined with the population adherence to restrict circulation (and therefore decrease contacts), contributed to the lowering of the TR in almost all states, an effect that was perceived in both capitals and inland cities. However, in spite of the continued maintenance of governmental restrictions in most regions, population adherence to isolation recommendations gradually decreased over time, even with the expansion of cases throughout the country. This was reflected in the <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3630" display="inline" altimg="si80.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> values, which we observed to have decreased in all states, but still insufficiently to consider SARS-CoV-2 transmission controlled in the country, as it remained above 1 for all Brazilian states, capital and inland cities in the studied period. Thus, public cooperation constitutes a particularly important challenge for tackling COVID-19 in low- and middle-income countries.</p>
              <p id="d1e3642">The analysis performed on the sub-measures implemented reveal that the Brazilian states lacked to endure measures restricting transportation (or did so in a very lax manner), strict lock-downs (as adopted by other countries), and even the mandatory use of masks at some places, the latter a low cost measure that plays an important rule to reduce the spread of the disease. Such restrictive policies have shown to significantly decrease the number of cases, deaths, and viral transmission in other countries (<xref rid="b53" ref-type="bibr">Tobías, 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b2" ref-type="bibr">Alfano and Ercolano, 2020</xref>). On the other hand, the economical costs imposed by harsher interventions is even more burdensome to developing countries, where large economical segments rely on consumption and services, usually involving physical contact, such as informal workers, tourism, service and retail businesses.</p>
              <p id="d1e3649">Once the entry of the virus was confirmed within each state, the capitals were the most affected initially, as shown by others as well (<xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">Candido et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">Candido et al.</xref>). Then, viral spread continued at different rates, with most of inland cities presenting an average effective reproduction number higher than the capital after the first TR change. This is a concerning trend considering the large inequalities in the access to health services as well as their distribution in Brazil (<xref rid="b54" ref-type="bibr">Travassos et al., 2006</xref>, <xref rid="b22" ref-type="bibr">Garcia-Subirats et al., 2014</xref>), which tend to concentrate near state capitals. We also observed that downward changes on TRs occurred first in the capitals, followed by the remaining cities. This effect can also be due to the flux between cities, which was not accounted in our modeling approach. Accordingly, the TR observed in capitals should also affect that of inland cities, as suggested by a meta-population compartmental model (<xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr">Costa et al., 2020</xref>), but the possibility of further waves of COVID-19 in these smaller cities, particularly with the lifting of measures, should not be ruled out. These results highlight the major role of state capitals as seeding spots, followed by the entry of cases towards smaller, inland cities. Capitals also tend to centralize international airports, ports, population density and industries (<xref rid="b26" ref-type="bibr">Jesus et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b59" ref-type="bibr">Xavier et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">Candido et al.</xref>, <xref rid="b20" ref-type="bibr">Forster et al., 2020</xref>).</p>
              <p id="d1e3672">We identified common trends in the stringency index that allowed the disclosure of three patterns, with the majority of states conforming to an increase-and-steady pattern, in which the set of governmental policies adopted remained unaltered over time. States that enforced and maintained mitigation measures were likely to observe a less pronounced relaxation of stay-at-home advises by their population, as measured by the SMRI. These results suggest the intimate relationship between the magnitude of governmental measures and the population adherence to such measures, particularly since higher values of stringency implicate in decreased opportunities of public activities. However, individuals throughout all states, in both capitals and inland cities, still reduced their adherence to social isolation in the course of time. The politicization of COVID-19 in Brazil (<xref rid="b32" ref-type="bibr">Lancet, 2020</xref>) could have had an impact on people’s behavior and compliance with sanitary recommendations, particularly when individuals downplay the health risks imposed by SARS-CoV-2, as has been suggested for other countries (<xref rid="b50" ref-type="bibr">Rothgerber et al., 2020</xref>).</p>
              <p id="d1e3684">We also observed that even in states that conformed to an increase-and-decrease stringency index pattern, at least a part of the population still maintained adherence to isolation. More studies are warranted to evaluate if this trend associates with specific age-groups, such as the elderly, employment status, such as individuals that have the possibility to continue working from home, education level or perception of risks around COVID-19.</p>
              <p id="d1e3686">The present study confirmed the findings about early implementation of interventions to mitigate the disease spread (<xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">Dehning et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b19" ref-type="bibr">Flaxman et al., 2020</xref>). In fact, the states that anticipated the enforcement of restriction measures were the ones with lower value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3694" display="inline" altimg="si79.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, representing a more controlled situation if compared to the other states. Nevertheless, with few exceptions, most of these states were classified as having an ID or IS pattern of mobility, and therefore the efforts were not sufficient to bring the transmission rate to control levels, as assessed by the <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3704" display="inline" altimg="si123.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> series. However, even with late TR change detection in these states, overall delays must be noticed. In fact, in the scenario of an unfolding epidemic, the delay in notification systems impacts the perception of the usefulness of implemented measures. Our results reveal the magnitude of this perception, where only 26% of the states showed a change on the TR with a maximum delay of 15 days for the perception of the first peak of enforced policies, with the remaining states having a significantly larger delay. These results call attention to this problem and highlight the importance of improving the surveillance system to better evaluate the impact of implemented measures and optimize their strictness specially in countries with very low resource levels.</p>
              <p id="d1e3713">Our work has some limitations. First, in order to estimate TRs (and changes thereof) we relied upon a generalized form of the SEIR model which explicitly considers asymptomatic/non-detected infections. Thus, albeit the estimates of model parameters (or their respective search intervals) were informed by the literature for other countries, they could be different from the reality of the ongoing epidemic in Brazil. However, while the true extent of SARS-CoV-2 transmission by asymptomatic/non-detected and pre-symptomatic individuals is still debated, current reports conclude that it is an important route of transmission (<xref rid="b35" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2020b</xref>, <xref rid="b23" ref-type="bibr">He et al., 2020</xref>, <xref rid="b42" ref-type="bibr">Nishiura et al., 2020</xref>). It is important to note that levels of COVID-19 detection may vary over time due to the differing testing capacity of each region, a data that to our knowledge is currently unavailable for the country. Our model reflects this phenomenon by the parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3721" display="inline" altimg="si55.svg"><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. However, the availability of data about the number of tests performed over time is a limitation. Also, there are noticeable notification delays that also present with different magnitudes throughout the regions in Brazil. In fact, Brazil has a total of 5,570 municipalities, this generates heterogeneities on the reporting date of the case notification. A systematic analysis to infer the reporting delay would require availability of data to at least measure a mean report delay interval, as others have done (<xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">Dehning et al., 2020</xref>). Additionally, this delay may change over time due to improvement or deterioration in the healthcare system. These are key points that should be included to overcome this type of bias and correctly estimate its uncertainties. This limitation may impact on the perception of the implemented measures as well as compromise the planning of new ones. However, our work further motivates the importance of an improved notification system for Brazil and other countries, which will contribute to better mitigate the current and future pandemics.</p>
              <p id="d1e3730">We used mobility data from mobile phones as proxies of social isolation as measured by the SMRI. In particular, the sample space of devices monitored using this technology cannot be considered a representative population sample, as state/cities with superior economic status will probably exhibit increased technology adoption by their populations, leading to better accuracy of the mobility patterns in these regions. This is in contrast to rural areas, for instance, where mobile phone usage is limited (<xref rid="b38" ref-type="bibr">Malaquias and Silva, 2020</xref>). However, considering the general widespread use of mobile phones in the country (with estimates that 60% of adults report owning a smartphone (<xref rid="b47" ref-type="bibr">Pew Research Center, 2019</xref>)), the general trends observed in our work should not be drastically altered by more accurate measurements of social mobility reduction. Lastly, the evaluation of all measures enforced is not trivial, and in our work we have only included the use of mask as health etiquette policies, with other NPIs such as sanitary cleaning of public and private places, the obligatory availability of 70% alcohol in stores, as well as economic measures such as emergency payments for the self-employed, reduction of taxes and others were not evaluated. Still, proper evaluation of these categories should be assessed.</p>
              <p id="d1e3742">In sum, our results point to the importance of timely deployment of interventions in curbing the first-wave of the COVID-19 epidemic in Brazil. Yet, population adherence represents a crucial factor for the success of this effort and represents a major challenge in low- and middle-income countries.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="d1e3744">
              <title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title>
              <p id="d1e3747"><bold>Daniel C.P. Jorge:</bold> Data curation, Formal analysis, Methodology, Software, Validation, Writing - review and editing. <bold>Moreno S. Rodrigues:</bold> Data curation, Formal analysis, Methodology, Software, Validation, Visualization, Writing - review and editing. <bold>Mateus S. Silva:</bold> Data curation, Formal analysis, Methodology, Software, Validation, Visualization, Writing - review and editing. <bold>Luciana L. Cardim:</bold> Conceptualization, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Validation, Writing - original draft, Writing - review and editing. <bold>Nívea B. da Silva:</bold> Conceptualization, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Validation, Writing - review and editing. <bold>Ismael H. Silveira:</bold> Formal analysis. <bold>Vivian A.F. Silva:</bold> Data curation, Formal analysis, Methodology, Validation, Writing - review and editing. <bold>Felipe A.C. Pereira:</bold> Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Software, Validation, Writing - review and editing. <bold>Arthur R. de Azevedo:</bold> Data curation, Formal analysis, Software, Validation, Visualization, Writing - review and editing. <bold>Alan A.S. Amad:</bold> Formal analysis, Methodology, Software, Validation, Writing - review and editing. <bold>Suani T.R. Pinho:</bold> Formal analysis, Methodology, Project administration, Validation, Writing - original draft, Writing - review and editing. <bold>Roberto F.S. Andrade:</bold> Formal analysis, Methodology, Project administration, Validation, Writing - review and editing. <bold>Pablo I.P. Ramos:</bold> Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Project administration, Validation, Visualization, Writing - original draft, Writing - review and editing. <bold>Juliane F. Oliveira:</bold> Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Project administration, Software, Validation, Visualization, Supervision, Writing - original draft, Writing - review and editing.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="COI-statement">
              <title>Declaration of Competing Interest</title>
              <p id="d1e3795">The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list id="bib1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="b1">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb1">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ajzenman</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cavalcanti</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Da Mata</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>More than words: Leaders’ speech and risky behavior during a pandemic</chapter-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b2">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb2">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Alfano</surname>
                      <given-names>V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ercolano</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The efficacy of lockdown against COVID-19: A cross-country panel analysis</article-title>
                  <source>Appl. Health Econ. Health Policy</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31432455</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b3">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aquino</surname>
                      <given-names>E.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Silveira</surname>
                      <given-names>I.H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pescarini</surname>
                      <given-names>J.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Aquino</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Souza-Filho</surname>
                      <given-names>J.A.d.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Social distancing measures to control the COVID-19 pandemic: potential impacts and challenges in Brazil</article-title>
                  <source>Ciência Saúde Coletiva</source>
                  <volume>25</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>2423</fpage>
                  <lpage>2446</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32520287</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b4">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb4">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Araújo</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Roraima tem transmissão comunitária de coronavírus, diz secretária-adjunta de Saúde</chapter-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <comment>
                    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://g1.globo.com/rr/roraima/noticia/2020/05/02/roraima-tem-transmissao-comunitaria-de-coronavirus-diz-secretaria-adjunta-de-saude.ghtml" id="interref6">https://g1.globo.com/rr/roraima/noticia/2020/05/02/roraima-tem-transmissao-comunitaria-de-coronavirus-diz-secretaria-adjunta-de-saude.ghtml</ext-link>
                  </comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b5">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb5">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Berger</surname>
                      <given-names>D.W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Herkenhoff</surname>
                      <given-names>K.F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huang</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mongey</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Testing and reopening in an SEIR model</article-title>
                  <source>Rev. Econ. Dyn.</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b6">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb6">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bittar</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Paraná já registra casos de transmissão comunitária do novo coronavírus</chapter-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <comment>
                    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cbncuritiba.com/parana-ja-registra-casos-de-transmissao-comunitaria-do-novo-coronavirus/" id="interref7">https://cbncuritiba.com/parana-ja-registra-casos-de-transmissao-comunitaria-do-novo-coronavirus/</ext-link>
                  </comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b7">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb7">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bolsonaro</surname>
                      <given-names>J.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Federal level decrees to overcome COVID-19 pandemic</chapter-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <comment>
                    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.planalto.gov.br/ccivil_03/_ato2019-2022/2020/decreto/d10282.htm" id="interref8">https://www.planalto.gov.br/ccivil_03/_ato2019-2022/2020/decreto/d10282.htm</ext-link>
                  </comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b8">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb8">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>Brazilian Judicial System</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <comment>
                    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.stf.jus.br/arquivo/cms/noticiaNoticiaStf/anexo/ADPF672liminar.pdf" id="interref9">http://www.stf.jus.br/arquivo/cms/noticiaNoticiaStf/anexo/ADPF672liminar.pdf</ext-link>
                  </comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b9">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sb9">Candido, D.S., Claro, I.M., de Jesus, J.G., Souza, W.M., Moreira, F.R.R., Dellicou, S., et al., Evolution and epidemic spread of SARS-CoV-2 in Brazil, Science, 369, pp. 1255–1260.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b10">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb10">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Candido</surname>
                      <given-names>D.D.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Watts</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abade</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kraemer</surname>
                      <given-names>M.U.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pybus</surname>
                      <given-names>O.G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Croda</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>de Oliveira</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Khan</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sabino</surname>
                      <given-names>E.C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Faria</surname>
                      <given-names>N.R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Routes for COVID-19 importation in Brazil</article-title>
                  <source>J. Travel Med.</source>
                  <volume>27</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>taaa042</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32211799</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b11">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb11">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cheng</surname>
                      <given-names>H.-Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jian</surname>
                      <given-names>S.-W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>D.-P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ng</surname>
                      <given-names>T.-C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Huang</surname>
                      <given-names>W.-T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lin</surname>
                      <given-names>H.-H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Contact tracing assessment of COVID-19 transmission dynamics in Taiwan and risk at different exposure periods before and after symptom onset</article-title>
                  <source>JAMA Int. Med.</source>
                  <volume>180</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1156</fpage>
                  <lpage>1163</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b12">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb12">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chowell</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hengartner</surname>
                      <given-names>N.W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Castillo-Chavez</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fenimore</surname>
                      <given-names>P.W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hyman</surname>
                      <given-names>J.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The basic reproductive number of ebola and the effects of public health measures: the cases of congo and uganda</article-title>
                  <source>J. Theoret. Biol.</source>
                  <volume>229</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <fpage>119</fpage>
                  <lpage>126</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15178190</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b13">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb13">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Coronavírus</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Dataset of cases of COVID-19 in Brazil</chapter-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <comment>
                    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://covid.saude.gov.br/" id="interref10">https://covid.saude.gov.br/</ext-link>
                  </comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b14">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb14">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Costa</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cota</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ferreira</surname>
                      <given-names>S.C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Outbreak diversity in epidemic waves propagating through distinct geographical scales</article-title>
                  <source>Phys. Rev. Res.</source>
                  <volume>2</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">043306</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b15">
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sb15">da Saúde declara transmissão comunitária nacional, M., <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.saude.gov.br/noticias/agencia-saude/46568-ministerio-da-saude-declara-transmissao-comunitaria-nacional" id="interref11">https://www.saude.gov.br/noticias/agencia-saude/46568-ministerio-da-saude-declara-transmissao-comunitaria-nacional</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b16">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb16">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dehning</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zierenberg</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Spitzner</surname>
                      <given-names>F.P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wibral</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Neto</surname>
                      <given-names>J.P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wilczek</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Priesemann</surname>
                      <given-names>V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Inferring change points in the spread of COVID-19 reveals the effectiveness of interventions</article-title>
                  <source>Science</source>
                  <volume>369</volume>
                  <issue>6500</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b17">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb17">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ferguson</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Laydon</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nedjati Gilani</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Imai</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ainslie</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Baguelin</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bhatia</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Boonyasiri</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cucunuba Perez</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cuomo-Dannenburg</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Impact of non-pharmaceutical interventions (NPIs) to reduce COVID19 mortality and healthcare demand</chapter-title>
                  <source>Imperial College, London</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b18">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb18">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ferretti</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wymant</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kendall</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhao</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nurtay</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Abeler-Dörner</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Parker</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bonsall</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fraser</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Quantifying SARS-CoV-2 transmission suggests epidemic control with digital contact tracing</article-title>
                  <source>Science</source>
                  <volume>368</volume>
                  <issue>6491</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b19">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb19">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Flaxman</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mishra</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gandy</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Unwin</surname>
                      <given-names>H.J.T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mellan</surname>
                      <given-names>T.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Coupland</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Whittaker</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhu</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Berah</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eaton</surname>
                      <given-names>J.W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Estimating the effects of non-pharmaceutical interventions on COVID-19 in europe</article-title>
                  <source>Nature</source>
                  <volume>584</volume>
                  <issue>7820</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
                  <lpage>261</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32512579</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b20">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb20">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Forster</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Forster</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Renfrew</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Forster</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Phylogenetic network analysis of SARS-CoV-2 genomes</article-title>
                  <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.</source>
                  <volume>117</volume>
                  <issue>17</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>9241</fpage>
                  <lpage>9243</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32269081</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b21">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb21">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fraser</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Estimating individual and household reproduction numbers in an emerging epidemic</article-title>
                  <source>PLoS One</source>
                  <volume>2</volume>
                  <issue>8</issue>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e758</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b22">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb22">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Garcia-Subirats</surname>
                      <given-names>I.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vargas</surname>
                      <given-names>I.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mogollón-Pérez</surname>
                      <given-names>A.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>De Paepe</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Da Silva</surname>
                      <given-names>M.R.F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Unger</surname>
                      <given-names>J.P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Borrell</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vázquez</surname>
                      <given-names>M.L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Inequities in access to health care in different health systems: a study in municipalities of central Colombia and north-eastern Brazil</article-title>
                  <source>Int. J. Equity Health</source>
                  <volume>13</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <fpage>10</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24479581</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b23">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb23">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>He</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lau</surname>
                      <given-names>E.H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Deng</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hao</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lau</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wong</surname>
                      <given-names>J.Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Guan</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tan</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Temporal dynamics in viral shedding and transmissibility of COVID-19</article-title>
                  <source>Nat. Med.</source>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>672</fpage>
                  <lpage>675</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32296168</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b24">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb24">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>InLoco</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <comment>
                    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://mapabrasileirodacovid.inloco.com.br/pt/" id="interref12">https://mapabrasileirodacovid.inloco.com.br/pt/</ext-link>
                  </comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b25">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb25">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Io</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Dataset of cases of COVID-19 in Brazil</chapter-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <comment>
                    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://brasil.io/datasets/" id="interref13">https://brasil.io/datasets/</ext-link>
                  </comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b26">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb26">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jesus</surname>
                      <given-names>J.G.d.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sacchi</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Candido</surname>
                      <given-names>D.d.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Claro</surname>
                      <given-names>I.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sales</surname>
                      <given-names>F.C.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Manuli</surname>
                      <given-names>E.R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Silva</surname>
                      <given-names>D.B.B.d.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Paiva</surname>
                      <given-names>T.M.d.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pinho</surname>
                      <given-names>M.A.B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Santos</surname>
                      <given-names>K.C.d.O.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Importation and Early Local Transmission of COVID-19 in Brazil, 2020</chapter-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <publisher-name>Revista do Instituto de Medicina Tropical de São Paulo</publisher-name>
                  <publisher-loc>SciELO Brasil</publisher-loc>
                  <fpage>62</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b27">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb27">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jorge</surname>
                      <given-names>D.C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rodrigues</surname>
                      <given-names>M.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Silva</surname>
                      <given-names>M.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cardim</surname>
                      <given-names>L.L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>da Silva</surname>
                      <given-names>N.B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Silveira</surname>
                      <given-names>I.H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Assessing the nationwide impact of COVID-19 mitigation policies on the transmission rate of SARS-CoV-2 in Brazil</chapter-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <comment>
                    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/Julian-sun/Assessing-the-nationwide-impact-of-COVID-19-mitigation-policies-on-the-transmission-rate-of-SARS-CoV.git" id="interref14">https://github.com/Julian-sun/Assessing-the-nationwide-impact-of-COVID-19-mitigation-policies-on-the-transmission-rate-of-SARS-CoV.git</ext-link>
                  </comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b28">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb28">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Keeling</surname>
                      <given-names>M.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rohani</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Modeling Infectious Diseases in Humans and Animals</chapter-title>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b29">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb29">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kissler</surname>
                      <given-names>S.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tedijanto</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goldstein</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Grad</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lipsitch</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Projecting the transmission dynamics of SARS-CoV-2 through the postpandemic period</article-title>
                  <source>Science</source>
                  <volume>3</volume>
                  <issue>21</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>433</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abb5793</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b30">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb30">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kissler</surname>
                      <given-names>S.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tedijanto</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goldstein</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Grad</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lipsitch</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Projecting the transmission dynamics of SARS-CoV-2 through the postpandemic period</article-title>
                  <source>Science</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b31">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb31">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kissler</surname>
                      <given-names>S.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tedijanto</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goldstein</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Grad</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lipsitch</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Projecting the transmission dynamics of SARS-CoV-2 through the postpandemic period</article-title>
                  <source>Science</source>
                  <volume>368</volume>
                  <issue>6493</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>860</fpage>
                  <lpage>868</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32291278</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b32">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb32">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lancet</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>COVID-19 in Brazil:“so what?”</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet (London, England)</source>
                  <volume>395</volume>
                  <issue>10235</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1461</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b33">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb33">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leung</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>J.T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leung</surname>
                      <given-names>G.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>First-wave COVID-19 transmissibility and severity in China outside hubei after control measures, and second-wave scenario planning: a modelling impact assessment</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b34">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb34">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>Q.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Guan</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhou</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tong</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ren</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leung</surname>
                      <given-names>K.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lau</surname>
                      <given-names>E.H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wong</surname>
                      <given-names>J.Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Early transmission dynamics in Wuhan, China, of novel coronavirus–infected pneumonia</article-title>
                  <source>New Engl. J. Med.</source>
                  <volume>382</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1199</fpage>
                  <lpage>1207</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31995857</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b35">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb35">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pei</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Song</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shaman</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Substantial undocumented infection facilitates the rapid dissemination of novel coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2)</article-title>
                  <source>Science</source>
                  <volume>368</volume>
                  <issue>6490</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>489</fpage>
                  <lpage>493</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32179701</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b36">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb36">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lin</surname>
                      <given-names>Q.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhao</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gao</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lou</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Musa</surname>
                      <given-names>S.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>M.H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cai</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>A conceptual model for the coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) outbreak in Wuhan, China with individual reaction and governmental action</article-title>
                  <source>Int. J. Infect. Dis.</source>
                  <volume>93</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>211</fpage>
                  <lpage>216</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32145465</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b37">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb37">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Linton</surname>
                      <given-names>N.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kobayashi</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hayashi</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Akhmetzhanov</surname>
                      <given-names>A.R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jung</surname>
                      <given-names>S.-m.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yuan</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kinoshita</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nishiura</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Incubation period and other epidemiological characteristics of 2019 novel coronavirus infections with right truncation: a statistical analysis of publicly available case data</article-title>
                  <source>J. Clin. Med.</source>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>538</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b38">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb38">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Malaquias</surname>
                      <given-names>R.F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Silva</surname>
                      <given-names>A.F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Understanding the use of mobile banking in rural areas of Brazil</article-title>
                  <source>Technol. Soc.</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">101260</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b39">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb39">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Miranda</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Pyswarms: a research toolkit for particle swarm optimization in python</article-title>
                  <source>J. Open Source Softw.</source>
                  <volume>3</volume>
                  <issue>21</issue>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <fpage>433</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b40">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb40">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mizumoto</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kagaya</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zarebski</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chowell</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Estimating the asymptomatic proportion of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) cases on board the Diamond Princess cruise ship, Yokohama, Japan, 2020</article-title>
                  <source>Eurosurveillance</source>
                  <volume>25</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2000180</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b41">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb41">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Moghadas</surname>
                      <given-names>S.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Shoukat</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fitzpatrick</surname>
                      <given-names>M.C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wells</surname>
                      <given-names>C.R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sah</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pandey</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sachs</surname>
                      <given-names>J.D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Meyers</surname>
                      <given-names>L.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Singer</surname>
                      <given-names>B.H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Projecting hospital utilization during the COVID-19 outbreaks in the United States</article-title>
                  <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.</source>
                  <volume>117</volume>
                  <issue>16</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>9122</fpage>
                  <lpage>9126</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32245814</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b42">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb42">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nishiura</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kobayashi</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Miyama</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Suzuki</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jung</surname>
                      <given-names>S.-m.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hayashi</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kinoshita</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yuan</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Akhmetzhanov</surname>
                      <given-names>A.R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Estimation of the asymptomatic ratio of novel coronavirus infections (COVID-19)</article-title>
                  <source>Int. J. Infect. Dis.</source>
                  <volume>94</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>154</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32179137</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b43">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb43">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Oliveira</surname>
                      <given-names>J.F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jorge</surname>
                      <given-names>D.C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Veiga</surname>
                      <given-names>R.V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rodrigues</surname>
                      <given-names>M.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Torquato</surname>
                      <given-names>M.F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>da Silva</surname>
                      <given-names>N.B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fiaconne</surname>
                      <given-names>R.L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Castro</surname>
                      <given-names>C.P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Paiva</surname>
                      <given-names>A.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cardim</surname>
                      <given-names>L.L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluating the burden of COVID-19 on hospital resources in bahia, Brazil: A modelling-based analysis of 14.8 million individuals</article-title>
                  <source>Nature Commun.</source>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <fpage>333</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33436608</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b44">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb44">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Panovska-Griffiths</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Can mathematical modelling solve the current Covid-19 crisis?</article-title>
                  <source>BMC Public Health</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b45">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb45">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Paulo</surname>
                      <given-names>F.D.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Maioria dos estados já tem mais de 70% de ocupação de UTI para Covid-19</chapter-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <comment>
                    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www1.folha.uol.com.br/cotidiano/2020/05/maioria-dos-estados-ja-tem-mais-de-70-de-ocupacao-de-uti-para-covid-19.shtml" id="interref15">https://www1.folha.uol.com.br/cotidiano/2020/05/maioria-dos-estados-ja-tem-mais-de-70-de-ocupacao-de-uti-para-covid-19.shtml</ext-link>
                  </comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b46">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb46">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Peixoto</surname>
                      <given-names>P.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Marcondes</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Peixoto</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Oliva</surname>
                      <given-names>S.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Modeling future spread of infections via mobile geolocation data and population dynamics. An application to COVID-19 in Brazil</article-title>
                  <source>PLoS One</source>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0235732</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b47">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb47">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>Pew Research Center</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Smartphone ownership is growing rapidly around the world, but not always equally</chapter-title>
                  <year>2019</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b48">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb48">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Prem</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Russell</surname>
                      <given-names>T.W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kucharski</surname>
                      <given-names>A.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Eggo</surname>
                      <given-names>R.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davies</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Flasche</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Clifford</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pearson</surname>
                      <given-names>C.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Munday</surname>
                      <given-names>J.D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The effect of control strategies to reduce social mixing on outcomes of the COVID-19 epidemic in Wuhan, China: a modelling study</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet Public Health</source>
                  <volume>5</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>e261</fpage>
                  <lpage>e270</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32220655</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b49">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb49">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Roche</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Garchitorena</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Roiz</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The impact of lockdown strategies targeting age groups on the burden of COVID-19 in France</article-title>
                  <source>Epidemics</source>
                  <volume>33</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100424</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b50">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb50">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rothgerber</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wilson</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Whaley</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rosenfeld</surname>
                      <given-names>D.L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Humphrey</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Moore</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bihl</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Politicizing the Covid-19 pandemic: Ideological differences in adherence to social distancing</chapter-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b51">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb51">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sanche</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lin</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xu</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Romero-Severson</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hengartner</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ke</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>High contagiousness and rapid spread of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2</article-title>
                  <source>Emerg. Infect. Diseases</source>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b52">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb52">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Thomas Hale APTP Sam Webster</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kira</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Oxford COVID-19 government response tracker</chapter-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b53">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb53">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tobías</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Evaluation of the lockdowns for the SARS-CoV-2 epidemic in Italy and Spain after one month follow up</article-title>
                  <source>Sci. Total Environ.</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">138539</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b54">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb54">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Travassos</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Oliveira</surname>
                      <given-names>E.X.G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Viacava</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Desigualdades geográficas e sociais no acesso aos serviços de saúde no Brasil: 1998 e 2003</article-title>
                  <source>Ciência Saúde Coletiva</source>
                  <volume>11</volume>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <fpage>975</fpage>
                  <lpage>986</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b55">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb55">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Van den Driessche</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Watmough</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Reproduction numbers and sub-threshold endemic equilibria for compartmental models of disease transmission</article-title>
                  <source>Math. Biosci.</source>
                  <volume>180</volume>
                  <issue>1–2</issue>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <lpage>48</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12387915</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b56">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb56">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wallinga</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lipsitch</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>How generation intervals shape the relationship between growth rates and reproductive numbers</article-title>
                  <source>Proc. R. Soc. B</source>
                  <volume>274</volume>
                  <issue>1609</issue>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <fpage>599</fpage>
                  <lpage>604</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b57">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb57">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Weitz</surname>
                      <given-names>J.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Beckett</surname>
                      <given-names>S.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Coenen</surname>
                      <given-names>A.R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Demory</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dominguez-Mirazo</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dushoff</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leung</surname>
                      <given-names>C.-Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Măgălie</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Park</surname>
                      <given-names>S.W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Modeling shield immunity to reduce COVID-19 epidemic spread</article-title>
                  <source>Nat. Med.</source>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>849</fpage>
                  <lpage>854</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32382154</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b58">
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb58">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>World Health Organization</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>WHO director-general’s opening remarks at the media briefing on COVID-19-11 march 2020</chapter-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b59">
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb59">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xavier</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Giovanetti</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Adelino</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fonseca</surname>
                      <given-names>V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Costa</surname>
                      <given-names>A.V.B.d.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ribeiro</surname>
                      <given-names>A.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Felicio</surname>
                      <given-names>K.N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The ongoing COVID-19 epidemic in minas gerais, Brazil: insights from epidemiological data and SARS-CoV-2 whole genome sequencing</article-title>
                  <source>Emerg. Microbes Infect.</source>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1824</fpage>
                  <lpage>1834</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32726185</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
            <sec id="appSB" sec-type="supplementary-material">
              <label>Appendix A</label>
              <title>Supplementary data</title>
              <p id="d1e3844">The following is the Supplementary material related to this article. <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1"><caption><title>MMC S1</title><p>Data and code used to produce the results presented herein.</p></caption><media xlink:href="mmc1.pdf"/></supplementary-material>
</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="data-availability">
              <title>Data availability</title>
              <p id="d1e1013">Codes used to produce the results presented herein and related datasets are available as supplementary material and in a public GitHub repository (<xref rid="b27" ref-type="bibr">Jorge et al., 2020</xref>). Case series data, stringency and SMRI series, model fits and details of estimates can be found in the on-line web page app at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://modelingtaskforce.shinyapps.io/transmission_rate_app/" id="interref1">https://modelingtaskforce.shinyapps.io/transmission_rate_app/</ext-link>.</p>
            </sec>
            <ack id="d1e3797">
              <title>Acknowledgments</title>
              <p id="d1e3800">This study was financed in part by the <funding-source id="GS1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100006740</institution-id><institution>Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior – Brazil</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> (CAPES) – Finance Code 001. STRP was supported by an International Cooperation grant (process number INT0002/2016) from <funding-source id="GS2"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100006181</institution-id><institution>Bahia Research Foundation (FAPESB), Brazil</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>. STRP and RFSA were supported by the National Institute of Science and Technology - Complex Systems from <funding-source id="GS3"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100003593</institution-id><institution>CNPq, Brazil</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>. JFO was supported by the <funding-source id="GS4">Center of Data and Knowledge Integration for Health</funding-source> (CIDACS) through the Zika Platform - a long-term surveillance platform for Zika virus and microcephaly (Unified Health System (SUS), Brazilian Ministry of Health). DCJ acknowledges a Scientific Initiation scholarship from <funding-source id="GS5"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100003593</institution-id><institution>CNPq, Brazil</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> (process number 117568/2019-8).MSS acknowledges a Scientific Initiation scholarship from <funding-source id="GS6"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100003593</institution-id><institution>CNPq, Brazil</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>
(process number 116731/2019-2). The authors acknowledge the helpful suggestions from members of the CoVida Network, in special to contributors to the Rede CoVida Modelling Task-force: Aureliano S. S. Paiva, Caio P. Castro, Gabriela L. Borges, Gervásio F. Santos, José G. B. Castro, José G. V. Miranda, Maira L. Souza, Maria Yury Ichihara, Matheus F. Torquato, Maurício L. Barreto, Raphael S. do Rosário, Rafael V. Veiga and Rosemeire L. Fiaconne. We acknowledge the InLoco team, namely José Luciano Melo, Raíza Oliveira, Afonso Delgado, Abel Borges, André De’Carli, Hector Pinheiro, Lucas Rufino, Gabriel Teotonio and Luiza Botelho for providing raw files of the Social mobility reduction data used here. We also acknowledge the open data initiative of Brasil.io.</p>
              <sec id="d1e3823">
                <title>Ethics statement</title>
                <p id="d1e3826">This study was conducted with publicly available data from the COVID-19 epidemic, published by the Ministry of Health of Brazil or third parties. Therefore, no approval by an ethics committee was required, according to Resolutions 466/2012 and 510/2016 (article 1, sections III and V) from the National Health Council (CNS), Brazil.</p>
              </sec>
            </ack>
            <fn-group>
              <fn id="fn2">
                <label>2</label>
                <p id="d1e3252">[.</p>
              </fn>
              <fn id="appSA" fn-type="supplementary-material">
                <label>Appendix A</label>
                <p id="d1e3834">Supplementary material related to this article can be found online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.epidem.2021.100465" id="interref5">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.epidem.2021.100465</ext-link>.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
