<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-03-11T00:47:44Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8564626" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8564626</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-11-03</datestamp>
        <setSpec>rsos</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">R Soc Open Sci</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">R Soc Open Sci</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">RSOS</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">royopensci</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Royal Society Open Science</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2054-5703</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>The Royal Society</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC8564626</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8564626</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">8564626</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34737874</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsos.210787</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">rsos210787</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="discipline-codes">
                  <compound-subject>
                    <compound-subject-part content-type="code">1008</compound-subject-part>
                  </compound-subject>
                  <compound-subject>
                    <compound-subject-part content-type="code">1003</compound-subject-part>
                  </compound-subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="subject-codes">
                  <compound-subject>
                    <compound-subject-part content-type="code">119</compound-subject-part>
                  </compound-subject>
                  <compound-subject>
                    <compound-subject-part content-type="code">50</compound-subject-part>
                  </compound-subject>
                  <compound-subject>
                    <compound-subject-part content-type="code">44</compound-subject-part>
                  </compound-subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Mathematics</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="type-of-publication">
                  <subject>Research Articles</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>A hybrid PDE–ABM model for viral dynamics with application to SARS-CoV-2 and influenza</article-title>
                <alt-title alt-title-type="short">A hybrid PDE–ABM model for viral dynamics with application to SARS-CoV-2 and influenza</alt-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9435-017X</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Marzban</surname>
                    <given-names>Sadegh</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="af1" ref-type="aff"/>
                  <email>sadegh.marzban@math.u-szeged.hu</email>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5899-9943</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Han</surname>
                    <given-names>Renji</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="af1" ref-type="aff"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6560-7581</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Juhász</surname>
                    <given-names>Nóra</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="af1" ref-type="aff"/>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9476-3284</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Röst</surname>
                    <given-names>Gergely</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="af1" ref-type="aff"/>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="af1">
                  <addr-line>Bolyai Institute, <institution>University of Szeged</institution>, Szeged 6720, <country>Hungary</country></addr-line>
                </aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="pub">
                <day>3</day>
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2021</year>
                <string-date>November 3, 2021</string-date>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="collection">
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>8</volume>
              <issue>11</issue>
              <elocation-id>210787</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>14</day>
                  <month>5</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <string-date>May 14, 2021</string-date>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>11</day>
                  <month>10</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                  <string-date>October 11, 2021</string-date>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2021 The Authors.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p>Published by the Royal Society under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="rsos.210787.pdf"/>
              <abstract>
                <p>We propose a hybrid partial differential equation–agent-based (PDE–ABM) model to describe the spatio-temporal viral dynamics in a cell population. The virus concentration is considered as a continuous variable and virus movement is modelled by diffusion, while changes in the states of cells (i.e. healthy, infected, dead) are represented by a stochastic ABM. The two subsystems are intertwined: the probability of an agent getting infected in the ABM depends on the local viral concentration, and the source term of viral production in the PDE is determined by the cells that are infected. We develop a computational tool that allows us to study the hybrid system and the generated spatial patterns in detail. We systematically compare the outputs with a classical ODE system of viral dynamics, and find that the ODE model is a good approximation only if the diffusion coefficient is large. We demonstrate that the model is able to predict SARS-CoV-2 infection dynamics, and replicate the output of <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> experiments. Applying the model to influenza as well, we can gain insight into why the outcomes of these two infections are different.</p>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group>
                <kwd>hybrid model</kwd>
                <x xml:space="preserve">, </x>
                <kwd>spatio-temporal dynamics</kwd>
                <x xml:space="preserve">, </x>
                <kwd>agent-based model</kwd>
                <x xml:space="preserve">, </x>
                <kwd>viral kinetics</kwd>
                <x xml:space="preserve">, </x>
                <kwd>SARS-CoV-2</kwd>
                <x xml:space="preserve">, </x>
                <kwd>influenza</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <funding-group specific-use="FundRef">
                <award-group>
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution>Youth Foundation of Zhejiang University of Science and Technology</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                  <award-id>2021QN001, 2021QN046</award-id>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
              <funding-group specific-use="FundRef">
                <award-group>
                  <funding-source>
                    <institution-wrap>
                      <institution>Hungarian grants</institution>
                    </institution-wrap>
                  </funding-source>
                  <award-id>EFOP-3.6.1-16-2016-00008 and TUDFO/47138- 1/2019-I</award-id>
                  <award-id>NKFIH FK 124016 and 2020-2.1.1-ED-2020-0000</award-id>
                  <award-id>NKFIH KKP 129877</award-id>
                </award-group>
              </funding-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="s1">
              <label>1<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p>Mathematical models have been powerful tools in tackling the challenges posed by the appearance of the COVID-19 disease caused by the novel SARS-CoV-2 coronavirus. In the ongoing and virtually unprecedented pandemic, these mathematical models are invaluable as they are able to provide insights or predictions based on mathematical analysis and computer simulations. This means that their results are obtained at an ideally low cost even in complex situations where real-life and real-time experiments to obtain these same results would be either extremely risky or simply not possible. There is a large variety of both large- and small-scale mathematical models related to COVID-19. The present article is dedicated to cellular level investigations—we examine virus dynamical phenomena such as in-host viral transmission between individual cells. Specifically, we use a hybrid mathematical approach for our study, focusing on SARS-CoV-2 and influenza infections.</p>
              <p>Throughout the investigation of the above-mentioned hybrid model, we need a simple and already comprehensively understood model that we can use as a reference system—for this purpose, we will consider a specific version of an ODE prototype model, the May–Nowak system (for an extensive overview, see [<xref rid="RSOS210787C1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]; while for a concrete application, see [<xref rid="RSOS210787C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]). This classical model is given by
<disp-formula id="RSOS210787UM1"><mml:math id="DM1" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mtable columnalign="left left" rowspacing=".5em" columnspacing="thickmathspace"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where the <italic toggle="yes">H</italic> = <italic toggle="yes">H</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">I</italic> = <italic toggle="yes">I</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) and <italic toggle="yes">V</italic> = <italic toggle="yes">V</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) functions respectively correspond to the number of healthy cells, infected cells and virus particles, and they depend on time only. This model plays a crucial part in our article in several ways: (a) in the development process of the more sophisticated hybrid model, we use the ODE model to compare and match the respective solutions, (b) we exploit the fact that there is more information available on the exact parameters of this classical model and use their converted version in the hybrid system, and finally (c) we can demonstrate both the advantages and challenges offered by the relatively new hybrid system in comparison to a well-known model.</p>
              <p>The above ODE model is widely used to describe in-host viral dynamics. While this method proves to be extremely useful, the quality of information it can provide is naturally limited since it uses time as its single independent variable, and cannot capture spatial effects. Spatio-temporal phenomena are ubiquitous in biological applications, and often we simply cannot afford to leave out such an important factor from our models: the most obvious example for this is virus diffusion itself, which makes it possible for viruses to physically reach susceptible cells. One of the most powerful tools that does capture these crucial spatial mechanisms is the rich analytical theory of partial differential equations—PDE models are often used to investigate complex systems in viral infection dynamics; see [<xref rid="RSOS210787C3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] just to mention one SARS-CoV-2-related example.</p>
              <p>Agent-based modelling is another (and in fact quite different) approach to describe complex space–time dynamics in viral spread. The cornerstone idea of this method is to define a discrete heterogeneous state space where the so-called agents or elements have collective interactions with each other and they change their states correspondingly [<xref rid="RSOS210787C4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The agent-based model (ABM) concept has several important applications within the field of virus dynamics; for example, in [<xref rid="RSOS210787C5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] the authors apply an ABM to simulate influenza interactions at the host level.</p>
              <p>As seen above, different frameworks—including ABMs and PDE systems—have been applied to construct viral dynamics models. An ABM is a great tool to include randomness and natural variability into the system, while PDEs are faster to evaluate numerically: by forming bridges between these two modelling strategies we arrive at a hybrid system, the so-called hybrid PDE–ABM model, which unites the different advantages of these methods (see [<xref rid="RSOS210787C6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]). For the purpose of investigating the in-host viral spread of SARS-CoV-2 and influenza, our hybrid model is chosen and tailored by carefully considering certain dimension-related aspects of the problem: virus particles are several orders of magnitude smaller than epithelial cells [<xref rid="RSOS210787C7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>–<xref rid="RSOS210787C9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], and as a consequence, it is natural to capture virus concentration by a continuous function, while cells are modelled in a straightforward way as discrete entities in space. In other words, we obtain our hybrid model by merging (a) a PDE representing virus concentration and (b) an ABM describing host cells and their three possible states (healthy, infected and dead). We complete the hybrid PDE–ABM model by formulating a meaningful connection between the separate parts, i.e. by giving definition to all the considerable interactions and feedback processes that take place between the model’s discrete and continuous parts, such as for example cells responding to their environment’s virus concentration level. We highlight that our implementation of the proposed hybrid system is based on a free and open source software package, HAL (Hybrid Automata Library) [<xref rid="RSOS210787C10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p>
              <p>The present article’s novelty consists both in its approach and results. While PDE–ABM hybrid models have existed before HAL [<xref rid="RSOS210787C10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], the latter is primarily focused to serve cancer-related research—we have adapted, configured, and applied this tool to allow investigations in a completely different field of application: host-level virus infections. Our methodology and results demonstrate that both our model and its implementation technique provide a suitable framework to investigate problems in virology and immunology. We emphasize the importance of monitoring virus propagation in both space and time—we show that simpler models that disregard spatial phenomena correspondingly lose predictive precision due to ignoring spatial diffusion. The numerical simulations we perform using the hybrid system as a foundation give spatially explicit information regarding cellular-level virus spread for SARS-CoV-2 in a high-resolution state space, which is one of the main achievements of our article. The successful, computer-simulated replication of real <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> experiments regarding SARS-CoV-2 propagation is also new to our knowledge. Finally, we highlight that our results allow us to gain insight into why the respective outcomes of influenza and SARS-CoV-2 infections are different.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="methods" id="s2">
              <label>2<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
              <title>Methods</title>
              <p>The purpose of this section is to give a detailed description of the two main systems we use to model virus spread. We begin by defining the hybrid PDE–ABM model and introducing its variables, then we briefly outline a classical ODE model—the latter can be viewed as a simpler mean-field model that approximates the more complex hybrid framework by averaging over spatial variables. Once all the fundamental features of both systems are defined, we continue this section by expressing the connection between the corresponding model parameters, and conclude with the numerical implementation of the hybrid system.</p>
              <sec id="s2a">
                <label>2.1<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <title>The hybrid PDE–ABM model</title>
                <p>As described in the Introduction, the main hybrid system is constructed via forming bridges between two important and rather different modelling techniques: we merge a discrete ABM and a continuous PDE, and we create a meaningful connection between them by carefully designing their interactions with each other. We highlight the fact that the model we obtain in this way is defined in both space and time.</p>
                <p>We begin by setting the notation for the domain we construct our model upon: let <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM1"><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> be the mathematical representation of the part of lung tissue, or in the case of an <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> experiment, the relevant area of the investigation we are considering. Now we are ready to introduce the discrete part of our hybrid system.</p>
                <p>One of the most important modelling decisions in the first part of the model construction is approaching epithelial cells as discrete agents. In more detail, we define a two-dimensional ABM state space by introducing a lattice of <italic toggle="yes">k</italic><sub>1</sub> × <italic toggle="yes">k</italic><sub>2</sub> agents representing epithelial cells: naturally, <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM2"><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and cells are identified via the (<italic toggle="yes">i</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">j</italic>) indices (corresponding to the respective agent’s place in the grid), where <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM3"><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">J</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo fence="false" stretchy="false">{</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo fence="false" stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, 1 ≤ <italic toggle="yes">j</italic> ≤ <italic toggle="yes">k</italic><sub>2</sub>}. By introducing the <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM4"><mml:msub><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> notation for the open set occupied by the (<italic toggle="yes">i</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">j</italic>)th cell, we obtain that <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM5"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo>⋃</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">J</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                <p>Regarding the states of the ABM space’s agents, each agent can have three possible states in our approach. This is formally grasped by the following state function, which represents the concept that a cell is either <italic toggle="yes">healthy</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">infected</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">dead</italic>:
<disp-formula id="RSOS210787UM2"><mml:math id="DM2" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mtable columnalign="right left" rowspacing=".5em" columnspacing="thickmathspace"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">if</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">the</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">th</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">cell</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">is</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">healthy</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">at</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">time</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">if</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">the</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">th</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">cell</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">is</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">infected</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">at</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">time</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">if</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">the</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">th</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">cell</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">is</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">dead</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">at</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">time</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>In terms of state dynamics, we use the following assumptions:</p>
                <p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>—<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>for simplicity, we do not account for cell division or cell birth taking place during the time frame of the infection;</p></list-item><list-item><label>—<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>the only reason for cell death is viral infection itself, i.e. death related to any other natural cause is ignored;</p></list-item><list-item><label>—<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>all healthy cells are susceptible target cells;</p></list-item><list-item><label>—<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>once a cell gets infected, it is not possible for it to become healthy again;</p></list-item><list-item><label>—<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>the <italic toggle="yes">healthy</italic>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="IM6"><mml:mo stretchy="false">→</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>
<italic toggle="yes">infected</italic> state change: a healthy cell may become infected once the virus has reached the given cell; moreover, infection is randomized and it occurs with a probability of <italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">I</italic></sub>, where we highlight that <italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">I</italic></sub> increases linearly with the virus concentration in the given cell (for more details see §2.3 on <italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">I</italic></sub>’s relationship to other parameters and §2.4 on implementation);</p></list-item><list-item><label>—<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p>the <italic toggle="yes">infected</italic>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="IM7"><mml:mo stretchy="false">→</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>
<italic toggle="yes">dead</italic> state change: an infected cell dies with a probability <italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">D</italic></sub>, but similarly to infection, death too is approached from a stochastic viewpoint.</p></list-item></list>The stochastic element in the above state changes is of key importance. The inclusion of natural randomness makes the complex PDE–ABM hybrid model not only more realistic than the relatively simple ODE model, but also compared to a pure PDE system.</p>
                <p>We note that apart from following the state changes of all cells on an individual level, we also introduce three additional system variables as functions taking discrete (in fact, natural) values: <italic toggle="yes">H</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">I</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) and <italic toggle="yes">D</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>), respectively, denote the total number of healthy, infected and dead cells in the two-dimensional ABM state space.</p>
                <p>Now we are ready to consider the second part of our hybrid model. Let us begin by observing that the size of an epithelial cell is relatively significant [<xref rid="RSOS210787C8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="RSOS210787C9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] and hence indeed it was a natural idea above to define cells as separate entities and follow their states on an individual level (instead of exclusively considering the total number of healthy, infected and dead cells as continuous functions for example). One of the cornerstone observations in the second part of the model is that viruses, on the other hand, are several orders of magnitude smaller compared to epithelial cells [<xref rid="RSOS210787C7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]—we incorporate this simple but crucial biological fact into our system by modelling virus concentration as a continuous function. Hence, in the second part of the model, we approach virus concentration <italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">h</italic></sup> = <italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">h</italic></sup>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">y</italic>) as a variable that is continuous in both space and time, and as such, we capture it by means of a partial differential equation:
<disp-formula id="RSOS210787M2x1"><label>2.1</label><mml:math id="DM3" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∂</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∂</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Δ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">J</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula>where <italic toggle="yes">D</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">V</italic></sub> denotes the virus diffusion coefficient, <italic toggle="yes">μ</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">V</italic></sub> is a constant ratio representing virus removal, while <italic toggle="yes">g</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub> stands for the viral source term (the latter is assumed to be continuous) for the (<italic toggle="yes">i</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">j</italic>)th cell. The above equation essentially grasps the basic concept that viruses spread across the domain primarily via diffusion (convective flows are ignored in this model), the immune system removes viruses in a constant ratio, while new virus particles are generated by infected cells in a process described by the <italic toggle="yes">g</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub> functions
<disp-formula id="RSOS210787M2x2"><label>2.2</label><mml:math id="DM4" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mtable columnalign="left left" rowspacing="4pt" columnspacing="1em"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">if</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">and</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">if</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">and</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">if</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">and</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">if</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∉</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p>
                <p>We point out that in the above formula, we do not specify any particular exact <italic toggle="yes">f</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">y</italic>) form for the viral source term <italic toggle="yes">g</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">y</italic>) for the case when <italic toggle="yes">s</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) = <italic toggle="yes">I</italic> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM8"><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> (i.e. when the (<italic toggle="yes">i</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">j</italic>)th cell is infected). As noted in [<xref rid="RSOS210787C11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], very little is known about the shape, duration and magnitude of viral burst, and hence we allow any reasonable and smooth <italic toggle="yes">f</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">y</italic>) function here that meets the following two criteria. Firstly, any concrete choice for <italic toggle="yes">g</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub> needs to represent the general fact that the (<italic toggle="yes">i</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">j</italic>)th epithelial cell starts secreting virions at some point after it becomes infected. Thus, naturally, <italic toggle="yes">g</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub> takes positive values at least in some subset of <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM9"><mml:msub><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> at some point after the event of infection (but of course, as formulated above, outside of this given cell <italic toggle="yes">g</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub> is zero). Secondly, the <italic toggle="yes">g</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub> function needs to be defined in a way so that the well-posedness of system (<xref rid="RSOS210787M2x1" ref-type="disp-formula">2.1</xref>) is guaranteed: specifically, any concrete definition of the viral source term has to be Hölder continuous with Hölder exponent <italic toggle="yes">α</italic> ∈ (0, 1), i.e. we assume <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM10"><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∞</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> for any <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> &gt; 0,<inline-formula><mml:math id="IM11"><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and any <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM12"><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">J</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The latter ensures the global existence of the solution of system (<xref rid="RSOS210787M2x1" ref-type="disp-formula">2.1</xref>) (see appendix B). As an example, we can consider a definition where we use the modified version of a constant rate release within the (<italic toggle="yes">i</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">j</italic>)th cell. As for the details and changes related to the construction of <italic toggle="yes">g</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub> in the implementation process, see §2.4.</p>
                <p>The PDE–ABM hybrid model cannot be complete without explicitly taking into account the meaningful interactions that each part of the system has on the other, hence we briefly highlight these connections again. The continuous viral part affects the agent-based subsystem through the <italic toggle="yes">healthy</italic>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="IM13"><mml:mo stretchy="false">→</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>
<italic toggle="yes">infected</italic> state change described in the ABM section above. On the other hand, the discrete ABM part makes a difference within the continuous viral equation thanks to the <italic toggle="yes">g</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub> source functions (representing the fact that once a cell gets infected, at some point it starts spreading the virus).</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2b">
                <label>2.2<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <title>The ODE model</title>
                <p>In this subsection, we consider a simpler viral dynamics system which will serve as a reference model for the hybrid framework in our epidemiological investigations. We consider the following—only time-dependent—ODE system:
<disp-formula id="RSOS210787M2x3"><label>2.3</label><mml:math id="DM5" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:mtable columnalign="right left" rowspacing=".5em" columnspacing="thickmathspace"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where the <italic toggle="yes">H</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">I</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">V</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) and <italic toggle="yes">D</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) functions represent the number of healthy cells, the number of productively infected cells, the number of viruses released by infected cells and the dead cells at time <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>, respectively, <italic toggle="yes">β</italic> denotes the healthy cells’ infection rate, <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic> stands for the death rate of infected cells, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> is the virus production rate and <italic toggle="yes">c</italic> is the virus removal rate. We emphasize the fact that unlike the hybrid PDE–ABM model, the above ODE system is not defined in space.</p>
                <p>Technically, the <italic toggle="yes">V</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) function can be defined to represent either the number of viruses or the virus concentration itself depending on the specific application we are considering. In the simulation results of §3, <italic toggle="yes">V</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) stands for concentration.</p>
                <p>Simply because of the physical meaning behind these functions, the respective initial values are naturally set in the region <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM14"><mml:mi>Γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo fence="false" stretchy="false">{</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo fence="false" stretchy="false">}</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>. For the well-posedness and boundedness of model (<xref rid="RSOS210787M2x3" ref-type="disp-formula">2.3</xref>), see appendix C.</p>
                <p>The basic reproduction number of system (<xref rid="RSOS210787M2x3" ref-type="disp-formula">2.3</xref>) is given by
<disp-formula id="RSOS210787M2x4"><label>2.4</label><mml:math id="DM6" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula>For the derivation of this number and how it governs the threshold dynamics of the system, see appendix D.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2c">
                <label>2.3<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <title>The connection between the two main models and their parameters</title>
                <p>In this subsection, we examine the relationship between the two main models’ respective parameters. Expressing these connections is not always a trivial task as the hybrid PDE–ABM framework exists in space, while the ODE model’s functions are defined as variables only in time. In order to match the two different systems’ corresponding parameters, we need to fix some basic features of the spatial domain: first of all, let <italic toggle="yes">A</italic> denote the complete area of the state space; moreover, for simplicity, let us assume that each cell has the area of a unit space—for the latter we introduce the notation <italic toggle="yes">σ</italic><sup>2</sup>. Finally, let <italic toggle="yes">τ</italic> denote the unit step in time.</p>
                <p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>(i)<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p><bold>Parameters related to cell death:</bold> We emphasize that the two main models use different approaches to quantify the chance of an infected cell’s death—on the one hand, the ODE model (<xref rid="RSOS210787M2x3" ref-type="disp-formula">2.3</xref>) works with a <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic> death <italic toggle="yes">rate</italic>; on the other hand, the hybrid system uses a <italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">D</italic></sub>
<italic toggle="yes">probability</italic>. We can easily obtain a conversion between probability and rate by following the exact meaning behind these parameters. When infected cells die with a death rate <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic>, their natural decay can be described by the function e<sup>−<italic toggle="yes">δt</italic></sup>; hence, the probability of an infected cell’s death between any two arbitrary time points <italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>2</sub> is given by
<disp-formula id="RSOS210787UM3"><mml:math id="DM7" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>Specifically, for a time interval of length <italic toggle="yes">τ</italic> the above formula means that an infected cell dies within that given time frame with a probability of 1 − e<sup>−<italic toggle="yes">δτ</italic></sup>.</p><p>Applying the Taylor expansion of the exponential function and combining it with the fact that <italic toggle="yes">τ</italic> is small, we arrive at the 1 − e<sup>−<italic toggle="yes">δτ</italic></sup> ≈ <italic toggle="yes">δτ</italic> approximation, i.e. the connection between <italic toggle="yes">δ</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">D</italic></sub> is given by
<disp-formula id="RSOS210787M2x5"><label>2.5</label><mml:math id="DM8" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula></p></list-item><list-item><label>(ii)<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p><bold>Parameters related to new infections:</bold> In this part, we establish a connection between the ODE model’s infection rate <italic toggle="yes">β</italic> and the hybrid system’s probability of infection <italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">I</italic></sub>. Similarly to the previous point, we need to quantify a relationship between parameters of different dimensions—one being a <italic toggle="yes">rate</italic>, the other a <italic toggle="yes">probability</italic>—but this time the solution is a bit more complex due to the role of spatial factors. We first focus on the hybrid model’s <italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">I</italic></sub> parameter solely within the context of the PDE–ABM system. We define the probability of a cell’s infection in a way that this probability is directly proportional to the local virus concentration <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM15"><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> in the (<italic toggle="yes">i</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">j</italic>)th cell (the number of viruses per unit space) and to the <italic toggle="yes">τ</italic> time unit, i.e. we have
<disp-formula id="RSOS210787M2x6"><label>2.6</label><mml:math id="DM9" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>ι</mml:mi><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM16"><mml:mi>ι</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is some appropriately set constant value. Our next step is to express the relationship between <italic toggle="yes">β</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">I</italic></sub> for a specifically chosen, simplified scenario—we temporarily assume a homogeneous virus distribution over the domain <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM17"><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. Now, the key to expressing <italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">I</italic></sub> in terms of <italic toggle="yes">β</italic> consists in carefully counting the newly infected cells over one iteration in both the ODE and the hybrid systems. Assuming <italic toggle="yes">H</italic> healthy cells and a <italic toggle="yes">V</italic> total number of viruses at a given time, the corresponding number in the ODE model is naturally <italic toggle="yes">β</italic> · <italic toggle="yes">V</italic> · <italic toggle="yes">H</italic> · <italic toggle="yes">τ</italic>. When we switch to the context of the spatial hybrid model, we need to keep in mind that the virus particles are now spread throughout the entire domain <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM18"><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, and as a consequence, a single cell is exposed only to the locally, physically present virus particles, whose number is <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM19"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. This means that the expected value of the total number of newly infected cells in the hybrid system is <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM20"><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>. Setting the respective values in the two main models equal leads us to
<disp-formula id="RSOS210787M2x7"><label>2.7</label><mml:math id="DM10" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>The final step is to combine (<xref rid="RSOS210787M2x6" ref-type="disp-formula">2.6</xref>) and (<xref rid="RSOS210787M2x7" ref-type="disp-formula">2.7</xref>)—by substituting <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM21"><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in the former we immediately obtain <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM22"><mml:mi>ι</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. The connection between <italic toggle="yes">β</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">I</italic></sub> is thus captured by
<disp-formula id="RSOS210787M2x8"><label>2.8</label><mml:math id="DM11" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p>We highlight that the hybrid model’s <italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">I</italic></sub> parameter takes the above form exclusively when the PDE–ABM model’s parameters are configured with a very specific goal in mind: to match the ODE system. Otherwise, when the hybrid software is used completely as a standalone, <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM23"><mml:mi>ι</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is simply a parameter in the hybrid model.</p></list-item><list-item><label>(iii)<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p><bold>Parameters related to virus production:</bold> The ODE model (<xref rid="RSOS210787M2x3" ref-type="disp-formula">2.3</xref>) parameter <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> corresponds to virus production rate per unit time. Respectively, in our spatial hybrid model’s virus dynamical equation (<xref rid="RSOS210787M2x1" ref-type="disp-formula">2.1</xref>) the parameter <italic toggle="yes">g</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub> represents the virus production rate per unit time per unit space<sup>2</sup>—in particular, <italic toggle="yes">g</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub> = <italic toggle="yes">f</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub> within infected cells (see (<xref rid="RSOS210787M2x2" ref-type="disp-formula">2.2</xref>)); hence, clearly, <italic toggle="yes">f</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub> matches <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item><label>(iv)<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p><bold>Parameters related to virus removal:</bold> Analogously, the respective pair of the hybrid model’s <italic toggle="yes">m</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">V</italic></sub> parameter is the ODE system’s <italic toggle="yes">c</italic> virus removal constant.</p></list-item><list-item><label>(v)<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p><bold>Parameters related to virus diffusion:</bold> We highlight that the hybrid model’s diffusive constant <italic toggle="yes">D</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">V</italic></sub> does not have a corresponding parameter in the ODE system, as the latter model is defined only in time and diffusivity is strictly related to spacial dimensions.</p></list-item></list>We summarize the respective parameters’ relationship to each other in <xref rid="RSOS210787TB1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>.
<table-wrap position="float" id="RSOS210787TB1"><label>Table 1<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label><caption><p>Description of the hybrid PDE–ABM model’s parameters and their relationship to the ODE system. Naturally, the notations [healthy cell], [infected cell] and [dead cell] represent a healthy cell, an infected cell and a dead cell—as a unit—respectively. Analogously, [virion]/<italic toggle="yes">σ</italic><sup>2</sup> stands for the concentration unit.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">symbol</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">parameter</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">unit</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">value corresponding to the ODE model</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">I</italic></sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">probability of infection for the (<italic toggle="yes">i</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">j</italic>)th cell</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="IM24"><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">D</italic></sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">probability of death of an infected cell</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">δ</italic> · <italic toggle="yes">τ</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">f</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">virus production rate of an infected cell</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="IM25"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">virion</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">D</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">V</italic></sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">virus diffusion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">σ</italic><sup>2</sup><italic toggle="yes">τ</italic><sup>−1</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">μ</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">V</italic></sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">virus removal rate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">τ</italic><sup>−1</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">c</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">H</italic><sub>0</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">initial number of healthy cells</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[healthy cell]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">H</italic><sub>0</sub></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sub>0</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">initial number of infected cells</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[infected cell]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sub>0</sub></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="IM26"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">initial value of virus concentration</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[virion]/<italic toggle="yes">σ</italic><sup>2</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>0</sub></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">D</italic><sub>0</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">initial number of dead cells</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[dead cell]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">D</italic><sub>0</sub></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><italic toggle="yes">σ</italic>: space unit.</p></fn><fn><p><italic toggle="yes">τ</italic>: time unit.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s2d">
                <label>2.4<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <title>Implementation</title>
                <p>This section describes important technical details related to the hybrid PDE–ABM framework’s implementation. Our numerical computations are based on a free and open source Java software package, HAL [<xref rid="RSOS210787C10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]; our source code is publicly accessible in the Github repository [<xref rid="RSOS210787C12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p>
                <p>We note that most of our work concerning implementation is centred around customizing the generic HAL package to our concrete virological application, e.g. managing and tracking healthy, infected and dead cells, or putting certain probablistic state change approaches into practice. The deeper, application-independent segments of the HAL library on the other hand do not require any further consideration or optimization from our side; we rely on these core parts without effectuating any modifications. Just to mention one example, the numerical stability for the finite difference diffusion fields is an essential, integral part of HAL itself, and our implementation respects and preserves the original code on these levels—as a consequence, we use the implicit method that the underlying HAL library uses for dealing with the diffusion term.</p>
                <p>We simulate the PDE–ABM model’s behaviour in an <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM27"><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mo>⊂</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> two-dimensional bounded domain, hence the Δ<italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">h</italic></sup> Laplacian takes the form of <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM28"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM29"><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. The resolution of the state space is chosen to be 200 × 200, which means we work with a total number of 40 000 cells (this choice is mainly due to the hybrid model’s computational demands—we found that concerning the number of cells, 40 000 is a reasonable value for exploring virus dynamics on an ordinary computer).</p>
                <p>Concerning the spatial boundary, we apply Neumann boundary conditions on the edges of the hybrid state space. This approach is favourable for our investigations by guaranteeing zero flux across the boundary. The ‘closed world’ we get as a result is beneficial since it allows us to realistically observe the damage caused by a certain amount of infected cells without external disturbance. Wall-like edges of laboratory assays also naturally correspond to no-flux Neumann boundary conditions, and thus we expect this setting to match the outcome of <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> experiments.</p>
                <p>As for the initial conditions in our simulations, we consider the case where we have zero virus concentration in the beginning, but we do have a small number of infected cells in the domain to start with—the virus will spread from these infected cells and, as a result, more and more originally healthy cells become infected. This first generation of infected cells is chosen and distributed randomly. Each cell independently has a 0.0005 probability to be in an infected state at the beginning of the simulation, otherwise it is in a healthy state (with probability 0.9995). The number of initially infected cells is denoted by <italic toggle="yes">χ</italic>. <xref rid="RSOS210787F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> illustrates the initial state of our hybrid PDE–ABM model.
<fig position="float" id="RSOS210787F1"><label>Figure 1<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label><caption><p>An ABM state space where most cells are healthy, while a small number of randomly infected cells start spreading the virus in the domain.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsos210787f01" position="float"/></fig></p>
                <p>After giving a clear definition of the initial and boundary conditions in our implementation, we highlight another interesting technical detail: the internal realization of the virus production functions. At the abstract definition of the hybrid PDE–ABM model, we assumed that the virus source term in (<xref rid="RSOS210787M2x1" ref-type="disp-formula">2.1</xref>) was continuous. This was important for certain theoretical reasons (see appendix B), but as we move on to implementation-related decisions and solutions, we make a simplifying step regarding this source function. We take a discretized approach, namely, throughout the simulations, a given cell’s <italic toggle="yes">g</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub> virus production function (and in particular, <italic toggle="yes">f</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub>) is quantified assuming that infected cells have a constant virus production rate; formally, <italic toggle="yes">g</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">y</italic>) = a non-<italic toggle="yes">zero constant</italic> when <italic toggle="yes">s</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) = <italic toggle="yes">I</italic> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM30"><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>. We highlight that what really happens at the implementation process is that in each time loop and for each cell (thus, for all <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM31"><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">J</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) we solve equation (<xref rid="RSOS210787M2x9" ref-type="disp-formula">2.9</xref>) to obtain the virus concentration in a given cell:
<disp-formula id="RSOS210787M2x9"><label>2.9</label><mml:math id="DM12" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∂</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∂</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Δ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula></p>
                <p>We also emphasize that in order to make the model as realistic as possible, we take some probabilistic considerations into account, and as a result we use a stochastic approach in the implementation of both cell infection and cell death.
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>—<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p><italic toggle="yes">Stochastic implementation of a healthy cell’s infection:</italic> In the <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM32"><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> expression (obtained in (<xref rid="RSOS210787M2x8" ref-type="disp-formula">2.8</xref>)), we assume that the infection rate <italic toggle="yes">β</italic> and the <italic toggle="yes">A</italic> area of the domain are constant, but <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM33"><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> is changing in both space and time—once the virus concentration is recalculated for a given cell, we then compare the correspondingly updated <italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">I</italic></sub> value with an <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM34"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula> random number, which is generated newly for each cell. In the case where the cell’s <italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">I</italic></sub> value is greater than <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM35"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula>, the cell in question gets infected.</p></list-item><list-item><label>—<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label><p><italic toggle="yes">Stochastic implementation of an infected cell’s death:</italic> Similarly, a random <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM36"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula> number is generated for each infected cell at each time step, and the given cell’s death is determined by comparing this random number with <italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">D</italic></sub>: naturally, the infected cell dies if <italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">D</italic></sub> is greater than <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM37"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:msubsup></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></list-item></list>All of the random numbers noted above are real numbers from standard uniform distribution on the interval (0,1) and they are obtained by means of Java’s random number generator.</p>
                <p><xref rid="RSOS210787F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> shows the flow diagram of the program we implemented to simulate the virus spread and observe the spatial distributions of infected cells.
<fig position="float" id="RSOS210787F2"><label>Figure 2<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label><caption><p>The program flow diagram of the PDE–ABM model’s numerical simulation based on HAL [<xref rid="RSOS210787C10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsos210787f02" position="float"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s3">
              <label>3<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
              <title>Results</title>
              <p>We present and explain our most significant computational results in this section. In particular, we illustrate the advantages of the spatio-temporal hybrid system over the classical ODE model, and we show an example where we successfully recreate the actual results of an <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> experiment assessing SARS-CoV-2 propagation. Moreover, by means of the PDE–ABM system, we explore and compare the spatial patterns of influenza and COVID-19.</p>
              <sec id="s3a">
                <label>3.1<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <title>Comparing the hybrid PDE–ABM model and the ODE model through their solutions</title>
                <p>This section is principally dedicated to illustrating the impact of the PDE–ABM model’s built-in extra information regarding spatial factors such as diffusion. In the following steps, we compare the numerical solutions of the (only time-dependent) ODE model and the hybrid spatio-temporal PDE–ABM system. We emphasize the fact that in this subsection, we consider a generic scenario that does not necessarily correspond to influenza or SARS-CoV-2 specifically. Our main goal here is to outline a comparison itself between the two main models making sure that their parameters represent the same virus infection in identical circumstances—with the very important exception of virus diffusion, which incorporates spatial effects.</p>
                <p>As for the ODE model’s simulation, we consider the following parameter values:
<disp-formula id="RSOS210787M3x1"><label>3.1</label><mml:math id="DM13" display="block"><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>8</mml:mn><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula></p>
                <p><xref rid="RSOS210787F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref> depicts the solution of the ODE model (<xref rid="RSOS210787M2x3" ref-type="disp-formula">2.3</xref>) using the parameter values defined in (<xref rid="RSOS210787M3x1" ref-type="disp-formula">3.1</xref>) and the initial conditions <italic toggle="yes">H</italic><sub>0</sub> = 40 000 − <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sub>0</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sub>0</sub> = 20, <italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>0</sub> = 0 and <italic toggle="yes">D</italic><sub>0</sub> = 0.
<fig position="float" id="RSOS210787F3"><label>Figure 3<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label><caption><p>A sample solution of model (<xref rid="RSOS210787M2x3" ref-type="disp-formula">2.3</xref>) considering the parameters given in (<xref rid="RSOS210787M3x1" ref-type="disp-formula">3.1</xref>) with <italic toggle="yes">H</italic><sub>0</sub> = 40 000 − <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sub>0</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sub>0</sub> = 20, <italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>0</sub> = 0 and <italic toggle="yes">D</italic><sub>0</sub> = 0 as initial values. (<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>) Number of cells over time and (<italic toggle="yes">b</italic>) virus concentration over time.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsos210787f03" position="float"/></fig></p>
                <p>Once the ODE parameters are set, most of the corresponding hybrid parameter values are automatically defined through the connections described in <xref rid="RSOS210787TB1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>. We obtain
<disp-formula id="RSOS210787M3x2"><label>3.2</label><mml:math id="DM14" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.04</mml:mn><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>8</mml:mn><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula></p>
                <p>Naturally—due to the fact that the ODE model is defined only in time—the hybrid system’s diffusion coefficient is an exceptional parameter missing from the list above. To demonstrate the notable difference made by virus diffusion in the hybrid model’s numerical solutions (and to compare the latter with the ODE model’s solution), we simulate our spatial model with two different diffusion coefficients:
<disp-formula id="RSOS210787M3x3"><label>3.3</label><mml:math id="DM15" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">and</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>20</mml:mn><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>4.</mml:mn></mml:math></disp-formula></p>
                <p>Figures <xref rid="RSOS210787F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> and <xref rid="RSOS210787F5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> illustrate the different cell and virus dynamics emerging from scenarios that are identical apart from their diffusion coefficients. Both graphs demonstrate cell states on the left and virus spread on the right, captured in four different time points. Infected cells (denoted by red squares) are apparently distributed randomly at the initial state, and virus spread in the domain is clearly originating from infected cells. Comparing these two images we can observe the following significant differences. Firstly, as one would naturally expect, a higher diffusion coefficient results in a much more homogeneous infection spread in space. In more detail, <xref rid="RSOS210787F4" ref-type="fig">figure 4</xref> captures a typical low-diffusion scenario where infected cells are found mainly in separate, island-resembling sets, while <xref rid="RSOS210787F5" ref-type="fig">figure 5</xref> shows a fundamentally different phenomenon: the layout of infected cells in the latter image is apparently much more even. An analogous difference is visible on the level of spatial virus distribution as well. On the one hand, <xref rid="RSOS210787F4" ref-type="fig">figure 4</xref> presents distinctive, sharp borders and well-defined lines that characterize low-diffusion virus dynamics; on the other hand, <xref rid="RSOS210787F5" ref-type="fig">figure 5</xref> shows—roughly speaking—foggy, blurred shades corresponding to the increased diffusion value. Our second observation is related to the total number of surviving cells by the end of the simulation: this value is clearly higher for the output obtained with a smaller diffusion coefficient, i.e. in <xref rid="RSOS210787F4" ref-type="fig">figure 4</xref>. In other words, according to our simulations, a higher diffusion value results in a higher number of cells that get damaged by infection (i.e. cells that are either currently infected or are already dead).
<fig position="float" id="RSOS210787F4"><label>Figure 4<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label><caption><p>Sample hybrid PDE–ABM results considering (<xref rid="RSOS210787M3x2" ref-type="disp-formula">3.2</xref>) and <bold><italic toggle="yes">D<sub>V</sub></italic></bold><sub>1</sub> = 0.2 at <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> = 0, 240, 480 and 720 (<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>–<italic toggle="yes">d</italic>). Infected, healthy and dead cells (denoted by red, green and black squares, respectively) are shown on the left and virus spread is depicted on the right in all four panels (<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>–<italic toggle="yes">d</italic>). The colour bar is understood in virions per unit space (<xref rid="RSOS210787TB1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsos210787f04" position="float"/></fig>
<fig position="float" id="RSOS210787F5"><label>Figure 5<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label><caption><p>Sample hybrid PDE–ABM results considering (<xref rid="RSOS210787M3x2" ref-type="disp-formula">3.2</xref>) and <bold><italic toggle="yes">D<sub>V</sub></italic></bold> <sub>2</sub> = 4 at <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> = 0, 240, 480, and 720 (<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>–<italic toggle="yes">d</italic>). Infected, healthy and dead cells (denoted by red, green and black squares, respectively) are shown on the left and virus spread is depicted on the right in all four panels (<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>–<italic toggle="yes">d</italic>). The colour bar is understood in virions per unit space (<xref rid="RSOS210787TB1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsos210787f05" position="float"/></fig></p>
                <p>Figures <xref rid="RSOS210787F6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> and <xref rid="RSOS210787F7" ref-type="fig">7</xref> examine identical scenarios with a different approach: they describe the corresponding virus dynamics in terms of aggregated cell numbers and virus concentration. These figures contain information in a condensed format—their clarity allows us to detect further dynamical differences caused by different diffusion values. Firstly, we can observe that the magnitude of the virus concentration peak is almost twofold bigger for a higher diffusion value (<xref rid="RSOS210787F7" ref-type="fig">figure 7</xref>) than in the corresponding lower diffusion case (<xref rid="RSOS210787F6" ref-type="fig">figure 6</xref>). The peak itself is reached at around 400<italic toggle="yes">τ</italic> for <italic toggle="yes">D</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">V</italic></sub><sub>2</sub> = 4, while for <italic toggle="yes">D</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">V</italic></sub><sub>1</sub> = 0.2 the analogous event takes place only after 600<italic toggle="yes">τ</italic>, i.e. in the latter case, the peak is reached approximately one and a half times slower. The sharpness of these peaks is clearly another significant difference too—a lower diffusion value seems to lead to a flatter virus concentration curve. We highlight that analogous features are visually obvious for the number of infected cells too. Finally, we observe that the faster fall in the number of healthy cells and the quicker increase in the number of dead cells in <xref rid="RSOS210787F7" ref-type="fig">figure 7</xref> suggest that in this particular setting a higher diffusion coefficient leads to a worse scenario overall, according to our results.
<fig position="float" id="RSOS210787F6"><label>Figure 6<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label><caption><p>A sample solution of the hybrid PDE–ABM model considering parameters specified in (<xref rid="RSOS210787M3x2" ref-type="disp-formula">3.2</xref>) and <bold><italic toggle="yes">D<sub>V</sub></italic></bold><sub>1</sub> = 0.2. (<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>) Number of cells over time and (<italic toggle="yes">b</italic>) virus concentration over time.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsos210787f06" position="float"/></fig>
<fig position="float" id="RSOS210787F7"><label>Figure 7<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label><caption><p>A sample solution of the hybrid PDE–ABM model considering parameters specified in (<xref rid="RSOS210787M3x2" ref-type="disp-formula">3.2</xref>) and <bold><italic toggle="yes">D<sub>V</sub></italic></bold><sub>2</sub> = 4. (<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>) Number of cells over time and (<italic toggle="yes">b</italic>) virus concentration over time.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsos210787f07" position="float"/></fig></p>
                <p>Finally, in <xref rid="RSOS210787F8" ref-type="fig">figure 8</xref>, we compare the solution of the ODE system with the respective numerical solutions calculated for our spatial hybrid model considering the previously described two different virus diffusion values. <xref rid="RSOS210787F8" ref-type="fig">Figure 8</xref> illustrates a special relationship between the solutions of the two main systems: increasing the spatial model’s diffusion coefficient apparently impacts the hybrid system’s solution in a way that it, roughly speaking, gets closer to the ODE model’s numerical solution—this corresponds to the fact that the ODE system represents a scenario where all particles can interact with any other particle, i.e. in some sense the diffusion coefficient is infinite. In other words, the lower the actual virus diffusion value is, the more important it is to consider a more complex spatio-temporal system to model the respective virus spread.
<fig position="float" id="RSOS210787F8"><label>Figure 8<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label><caption><p>Comparison between the ODE model and the hybrid PDE–ABM system with two different diffusion values (as given in (<xref rid="RSOS210787M3x3" ref-type="disp-formula">3.3</xref>)). It is clearly seen that the outputs are very similar for a high diffusion coefficient, as opposed to the case of low diffusion coefficient. (<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>) Virus concentration over time, (<italic toggle="yes">b</italic>) number of healthy cells over time, (<italic toggle="yes">c</italic>) number of infected cells over time and (<italic toggle="yes">d</italic>) number of dead cells over time.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsos210787f08" position="float"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="s3b">
                <label>3.2<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                <title>Applications</title>
                <p>In one way or another, all applications of the proposed PDE–ABM hybrid model naturally focus on exploiting or predicting spatial information regarding virus spread. The first application detailed in §3.2.1 is dedicated to the latter; here we perform a simulation to obtain as much information as possible on the spatial dynamics of a COVID-19 infection and we compare our computer-generated predictions with actual results of <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> experiments. On the other hand, §3.2.2 is dedicated to observing some important differences between influenza and COVID-19—these are identified more easily thanks to the additional spatial information that is integrated into the hybrid model.</p>
                <sec id="s3b1">
                  <label>3.2.1<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                  <title>Predicting the spatio-temporal spread of SARS-CoV-2 in human airway epithelial cells</title>
                  <p>Perhaps one of the most straightforward applications is the prediction of spatial virus propagation itself. In this first scenario, we simulate the spatial spread of a SARS-CoV-2 infection over the course of 7 days and we compare our results with real-life observations obtained by scientific experiments. Specifically, we consider fig. 4B in [<xref rid="RSOS210787C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], where the authors examine the spread of fluorescent SARS-CoV-2 in human airway epithelial cells at the indicated days with or without peptide treatment—naturally, when we compare our results, we focus on the graphs listed in the line that corresponds to our scenario (i.e. investigating uninhibited virus propagation excluding any treatment).</p>
                  <p>Examining <xref rid="RSOS210787F9" ref-type="fig">figure 9</xref><italic toggle="yes">b</italic> and <xref rid="RSOS210787F9" ref-type="fig">9</xref><italic toggle="yes">a</italic> (the latter is part of fig. 4B in [<xref rid="RSOS210787C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]), we observe that the key events and features of virus spread match in a reassuring way: the first significant and bigger sign of infection appears at day 4, a clearly visible peak is reached at day 6, while a slight decrease in the infection’s severity starts to show between day 6 and day 7. At the same time, we highlight that there is a natural limit to how accurately our simulations can recreate the specific events depicted in [<xref rid="RSOS210787C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]: firstly, to our best knowledge, the exact values of virus death rate, infection rate and diffusion are not specified in [<xref rid="RSOS210787C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Secondly, the authors have not disclosed the number of cells they worked with—this means that the resolutions of the corresponding ABM fields are different (theirs being unknown). The latter is particularly important as it is most likely one of the reasons why the computer-simulated results are less ‘sharp’ compared to the experimental scenario’s images: roughly speaking, the generated results resemble ink spreading in water to some extent, while the <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> results have an apparent grain-like structure. This matter can possibly be the subject of future investigation.
<fig position="float" id="RSOS210787F9"><label>Figure 9<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label><caption><p>Numerical prediction of virus propagation. (<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>) Experimental <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> results of [<xref rid="RSOS210787C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] assessing viral spread. (<italic toggle="yes">b</italic>) The simulated spatio-temporal dynamics of SARS-CoV-2 virus spread in human airway epithelial cells—the results were obtained by our source code implementing the hybrid PDE–ABM model. This sequence of pictures from our model output shows a striking resemblance to fig. 4B in [<xref rid="RSOS210787C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] (seen below), where the latter depicts real experimental results assessing viral propagation. Note the colour choice we apply in this figure: in order to match our simulation’s colours to the experimental results in [<xref rid="RSOS210787C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], in these particular images the colour green represents virus particles and not healthy cells.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsos210787f09" position="float"/></fig></p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s3b2">
                  <label>3.2.2<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
                  <title>Investigating and comparing the main properties of influenza and COVID-19</title>
                  <p>While §3.1 focused on comparing the ODE model’s and the hybrid system’s respective solutions in a generic scenario, the present—and in some sense, main—section’s goal is to explore these solutions for two specific viruses, namely, influenza and SARS-CoV-2.</p>
                  <p>In order to investigate the propagation of an influenza or COVID-19 infection, we need to set up both of our models with parameters that represent the features of the previously mentioned viruses as accurately as possible. This is a non-trivial task not only because SARS-CoV-2 is relatively new for scientists, but also because several other small, technical, but important issues arise when we want to compare two different kinds of solutions. One particularly intriguing example is the accurate setting of the <italic toggle="yes">D</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">V</italic></sub> diffusion coefficient—the <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM38"><mml:mn>0.65</mml:mn><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">min</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> value we use in the remaining part of this article is chosen from a reasonable range. We elaborate the limitations, practical considerations and further details concerning the parametrization process in appendix A. Here, we just refer to the tables containing the final values—the ODE model’s parameter setting is summed up in <xref rid="RSOS210787TB2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>, while the parameter values we use during the simulations for the hybrid PDE–ABM model are given in <xref rid="RSOS210787TB3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>.
<table-wrap position="float" id="RSOS210787TB2"><label>Table 2<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label><caption><p>Description of the parameters of ODE model (2.3). Naturally, the notations [healthy cell], [infected cell] and [dead cell] represent a healthy cell, an infected cell and a dead cell—as a unit—respectively.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">symbol</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">parameter</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">unit</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">value for influenza</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">value for COVID-19</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ref.</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">β</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">infection rate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ml [virus copy]<sup>−1</sup> min<sup>−1</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 × 10<sup>−</sup><sup>7</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 × 10<sup>−7</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">δ</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">infected cell death rate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">min<sup>−1</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.66 × 10<sup>−3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2 × 10<sup>−4</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="RSOS210787C12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="RSOS210787C14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">virus production rate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[virus copy] min<sup>−1</sup> ml<sup>−1</sup> [infected cell]<sup>−1</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.666 × 10<sup>−2</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.72 × 10<sup>−3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="RSOS210787C12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="RSOS210787C14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">c</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">virus removal rate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">min<sup>−1</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.08 × 10<sup>−3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67 × 10<sup>−3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="RSOS210787C12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="RSOS210787C14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">H</italic><sub>0</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">initial number of healthy cells</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[healthy cell]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 000 − 20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 000 − 20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sub>0</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">initial number of infected cells</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[infected cell]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>0</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">initial value of virus concentration</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="IM39"><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">virus</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">copy</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">ml</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">D</italic><sub>0</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">initial number of dead cells</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[dead cell]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><inline-formula><mml:math id="IM40"><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">min</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap position="float" id="RSOS210787TB3"><label>Table 3<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label><caption><p>Description of the hybrid PDE–ABM model’s parameters. Naturally, the notations [healthy cell], [infected cell] and [dead cell] represent a healthy cell, an infected cell and a dead cell—as a unit—respectively.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">symbol</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">parameter</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">unit</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">value for COVID-19</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">value for influenza</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ref.</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">I</italic></sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">probability of infection</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="IM41"><mml:mn>3.76</mml:mn><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="IM42"><mml:mn>4.04</mml:mn><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">D</italic></sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">probability of the infected cell death</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.66 × 10<sup>−3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.2 × 10<sup>−4</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">f</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">virus production from an infected cell</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[virus copy] ml<sup>−1</sup> min<sup>−1</sup> [infected cell]<sup>−1</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.666 × 10<sup>−2</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.72 × 10<sup>−3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">μ</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">V</italic></sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">virus removal rate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">min<sup>−1</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.08 × 10<sup>−3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67 × 10<sup>−3</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">D</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">V</italic></sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">virus diffusion</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="IM43"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[3.18 × 10<sup>−3</sup>, 3.18]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[3 × 10<sup>−6</sup>, 3]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[<xref rid="RSOS210787C11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="RSOS210787C15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="IM44"><mml:msup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">min</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.97 × 10<sup>−3</sup>, 0.97]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[0.9 × 10<sup>−6</sup>, 0.9]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">appendix A</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">H</italic><sub>0</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">initial number of healthy cells</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[healthy cell]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 000 − <italic toggle="yes">χ</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 000 − <italic toggle="yes">χ</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sub>0</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">initial number of infected cells</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[infected cell]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">χ</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">χ</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="IM45"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">initial value of virus concentration</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><inline-formula><mml:math id="IM46"><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">virus</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">copy</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">ml</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">cell</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">D</italic><sub>0</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">initial number of dead cells</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">[dead cell]</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><italic toggle="yes">σ</italic> = 14 μm.</p></fn><fn><p><inline-formula><mml:math id="IM47"><mml:mi>τ</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">min</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
                  <p>Now we are ready to compare the two different models’ predictive performances. Firstly, we consider the case of influenza. <xref rid="RSOS210787F10" ref-type="fig">Figure 10</xref> shows the respective numerical solutions obtained by the ODE model and the hybrid system—we note that the solution given by the ODE model is similar to the one described in [<xref rid="RSOS210787C16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. We also refer back to an observation we made in §3.1 regarding the diffusion coefficients: the lower this diffusion value is, the further the hybrid and ODE models’ respective solutions are from each other. Finally, we highlight another important aspect in connection with <xref rid="RSOS210787F10" ref-type="fig">figure 10</xref>. The authors of [<xref rid="RSOS210787C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="RSOS210787C17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>] suggest that in the upper respiratory tract about 30–50% of the epithelial cells are destroyed at the peak of infection. This corresponds to our simulated results in a reassuring way.
<fig position="float" id="RSOS210787F10"><label>Figure 10<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label><caption><p>Comparison of the ODE model (solid lines) and the hybrid PDE–ABM model (dashed lines) for influenza using the parameters in tables <xref rid="RSOS210787TB2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and <xref rid="RSOS210787TB3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, applying <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM48"><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">min</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> in the hybrid model. All panels depict a change taking place over the course of 7 days; specifically, (<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>) viral load, (<italic toggle="yes">b</italic>) number of healthy cells, (<italic toggle="yes">c</italic>) number of infected cells and (<italic toggle="yes">d</italic>) number of dead cells.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsos210787f10" position="float"/></fig></p>
                  <p>The second subject of our comparative investigations is COVID-19. Similarly to the concept of the previous image, <xref rid="RSOS210787F11" ref-type="fig">figure 11</xref> demonstrates the simulated results given by the ODE model and the PDE–ABM hybrid system, but in this case the computations were executed with the parameters representing COVID-19. We observe that the ODE model and the hybrid system generate solutions that are somewhat closer to each other than their respective solutions computed for influenza.
<fig position="float" id="RSOS210787F11"><label>Figure 11<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label><caption><p>Comparison of the ODE model (solid lines) and the hybrid PDE–ABM model (dashed lines) for SARS-CoV-2 using the parameters in tables <xref rid="RSOS210787TB2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and <xref rid="RSOS210787TB3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, applying <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM49"><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">min</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> in the hybrid model. All panels depict a change taking place over the course of seven days; specifically, (<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>) viral load, (<italic toggle="yes">b</italic>) number of healthy cells, (<italic toggle="yes">c</italic>) number of infected cells and (<italic toggle="yes">d</italic>) number of dead cells.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsos210787f11" position="float"/></fig></p>
                  <p>From this point, in this section, we examine influenza and SARS-CoV-2 propagation exclusively by means of the hybrid PDE–ABM system.</p>
                  <p>In order to compare the dynamical features of SARS-CoV-2 and influenza, we firstly simulate the viral load and the number of infected cells for both of these two viruses. The numerical solutions are presented in <xref rid="RSOS210787F12" ref-type="fig">figure 12</xref> (the respective functions for the two different viruses are shown together). First of all, we highlight that while the solutions depicted in this image are only time-dependent functions, the advantage of the hybrid PDE–ABM model is present even behind this particular result—the fact that these numerical solutions were calculated by means of the spatio-temporal hybrid model ensures that their respective values take important physical aspects such as diffusion into account. In particular, we refer to [<xref rid="RSOS210787C18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] for connecting some of our results to real data and describing the course of influenza infection: this work reports that virus shedding increases sharply between 0.5 and 1 day after challenge and peaks at day 2, while the average duration of viral shedding is 4.8 days. Our computer simulated results shown in <xref rid="RSOS210787F12" ref-type="fig">figure 12</xref> for influenza clearly match with the experimental data of [<xref rid="RSOS210787C18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].
<fig position="float" id="RSOS210787F12"><label>Figure 12<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label><caption><p>The difference between influenza and SARS-CoV-2 infections. The viral load (<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>) and the number of infected cells (<italic toggle="yes">b</italic>) simulated for influenza (dashed line) and COVID-19 (solid line) using the hybrid PDE–ABM model with <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM50"><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">min</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsos210787f12" position="float"/></fig></p>
                  <p>Some of the results in <xref rid="RSOS210787F12" ref-type="fig">figure 12</xref> might seem surprising at first sight. <xref rid="RSOS210787F12" ref-type="fig">Figure 12</xref><italic toggle="yes">a</italic> demonstrates that in terms of viral load the peak occurs sooner for influenza, and the value itself taken at this peak is much higher too for influenza compared to COVID-19. On the other hand, if we consider the number of infected cells, <xref rid="RSOS210787F12" ref-type="fig">figure 12</xref><italic toggle="yes">b</italic> represents temporal behaviours—and in particular peak values—that in some sense seem like the opposite of the previous observations made for virus concentration. In more detail, the peak of the number of infected cells is much higher for COVID-19 than the respective value for influenza; however, in terms of time to peak, influenza remains the ‘faster’ virus out of the two by reaching its maximum in less than 2 days.</p>
                  <p>The intriguing features pointed out above will be addressed in more detail after the following discussion of spatial patterns.</p>
                  <p>Figures <xref rid="RSOS210787F13" ref-type="fig">13</xref> and <xref rid="RSOS210787F14" ref-type="fig">14</xref> demonstrate the distributional patterns of influenza and SARS-CoV-2 propagation. Comparing <xref rid="RSOS210787F13" ref-type="fig">figure 13</xref> with <xref rid="RSOS210787F14" ref-type="fig">figure 14</xref>, it is apparent that while both COVID-19 and influenza propagation tend to show spatial patterns that, roughly speaking, resemble flocks or well-outlined explosions, the sharpness itself of this phenomenon is slightly weaker in the case of COVID-19. In particular, we refer to <xref rid="RSOS210787F13" ref-type="fig">figure 13</xref><italic toggle="yes">b</italic> versus <xref rid="RSOS210787F14" ref-type="fig">figure 14</xref><italic toggle="yes">c</italic>: if these images are approached as terrain levels, then the land described by influenza generally seems to have larger gradients in terms of topographic contour lines. We note that this becomes even more apparent for higher diffusion values, where we see rather homogeneous, blurry spatial patterns for SARS-CoV-2, while influenza infection preserves sharper frontlines. We provide supplementary images dedicated to exploring the model’s sensitivity to different diffusion parameters in our public github repository [<xref rid="RSOS210787C12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], where we also share further visual data to grasp the infection dynamics.
<fig position="float" id="RSOS210787F13"><label>Figure 13<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label><caption><p>Simulated spatio-temporal numerical solutions captured (<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>) 16 h, (<italic toggle="yes">b</italic>) 24 h, (<italic toggle="yes">c</italic>) 48 h and (<italic toggle="yes">d</italic>) 64 h after influenza infection. The computations were performed by means of the hybrid PDE–ABM model using <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM51"><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">min</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>. Infected, healthy and dead cells (denoted by red, green and black squares, respectively) are shown on the left, while virus spread is depicted on the right in all four panels (<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>–<italic toggle="yes">d</italic>). The colour bar is understood in virus copies per ml per cell (<xref rid="RSOS210787TB3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsos210787f13" position="float"/></fig>
<fig position="float" id="RSOS210787F14"><label>Figure 14<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label><caption><p>Simulated spatio-temporal numerical solutions captured (<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>) 32 h, (<italic toggle="yes">b</italic>) 40 h, (<italic toggle="yes">c</italic>) 56 h and (<italic toggle="yes">d</italic>) 88 h after SARS-CoV-2 infection. The computations were performed by means of the hybrid PDE–ABM model using <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM52"><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">min</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>. Infected, healthy and dead cells (denoted by red, green and black squares, respectively) are shown on the left, while virus spread is depicted on the right in all four panels (<italic toggle="yes">a</italic>–<italic toggle="yes">d</italic>). The colour bar is understood in virus copies per ml per cell (<xref rid="RSOS210787TB3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsos210787f14" position="float"/></fig></p>
                  <p>We finish this section with emphasizing the significance of the hybrid PDE–ABM model by revisiting the results presented in connection with <xref rid="RSOS210787F12" ref-type="fig">figure 12</xref> and observing them in a new light—in particular, we explore how the detailed spatio-temporal layouts given in figures <xref rid="RSOS210787F13" ref-type="fig">13</xref> and <xref rid="RSOS210787F14" ref-type="fig">14</xref> contribute to a better understanding of the original functions of (and questions behind) <xref rid="RSOS210787F12" ref-type="fig">figure 12</xref>.</p>
                  <p>As we have seen in the discussion of <xref rid="RSOS210787F12" ref-type="fig">figure 12</xref>, the number of infected cells have a significantly smaller peak value for influenza compared to COVID-19. The new information regarding spatial patterns in figures <xref rid="RSOS210787F13" ref-type="fig">13</xref> and <xref rid="RSOS210787F14" ref-type="fig">14</xref> gives insight into what really happens in the background. The fact that the ratio of red and black agents can be so high for SARS-CoV-2, while it always remains relatively low for influenza suggests that influenza-infected cells do not live nearly as long as cells infected by SARS-CoV-2 (in fact, this is supported by the <italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">D</italic></sub> values of <xref rid="RSOS210787TB3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>).</p>
                  <p>Carefully comparing figures <xref rid="RSOS210787F13" ref-type="fig">13</xref> and <xref rid="RSOS210787F14" ref-type="fig">14</xref> can also help us identify a reason why the (quick) viral load peak is higher for influenza in <xref rid="RSOS210787F12" ref-type="fig">figure 12</xref> when its cell-analogue is clearly higher for COVID-19. We begin by exploring what happens on the level of virus concentration when we have (approximately) the same amount of infected cells. In particular, figures <xref rid="RSOS210787F13" ref-type="fig">13</xref><italic toggle="yes">b</italic> and <xref rid="RSOS210787F14" ref-type="fig">14</xref><italic toggle="yes">b</italic> are both scenarios where we seem to have approximately the same amount of infected cells, and at the same time the difference between the corresponding virus concentration images is strikingly apparent. This suggests that the key feature behind the originally mentioned phenomenon might be a difference between the strength of the respective viral source functions—this is in fact verified by the <italic toggle="yes">f</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic>,<italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub> values of <xref rid="RSOS210787TB3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>. Hence, these observations are significant not just in themselves, but also examples of biological insights provided by the hybrid PDE–ABM model.</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s4">
              <label>4<x xml:space="preserve">. </x></label>
              <title>Discussion</title>
              <p>In this paper, we have applied two different models for investigating the dynamical aspects of virus spread. The first model we considered was a hybrid PDE–ABM system, which is essentially a result of merging a discrete state space representing epithelial cells with a continuous reaction–diffusion equation grasping virus concentration. At the same time, we have used the so-called May–Nowak system—a well-known version of the classical ODE model—as a reference system. As for theoretical completeness, we provide a rigorous analysis of both models in the appendices, including a well-posedness result related to the hybrid model and the study of the ODE model’s temporal dynamics.</p>
              <p>The hybrid model’s computational implementation and the careful exploration of its results are in some sense the heart of our work—we highlight that our program code is based on a free and open source Java library, HAL [<xref rid="RSOS210787C10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], commonly used for oncology modelling.</p>
              <p>Compared to the ODE system, both the decisive advantages and the main difficulties of the hybrid model are naturally related to the PDE–ABM system’s added (and quite high-level) complexity: the inclusion of spatial effects. On the one hand, the limiting factors of this model include an increased computational demand and the fact that it is virtually impossible to consider a really large number of cells on an ordinary computer (we worked with a slice of tissue consisting of 4 × 10<sup>4</sup> cells). On the other hand, however, this hybrid model provides us with the invaluable spatial distribution of infection spread: by running simulations for influenza and SARS-CoV-2 propagation, the results of our spatio-temporal PDE–ABM system suggested that influenza seems to generate sharper frontlines in virus concentration than COVID-19 does; moreover, especially for higher diffusion values, COVID-19 visibly spreads in a more homogeneous manner compared to influenza. This simply would not have been possible using the ODE model as the latter is defined only in time. The ODE system represents a scenario where all cells can interact with all virus particles, or in other words, it implicitly assumes an infinite diffusion coefficient in some sense. Real-life viruses however clearly have a finite diffusion rate. This also means that if the specific virus in question has a relatively low diffusion rate, then the ODE model’s predictions regarding infection dynamics will be less accurate: the lower the diffusion coefficient, the more important it is to apply the more complex and more suitable spatial hybrid model. This phenomenon can be observed in <xref rid="RSOS210787F8" ref-type="fig">figure 8</xref>: a small diffusion value results in great differences between the respective solutions of the PDE–ABM system and the ODE model (<xref rid="RSOS210787M2x3" ref-type="disp-formula">2.3</xref>), while the solutions are indeed close to each other for a larger diffusion value.</p>
              <p>In terms of verifying the accuracy and correctness of our proposed model, we highlight the results of §3.2.1—we have relatively successfully recreated the real results of a scientific <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> experiment: our computer-simulated results matched the actual events and features of infection spread on a satisfactory level. Regarding correctness, we refer to <xref rid="RSOS210787F10" ref-type="fig">figure 10</xref> as well: about 30% to 50% of the epithelial cells are destroyed in the upper respiratory system at the peak of infection, which corresponds to the observations of [<xref rid="RSOS210787C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="RSOS210787C17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].</p>
              <p>As for possible further improvements and applications of our hybrid spatial model, we mention two main points. Firstly, fine-tuning features such as immune response processes, time delay between infection and virus production, and the phenomenon of cell regeneration are ignored in our current study. These can be the subject of possible future work, although we note that the present model itself can also be considered to be highly realistic in specific cases where some of the above mentioned elements are naturally negligible (e.g. at the short early phase of an infection the immune system has typically not responded yet, while the time frame is too short for cell regeneration to be relevant). Secondly, we plan to apply the hybrid system for parameter fitting analogously as [<xref rid="RSOS210787C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] used the ODE model for a similar task for the case of influenza A. In more detail, the authors of [<xref rid="RSOS210787C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] calculated a best fit of the ODE model using experimental data on viral load—they extracted viral kinetic parameters such as infection rate, virus production rate, viral clearance rate and the half-life of free infectious viruses. We simulated the corresponding scenario with both systems and—as expected, considering the relatively low diffusion value set for influenza—there was an apparent difference between the respective numerical solutions of the ODE model and the hybrid system. According to our results, [<xref rid="RSOS210787C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] somewhat underestimates the <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sub>0</sub> value: as <xref rid="RSOS210787F10" ref-type="fig">figure 10</xref> shows, in order to obtain a solution with the PDE–ABM model that corresponds to the ODE solution (and hence to the real curve), it seems that the <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sub>0</sub> value of the hybrid model needs to be higher than the value estimated by [<xref rid="RSOS210787C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] to fit the experimental data. This is another example of how the assumption of homogeneous virus spread can be misleading—the kinetic values obtained by Baccam <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic> [<xref rid="RSOS210787C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] could be adjusted towards their real biological value by means of the hybrid PDE–ABM model. Thus, parameter estimation and fitting the stochastic hybrid model to various virological data is something we also consider as valuable future work.</p>
              <p>The complex hybrid approach allows our model to capture fundamental physical processes such as diffusion. We have seen that this is paramount in analysing spatio-temporal virus spread, but we emphasize that virus diffusion itself is not the only example for this feature’s significance. Future works using this framework may consider immune response or antiviral drugs. For the latter, drug diffusion is essential, since spatial heterogeneity naturally arises as the drug enters the tissue through the capillary network. Hence, the diffusive property has a key role in the analysis of antiviral drug effectiveness, which can be precisely evaluated only in a spatio-temporal context, and our proposed model can be of great use for assessing potential COVID-19 treatment strategies.</p>
              <p>Our final synopsis is that the hybrid PDE–ABM model is better suited for thorough and detailed virus spread assessment than the classical ODE system. Following virus propagation on an individual cellular level and taking important spatial effects into account result in a more accurate and complete picture regarding the infection’s outcome. Even though the additional integrated details clearly come at a price in terms of computational demand, this pays off very well in the form of information on spatial virus distribution and more accurate predictions.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
              <title>Supplementary Material</title>
              <supplementary-material position="float" content-type="local-data">
                <media xlink:href="rsos210787_review_history.pdf">
                  <caption>
                    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
                  </caption>
                </media>
              </supplementary-material>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <sec id="s5">
              <title>Data accessibility</title>
              <p>Data and relevant code for this research work are stored in GitHub: <uri xlink:href="https://github.com/sadeghmarzban/Hybrid-PDE-ABM-for-viral-dynamics">https://github.com/sadeghmarzban/Hybrid-PDE-ABM-for-viral-dynamics</uri> and have been archived within the Zenodo repository: <uri xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4758518">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4758518</uri>.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s6">
              <title>Authors' contributions</title>
              <p>Conceptualization: G.R.; theoretical analysis: R.H., G.R.; software development, numerical simulations, visualization: S.M.; supervision: G.R.; literature review: all authors; writing: N.J.; mathematical modelling: all authors; reviewing and editing: all authors.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s7">
              <title>Competing interests</title>
              <p>We declare we have no competing interests.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s8">
              <title>Funding</title>
              <p>R.H. acknowledges the financial support from Youth Foundation of Zhejiang University of Science and Technology (grant nos. 2021QN001, 2021QN046). S.M. and R.H. were supported by Hungarian grant NKFIH KKP 129877. N.J. was supported by EFOP-3.6.1-16-2016-00008 and TUDFO/47138-1/2019-ITM. G.R. was supported by NKFIH FK 124016 and 2020-2.1.1-ED-2020-0000.</p>
            </sec>
            <app-group>
              <app>
                <title>Appendix A. Technical details related to parameter values</title>
                <p>This appendix is dedicated to important practical details related to the calculation of the numerical data presented in tables <xref rid="RSOS210787TB2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and <xref rid="RSOS210787TB3" ref-type="table">3</xref>.</p>
                <p>We begin with the ODE model’s parameter setting which is summed up in <xref rid="RSOS210787TB2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>. The parameters representing influenza and COVID-19 are defined according to [<xref rid="RSOS210787C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="RSOS210787C14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], respectively. We detail two technical considerations we used during the parametrization process. (i) Firstly, in order to make sure that the respective results of the ODE system and the hybrid model are comparable, we need to initialize them with the same number of healthy cells. Due to the high computational load of the latter system, this number is naturally limited—in our case, we use <italic toggle="yes">H</italic><sub>0</sub> = 4 × 10<sup>4</sup>. However, this number is lower than the number of healthy cells used in [<xref rid="RSOS210787C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="RSOS210787C14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], which is problematic as it affects the value of <italic toggle="yes">R</italic><sub>0</sub>. Hence, to counterbalance the impact of the different <italic toggle="yes">H</italic><sub>0</sub> value, we modify the value of <italic toggle="yes">β</italic> correspondingly. (ii) Secondly, the viral load for influenza in [<xref rid="RSOS210787C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] is given in <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM53"><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">TCID</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>50</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">ml</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> units, while [<xref rid="RSOS210787C14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>] specifies the viral load index for COVID-19 in copies ml<sup>−1</sup>. To overcome this, we apply the results of [<xref rid="RSOS210787C19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], we assume that a TCID<sub>50</sub> unit corresponds to 2 × 10<sup>3</sup> viral copies and we change the <italic toggle="yes">β</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> values in the influenza parameter setting correspondingly.</p>
                <p>As for the hybrid PDE–ABM model, the exact parameter values we use during the simulations are given in <xref rid="RSOS210787TB3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>. With the exception of the diffusion coefficient, all of the hybrid model’s parameter values have been calculated indirectly: we used the ODE parameters as a starting point and we combined these with the results detailed in <xref rid="RSOS210787TB1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>—knowing the formal connection between the respective ODE and PDE–ABM parameters we can easily obtain the hybrid parameters in question.</p>
                <p>We also point out a significant difference between the units of <xref rid="RSOS210787TB1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref> (§2) and <xref rid="RSOS210787TB3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref> (§3.2). While in the more theoretical §2, we conveniently used abstract units such as <italic toggle="yes">σ</italic><sup>2</sup>/<italic toggle="yes">τ</italic>, in §3.2.2 dedicated to specific applications all units become concrete (e.g. <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM54"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">min</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>). This raises an interesting technical question—the relationship between the real-life space unit μm and the abstract space unit <italic toggle="yes">σ</italic> still internally used within the implementation. In the present article, we use the physiologically accurate <italic toggle="yes">σ</italic> = 14 μm setting.</p>
                <p>Finally, we highlight two intriguing aspects of the diffusion coefficients.</p>
                <p>
                  <list list-type="simple">
                    <list-item>
                      <label>(i)<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label>
                      <p><bold>Uncertainty.</bold> There is scarce information on the diffusion coefficients in the literature, and the specific values vary depending on environmental factors as well. As a guideline, in <xref rid="RSOS210787TB3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>, we use the estimates of [<xref rid="RSOS210787C11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="RSOS210787C15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Due to the similar size of virions, we apply the same <italic toggle="yes">D</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">V</italic></sub> value—specifically, <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM55"><mml:mn>0.65</mml:mn><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>—in our simulations both for influenza and SARS-CoV-2. The sensitivity to the respective parameter choice is explored through the supplementary images available in our github repository [<xref rid="RSOS210787C12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item>
                      <label>(ii)<x xml:space="preserve"> </x></label>
                      <p><bold>Unit conversion.</bold> Diffusion values are normally given in units <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM56"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>. To be used in HAL [<xref rid="RSOS210787C10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], the <italic toggle="yes">D</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">V</italic></sub> values need to be converted into dimensionless numbers, adjusting them to the respective units used by the software. As the unit space <italic toggle="yes">σ</italic> in HAL corresponds to 14 μm, we have
<disp-formula id="RSOS210787MA1"><label>A 1</label><mml:math id="DM16" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>60</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mn>14</mml:mn><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">min</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula>In our simulations (see [<xref rid="RSOS210787C12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]), we investigated the dynamics generated by diffusion values of <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM57"><mml:mn>0.1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>…</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.9</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">min</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>—in particular, the results communicated in the main text were obtained with <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM58"><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">min</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.65</mml:mn><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">m</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                </p>
              </app>
              <app>
                <title>Appendix B. The well-posedness and ultimate boundedness of the PDE model</title>
                <p>In this appendix, we establish the global existence and ultimate boundedness of the virus concentration function described by equation (<xref rid="RSOS210787M2x1" ref-type="disp-formula">2.1</xref>). We make the following suitable assumption:
<disp-formula id="RSOS210787UM4"><mml:math id="DM17" display="block"><mml:mtable columnalign="right left" rowspacing=".5em" columnspacing="thickmathspace"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="bold">H</mml:mi><mml:mn mathvariant="bold">1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo mathvariant="bold" stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∞</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∩</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∞</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∞</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">is</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">non</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>-</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">negative</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">for</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">each</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">J</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">and</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula></p>
                <statement id="st1">
                  <title>Theorem B.1 (Well-posedness and ultimate boundedness).</title>
                  <p><italic toggle="yes">Let</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="IM59"><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mo>⊂</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="double-struck">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula><italic toggle="yes">be a bounded domain with smooth boundary. Suppose that the parameters</italic><italic toggle="yes">D</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">V</italic></sub>, <italic toggle="yes">μ</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">V</italic></sub><italic toggle="yes">are positive. Then for a non-negative initial value function</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="IM60"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula><italic toggle="yes">system</italic> (<italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="RSOS210787M2x1" ref-type="disp-formula">2.1</xref></italic>) <italic toggle="yes">has a unique non-negative global solution</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">h</italic></sup>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">y</italic>) <italic toggle="yes">defined on</italic>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="IM61"><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∞</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. <italic toggle="yes">Moreover, the solution</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">h</italic></sup>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">y</italic>) <italic toggle="yes">is ultimately bounded and satisfies</italic>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="IM62"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">limsup</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">→</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∞</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">max</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mo accent="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>, <italic toggle="yes">where</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">B</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">is defined in</italic> (<italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="RSOS210787MB1" ref-type="disp-formula">B 1</xref></italic>).</p>
                </statement>
                <statement id="st2">
                  <title>Proof.</title>
                  <p>We use the lower–upper solution method for our proof. According to <bold>(H<sub>1</sub>)</bold>, we define
<disp-formula id="RSOS210787MB1"><label>B 1</label><mml:math id="DM18" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∥</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">J</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∥</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∞</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∞</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula>Let <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM63"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">sup</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Ω</mml:mi><mml:mo accent="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>:</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">and</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo></mml:munder><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mstyle></mml:math></inline-formula>. Since
<disp-formula id="RSOS210787MB2"><label>B 2</label><mml:math id="DM19" display="block"><mml:mtable columnalign="right left" rowspacing=".5em" columnspacing="thickmathspace"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∂</mml:mi><mml:mover><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo accent="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∂</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Δ</mml:mi><mml:mover><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo accent="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo accent="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo movablelimits="false">∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">J</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>and
<disp-formula id="RSOS210787MB3"><label>B 3</label><mml:math id="DM20" display="block"><mml:mtable columnalign="right left" rowspacing=".5em" columnspacing="thickmathspace"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∂</mml:mi><mml:munder><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo></mml:munder><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∂</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Δ</mml:mi><mml:munder><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo></mml:munder><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:munder><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo></mml:munder><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo movablelimits="false">∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">J</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo movablelimits="false">∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">J</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>Clearly, the boundary condition satisfies <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM64"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∂</mml:mi><mml:mover><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo accent="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∂</mml:mi><mml:mi>ν</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∂</mml:mi><mml:munder><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo></mml:munder></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∂</mml:mi><mml:mi>ν</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and the initial condition satisfies <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM65"><mml:mover><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo accent="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo movablelimits="true">sup</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo></mml:munder><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>. Thus <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM66"><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo accent="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo></mml:munder><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> is a pair of coupled upper solution and lower solution of system (<xref rid="RSOS210787M2x1" ref-type="disp-formula">2.1</xref>). From (<bold>H<sub>1</sub></bold>), we get that the function <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM67"><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">J</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> is Hölder continuous with exponent <italic toggle="yes">α</italic> with respect to <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">x</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">y</italic> on <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM68"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM69"><mml:msub><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM70"><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM71"><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">min</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:munder><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo></mml:munder><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM72"><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">max</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo accent="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>. In view of [<xref rid="RSOS210787C20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, theorem 2.4.6], system (<xref rid="RSOS210787M2x1" ref-type="disp-formula">2.1</xref>) has a unique solution defined on <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM73"><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> satisfying
<disp-formula id="RSOS210787MB4"><label>B 4</label><mml:math id="DM21" display="block"><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula>By the arbitrariness of <italic toggle="yes">T</italic>, the solution of system (<xref rid="RSOS210787M2x1" ref-type="disp-formula">2.1</xref>) exists globally in time. Clearly, from the definition of <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM74"><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>, we know that <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM75"><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>⋆</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">max</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo fence="false" stretchy="false">{</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo movablelimits="true">sup</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo fence="false" stretchy="false">}</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>. Then it follows from (<xref rid="RSOS210787MB4" ref-type="disp-formula">B 4</xref>) that <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM76"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">limsup</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">→</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∞</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">max</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mo accent="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>, which ends the proof of the theorem. ▪</p>
                </statement>
                <p>In fact, since <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM77"><mml:munder><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">J</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∞</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>, it follows from the regularity theory of parabolic equations that system (<xref rid="RSOS210787M2x1" ref-type="disp-formula">2.1</xref>) has a unique classical solution <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM78"><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∞</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>. Here, the lower–upper solution method is mainly employed to estimate the upper bound of virus particles in the whole spatial domain <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM79"><mml:mi>Ω</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> as time evolves.</p>
              </app>
              <app>
                <title>Appendix C. The well-posedness and boundedness of the ODE model</title>
                <statement id="st3">
                  <title>Theorem C.1.</title>
                  <p><italic toggle="yes">Let us suppose</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="IM80"><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>Γ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula><italic toggle="yes">for our initial data. Then system</italic> (<italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="RSOS210787M2x3" ref-type="disp-formula">2.3</xref></italic>) <italic toggle="yes">has a unique solution</italic>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="IM81"><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>∈</mml:mo><mml:mi>Γ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, <italic toggle="yes">i.e</italic>. <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM82"><mml:mi>Γ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>
<italic toggle="yes">is positively invariant. Furthermore, the solution of system</italic> (<italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="RSOS210787M2x3" ref-type="disp-formula">2.3</xref></italic>) <italic toggle="yes">satisfies</italic>
<disp-formula id="RSOS210787MC1"><label>C 1</label><mml:math id="DM22" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable columnalign="left left" rowspacing=".5em" columnspacing="thickmathspace"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">limsup</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">→</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∞</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">limsup</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">→</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∞</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">min</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo fence="false" stretchy="false">{</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo fence="false" stretchy="false">}</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><italic toggle="yes">where</italic>
<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> = <italic toggle="yes">H</italic><sub>0</sub> + <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sub>0</sub> + <italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>0</sub> + <italic toggle="yes">D</italic><sub>0</sub>.</p>
                </statement>
                <statement id="st4">
                  <title>Proof.</title>
                  <p><bold>Existence and uniqueness.</bold> By the continuity of the right-hand side of equation (<xref rid="RSOS210787M2x3" ref-type="disp-formula">2.3</xref>), system (<xref rid="RSOS210787M2x3" ref-type="disp-formula">2.3</xref>) has at least one solution in [0, <italic toggle="yes">b</italic>) with 0 &lt; <italic toggle="yes">b</italic> ≤ ∞. Since the term on the right-hand side of system (<xref rid="RSOS210787M2x3" ref-type="disp-formula">2.3</xref>) satisfies the local Lipschitz property with respect to <italic toggle="yes">H</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">V</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">D</italic> in <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM83"><mml:mi>Γ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, the uniqueness of solutions follows from the standard theory of ordinary differential equations.</p>
                  <p><bold>Positive invariance and boundedness</bold><bold>.</bold> For <italic toggle="yes">H</italic> ≥ 0, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic> ≥ 0, <italic toggle="yes">V</italic> ≥ 0, <italic toggle="yes">D</italic> ≥ 0, since
<disp-formula id="RSOS210787MC2"><label>C 2</label><mml:math id="DM23" display="block"><mml:mtable columnalign="right left" rowspacing=".5em" columnspacing="thickmathspace"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo fence="false" stretchy="false">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo fence="false" stretchy="false">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo fence="false" stretchy="false">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo fence="false" stretchy="false">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>it follows from [<xref rid="RSOS210787C21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, theorem 5.2.1] that the solution (<italic toggle="yes">H</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">I</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">V</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">D</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>)) of system (<xref rid="RSOS210787M2x3" ref-type="disp-formula">2.3</xref>) is non-negative for all <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> ≥ 0 whenever <italic toggle="yes">H</italic><sub>0</sub> ≥ 0, <italic toggle="yes">I</italic><sub>0</sub> ≥ 0, <italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>0</sub> ≥ 0, <italic toggle="yes">D</italic><sub>0</sub> ≥ 0. Therefore, <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM84"><mml:mi>Γ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is positively invariant with respect to system (<xref rid="RSOS210787M2x3" ref-type="disp-formula">2.3</xref>).</p>
                  <p>Since <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM85"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, we get 0 ≤ <italic toggle="yes">H</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) ≤ <italic toggle="yes">H</italic><sub>0</sub>. Also from system (<xref rid="RSOS210787M2x3" ref-type="disp-formula">2.3</xref>), we obtain
<disp-formula id="RSOS210787MC3"><label>C 3</label><mml:math id="DM24" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="1em"/><mml:mo stretchy="false">⇒</mml:mo><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula>As <italic toggle="yes">H</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) ≥ 0, <italic toggle="yes">D</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) ≥ 0, we get <italic toggle="yes">I</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) ≤ <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> − <italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>0</sub>. From the third equation of system (<xref rid="RSOS210787M2x3" ref-type="disp-formula">2.3</xref>), we have
<disp-formula id="RSOS210787UM5"><mml:math id="DM25" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula>which implies that
<disp-formula id="RSOS210787MC4"><label>C 4</label><mml:math id="DM26" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">limsup</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">→</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∞</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula>From (<xref rid="RSOS210787MC4" ref-type="disp-formula">C 4</xref>), we know that for any <italic toggle="yes">ɛ</italic> &gt; 0 there exists <italic toggle="yes">T</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">ɛ</italic>) &gt; 0, such that when <italic toggle="yes">t</italic> ≥ <italic toggle="yes">T</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">ɛ</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">V</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) ≤ (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">N</italic> − <italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>0</sub>)/<italic toggle="yes">c</italic>) + <italic toggle="yes">ɛ</italic>. Thus
<disp-formula id="RSOS210787UM6"><mml:math id="DM27" display="block"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula>By the comparison principle of ordinary differential equations, we get
<disp-formula id="RSOS210787MC5"><label>C 5</label><mml:math id="DM28" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">limsup</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">→</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∞</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula>Since <italic toggle="yes">I</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>) ≤ <italic toggle="yes">N</italic> − <italic toggle="yes">V</italic><sub>0</sub>, we get <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM86"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">limsup</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">→</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">∞</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>≤</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">min</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo fence="false" stretchy="false">{</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo> </mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo fence="false" stretchy="false">}</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>. This completes the proof. ▪</p>
                </statement>
              </app>
              <app>
                <title>Appendix D. The threshold dynamics of the ODE model</title>
                <p>The basic reproduction number <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM87"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> can be deduced by simple reasoning: a single infected cell produces virus with rate <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> during its expected lifetime 1/<italic toggle="yes">δ</italic>, summing up to <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>/<italic toggle="yes">δ</italic> viruses. Virus particles generate infected cells (in a healthy cell population) with rate <italic toggle="yes">βH</italic><sub>0</sub>, in an expected time period 1/<italic toggle="yes">c</italic>. Overall, we find the number of new infected cells originated from the initial cell as given in (<xref rid="RSOS210787M2x4" ref-type="disp-formula">2.4</xref>). For a more formal derivation, one can also use the next generation approach [<xref rid="RSOS210787C22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p>
                <statement id="st5">
                  <title>Theorem D.1.</title>
                  <p><italic toggle="yes">If</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="IM88"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>, <italic toggle="yes">then the disease-free equilibrium of the form</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="IM89"><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula><italic toggle="yes">is unstable, where</italic><italic toggle="yes">H</italic><sub>0</sub> &gt; 0, <italic toggle="yes">D</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">s</italic></sub>
<italic toggle="yes">being an arbitrary non</italic><italic toggle="yes">-</italic><italic toggle="yes">negative constant. This means an infection can be established. Furthermore, system</italic> (<italic toggle="yes"><xref rid="RSOS210787M2x3" ref-type="disp-formula">2.3</xref></italic>) <italic toggle="yes">cannot undergo a Hopf bifurcation around</italic>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="IM90"><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                </statement>
                <statement id="st6">
                  <title>Proof.</title>
                  <p>The Jacobian matrix <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM91"><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> around the disease-free equilibrium <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM92"><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is given by
<disp-formula id="RSOS210787MD1"><label>D 1</label><mml:math id="DM29" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mi>J</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mtable rowspacing="4pt" columnspacing="1em"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula>Thus the characteristic equation can be calculated as
<disp-formula id="RSOS210787MD2"><label>D 2</label><mml:math id="DM30" display="block"><mml:msup><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula>which has eigenvalues <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM93"><mml:msub><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>±</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Clearly, if <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM94"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="script">R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> then <italic toggle="yes">λ</italic><sub>3</sub> &gt; 0 and <italic toggle="yes">λ</italic><sub>4</sub> &lt; 0, i.e. the characteristic equation (D 2) has a positive real eigenvalue, which indicates that <inline-formula><mml:math id="IM95"><mml:msub><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>∗</mml:mo></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is unstable. In addition, it is easy to see that there are no pairs of purely imaginary roots in characteristic equation (D 2) for any variational parameter, which implies that a Hopf bifurcation cannot occur. This completes the proof of the theorem. ▪</p>
                </statement>
              </app>
            </app-group>
            <ref-list>
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="RSOS210787C1">
                <label>1<x xml:space="preserve">.</x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>May</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2000</year><source>Virus dynamics: mathematical principles of immunology and virology</source>. <publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSOS210787C2">
                <label>2<x xml:space="preserve">.</x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Baccam</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beauchemin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Macken</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hayden</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Perelson</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2006</year><article-title>Kinetics of influenza A virus infection in humans</article-title>. <source>J. Virol.</source><volume><bold>80</bold></volume>, <fpage>7590</fpage>-<lpage>7599</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.01623-05</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16840338</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSOS210787C3">
                <label>3<x xml:space="preserve">.</x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Peter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dittrich</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>B</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2021</year><article-title>Structure and hierarchy of SARS-CoV-2 infection dynamics models revealed by reaction network analysis</article-title>. <source>Viruses</source><volume><bold>13</bold></volume>, <fpage>14</fpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/v13010014</pub-id>)</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSOS210787C4">
                <label>4<x xml:space="preserve">.</x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Macal</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>North</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2005</year><article-title>Tutorial on agent-based modeling and simulation</article-title>. In <conf-name>Proc. Winter Simulation Conf</conf-name>., <conf-loc>Orlando, FL, USA</conf-loc>, <conf-date>4 December 2005</conf-date>, <fpage>p. 14</fpage>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>IEEE</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSOS210787C5">
                <label>5<x xml:space="preserve">.</x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Arduin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>de Cellès</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guillemot</surname><given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Watier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Opatowski</surname><given-names>L</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2017</year><article-title>An agent-based model simulation of influenza interactions at the host level: insight into the influenza-related burden of pneumococcal infections</article-title>. <source>BMC Infect. Dis.</source><volume><bold>17</bold></volume>, <fpage>382</fpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-017-2464-z</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28577533</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSOS210787C6">
                <label>6<x xml:space="preserve">.</x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cilfone</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kirschner</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Linderman</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2015</year><article-title>Strategies for efficient numerical implementation of hybrid multi-scale agent-based models to describe biological systems</article-title>. <source>Cell. Mol. Bioeng.</source><volume><bold>8</bold></volume>, <fpage>119</fpage>-<lpage>136</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12195-014-0363-6</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26366228</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSOS210787C7">
                <label>7<x xml:space="preserve">.</x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bar-On</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Flamholz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Milo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2020</year><article-title>Science Forum: SARS-CoV-2 (COVID-19) by the numbers</article-title>. <source>Elife</source><volume><bold>9</bold></volume>, <fpage>e57309</fpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.57309</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32228860</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSOS210787C8">
                <label>8<x xml:space="preserve">.</x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Carcaterra</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Caruso</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2021</year><article-title>Alveolar epithelial cell type II as main target of SARS-CoV-2 virus and COVID-19 development via NF-Kb pathway deregulation: a physio-pathological theory</article-title>. <source>Med. Hypotheses</source><volume><bold>146</bold></volume>, <fpage>110412</fpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mehy.2020.110412</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33308936</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSOS210787C9">
                <label>9<x xml:space="preserve">.</x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2006</year><article-title>Biology of alveolar type II cells</article-title>. <source>Respirology</source><volume><bold>11</bold></volume>, <fpage>S12</fpage>-<lpage>S15</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1843.2006.00800.x</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16423262</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSOS210787C10">
                <label>10<x xml:space="preserve">.</x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bravo</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></string-name></person-group><italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic><year>2020</year><article-title>Hybrid automata library: a flexible platform for hybrid modeling with real-time visualization</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput. Biol.</source><volume><bold>16</bold></volume>, <fpage>e1007635</fpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1007635</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32155140</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSOS210787C11">
                <label>11<x xml:space="preserve">.</x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Beauchemin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Forrest</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Koster</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2006</year><article-title>Modeling influenza viral dynamics in tissue</article-title>. In <conf-name>Int. Conf. on Artificial Immune Systems</conf-name>, <conf-loc>Oeiras, Portugal</conf-loc>, <conf-date>4–6 September 2006</conf-date>, pp. <fpage>23</fpage>–<lpage>36</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Berlin, Germany</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSOS210787C12">
                <label>12<x xml:space="preserve">.</x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="std"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Marzban</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Juhász</surname><given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Röst</surname><given-names>G</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2021</year><comment>Hybrid PDE-ABM model for viral dynamics</comment>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5281/zenodo.4758518</pub-id>).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSOS210787C13">
                <label>13<x xml:space="preserve">.</x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Outlaw</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></string-name></person-group><italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic><year>2020</year><article-title>Inhibition of Coronavirus entry <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">ex vivo</italic> by a lipid-conjugated peptide derived from the SARS-CoV-2 spike glycoprotein HRC domain</article-title>. <source>MBio</source><volume><bold>11</bold></volume>, <fpage>e01935-20</fpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.01935-20</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33082259</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSOS210787C14">
                <label>14<x xml:space="preserve">.</x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hernandez-Vargas</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Velasco-Hernandez</surname><given-names>JX</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2020</year><article-title>In-host mathematical modelling of COVID-19 in humans</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Control</source><volume><bold>50</bold></volume>, <fpage>448</fpage>-<lpage>456</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arcontrol.2020.09.006</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33020692</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSOS210787C15">
                <label>15<x xml:space="preserve">.</x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sego</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name></person-group><italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic><year>2020</year><article-title>A modular framework for multiscale, multicellular, spatiotemporal modeling of acute primary viral infection and immune response in epithelial tissues and its application to drug therapy timing and effectiveness</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput. Biol.</source><volume><bold>16</bold></volume>, <fpage>e1008451</fpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1008451</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33347439</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSOS210787C16">
                <label>16<x xml:space="preserve">.</x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hernandez-Vargas</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2019</year><source>Modeling and control of infectious diseases in the host: with MATLAB and R</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSOS210787C17">
                <label>17<x xml:space="preserve">.</x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bocharov</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Romanyukha</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>1994</year><article-title>Mathematical model of antiviral immune response III. Influenza A virus infection</article-title>. <source>J. Theor. Biol.</source><volume><bold>167</bold></volume>, <fpage>323</fpage>-<lpage>360</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/jtbi.1994.1074</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7516024</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSOS210787C18">
                <label>18<x xml:space="preserve">.</x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Carrat</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vergu</surname><given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ferguson</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lemaitre</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cauchemez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leach</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Valleron</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2008</year><article-title>Time lines of infection and disease in human influenza: a review of volunteer challenge studies</article-title>. <source>Am. J. Epidemiol.</source><volume><bold>167</bold></volume>, <fpage>775</fpage>-<lpage>785</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwm375</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18230677</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSOS210787C19">
                <label>19<x xml:space="preserve">.</x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Elankumaran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marr</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2011</year><article-title>Concentrations and size distributions of airborne influenza A viruses measured indoors at a health centre, a day-care centre and on aeroplanes</article-title>. <source>J. R. Soc. Interface</source><volume><bold>8</bold></volume>, <fpage>1176</fpage>-<lpage>1184</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsif.2010.0686</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21300628</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSOS210787C20">
                <label>20<x xml:space="preserve">.</x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>QY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>ZY</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>MX</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2011</year><source>Introduction to reaction-diffusion equations</source>. <publisher-loc>Beijing, China</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Science Press</publisher-name><comment>(in Chinese)</comment>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSOS210787C21">
                <label>21<x xml:space="preserve">.</x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2008</year><source>Monotone dynamical systems: an introduction to the theory of competitive and cooperative systems</source>. <publisher-loc>Providence, RI</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>American Mathematical Society</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="RSOS210787C22">
                <label>22<x xml:space="preserve">.</x></label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Van den Driessche</surname><given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Watmough</surname><given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2002</year><article-title>Reproduction numbers and sub-threshold endemic equilibria for compartmental models of disease transmission</article-title>. <source>Math. Biosci.</source><volume><bold>180</bold></volume>, <fpage>29</fpage>-<lpage>48</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0025-5564(02)00108-6</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12387915</pub-id></mixed-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
