<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-03-11T00:47:39Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8565045" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8565045</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-11-03</datestamp>
        <setSpec>pheelsevier</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.xsd" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Physica A</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Physica A</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Physica a</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0378-4371</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">0378-4371</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Elsevier B.V.</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC8565045</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8565045</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">8565045</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34744295</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pii">S0378-4371(21)00839-6</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.physa.2021.126566</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">126566</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>COVID-19 spreading under containment actions</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au000001">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Cornes</surname>
                    <given-names>F.E.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
                  <xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au000002">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Frank</surname>
                    <given-names>G.A.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au000003">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Dorso</surname>
                    <given-names>C.O.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Departamento de Física, Facultad de Ciencias Exactas y Naturales, Universidad de Buenos Aires, Pabellón I, Ciudad Universitaria, 1428 Buenos Aires, Argentina</aff>
                <aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Unidad de Investigación y Desarrollo de las Ingenierías, Universidad Tecnológica Nacional, Facultad Regional Buenos Aires, Av. Medrano 951, 1179 Buenos Aires, Argentina</aff>
                <aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Instituto de Física de Buenos Aires, Pabellón I, Ciudad Universitaria, 1428 Buenos Aires, Argentina</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author.</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>3</day>
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.-->
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <day>15</day>
                <month>2</month>
                <year>2022</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>3</day>
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>588</volume>
              <fpage>126566</fpage>
              <lpage>126566</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>16</day>
                  <month>2</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>15</day>
                  <month>7</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2021 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
                <copyright-holder>Elsevier B.V.</copyright-holder>
                <license>
                  <license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="d1e1499">
                <p>We propose an epidemiological model that explores the effect of human mobility on the spatio-temporal dynamics of the COVID-19 outbreak, in the spirit to those considered in Refs. Barmak et al. (2011, 2016) and Medus and Dorso (2011) <xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. We assume that people move around in a city of 120 × 120 blocks with 300 inhabitants in each block. The mobility pattern is associated to a complex network in which nodes represent blocks while the links represent the traveling path of the individuals (see below). We implemented three confinement strategies in order to mitigate the disease spreading: (1) global confinement, (2) partial restriction to mobility, and (3) localized confinement. In the first case, it was observed that a global isolation policy prevents the massive outbreak of the disease. In the second case, a partial restriction to mobility could lead to a massive contagion if this was not complemented with sanitary measures such as the use of masks and social distancing. Finally, a local isolation policy was proposed, conditioned to the health status of each block. It was observed that this mitigation strategy was able to contain and even reduce the outbreak of the disease by intervening in specific regions of the city according to their level of contagion. It was also observed that this strategy is capable of controlling the epidemic in the case that a certain proportion of those infected are asymptomatic.</p>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group id="d1e1531">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>COVID-19</kwd>
                <kwd>Pandemic</kwd>
                <kwd>Human mobility</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="sec1">
              <label>1</label>
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p id="d1e1550">In the absence of a vaccine, strategies based on non-pharmaceutical interventions were proposed to contain the COVID-19 pandemic. Social distancing policies, specific mobility restrictions and lockdowns, among others, were the more common ones. Such policies should be implemented for long periods (typically months) to avoid re-emergence of the epidemic once lifted. Therefore, quantitative research is still needed to assess the efficacy of non-pharmaceutical interventions and their timings.</p>
              <p id="d1e1552">Many works analyze real-time mobility data in order to relate the changes in the mobility patterns and the disease propagation. Ref. <xref rid="b2" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref> reports a correlation between the mobility pattern and the reduction of new infections. However, a delay of 2–3 weeks exist between both magnitudes due to the incubation period of the disease. Ref. <xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref> also finds that traveling restrictions and social distancing were effective actions (among others) in the containment of the COVID-19 disease in China. Additionally, Ref. <xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref> and Ref. <xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref> analyze the European and US cases, respectively. The later arrives to the conclusion that a small minority of “super-spreader” places are the responsible for the wide propagation of the infection.</p>
              <p id="d1e1571">The changes in the mobility patterns are a consequence of the kind of quarantine. Ref. <xref rid="b6" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, for instance, proposes a special kind of quarantine that reduces the disease infection while allowing the socio-economic activity. In a similar way, Ref. <xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref> proposes a cyclic schedule of 4-days work and 10-days lockdown. An improved version of this strategy can also be found in Ref. <xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. Moreover, Ref. <xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref> concludes that an alternated strategy of lockdown and release will gradually reduce the “cost” of an epidemic, as suggested by the Parrondo’s games.</p>
              <p id="d1e1590">Ref. <xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref> carried out a detailed comparison between the strategies applied in different countries for the disease control. The investigation concluded that either the mobility control, the coordination with neighboring countries and the testing procedures are the key issues for containing and reducing the number of new cases. However, it was also observed in Ref. <xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref> that other social factors, like globalization or extreme centralization, can run the food (or goods) supply to a critical stage.</p>
              <p id="d1e1600">Many other complex scenarios can be found in the literature. For instance, Ref. <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref> analyzes the influence of human behavior on the infectious disease transmission. Refs. <xref rid="b13" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref> focus on the effects of vaccination during the pandemic and the vaccination repurposing, respectively. Ref. <xref rid="b15" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref> studies the potential effectiveness of targeted mass prophylactic use of antiviral drugs as a containment strategy. The role of “super-spreader” events can also be found in Refs. <xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>.</p>
              <p id="d1e1619">Our concern is actually placed on the effectiveness of mobility restrictions. Ref. <xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref> shows real evidence of the consequences of restrictions on the daily records of deaths. These authors state that deaths are expected to diminish after 3–4 weeks of establishing travel restrictions. However, this point has been questioned in the context of limited healthcare resources. Ref. <xref rid="b19" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref> considers a scenario of limitations in the availability of mechanical ventilators, among other resources. They notice that early mobility restrictions are useful while upgrading the healthcare capacity (short-term efficiency), but do not necessarily ensure a long term reduction of deaths.</p>
              <p id="d1e1629">The mobility restrictions may also apply to quite different scales. In a quite enlightening work, in Ref. <xref rid="b20" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref> the authors developed a dual network, attaining for short-scale and long scale mobilities (say, the land commuting system and the airline traffic, respectively). Both exhibit different dynamics, and thus, the mobility restrictions are expected to differ according to the global or local context. Further considerations on topological issues were explored in Refs. <xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, <xref rid="b22" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>.</p>
              <p id="d1e1639">In this work we consider the spread of a disease mimicking the COVID-19. We propose a simple model of a city consisting of a square lattice of N<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1642" display="inline" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mo>×</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>N nodes. Each node represents a block populated, at the start of the simulations, by M agents. Some of the agents will remain in the block while others will move around in the city (see Section <xref rid="sec2" ref-type="sec">2</xref> for full description). This agents will be subjected to a SEIR kind of epidemic dynamics. We simulated and compared different confinement strategies in order to mitigate the disease propagation. We limit our investigation to the mobility within the city area. We emphasize, however, that our analysis focuses on the containment strategies at the level of a city like the one we live in, and in which this kind of containment has been (partially) applied.</p>
              <p id="d1e1651">In Section <xref rid="sec2" ref-type="sec">2</xref> we detail the characteristics of our epidemiological model and the different mitigation strategies. Section <xref rid="sec3" ref-type="sec">3</xref> describes the simulation procedure. Section <xref rid="sec4" ref-type="sec">4</xref> displays the results of our investigation, while Section <xref rid="sec5" ref-type="sec">5</xref> is dedicated to the discussion of the main results. The conclusions are drawn in Section <xref rid="sec6" ref-type="sec">6</xref>.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec2">
              <label>2</label>
              <title>The epidemiological model</title>
              <p id="d1e1684">There are three main ingredients in the description of the COVID-19 contagion and spatial spreading: the scenario where the process takes place (Section <xref rid="sec2.1" ref-type="sec">2.1</xref>), the mobility patterns of the individuals (Section <xref rid="sec2.2" ref-type="sec">2.2</xref>) and the epidemiological dynamics of the individuals (Section <xref rid="sec2.3" ref-type="sec">2.3</xref>).</p>
              <sec id="sec2.1">
                <label>2.1</label>
                <title>The stage</title>
                <p id="d1e1707">
                  <italic>City</italic>
                </p>
                <p id="d1e1710">The simulation of the evolution of COVID-19 is performed in a schematic city in which the basic unit is the block. The city is represented by an homogeneous urban area of <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1713" display="inline" altimg="si48.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>120</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">×</mml:mo><mml:mn>120</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> blocks placed in a square grid. The size of each block is <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1723" display="inline" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
 m<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1731" display="inline" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
 m. The simulated grid corresponds to a big city, like Buenos Aires, Argentina. Each block hosts 300 people but this quantity may vary during the day (see next Section). The total population of the simulated city is 4.32 M similar to the Ciudad Autonoma de Buenos Aires’ population.</p>
                <p id="d1e1743">
                  <italic>Network construction</italic>
                </p>
                <p id="d1e1746">The human mobility pattern between the blocks is accomplished by building a weighted and directed network. The nodes represent the blocks, while the links represent the human mobility from one block to another one. We consider two different links: short and long links.</p>
                <p id="d1e1748">Each node is linked with its first neighbors by a short link, as we illustrate in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1(a)</xref>. They represent the human mobility pattern between all neighboring blocks. Notice that these links generate a connected graph. As we will see later, this characteristic of the network will allow the disease to reach all parts of the city (as long as it is not locked during the epidemic).</p>
                <p id="d1e1754">On the other side, recent investigation on human mobility shows that the traveling lengths of the individuals follows a Levy distribution given by <xref rid="b23" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>
<disp-formula id="fd1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="d1e1767" display="block" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">∝</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1805" display="inline" altimg="si6.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> stands for the probability that an individual reaches a distance <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1819" display="inline" altimg="si7.svg"><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1824" display="inline" altimg="si8.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
 m and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1841" display="inline" altimg="si9.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>75</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> correspond to empirical parameters.</p>
                <p id="d1e1854">We built a network of long links following the Levy mobility pattern. This network is illustrated in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1(b)</xref>. The procedure was as follows<fig id="fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Schematic representation of a city network. The city is composed by 120 × 120 blocks placed on a square grid. They are linked by (a) four short links connecting neighboring nodes and (b) long links connecting far away nodes (see text for more details). The city corresponds to the union of these two sub-networks.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="d1e1862">
                  <list list-type="simple" id="d1e1864">
                    <list-item id="lst1">
                      <label>1.</label>
                      <p id="d1e1868">We randomly chose a node.</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item id="lst2">
                      <label>2.</label>
                      <p id="d1e1873">We then select randomly (according to the Levy distribution) the length <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1876" display="inline" altimg="si7.svg"><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> of the next link.</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item id="lst3">
                      <label>3.</label>
                      <p id="d1e1883">We link the node from step 1 to any (random) node located at the distance <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1886" display="inline" altimg="si7.svg"><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> in any direction.</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                </p>
                <p id="d1e1890">Notice that each node may have more than one <italic>long link</italic>. Recall that these links are complementary to the short links connecting neighboring blocks (say, four neighbors per block).</p>
                <p id="d1e1896">The total number of long links will depend on how many times we repeat the above steps. Thus, we looped these steps until the geodesic path of the network resembled the one expected for a “small world” network <xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. As a general rule, we found that this condition was fulfilled after 25% of the nodes had at least one long link. <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> summarizes the final set of parameter.</p>
                <p id="d1e1906">Finally, we stress the fact that the links between different blocks are assigned at the beginning of the simulation. Thereafter, the links remain fixed until the end of the simulation.</p>
                <p id="d1e1908">
                  <table-wrap position="anchor" id="tbl1">
                    <label>Table 1</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Most relevant parameters used in the simulation of COVID-19 epidemic along the mobility network.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
                      <tbody>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Number of nodes (blocks)</td>
                          <td align="left">120 × 120</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Population per block</td>
                          <td align="left">300</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Short links</td>
                          <td align="left">Between first neighbors</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Long links</td>
                          <td align="left">Over 25% of the nodes</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left">Total number of links</td>
                          <td align="left">31825</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1365" display="inline" altimg="si12.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> (Levy distribution)</td>
                          <td align="left">100 m</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                          <td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1383" display="inline" altimg="si55.svg"><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> (Levy distribution)</td>
                          <td align="left">1.75</td>
                        </tr>
                      </tbody>
                    </table>
                  </table-wrap>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2.2">
                <label>2.2</label>
                <title>Mobility pattern</title>
                <p id="d1e1916">We follow a similar scheme as in Ref. <xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, <xref rid="b25" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref> for the individuals’ mobility. This means that we divide the population of each block into two groups: <italic>stationary</italic> and <italic>non-stationary</italic> individuals. The former is composed by infected individuals while the latter is made up of susceptible, exposed and removed individuals.</p>
                <p id="d1e1928">We will assume that <italic>stationary</italic> individuals stay in their original block. We will further assume, in the spirit of Ref. <xref rid="b25" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, that 50% of the <italic>non-stationary</italic> stay in their original block, while the other 50% is considered to be mobile during the simulation. In this sense, we assume that 60% of the <italic>non-stationary</italic> individuals travel (via short links) from their original block to the neighboring block. And, the remaining 40% travel (via long links) from their original block to far blocks as indicated in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>.</p>
                <p id="d1e1948">
                  <fig id="fig2">
                    <label>Fig. 2</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Schematic representation of the behavior of the population for a single block. The population is composed by susceptible (S), exposed (E), infected (I) and removed (R) individuals. Infected individuals stay at home during the simulation process while the 50% of the susceptible, exposed and removed individuals move to another blocks (see text for more details).</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="gr2_lrg"/>
                  </fig>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="d1e1951">
                <title>Daily displacements of the individuals</title>
                <p id="d1e1954">Each moving individual is assumed to stay 1/2 of the day in its original block while the other 1/2 of the day he (she) moves to another block. They go to his (her) destination (work) everyday, and at the end of the day return back to their original block (home). This mechanism is performed reversing the direction of the links between blocks.</p>
                <p id="d1e1956"><xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref> shows a schematic representation of the human mobility pattern during each day (we illustrate this by a small city of 4<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1962" display="inline" altimg="si15.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="1em" class="nbsp"/><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">×</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="1em" class="nbsp"/><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> blocks for a better visualization). Recall from the last section that the links represent the mobility pattern between different blocks. Thus, moving humans travel through the links from one block to another one.</p>
                <p id="d1e1971">Notice that the population inside each block is always 300 during the night hours. This remains fixed during the day hours only in the “Home” scenario (see <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3(a)</xref>). The disease evolution in each node is therefore determined by the health care conditions within the block. However, in the “Work” scenario (see <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3(c)</xref>), people arrive or depart from each block during the day according to the <italic>in–out</italic> links (network heterogeneity). The disease evolution, thus, mixes between visitors and inhabitants of each block, yielding to a much complex dynamic than in the “Home” scenario.<fig id="fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Schematic illustration of the epidemic model incorporating individual human mobility during each day. The node colors represent the population of each block (see scale bar on the right). (a) The day starts with all individuals at home. (b) At 12 o’clock, 50% of the population of each block moves to other cells, according to the pre-assigned mobility pattern. The arrows represent the movement direction. (c) The population of each block after mobile humans traveled to the working block. (d) Then, at 24 o’clock those humans that traveled from home to work return back to home. At the end of the day, the population of each block is the same as that in the beginning of the day. The sequence (a–d) repeats every day until the end of the simulation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="d1e1986">The “Work” scenario exhibits similarity to the type-II metapopulation models (see Ref. <xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref> for details). These are quite suitable models for describing the healthy to infected transition in a complex network. However, we are not interested in the stationary situation, but in the time evolution since a few people become infected. Therefore, unlike the usual metapopulation analysis, we do not consider mean population values at each node (<italic>i.e.</italic> block). The daily fluctuations of the amount of people at each node is a relevant issue in our model.</p>
                <p id="d1e1995">We finally call the attention on the fact that we do not include specific features in our model, such as geographical population distribution, detailed medical and demographical factor, etc. Instead, we will investigate those common characteristics that affect the disease dynamic during a epidemic. The vaccination and the use of antiviral drugs as a containments strategies or “super-spreader” events, will not be part of the investigation.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2.3">
                <label>2.3</label>
                <title>Epidemiological dynamics of the individuals</title>
                <p id="d1e2002">In order to describe the time evolution of a given population when a fraction gets infected, we resort to the SEIR compartmental models. These models consider that the individuals can be in four successive states: susceptible (S), exposed (E), infected (I) and removed (R). Details on each state can be found in Refs. <xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, <xref rid="b25" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>, <xref rid="b26" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, <xref rid="b27" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>. The “exposed” state appears whenever the disease undergoes an “incubation” period, as occurs in the context of the COVID-19. The “removed” state includes either recovered and dead people.</p>
                <p id="d1e2008">The equations that describe the evolution of the infection read as follows <xref rid="b26" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>, <xref rid="b27" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>
<disp-formula id="fd2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="d1e2021" display="block" altimg="si16.svg"><mml:mfenced open="{"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable align="axis" equalrows="false" columnlines="none none" equalcolumns="false" class="array"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="array" columnalign="center"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="array" columnalign="center"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="array" columnalign="center"><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="array" columnalign="center"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="array" columnalign="center"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="array" columnalign="center"><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="array" columnalign="center"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="array" columnalign="center"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="array" columnalign="center"><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="array" columnalign="center"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>˙</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="array" columnalign="center"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="array" columnalign="center"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd class="array" columnalign="center"><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="array" columnalign="center"><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd class="array" columnalign="center"><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
                <p id="d1e2249">where <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2252" display="inline" altimg="si22.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2280" display="inline" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, etc. correspond to the fraction of people in each state. For the purpose of simplicity, we will consider the coefficients <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2308" display="inline" altimg="si55.svg"><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2314" display="inline" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2319" display="inline" altimg="si26.svg"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2324" display="inline" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> as fixed parameters. The parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2329" display="inline" altimg="si55.svg"><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> (infection rate) depends on intrinsic ingredients like the infectivity of the virus under consideration and extrinsic ones like the contact frequency. Besides, the parameters <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2335" display="inline" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2340" display="inline" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> depend exclusively on the illness under consideration.</p>
                <p id="d1e2344">The basic reproduction number <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2347" display="inline" altimg="si31.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is defined at the beginning of the propagation process as <xref rid="b28" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>
<disp-formula id="fd3"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="d1e2367" display="block" altimg="si32.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
                <p id="d1e2385">This quantity represents the number of individuals that are infected by the first infected individuals (say, at the beginning of the disease). It is straight forward that the infection will blossom if <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2388" display="inline" altimg="si31.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is larger than 1. On the contrary, if this quantity is smaller than 1 the infection vanishes.</p>
                <p id="d1e2397"><xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref> shows the time evolution of either the SEIR model for a single block and for the whole mobility model (see caption for details). Notice that the latter shifts the date for the maximum infection to approximately 150. We will analyze this behavior in more detail in Section <xref rid="sec4" ref-type="sec">4</xref>.</p>
                <p id="d1e2407">
                  <fig id="fig4">
                    <label>Fig. 4</label>
                    <caption>
                      <p>Normalized number of susceptibles ( <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1001_lrg.gif"/>
), exposed ( <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1002_lrg.gif"/>
), infected ( <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1003_lrg.gif"/>
) and removed ( <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1004_lrg.gif"/>
) as a function of time. In (a) we simulated a single block, while in (b) the scenario corresponds to a city composed by 120 × 120 blocks placed on a square grid (see Section <xref rid="sec2.1" ref-type="sec">2.1</xref>). The plots are normalized with respect to the total population in the city: (a) 300 and (b) 4.32 M (<italic>i.e.</italic> 300 individuals per block). In both cases, the disease spreads without any kind of intervention strategy. The infection rate equals <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e95" display="inline" altimg="si34.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>75</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> all along the propagation process. The simulation started with 20 infected individuals located in the single block (a) and at the central block of the city (b). The rest of the individuals were assumed to be in the susceptible state.</p>
                    </caption>
                    <graphic xlink:href="gr4_lrg"/>
                  </fig>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec2.4">
                <label>2.4</label>
                <title>Lockdown types</title>
                <p id="d1e2415">In this section we define the proposed containment strategies which we have found useful in order to mitigate the disease. We divide the different types of quarantine according to their level of real life implementation difficulty</p>
                <p id="d1e2417">
                  <list list-type="simple" id="d1e2419">
                    <list-item id="lst4">
                      <label>•</label>
                      <p id="d1e2423">Global lockdown</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item id="lst5">
                      <label>•</label>
                      <p id="d1e2428">Imperfect lockdown</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item id="lst6">
                      <label>•</label>
                      <p id="d1e2433">Local lockdown</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                </p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="d1e2435">
                <title>Global lockdown scenario (GLs)</title>
                <p id="d1e2438">This type of lockdown consists in the isolation of each block. This means that people remain in their “home” blocks. We stress the fact that, within this strategy, society as a whole enters in lockdown. We illustrate this containment action in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5(b)</xref>.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="d1e2444">
                <title>Imperfect lockdown scenario (IGLs)</title>
                <p id="d1e2447">As in the previous case, the whole society adopts the same behavior. But, in this mitigation strategy, we partially reduce the movement between different blocks. Recall from Section <xref rid="sec2.2" ref-type="sec">2.2</xref> that 50% of the <italic>non-stationary</italic> individuals move from their original block to another one. In this strategy, we reduce the level of mobility between blocks. Notice that the global quarantine corresponds to a full reduction of the mobility. We scheme this containment action in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5(c)</xref>.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="d1e2461">
                <title>Local lockdown scenario (LLs)</title>
                <p id="d1e2464">Unlike the other lockdown types, this applies to certain blocks and not to the whole society. Only those blocks that have a certain number of infected people are isolated. In this sense, the population of the isolated block are prohibited to travel around the city. This is achieved in practice by “cutting” the links to/from the infected blocks. We illustrate this containment action in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5(d)</xref>.</p>
                <p id="d1e2470">As a final remark, we stress the fact that full and localized isolation of blocks solely occurs in GLs and LLs, respectively. But, in IGLs there is no isolation of the blocks at all. Actually, the number of people moving between the blocks is partially reduced.<fig id="fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>(a–d) Schematic representation of different types of mitigation strategies (exemplified by a 4 × 4 grid). The lines represent the human mobility pattern between blocks. (a) People are allowed to evolve freely, equivalent to a “continuous activity” scenario. That is, there is no intervention during the epidemic. (b–d) Before a given day, individuals move freely from one block to another according to the mobility pattern. After that, (b) all blocks are isolated, (c) the flow between blocks (represented by red arrows) is reduced but the mobility pattern is unaffected, (d) those blocks with a number of infected individuals greater than a certain threshold are isolated (labeled with a red flag). The other blocks remain linked to each other (labeled with a green flag). See text for more details.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr5_lrg"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec3">
              <label>3</label>
              <title>Numerical simulations</title>
              <p id="d1e2479">We integrate the SEIR equations by means of the Runge Kutta 4th-order method. The chosen time step was 0.1 (days). The SEIR equations were updated twice a day (after the people left their homes and after they returned back (see <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>, <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>).</p>
              <p id="d1e2485">As mentioned in Section <xref rid="sec2.3" ref-type="sec">2.3</xref>, the parameters <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2493" display="inline" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2498" display="inline" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> represent the incubation rate and the recuperation rate, respectively. Therefore, <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2504" display="inline" altimg="si37.svg"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2516" display="inline" altimg="si38.svg"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> correspond to the mean incubation time and the mean recovery time, respectively. According to preliminary estimations for COVID-19, we consider the following parameter values for the SEIR model: <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2528" display="inline" altimg="si39.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
 days and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2548" display="inline" altimg="si40.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
 days <xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="b29" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, <xref rid="b30" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, <xref rid="b31" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>, <xref rid="b32" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>.</p>
              <p id="d1e2570">Infected individuals remain at their “Home” until evolving into the removed state. Susceptible, exposed and removed individuals are able to move from one block to another. The simulation started with 20 infected individuals located at the central block of the city, while the rest of the individuals were assumed to be in the susceptible state.</p>
              <p id="d1e2572">According to preliminary estimations for COVID-19, the basic reproduction number <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2575" display="inline" altimg="si31.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is (approximately) 3 <xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="b33" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>, <xref rid="b34" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. This means that the infection rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2589" display="inline" altimg="si67.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is 0.75 (considering <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2600" display="inline" altimg="si40.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
 days). The implementation of complementary health policies (use of mask, social distancing policies, among others) tends to reduce the contact frequency, and, therefore, the infection rate (<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2620" display="inline" altimg="si55.svg"><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>). Thus, we will also examine situations accomplishing infection rates of a fraction of <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2625" display="inline" altimg="si67.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec4">
              <label>4</label>
              <title>Results</title>
              <p id="d1e2639">We will examine three major scenarios affecting the human mobility:</p>
              <p id="d1e2641">
                <list list-type="simple" id="d1e2643">
                  <list-item id="lst7">
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <p id="d1e2647">The (global) lockdown scenario assumes that people remain confined at home until the epidemic is almost over. See details in Section <xref rid="sec4.1" ref-type="sec">4.1</xref>.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item id="lst8">
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <p id="d1e2657">The scenario where the confinement recommendation is followed by a fraction of the city inhabitants. We assume that the traveling individuals move around according to the Levy pattern explained in Section <xref rid="sec2" ref-type="sec">2</xref>. See further details on this scenario in Section <xref rid="sec4.2" ref-type="sec">4.2</xref>.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item id="lst9">
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <p id="d1e2672">Mobility is suppressed only for the inhabitants of “infected blocks”. That is, common life mobility is sustained between blocks where no symptoms of the disease appeared. See Section <xref rid="sec4.3" ref-type="sec">4.3</xref> for details.</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </p>
              <p id="d1e2679">This last scenario is the most cumbersome one since “non-symptomatic” does not actually mean “non-infected”. We will explicitly introduce a set of “non-symptomatic” individuals in this scenario, in order to understand possible flaws to confinement.</p>
              <sec id="sec4.1">
                <label>4.1</label>
                <title>Global lockdown scenario (GLs)</title>
                <p id="d1e2686">The GLs means that people remain confined within the block where she (he) lives. It corresponds to a sudden break of the mobility around the city in the context of our model. We assume, however, that people may still get in contact within their own block.</p>
                <p id="d1e2688">In this case, we consider the mobility suppression as the only heath-care policy. Additional health-care recommendations for the every day living (say, masks, common rooms disinfections, etc.) are considered in <xref rid="appA" ref-type="sec">Appendix A</xref>. We will come back to this issue at the end of this Section.</p>
                <p id="d1e2694"><xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6(a)</xref> shows the number of new infected people along time for three different lockdown periods (see caption for details). It is also shown the evolution for the case of no lockdown at all. The mobility cutoff prevents the infection curves in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6(a)</xref> from growing almost immediately after the beginning of the lockdown. The disease, however, disappears (approximately) 50 days (or 7 weeks) after. This is the time it take the susceptible or exposed individuals in each block to surpass the disease.<fig id="fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>(a) Number of new infected and (b) normalize number of removed as a function of time. The plot in (b) is normalized with respect to the total population in the city (4.32 M). The GLs is applied when the number of new infected equals to: <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1005_lrg.gif"/>
 5k, <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1006_lrg.gif"/>
 10k and <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1007_lrg.gif"/>
 30k new infected individuals. <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1008_lrg.gif"/>
 corresponds to the scenario of no lockdown at all. The infection rate remains constant along the simulation process and equals to <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e167" display="inline" altimg="si34.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>75</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. That is, there is no complementary health-care policies during the lockdown. The different lockdown implementation days are indicated by vertical lines.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr6_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="d1e2706"><xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6(b)</xref> exhibits the number of removed individuals as a function of time (see caption for details). These correspond to those individuals that previously appear as infected in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Fig. 6(a)</xref>. It can be seen that the number of removed individuals increases since the outbreak of the disease, but it reaches a plateau soon after the lockdown is established. The plateau level, however, depends strongly on the starting date of the lockdown. Recall that the disease evolves only within the infected blocks after the lockdown implementation. Thus, the earlier the lockdown, the less number of infected (and removed) blocks at the end of the disease.</p>
                <p id="d1e2715">We now turn to the city map, in order to get a more accurate picture of the results so far. <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref> displays the city as a square arrangement of blocks (see caption for details). Each “pixel” corresponds to a block, and the pixel color is associated to the corresponding scale on the left, which states the number of infected and the normalized number of removed per block. The snapshots capture the disease propagation from a single block located at the center of the map. A complete lockdown occurs at day 100.</p>
                <p id="d1e2721">The successive snapshots display a seemingly symmetrical propagation pattern, shortly after the outbreak. However, “secondary” focuses appear around the main focus due to those long traveling individuals. Recall that we assumed that human mobility follows a Levy-flight distribution (see Section <xref rid="sec2.1" ref-type="sec">2.1</xref>).<fig id="fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>(a) Total number of new infected and (b) normalized number of removed as a function of time. The plot in (b) is normalized with respect to the total population in the city (4.32 M). The GLs started at the day 100 after the first infected was detected. This is indicated by a vertical line in (a) and (b). The red continuous line corresponds to the scenario of no lockdown at all, while the lockdown case is indicated by green triangles. (Lower) Spatial distribution of the number of infected individuals for the five different dates (indicated in (a) and (b) by blue squares). The scale bar on the right corresponds to the number of infected and the normalized number of removed per block, respectively. The normalization was computed with respect to the population of each block. The infection rate remains constant along the simulation process and equals <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e196" display="inline" altimg="si34.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>75</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The city was composed by <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e215" display="inline" altimg="si48.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>120</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">×</mml:mo><mml:mn>120</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> blocks placed on a square grid with 300 individuals per block.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr7_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="d1e2730">Notice that the lockdown implementation (from day 100 onwards) somehow “freezes” the picture until the disease disappears (say, 50 days after). People continue to get infected within each block during the “quarantine” period. Complementary health-care recommendations may be required for the disease control within each block.</p>
                <p id="d1e2732"><xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Fig. 8</xref> shows the number of  “infected blocks”, regardless of the number of infected people in the block (see caption for details). These curves quantify the infection map displayed in <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>, and resumes the effects of the full lockdown.</p>
                <p id="d1e2741">We may conclude that the GLs appears as a reliable strategy for avoiding the disease propagation. But the main drawback is that “non-infected” blocks will enter the “quarantine”. <xref rid="appA" ref-type="sec">Appendix A</xref> further shows the effects of complementary health-care policies.<fig id="fig8"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Normalized number of infected blocks as a function of time. The plot is normalized with respect to the total number of blocks (14.4 k). Any block is classified as “infected” if at least one individual in the block is infected. We only consider people “living in the block” (say, those that sleep in there). The global lockdown is applied when the number of new infected equals to: <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1009_lrg.gif"/>
 5k, <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1010_lrg.gif"/>
 10k and <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1011_lrg.gif"/>
30k new infected individuals. <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1012_lrg.gif"/>
 corresponds to the scenario of no lockdown at all. The infection rate remains constant along the simulation process and equals <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e269" display="inline" altimg="si34.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>75</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. That is, there is no complementary health-care policies during the lockdown. The different lockdown implementation days are indicated by vertical lines.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr8_lrg"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec4.2">
                <label>4.2</label>
                <title>The imperfect global scenario (IGLs)</title>
                <p id="d1e2754">In this case we model a situation in which the GLs cannot be implemented. We distinguish, however, two groups which cannot be kept confined: workers from essential activities (say, health care, food supply or public order services, etc.) or those who decide not to accept the confinement recommendation. The former are expected to follow complementary health-care recommendations, while the latter might not. For this reason, we will examine relaxed confinement conditions and infection rates reduction.</p>
                <p id="d1e2756"><xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9(a)</xref> shows how the infection curves change as the number of agents which do not accept the movement restriction increases (see caption for details). The confinement starts at the vertical line. Notice that the propagation stops dramatically for the complete confinement situation. But the possibility of stopping the outbreak vanishes if a fraction of people (as small as 20%) still move around. A quick inspection of <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9(b)</xref> confirms this point.</p>
                <p id="d1e2765">We also notice from <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9(b)</xref> that the total number of removed people at the end of the lockdown is the same for any IGLs. This appears to be in disagreement with the stochastic point of view, where the mobility reduction yields to the reduction in the probability of meeting people. We should remark that the meeting probability is somehow included in the infection rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2774" display="inline" altimg="si55.svg"><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> within the SEIR model. Thus, for a complete picture of the IGLs, it is necessary to explore different values of <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2779" display="inline" altimg="si55.svg"><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, as described below.<fig id="fig9"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p>(a) Number of new infected people and (b) normalized number of removed individuals as a function of time. The plot in (b) is normalized with respect to the total population in the city (4.32 M). The IGLs is applied when the number of new infected equals to 5k (say, at day 66). From the lockdown implementation day, the percentage of individuals that move around is: <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1013_lrg.gif"/>
 0%, <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1014_lrg.gif"/>
20% and <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1015_lrg.gif"/>
50%. <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1016_lrg.gif"/>
 corresponds to the scenario of no lockdown at all (100% of moving people). We consider a partial break of the mobility as the only heath-care policy. Thus, the infection rate equals <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e332" display="inline" altimg="si34.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>75</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> all along the propagation process.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr9_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="d1e2783"><xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10</xref> examines the number of removed individuals (<italic>i.e.</italic> agents that have undergone the complete cycle of the illness, and have either reached a healthy state or have died) at the end of the epidemic in terms of the complementary health-care policies. Two startup days for the lockdown are shown (see caption for details). We can see that the number of removed individuals experiences a dramatic change at <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2792" display="inline" altimg="si53.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">≈</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for the different moving people situations, regardless of the startup day of the lockdown. This confirms the necessity of proper policies when these situations are expected to occur.</p>
                <p id="d1e2814">We improved on the above results by displaying in <xref rid="fig11" ref-type="fig">Fig. 11</xref> the contour maps for different mobility situations, as a function of the lockdown date. Notice that <xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10</xref> corresponds to date 66 in both contour maps (see caption in <xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">Fig. 10</xref>).<fig id="fig10"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p>Normalized number of removed people as a function of the infection rate at the end of the epidemic. The plot is normalized with respect to the total population in the city (4.32 M). The IGLs is applied when the number of new infected equals to: (a) 5k and (b) 30k. Since the lockdown implementation day, the percentage of individuals that move around is: <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1017_lrg.gif"/>
 0%, <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1018_lrg.gif"/>
20% and <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1019_lrg.gif"/>
50%. <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1020_lrg.gif"/>
 corresponds to the scenario of no lockdown at all (100% of moving people). Also, from the lockdown implementation day, the infection rate change from <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e395" display="inline" altimg="si34.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>75</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e414" display="inline" altimg="si55.svg"><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. The city was composed by <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e420" display="inline" altimg="si48.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>120</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">×</mml:mo><mml:mn>120</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> blocks placed on a square grid with 300 individuals per block.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr10_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="d1e2830"><xref rid="fig11" ref-type="fig">Fig. 11</xref> expresses the fact that whenever the human mobility is suppressed, the number of removed individuals depends (almost exclusively) on the timing of the lockdown implementation. That is, the earlier the lockdown, the lower the number of removed. Besides, if mobility cannot be suppressed (say, 50% of the people still move around), then complementary health-care policies should be heavily implemented, in order to avoid a massive contagion. This appears as an essential issue for late lockdowns.</p>
                <p id="d1e2835">We close this section with the following conclusion: a complete mobility suppression appears as the most effective way of reducing the number of casualties. Essential workers following strict health-care recommendations (say, masks, behavioral protocols, etc.) that move around, however, will not spread the disease to uncontrolled levels. But, a small fraction of people moving around out of protocol can spoil the mitigation efforts.<fig id="fig11"><label>Fig. 11</label><caption><p>Normalized number of removed individuals (see scale on the right) as a function of the lockdown implementation day and the infection rate (<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e439" display="inline" altimg="si57.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). The normalization was done taking into account the city population. The infection rate changes from <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e454" display="inline" altimg="si34.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>75</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e473" display="inline" altimg="si55.svg"><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> since the lockdown implementation day.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr11_lrg"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec4.3">
                <label>4.3</label>
                <title>Local lockdown scenario (LLs)</title>
                <p id="d1e2844">The local lockdown means that people remain confined within the block where he (she) lives, depending on the infection level of their block. That is, those blocks surpassing a certain “threshold” of infected people are immediately isolated, while the others remain “open”. As in the case of the GLs, we assume that people from an isolated block may still get in contact within this block. We consider the mobility break as the only heath policy.</p>
                <p id="d1e2846">The local lockdown relies on the idea that the early detection of the infected can prevent the disease from spreading around the city. This idea presumes insignificant or null detection flaws. But in practice, a few infected individuals may not be detected due to wrong testings, or do not present symptoms at all. Our concern is on these situations. We will assume that a small fraction of infected people per block cannot actually be detected. This means that the lockdown occurs after surpassing a “threshold” of infected people (although not detected).<fig id="fig12"><label>Fig. 12</label><caption><p>(a) Number of new infected people and (b) normalized number of removed individuals as a function of time. The plot in (b) is normalized with respect to the total population in the city (4.32 M). The LLs is applied when the number of new infected equals to 30k (indicate by the vertical line, at day 100). The locked blocks are those that exceed the following thresholds: <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1021_lrg.gif"/>
0, <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1022_lrg.gif"/>
5 and <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1023_lrg.gif"/>
 10 individuals (see text for details). <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1024_lrg.gif"/>
 corresponds to the scenario of no lockdown at all. We consider the isolation of the infected blocks as the only heath-care policy. Thus, the infection rate equals <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e523" display="inline" altimg="si34.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>75</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> all along the propagation process.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr12_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="d1e2850"><xref rid="fig12" ref-type="fig">Fig. 12</xref> represent the usual infection and passed over curves as a function of time, respectively (see caption for details). A quick inspection of these curves show that the disease decays almost immediately if the lockdown process occurs just after the first infected appeared in the block. Otherwise, the number of infected people continues increasing until the day 150 (approximately).</p>
                <p id="d1e2855"><xref rid="fig12" ref-type="fig">Fig. 12</xref> can be compared to its counterpart in the context of the IGLs, that is, <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9(a)</xref>. The time scales in both situations appear quite similar, although the curves in <xref rid="fig12" ref-type="fig">Fig. 12(a)</xref> do not extend further than 200 days.</p>
                <p id="d1e2868">The “threshold” of non-detected people is responsible for the time lapse between the lockdown day and the end of the disease. This can be confirmed through <xref rid="fig13" ref-type="fig">Fig. 13</xref>, that shows the contour maps for the infected blocks (see caption for details). Notice that the non-detected blocks (say, the orange ones) become more relevant as the “threshold” level increases.<fig id="fig13"><label>Fig. 13</label><caption><p>Spatial distribution of the blocks according to their infected state at the lockdown implementation day (100). Those blocks without infected individuals are represented in black, while those blocks with a number of infected people lower (greater) than the threshold (see legend) are represent in orange (blue). Blue blocks were isolated from the rest, while black and orange blocks were “opened”. The infection rate remains constant along the simulation process and equals <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e550" display="inline" altimg="si34.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>75</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The city was composed by <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e569" display="inline" altimg="si48.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>120</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">×</mml:mo><mml:mn>120</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> blocks placed on a square grid with 300 individuals per block.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr13_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="d1e2876"><xref rid="fig14" ref-type="fig">Fig. 14</xref> exhibits the fraction of isolated blocks with respect to those blocks attaining at least an infected individual. We can observe that half of the infected blocks are actually not detectable for a threshold as low as 5 individuals per block. This is a strong warning on the effectivity of the LLs. Public health officers will lock down as many blocks as detected, but the undetected will actually continue the propagation.</p>
                <p id="d1e2881">Whatever the efforts to detect infected, it seems that <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2886" display="inline" altimg="si64.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>40</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">−</mml:mo><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>45</mml:mn><mml:mtext>%</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> of the infected individuals do not experience noticeable symptoms <xref rid="b35" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. We introduced this phenomenon into our simulations. <xref rid="fig15" ref-type="fig">Fig. 15</xref> shows the overall removed people for an increasing number of “non-symptomatic” individuals. This confirms once more the lack of effectivity of the local lockdown if no other policy is established.<fig id="fig14"><label>Fig. 14</label><caption><p>Normalized number of isolate blocks with respect to the total number of infected blocks as a function of time. The LLs is applied when the number of new infected equals to 30k (indicated by the vertical line, at day 100). The locked blocks are those that exceed the following thresholds: <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1025_lrg.gif"/>
0, <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1026_lrg.gif"/>
5, <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1027_lrg.gif"/>
 10, <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1028_lrg.gif"/>
20 and <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1029_lrg.gif"/>
40 individuals (see text for details). The dashed lines corresponds to the behavior of both magnitudes before the lockdown implementation. The infection rate remains constant along the simulation process and equals <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e629" display="inline" altimg="si34.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>75</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr14_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="d1e2907">A thoughtful policy should include either strategic testings and backward tracing of the infected, from our point of view. We simulated this policy by tracing back any infected people to where she (he) belonged before being detected. The procedure in a nutshell is as follows:<fig id="fig15"><label>Fig. 15</label><caption><p>Normalized number of removed individuals (at the end of the epidemic) as a function of the percentage of asymptomatic individuals. The normalization was done taking into account the city population. The LLs started at the day 100 after the first infected was detected. The infection threshold is five individuals. From the lockdown implementation day, the infection rate switches from <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e656" display="inline" altimg="si34.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>75</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e675" display="inline" altimg="si66.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>075</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1030_lrg.gif"/>
, while remains constant (<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e699" display="inline" altimg="si67.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>) in <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1031_lrg.gif"/>
.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr15_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="d1e2911">
                  <list list-type="simple" id="d1e2913">
                    <list-item id="lst10">
                      <label>•</label>
                      <p id="d1e2917">Test a random block. If infected, trace back <italic>all</italic> the individuals to the block they visited before.</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item id="lst11">
                      <label>•</label>
                      <p id="d1e2925">Test <italic>all</italic> the blocks recognized as visited immediately before.</p>
                    </list-item>
                    <list-item id="lst12">
                      <label>•</label>
                      <p id="d1e2933">Lock down any of the above if infected.</p>
                    </list-item>
                  </list>
                </p>
                <p id="d1e2936">The results from these simulations are shown in <xref rid="appC" ref-type="sec">Appendix C</xref>. The testing procedure exhibits a noticeable efficiency (say, a noticeable decay in the number of removed people) if at least 80% of the blocks can be tested. The back-tracing procedure further reduces this fraction significantly. Other complementary health-care policies (like masks, distancing, etc.) can also improve significantly the number of removed individuals (see <xref rid="appC" ref-type="sec">Appendix C</xref> for details). In summary, the simulation results confirm our intuition on the effectivity of the back-tracing methodology.</p>
                <p id="d1e2946">We conclude from this Section that the effectivity of any LLs will strongly depend on breaking off the mobility of infected people. If this fails (because of asymptomatic or unreachable people), the disease will spread dramatically throughout the city. The strategic testing and back-tracing of the infected should be considered as an essential tool for the disease mitigation.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec5">
              <label>5</label>
              <title>Analysis of the effects of the different strategies</title>
              <p id="d1e2953">In this Section we discuss the performance of the GLs, IGLs and LLs. We limit our analysis to the following points</p>
              <p id="d1e2955">
                <list list-type="simple" id="d1e2957">
                  <list-item id="lst13">
                    <label>(a)</label>
                    <p id="d1e2961">The performance of the lockdown is actually associated to the mitigation of the disease. Smooth infection curves are preferred in order to avoid stressing the medical care system.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item id="lst14">
                    <label>(b)</label>
                    <p id="d1e2966">Lockdowns seriously damage the economy. The less disturbing and shorter lasting actions on non-infected people are therefore preferred.</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </p>
              <p id="d1e2968">We propose a merit function in order to rate the performance of the different lockdown strategies above mentioned, with respect to conditions (a) and (b). We will consider the fraction of the new infected people at any time <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2971" display="inline" altimg="si68.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (or <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2984" display="inline" altimg="si69.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> at step <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e2994" display="inline" altimg="si70.svg"><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> of the simulation) and the mobility <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3000" display="inline" altimg="si71.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> as the most relevant quantities for building the merit function (see below for the precise definitions). Thus, the merit function will be expressed as <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3013" display="inline" altimg="si72.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
              <p id="d1e3033">Notice from Section <xref rid="sec4" ref-type="sec">4</xref> that the maximum number of new infected people is quite different for the examined scenarios (see, for example, <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>, <xref rid="fig12" ref-type="fig">Fig. 12</xref>). Our merit function will consider the new infected people (<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3046" display="inline" altimg="si73.svg"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>) normalized with respect to the maximum number of new infected when no lockdown is carried out. Accordingly, we will consider the mobility fraction (<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3053" display="inline" altimg="si102.svg"><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>) as the amount of traveling people normalized with respect to the traveling people before the lockdown.</p>
              <p id="d1e3057">The topic (a) concerns the infected people. The successful lockdown will mitigate the overall number of infected people. Our first proposal would be to rate the performance as the cumulative value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3060" display="inline" altimg="si73.svg"><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> along the lockdown period. This approach, however, does not consider the stressing of the medical care system. For instance, it does not make any difference between sharp infection curves and smooth ones, provided that the total number of infected people are the same. We can therefore improve the proposed function by cumulating the fractions <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3065" display="inline" altimg="si76.svg"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula>, for <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3075" display="inline" altimg="si77.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The coefficient <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3086" display="inline" altimg="si78.svg"><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> introduces a penalty to the sharp maximum (see below).</p>
              <p id="d1e3090">The topic (b) concerns the non-infected people. The lockdown breaks the routine of the traveling fraction of people <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3093" display="inline" altimg="si79.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.16667em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and consequently, the economic activity. We propose rating the performance of the non-infected motion as the aggregate of a linear function of <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3111" display="inline" altimg="si79.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.16667em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
              <p id="d1e3128">We express our merit function as follows <disp-formula id="fd4"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="d1e3137" display="block" altimg="si81.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo class="biggl" fence="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="false" class="overbrace"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>︷</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">(a)</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="false" class="overbrace"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.16667em"/><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>⋅</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>︷</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">(b)</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo class="biggr" fence="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
              <p id="d1e3227">where <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3230" display="inline" altimg="si82.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> stands for the day of the lockdown. The term (a) refers to the medical care cost, and the term (b) refers to the economical cost.</p>
              <p id="d1e3247">Notice that in regular working days <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3250" display="inline" altimg="si83.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3260" display="inline" altimg="si84.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. This yields a daily economical cost equal to <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3270" display="inline" altimg="si85.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, according to <xref rid="fd4" ref-type="disp-formula">(4)</xref>. We rate this cost as the null cost (<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3286" display="inline" altimg="si86.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) for practical reasons. Thus, we set <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3296" display="inline" altimg="si87.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to hold this condition. The cost function then reads <disp-formula id="fd5"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="d1e3317" display="block" altimg="si88.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">∑</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo class="biggl" fence="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover class="overset"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="false" class="overbrace"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>︷</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">(a)</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mover class="overset"><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="false" class="overbrace"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.16667em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>⋅</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>︷</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">(b)</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo class="biggr" fence="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
</p>
              <p id="d1e3415">This expression shows that an increase in the number of new infected people (although keeping <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3418" display="inline" altimg="si84.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) yields an increase in the medical cost (a) and the economical cost (b). The implementation of a strict lockdown (<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3429" display="inline" altimg="si90.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) further increases the economical cost (b) to its maximum value. The intermediate situations will be more or less costly according to the balance between the medical care cost (a) and the economical cost(b) in expression <xref rid="fd5" ref-type="disp-formula">(5)</xref>. The parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3444" display="inline" altimg="si111.svg"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the decisive parameter in the balance between the medical care, and economical cost.</p>
              <p id="d1e3448">We stress that the proposed function <xref rid="fd5" ref-type="disp-formula">(5)</xref> is limited to items (a) and (b), while other presumably important arguments could have been left aside for simplicity. We also fixed <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3455" display="inline" altimg="si92.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for practical reasons, but we checked that <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3465" display="inline" altimg="si100.svg"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> behaves qualitatively the same for other values <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3471" display="inline" altimg="si77.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (not shown).</p>
              <p id="d1e3480">The parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3483" display="inline" altimg="si111.svg"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is actually the only free parameter in our cost function. It stands as a weighting factor for the economical cost. We will discuss the behavior of <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3488" display="inline" altimg="si100.svg"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> for the lockdown strategies appearing in Section <xref rid="sec4" ref-type="sec">4</xref> while varying the values of <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3499" display="inline" altimg="si111.svg"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
              <p id="d1e3503">Let us first examine the medical care cost (a) and economical cost (b) separately. <xref rid="fig16" ref-type="fig">Fig. 16</xref> plots these costs for the situations shown in <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>, <xref rid="fig12" ref-type="fig">Fig. 12</xref>, respectively (see caption for details). The varying parameter is different on each plot, that is, the horizontal axis corresponds to the mobility in <xref rid="fig16" ref-type="fig">Fig. 16(a)</xref> and to the threshold level in <xref rid="fig16" ref-type="fig">Fig. 16(b)</xref>. The horizontal scale in <xref rid="fig16" ref-type="fig">Fig. 16(a)</xref> runs from the most strict situation at the origin (<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3528" display="inline" altimg="si98.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) to the normal moving situation (<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3540" display="inline" altimg="si84.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). Analogously, the horizontal scale in <xref rid="fig16" ref-type="fig">Fig. 16(b)</xref> runs from the most early detection at the origin to a detection level of 10 individuals. We present, however, both plots together in order to visualize the behavior of the GLs, IGLs and LLs as the lockdown becomes more and more relaxed. <xref rid="fig16" ref-type="fig">Fig. 16</xref> resumes, indeed, the costs as a function of the lockdown strictness.</p>
              <p id="d1e3557">We notice from <xref rid="fig16" ref-type="fig">Fig. 16</xref> that the medical cost, although different, shows a quite similar behavior in the IGLs and the LLs (see green squares in there). The economical costs, however, differ from each other when the lockdowns are very strict. The mutual differences vanish for the relaxed situations, no matter if the lockdown is global or local.</p>
              <p id="d1e3563">The dramatic increase of the economical cost (for the strict global lockdowns) is a matter of concern. <xref rid="fig16" ref-type="fig">Fig. 16(a)</xref> reports this phenomenon for small mobility values (IGLs), although not for the null mobility situation (GLs). The null mobility situation means that the disease remains confined to each block. But if a few agents avoid the lockdown, they can additionally spread the disease to other non-infected blocks. Thus, the perfect lockdown situation and the imperfect situation are quite different ones. This can be verified by observing <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9</xref>. The infection curve smoothens and widens as the mobility switches from 0% to 20%. For a mobility fraction of 50% the curve narrows back again.<fig id="fig16"><label>Fig. 16</label><caption><p>Medical care cost ( <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1032_lrg.gif"/>
) and economical cost ( <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1033_lrg.gif"/>
) for the scenarios analyzed in Section <xref rid="sec4" ref-type="sec">4</xref>. The inset shows the total cost <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e747" display="inline" altimg="si100.svg"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> assuming <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e752" display="inline" altimg="si101.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. (a) Implementation of the GLs and IGLs vs. <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e766" display="inline" altimg="si102.svg"><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. The dashed lines means that the economical cost for mobilities between 0% and 5% are greater than 300. (b) Implementation of the LLs vs. the infection threshold. In both cases, the lockdown is applied when the number of new infected equals to 5k. The infection rate remains constant along the simulation process and equals <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e772" display="inline" altimg="si34.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>75</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr16_lrg"/></fig></p>
              <p id="d1e3575">Either <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Fig. 9(a)</xref> and <xref rid="fig16" ref-type="fig">Fig. 16(a)</xref> point out that small mobility values induce a slow spreading dynamics (<italic>i.e.</italic> no massive propagation). This does not stress the medical care system, but yields long disruptions of the working routines. Notice from the cost expression <xref rid="fd5" ref-type="disp-formula">(5)</xref> that the term (b) is linear to <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3594" display="inline" altimg="si104.svg"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> if <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3599" display="inline" altimg="si105.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">≈</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Thus, the long lasting lockdowns are responsible for the increase in the economical costs.</p>
              <p id="d1e3608">The LLs isolates the infected blocks only. The mobility is locally suppressed, and the whole scene undergoes a mixture of blocks with full mobility and blocks that are isolated. This is a dynamical process where the blocks become isolated and are opened back again. The net result is that the overall mobility is not significantly reduced along the lockdown, and therefore, the spreading dynamic does not “slow down” completely, as already noticed in <xref rid="fig12" ref-type="fig">Fig. 12(a)</xref>. Recall that the curves therein do not extend further than 200 days, no matter the detection threshold. This prevents the dramatic increase in the economic costs, as shown in <xref rid="fig16" ref-type="fig">Fig. 16(b)</xref>.</p>
              <p id="d1e3618">We turn now to the discussion of the different lockdown strategies performance. <xref rid="fig17" ref-type="fig">Fig. 17</xref> shows the total cost <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3625" display="inline" altimg="si100.svg"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> as a function of the weighting factor <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3630" display="inline" altimg="si111.svg"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> (see caption for details). Notice that although <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3636" display="inline" altimg="si111.svg"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> can be chosen freely, it seems unrealistic to allow values yielding to costs beyond the cost of no-lockdown at all. We will consider the unlocked situation as the bounding value to <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3641" display="inline" altimg="si100.svg"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, as shown in red in <xref rid="fig17" ref-type="fig">Fig. 17</xref> (see caption for details).</p>
              <p id="d1e3649"><xref rid="fig17" ref-type="fig">Fig. 17</xref> reports the minimum cost situation in blue color ( <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1045_lrg.gif"/>
) for the GLs and LLs. These correspond to either the most strict global lockdown (<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3668" display="inline" altimg="si98.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) or the most early detection for the local lockdown (say, the null threshold). The latter attains a better performance with respect to the former for all the explored values of <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3678" display="inline" altimg="si111.svg"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>.<fig id="fig17"><label>Fig. 17</label><caption><p>(a) Cost function <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e799" display="inline" altimg="si100.svg"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> as a function of the weighting parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e804" display="inline" altimg="si111.svg"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> for the GLs and IGLs. From the lockdown implementation day, the percentage of individuals that move around is: <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1034_lrg.gif"/>
0% (GLs), <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1035_lrg.gif"/>
5%, <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1036_lrg.gif"/>
10%, <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1037_lrg.gif"/>
25% and <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1038_lrg.gif"/>
 50%. (b) Cost function <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e852" display="inline" altimg="si100.svg"><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> as a function of the weighting parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e857" display="inline" altimg="si111.svg"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> for the LLs. The locked blocks are those that exceed the following thresholds: <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1039_lrg.gif"/>
0, <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1040_lrg.gif"/>
2, <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1041_lrg.gif"/>
3, <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1042_lrg.gif"/>
5 and <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1043_lrg.gif"/>
 10 individuals. In both cases, <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1044_lrg.gif"/>
 corresponds to the scenario of no lockdown at all. Also, the lockdown is applied when the number of new infected equals to 5k. The infection rate remains constant along the simulation process and equals <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e913" display="inline" altimg="si34.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>75</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr17_lrg"/></fig></p>
              <p id="d1e3682">The economical cost (b) is responsible for the slope of the curves in <xref rid="fig17" ref-type="fig">Fig. 17</xref>. The almost flat slope observed for the null threshold means that the daily cost for this situation is negligible. This is in agreement with an early detection, where the fraction of infected people is quite small (<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3690" display="inline" altimg="si117.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">≈</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) and most of the non-infected people are allowed to move around (<inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3701" display="inline" altimg="si118.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">≈</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). The reader can check that this yields to vanishing values for the term (b) in our cost model <xref rid="fd5" ref-type="disp-formula">(5)</xref>.</p>
              <p id="d1e3716">We further notice that the curves’ slope increases for increasing detection thresholds in <xref rid="fig17" ref-type="fig">Fig. 17(b)</xref>. This occurs because of the increase in the daily economical cost, although the lockdown period remains close to <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3723" display="inline" altimg="si119.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">≈</mml:mo><mml:mn>200</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
 days. Interestingly, the lockdown curves in <xref rid="fig17" ref-type="fig">Fig. 17(b)</xref> meet the no-lockdown curve for thresholds surpassing 2–3 infected people. This makes the lockdown curves only valid for small values of <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3740" display="inline" altimg="si111.svg"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> (say, below 0.7).</p>
              <p id="d1e3744">Recall that the IGLs experiences a dramatic increment of the economical cost for small mobility fractions (see <xref rid="fig16" ref-type="fig">Fig. 16(a)</xref>). As a result, the lockdown curves always meet the no-lockdown curve at some point (except for <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3751" display="inline" altimg="si98.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), as shown in <xref rid="fig17" ref-type="fig">Fig. 17(a)</xref>. This is quite a difference with respect to the local strategy, since the lockdown curves are always limited to small values of <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3766" display="inline" altimg="si111.svg"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> (except for <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3771" display="inline" altimg="si98.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>).</p>
              <p id="d1e3780">Let us close the discussion with the following comments. We showed that the most strict implementation of either the global or local lockdown leads to the optimum performance (although the local one is preferred, as discussed above). But we noticed that there is some space left for partially effective lockdowns, if the most strict conditions are not attainable. The degree of effectiveness depends on the balance between the medical care costs and the economical costs, within this model.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec6">
              <label>6</label>
              <title>Conclusions</title>
              <p id="d1e3787">This work concerns with the effect of human mobility in the context of a model for the spatio-temporal evolution of the COVID-19 outbreak. People move according to the Levy distribution and get into contact with each other during their daily routine. The lockdowns prevent these contacts from occurring, and thus, mitigate the propagation of the disease. Our investigation studies different lockdown scenarios and performs a careful evaluation of their effectiveness. We draw some recommendations for the better performance of the lockdown.</p>
              <p id="d1e3789">We assumed a SEIR compartmental model (with constant infection rates) for the inhabitants of a block. Each block was considered as a node within a square network of 120 × 120 nodes. People were allowed to travel twice a day between blocks. The initial conditions for the simulations considered 20 infected individuals located at the central block of the network, while the rest of the individuals were assumed to be in the susceptible state.</p>
              <p id="d1e3791">We focused on three scenarios: the full lockdown of all the blocks (perfect scenario), the partial lockdown of all the blocks (imperfect scenario), and the lockdown of only the infected blocks (local lockdown). We sustained the lockdown until the disease propagation was (almost) over.</p>
              <p id="d1e3793">We first noticed that the success of any control action depends strongly on canceling the mobility around the city. But a small number of individuals may spoil the effectiveness of these actions if they do not follow the confinement recommendations. This is, in our opinion, the major risk when implementing any lockdown strategy.</p>
              <p id="d1e3795">We further built a cost function to rate the three strategies. We arrived to the conclusion that full lockdowns, or, the (very) early detection and isolation strategy are the most effective ones. The local isolation strategy is preferred, though, since it appears as the less costly in the context of our model.</p>
              <p id="d1e3797">It is important to emphasize that strict lockdown policies also allow for short periods of isolation. More relaxed lockdowns are less costly daily, but cumulate large costs after an extended period of time. The full lockdown looses efficacy if the mobility is not completely canceled, as already mentioned. Our model shows that local lockdowns can still be quite effective even if a small number of infected people is not detected (and isolated).</p>
              <p id="d1e3799">Finally, we emphasize that the goal of our investigation is to show that each lockdown strategy yields different medical care and economical costs. And therefore, a quite different overall cost. The ultimate decision on whether to choose a global or local lockdown on a specific circumstance will depend on the chosen balance between the medical care cost and the economical cost due to routine disruptions. We consider that this work is a useful framework for the policy makers. We will leave this discussion open for future research.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="d1e3801">
              <title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title>
              <p id="d1e3804"><bold>F.E. Cornes:</bold> Epidemiological dynamics, Investigation. <bold>G.A. Frank:</bold> Numerical simulations, Investigation, Supervision. <bold>C.O. Dorso:</bold> Epidemiological dynamics, Investigation, Supervision.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="COI-statement">
              <title>Declaration of Competing Interest</title>
              <p id="d1e3817">The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list id="bib1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="b1">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb1">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Medus</surname>
                      <given-names>A.D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dorso</surname>
                      <given-names>C.O.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>Diseases spreading through individual based models with realistic mobility patterns</part-title>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <comment>
                    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1104.4913" id="interref1">arXiv:1104.4913</ext-link>
                  </comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b2">
                <label>2</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sb2">H. Badr, H. Du, M. Marshall, E. Dong, M. Squire, L. Gardner, Association between mobility patterns and covid-19 transmission in the USA: A mathematical modelling study, Lancet. Infect. Dis. 20.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b3">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb3">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tian</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>C.-H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kraemer</surname>
                      <given-names>M.U.G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cai</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xu</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>Q.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cui</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Song</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zheng</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>Q.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bjornstad</surname>
                      <given-names>O.N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Grenfell</surname>
                      <given-names>B.T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pybus</surname>
                      <given-names>O.G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dye</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>An investigation of transmission control measures during the first 50 days of the covid-19 epidemic in china</article-title>
                  <source>Science</source>
                  <volume>368</volume>
                  <issue>6491</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>638</fpage>
                  <lpage>642</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32234804</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b4">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb4">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Flaxman</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mishra</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gandy</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Estimating the effects of non-pharmaceutical interventions on covid-19 in Europe</article-title>
                  <source>Nature</source>
                  <volume>584</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>257</fpage>
                  <lpage>261</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32512579</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b5">
                <label>5</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sb5">S. Chang, E. Pierson, P.W. Koh, J. Gerardin, B. Redbird, D. Grusky, J. Leskovec, Mobility network models of covid-19 explain inequities and inform reopening, Nature.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b6">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb6">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Meidan</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Schulmann</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cohen</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Haber</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yaniv</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sarid</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Barzel</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>Alternating quarantine for sustainable epidemic mitigation</part-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b7">
                <label>7</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sb7">O. Karin, Y.M. Bar-On, T. Milo, I. Katzir, A. Mayo, Y. Korem, B. Dudovich, E. Yashiv, A.J. Zehavi, N. Davidovich, R. Milo, U. Alon, Adaptive cyclic exit strategies from lockdown to suppress covid-19 and allow economic activity, medRxiv.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b8">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb8">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cornes</surname>
                      <given-names>F.E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Frank</surname>
                      <given-names>G.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dorso</surname>
                      <given-names>C.O.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>Cyclical lock-down and the economic activity along the pandemic of covid-19</part-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <comment>
                    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.06409" id="interref2">arXiv:2006.06409</ext-link>
                  </comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b9">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb9">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cheong</surname>
                      <given-names>K.H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wen</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lai</surname>
                      <given-names>J.W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Relieving cost of epidemic by parrondo’s paradox: A covid-19 case study</article-title>
                  <source>Adv. Sci.</source>
                  <volume>7</volume>
                  <issue>24</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2002324</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b10">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb10">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lai</surname>
                      <given-names>J.W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cheong</surname>
                      <given-names>K.H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Superposition of covid-19 waves, anticipating a sustained wave, and lessons for the future</article-title>
                  <source>BioEssays</source>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <issue>12</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2000178</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b11">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb11">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cheong</surname>
                      <given-names>K.H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jones</surname>
                      <given-names>M.C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Introducing the 21st century’s new four horsemen of the coronapocalypse</article-title>
                  <source>BioEssays</source>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2000063</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b12">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb12">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhao</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kuang</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>C.-H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bi</surname>
                      <given-names>K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ben-Arieh</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Risk perception and human behaviors in epidemics</article-title>
                  <source>IISE Trans. Healthc. Syst. Eng.</source>
                  <volume>8</volume>
                  <issue>4</issue>
                  <year>2018</year>
                  <fpage>315</fpage>
                  <lpage>328</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b13">
                <label>13</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sb13">A.D. Paltiel, J.L. Schwartz, A. Zheng, R.P. Walensky, Clinical outcomes of a covid-19 vaccine: Implementation over efficacy, Health Aff. 0 (0).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b14">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb14">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cheong</surname>
                      <given-names>K.H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Repurposing vaccines in the fight against covid-19</article-title>
                  <source>BioEssays</source>
                  <volume>42</volume>
                  <issue>11</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2000234</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b15">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb15">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ferguson</surname>
                      <given-names>N.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cummings</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cauchemez</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Strategies for containing an emerging influenza pandemic in southeast Asia</article-title>
                  <source>Nature</source>
                  <volume>437</volume>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <fpage>209</fpage>
                  <lpage>214</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16079797</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b16">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb16">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cave</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Covid-19 super-spreaders: Definitional quandaries and implications</article-title>
                  <source>Asian Bioeth. Rev.</source>
                  <volume>12</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>235</fpage>
                  <lpage>242</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b17">
                <label>17</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sb17">B.F. Nielsen, K. Sneppen, Superspreaders provide essential clues for mitigation of covid-19, medRxiv.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b18">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb18">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bradde</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cerruti</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bouchaud</surname>
                      <given-names>J.-P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>Did lockdowns serve their purpose?</part-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <comment>
                    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2006.09829" id="interref3">arXiv:2006.09829</ext-link>
                  </comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b19">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb19">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Burda</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Modelling excess mortality in covid-19-like epidemics</article-title>
                  <source>Entropy</source>
                  <volume>22</volume>
                  <issue>11</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1236</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b20">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb20">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Balcan</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Colizza</surname>
                      <given-names>V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gonçalves</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hu</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ramasco</surname>
                      <given-names>J.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vespignani</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Multiscale mobility networks and the spatial spreading of infectious diseases</article-title>
                  <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.</source>
                  <volume>106</volume>
                  <issue>51</issue>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <fpage>21484</fpage>
                  <lpage>21489</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20018697</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b21">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb21">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Colizza</surname>
                      <given-names>V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pastor-Satorras</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Vespignani</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Reaction–diffusion processes and metapopulation models in heterogeneous networks</article-title>
                  <source>Nat. Phys.</source>
                  <volume>3</volume>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <fpage>276</fpage>
                  <lpage>282</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b22">
                <label>22</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sb22">A. Barrat, M. Barthélemy, A. Vespignani, Dynamical Processes on Complex Networks, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, UK.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b23">
                <label>23</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sb23">H.C. González, M.A. Barabási, Understanding individual human mobility patterns, Nature.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b24">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb24">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Barmak</surname>
                      <given-names>D.H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dorso</surname>
                      <given-names>C.O.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Otero</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Solari</surname>
                      <given-names>H.G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Dengue epidemics and human mobility</article-title>
                  <source>Phys. Rev. E</source>
                  <volume>84</volume>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">011901</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b25">
                <label>25</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb25">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Barmak</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dorso</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Otero</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Modelling dengue epidemic spreading with human mobility</article-title>
                  <source>Physica A</source>
                  <volume>447</volume>
                  <year>2016</year>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <lpage>140</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b26">
                <label>26</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb26">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Anderson</surname>
                      <given-names>R.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>May</surname>
                      <given-names>R.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>Infectious Diseases of Humans</part-title>
                  <year>1991</year>
                  <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
                  <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b27">
                <label>27</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sb27">W.O. Kermack, A.G. McKendrick, A contribution to the mathematical theory of epidemics, Proc. R. Soc. Lond. A 115.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b28">
                <label>28</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sb28">S.W. Park, B.M. Bolker, D. Champredon, D.J. Earn, M. Li, J.S. Weitz, B.T. Grenfell, J. Dushoff, Reconciling early-outbreak estimates of the basic reproductive number and its uncertainty: Framework and applications to the novel coronavirus (sars-cov-2) outbreak, medRxiv.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b29">
                <label>29</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb29">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bar-On</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Flamholz</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Phillips</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Milo</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Science forum: Sars-cov-2 (covid-19) by the numbers</article-title>
                  <source>ELife</source>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e57309</object-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b30">
                <label>30</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sb30"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/es/healthtopics/coronavirus" id="interref4">https://www.who.int/es/healthtopics/coronavirus</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b31">
                <label>31</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sb31"><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://coronavirus.jhu.edu/" id="interref5">https://coronavirus.jhu.edu/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b32">
                <label>32</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb32">
                  <article-title>The incubation period of coronavirus disease 2019 (covid-19) from publicly reported confirmed cases: Estimation and application</article-title>
                  <source>Ann. Intern. Med.</source>
                  <volume>172</volume>
                  <issue>9</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>577</fpage>
                  <lpage>582</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32150748</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b33">
                <label>33</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sb33">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>E.C. for Disease Prevention, C</surname>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>Coronavirus disease 2019 (covid-19) in the eu/ eea and the UK – eighth update</part-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <comment>Rapid Risk Assessment (8)</comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b34">
                <label>34</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other" id="sb34">Y. Liu, A.A. Gayle, A. Wilder-Smith, J. Rocklöv, The reproductive number of COVID-19 is higher compared to SARS coronavirus, J. Travel Med. 27 (2).</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="b35">
                <label>35</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sb35">
                  <article-title>Prevalence of asymptomatic sars-cov-2 infection</article-title>
                  <source>Ann. Intern. Med.</source>
                  <volume>173</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>362</fpage>
                  <lpage>367</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32491919</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
            <sec id="appA">
              <label>Appendix A</label>
              <title>Global lockdown with complementary health policies</title>
              <p id="d1e3850">We analyze here the effects of complementary health policies during the global lockdown. <xref rid="figA.18" ref-type="fig">Fig. A.18(a)</xref> shows the number of new infected people along time for three different infection rate (see caption for details). It is also shown the evolution for the case of no lockdown at all. The mobility cutoff prevents the infection curves in <xref rid="figA.18" ref-type="fig">Fig. A.18(a)</xref> from growing almost immediately after the beginning of the lockdown. In this sense, the more additional health policies, the faster decrease of the new infected individuals.</p>
              <p id="d1e3860"><xref rid="figA.18" ref-type="fig">Fig. A.18(b)</xref> exhibits the number of individuals that passed over the disease as a function of time (see caption for details). These correspond to those individuals that previously appear as infected in <xref rid="figA.18" ref-type="fig">Fig. A.18(a)</xref>. First, it can be seen that the number of removed individuals increase since the outbreak of the disease. Second, it reaches a plateau soon after the lockdown is established. The plateau level, however, strongly depends on the complementary health policies. The more “intense” health policies (<italic>i.e.</italic> the lower infection rate), the lower number of removed individuals.<fig id="figA.18"><label>Fig. A.18</label><caption><p>(a) Number of new infected people and (b) normalized number of removed individuals as a function of time. The plot in (b) is normalized with respect to the total population of the city (4.32 M). The global lockdown started at the day 100 after the first infected was detected. This is indicated by a vertical line in (a) and (b). Before this day, the infection rate equals to <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e943" display="inline" altimg="si34.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>75</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. However, from this day, the infection rate equals: <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1046_lrg.gif"/><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e971" display="inline" altimg="si125.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1047_lrg.gif"/>
 <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1001" display="inline" altimg="si126.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1048_lrg.gif"/><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1032" display="inline" altimg="si67.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>. <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1049_lrg.gif"/>
 corresponds to the scenario of no lockdown at all. In the last case, the infection rate remains constant along the simulation process and equals to <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1051" display="inline" altimg="si34.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>75</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr18_lrg"/></fig></p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="appB">
              <label>Appendix B</label>
              <title>Comparison between global and local lockdown</title>
              <p id="d1e3880">This appendix compare the global and local lockdown in terms of the new infected individuals. Recall that the global lockdown “cutoff” the human mobility around the city. In this sense, all blocks are isolated from the rest regardless of whether they are “infected” or not. On the contrary, the mobility is suppressed (depending the infected threshold) only for the inhabitants of “infected blocks” in the local lockdown.</p>
              <p id="d1e3882"><xref rid="figB.19" ref-type="fig">Fig. B.19</xref> shows the number of new infected people along time implementing a global and local lockdown (see caption for details). It is also shown the evolution for the case of no lockdown at all. It can be seen that both curves matches along time. This means that it is not necessary isolated all blocks to reduce the infection. In this sense, as can be expected, only is necessary isolated those infected blocks. Therefore, we can conclude that the local lockdown is the “efficient” case of the global lockdown.<fig id="figB.19"><label>Fig. B.19</label><caption><p>Comparison between the number new infected in the global ( <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1050_lrg.gif"/>
) and local ( <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1051_lrg.gif"/>
) lockdown scenario. The global and local lockdown started at the day 100 after the first infected was detected. This is indicated by a vertical line. From this day, all those infected blocks in which the number of infected exceeds 0 are isolated (in the local lockdown scenario). <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1052_lrg.gif"/>
 corresponds to the scenario of no lockdown at all. From the lockdown implementation day, the infection rate switches from <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1103" display="inline" altimg="si34.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>75</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1122" display="inline" altimg="si125.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (in both cases).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr19_lrg"/></fig></p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="appC">
              <label>Appendix C</label>
              <title>Implementation of the testing &amp; back-tracing strategy</title>
              <p id="d1e3895">We represent in this Section a possible testing procedure by means of a probability <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3898" display="inline" altimg="si131.svg"><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> as follows:</p>
              <p id="d1e3902">
                <list list-type="simple" id="d1e3904">
                  <list-item id="lst15">
                    <label>1.</label>
                    <p id="d1e3908">We first chose (and test) a block at random with probability <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3911" display="inline" altimg="si131.svg"><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item id="lst16">
                    <label>2.</label>
                    <p id="d1e3918">If the chosen block is infected, we lock down the block until the disease disappears. If not, the block remains “open”.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item id="lst17">
                    <label>3.</label>
                    <p id="d1e3923">We trace back and test <italic>all</italic> the individuals who visited the infected block.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item id="lst18">
                    <label>4.</label>
                    <p id="d1e3931">We lock down any of the above blocks if infected.</p>
                  </list-item>
                  <list-item id="lst19">
                    <label>5.</label>
                    <p id="d1e3936">We repeat this procedure every day.</p>
                  </list-item>
                </list>
              </p>
              <p id="d1e3938"><xref rid="figC.20" ref-type="fig">Fig. C.20</xref> shows the number of new infected people along time for three different testing probabilities (see caption for details). It is also shown the time evolution for the case of no lockdown at all. Notice that the propagation decreases dramatically for the ideal tested scenario. But the possibility of stopping the outbreak vanishes in a bad (or poor) testing scenario. As can be seen in <xref rid="figC.20" ref-type="fig">Fig. C.20</xref> the back-tracing of the infected improves the mitigation strategy.</p>
              <p id="d1e3947"><xref rid="figC.21" ref-type="fig">Fig. C.21</xref> shows the number of removed individuals at the end of the epidemic in terms of the testing probability <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e3956" display="inline" altimg="si131.svg"><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> for three different complementary health policies (see caption for details). It can be seen that, in a scenario without complementary health policies (blue squares in <xref rid="figC.21" ref-type="fig">Fig. C.21</xref>), a massive testing (of more than 80%) is the only tool to avoid a wide spreading on the population. Note that this percentage is significantly reduced to 60% if a back tracing policy is also implemented.<fig id="figC.20"><label>Fig. C.20</label><caption><p>Number of new infected people as a function of time. The local lockdown is applied when the number of new infected equals to 5k (indicated by the vertical line). From the lockdown implementation day, we test each block with probability equal to: <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1053_lrg.gif"/>
 100%, <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1054_lrg.gif"/>
 75% and <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1055_lrg.gif"/>
 25% (see text for details). <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1056_lrg.gif"/>
 corresponds to the scenario of no lockdown at all (<italic>i.e.</italic><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1189" display="inline" altimg="si133.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mtext>%</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). Dashed lines corresponds to the scenario including back tracing of the infected individuals. Those infected blocks are isolated until the infection inside the corresponding block disappears. We consider the isolation of the infected blocks as the only heath policy. Thus, the infection rate equals to <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1201" display="inline" altimg="si34.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>75</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> all along the propagation process.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr20_lrg"/></fig></p>
              <p id="d1e3964">Notice from <xref rid="figC.21" ref-type="fig">Fig. C.21</xref> that the implementation of strict complementary health policies (such as the use of a mask and social distancing) improves the mitigation of the disease.</p>
              <p id="d1e3970">
                <fig id="figC.21">
                  <label>Fig. C.21</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Normalized number of removed individuals at the end of the epidemic as a function of the testing probability. The normalization was done with respect to the city population. The local lockdown is applied when the number of new infected equals to 5k. From the lockdown implementation day, the infection rate switches from <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1228" display="inline" altimg="si34.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak" linebreakstyle="after">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mn>75</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to: <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1057_lrg.gif"/>
 <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1256" display="inline" altimg="si67.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1058_lrg.gif"/>
 <inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1274" display="inline" altimg="si126.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-graphic xlink:href="fx1059_lrg.gif"/><inline-formula><mml:math id="d1e1305" display="inline" altimg="si125.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>β</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (see text for more details). Dashed lines corresponds to the scenario including back tracing of the infected individuals. Those infected blocks were isolated until the infection within the corresponding block disappears.</p>
                  </caption>
                  <graphic xlink:href="gr21_lrg"/>
                </fig>
              </p>
            </sec>
            <ack id="d1e3819">
              <title>Acknowledgments</title>
              <p id="d1e3822">This work was supported by the <funding-source id="GS1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100002923</institution-id><institution>National Scientific and Technical Research Council, Argentina</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> (spanish: Consejo Nacional de Investigaciones Científicas y Técnicas - CONICET, Argentina) and grant <funding-source id="GS2"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100010253</institution-id><institution>Programación Científica 2018 (UBACYT), Argentina</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source> Number 20020170100628BA. G. Frank thanks <funding-source id="GS3"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/100014552</institution-id><institution>Universidad Tecnológica Nacional (UTN), Argentina</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source>
for partial support through Grant PID Number SIUTNBA0006595.</p>
            </ack>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
