<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-03-11T00:52:39Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8205286" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8205286</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-06-16</datestamp>
        <setSpec>pheelsevier</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.xsd" article-type="research-article">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Commun Nonlinear Sci Numer Simul</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Commun Nonlinear Sci Numer Simul</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Communications in Nonlinear Science &amp; Numerical Simulation</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">1007-5704</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1878-7274</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Elsevier B.V.</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC8205286</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8205286</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">8205286</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34149236</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pii">S1007-5704(21)00239-2</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cnsns.2021.105927</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">105927</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Research Paper</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Network synchronization, stability and rhythmic processes in a diffusive mean-field coupled SEIR model</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0001">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Verma</surname>
                    <given-names>Tina</given-names>
                  </name>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0002">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Gupta</surname>
                    <given-names>Arvind Kumar</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="cor0001" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="aff0001">Department of Mathematics, Indian Institute of Technology Ropar, Rupnagar, 140001, Punjab, India</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor0001"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author.</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>15</day>
                <month>6</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.-->
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <month>11</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>15</day>
                <month>6</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>102</volume>
              <fpage>105927</fpage>
              <lpage>105927</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>23</day>
                  <month>12</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>14</day>
                  <month>4</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>12</day>
                  <month>6</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2021 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
                <copyright-holder>Elsevier B.V.</copyright-holder>
                <license>
                  <license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="abs0001">
                <p>Connectivity and rates of movement have profound effect on the persistence and extinction of infectious diseases. The emerging disease spread rapidly, due to the movement of infectious persons to some other regions, which has been witnessed in case of novel coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19). So, the networks and the epidemiology of directly transmitted infectious diseases are fundamentally linked. Motivated by the recent empirical evidence on the dispersal of infected individuals among the patches, we present the epidemic model SEIR (Susceptible-Exposed-Infected-Recovered) in which the population is divided into patches which form a network and the patches are connected through mean-field diffusive coupling. The corresponding unstable epidemiology classes will be synchronized and achieve stable state when the patches are coupled. Apart from synchronization and stability, the coupled model enables a range of rhythmic processes such as birhythmicity and rhythmogenesis which have not been investigated in epidemiology. The stability of Disease Free Equilibrium (or Endemic Equilibrium) is attained through cessation of oscillation mechanism namely Oscillation Death (OD) and Amplitude Death (AD). Corresponding to identical and non-identical epidemiology classes of patches, the different steady states are obtained and its transition is taking place through Hopf and transcritical bifurcation.</p>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group id="keys0001">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>SEIR model</kwd>
                <kwd>Patches</kwd>
                <kwd>Birhythmicity</kwd>
                <kwd>Coupling</kwd>
                <kwd>Stability</kwd>
                <kwd>Rhythmogenesis</kwd>
                <kwd>Amplitude death</kwd>
                <kwd>Oscillation death</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="sec0001">
              <label>1</label>
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p id="p0006">For last many years, several researchers of different fields are working on epidemic modeling which mainly consists of two components i.e., disease state model and its connectivity. The disease model describes the effect of infection over the population with respect to time and connectivity determines the contact and movement among the population. To clarify the dynamics of transmitting infectious diseases such as measles, mumps, West-Nile virus and Nipah virus so on, multi-patch epidemic models <xref rid="bib0001" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0002" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref> have been studied in the literature of mathematical epidemiology. The mathematical epidemiology models are based on the compartments such as Susceptible<inline-formula><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si16.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, Exposed <inline-formula><mml:math id="M2" altimg="si17.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, Infected <inline-formula><mml:math id="M3" altimg="si18.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and Recovered <inline-formula><mml:math id="M4" altimg="si19.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.The dispersal of population affects the dynamics of disease. The infectious disease brings misery and cause millions of death every year <xref rid="bib0004" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. Significantly, recent example is COVID-19 <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref> which has affected most of the countries. It was originated in China and spread in most of the countries through dispersal of infected ones. So, the dispersal of population plays an important role during the disease spread.</p>
              <p id="p0007">The dispersal among separated patches connects the corresponding epidemiology classes and generate rhythmic processes. Birhythmicity is an important concept in rhythmic process which is one of the dynamical feature of non linear systems and studied in the fields of physics, chemistry and biology. It is an interesting demonstration of multi-stability that arises in many natural as well as human-made systems. Birhythmic oscillations which appear in living systems are the intracellular Ca2+ oscillations <xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, glycolytic oscillations and enzymatic reactions <xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, the circadian oscillation in Period (PER) and Timeless (TIM) proteins in Drosophila <xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, the cyclic AMP signaling system of the slime mold Dictyostelium discoideum <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref> and rhythm that arises in population dynamics <xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. Aside from living systems, many artificial systems also exhibit birhythmic oscillations (e.g., the wind-induced mechanical energy harvesting system <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0016" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>). Another important concept of rhythmic oscillation is rhythmogenesis which is the inverse of the amplitude death. The mechanism of rhythmogenesis has been studied in the respiratory center <xref rid="bib0017" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref> and is used for defining the process of breath generation. The dispersal induced synchrony <xref rid="bib0018" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0019" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, brings rhythmic process in the compartment classes of the population when these spatial separated patches are connected through coupling for dispersal. In the same manner, dispersal induced stability <xref rid="bib0021" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref> stabilizes all the oscillators (Susceptible, Exposed, Infected and Recovered) of the patches.</p>
              <p id="p0008">The effects of the coupling on the population usually depends on the nature of coupling, its strength and the dynamic behaviour of the compartment classes of the population. In the present work, mean-field diffusive coupling <xref rid="bib0022" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref> is used for the connectivity of the patches. The dynamics of population in the patches can be easily modelled through differential equations. Generally, when the coupling is moderate and weak then the oscillators (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M5" altimg="si20.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M6" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>) of the patches oscillate in the synchronized manner. When the coupling is strong and high, these oscillators suppress or quench and drive each other to attain a fixed point <xref rid="bib0023" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. The intriguing effects are AD (Amplitude Death) and OD (Oscillation Death) to deal with the cessation of oscillations <xref rid="bib0024" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. AD is the suppression of oscillations in trivial homogenous steady state (HSS) whereas OD is formation of inhomogeneous steady state. On the other hand, coupling can regenerate the oscillations from steady state which is called rhythmogenesis <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. So, rhythmogenesis is a coupling induced oscillation that takes the entire system from steady state to oscillatory state. From biology prospective of rhythm, birhythmicity is one more fascinating event <xref rid="bib0026" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. The phenomenon of birhythmicity is defined as the coexistence of two stable limit cycles of different frequencies and amplitude which are separated by an unstable limit cycle. Since, dispersal plays an important role for transmission of disease thus birhythmicity and rhythmogenesis, which are induced by coupling, are not explored so it requires special attention.</p>
              <p id="p0009">The issues involved in the present paper are how the movement of an infected individual can effect the public at large and whether the effect would be same for identical epidemiology classes and non-identical epidemiology classes i.e., when all the parameters for each patch are same and different respectively.</p>
              <p id="p0010">We considered SEIR model in which the patches are connected using mean-field diffusive coupling for dispersal. After the study, it has been found that the state of synchronization of the patches and stability is obtained through the movement of infected individual. The effect of coupling is not same for identical and non-identical epidemiology classes. In identical epidemiology classes, the state of synchronization, birhythmicity and stability is obtained whereas in non-identical epidemiology classes, apart from these states, one new state rhythmogenesis is also obtained which is a novel effect involving generation of oscillations observed when two quiescent oscillators are coupled.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0002">
              <label>2</label>
              <title>Model formulation</title>
              <p id="p0011">We consider a model in which the host population is divided into <inline-formula><mml:math id="M7" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> patches which forms a network. In the network, each patch represent a node with bidirectional links <inline-formula><mml:math id="M8" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. Here <inline-formula><mml:math id="M9" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> represents the total number of connections each node has with other nodes containing itself too. The subpopulation in each patch (or node) is divided into four epidemiology classes <inline-formula><mml:math id="M10" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M11" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M12" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M13" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. Here, each node represent a city or a town, a country, or a small domain such as neighborhoods, which belong respectively to the global domain of interest, which could in turn represent a part of a continent or even a whole continent etc. The interactions among the epidemiology compartments (namely <inline-formula><mml:math id="M14" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M15" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M16" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M17" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>) within the patch and their associated migration among the patches are modeled using SEIR model. This model involves logistic growth <xref rid="bib0027" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, bilinear incidence rate <xref rid="bib0028" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, natural death rate <xref rid="bib0029" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, death due to disease <xref rid="bib0029" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>, transmission rate from exposed to infected population and recovery rate.</p>
              <p id="p0012">Since the movement of the susceptible population will not change the dynamics significantly however the dynamics will change even if there is movement of a single infected person. So, we have considered the movement of the infected ones only. The mean-field coupling is used in the compartment class <inline-formula><mml:math id="M18" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. The dynamics in the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M19" altimg="si22.svg"><mml:msup><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> patch of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M20" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M21" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M22" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M23" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> using mean-field diffusive coupling is defined as follows:<disp-formula id="eq0001"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M24" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="eq0002"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M25" altimg="si24.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="eq0003"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M26" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="eq0004"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="M27" altimg="si26.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M28" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M29" altimg="si28.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
              <p id="p0013">The parameters in the above equations are defined as follows: In the compartment class of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M30" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M31" altimg="si29.svg"><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the growth rate of Susceptible with its carrying capacity <inline-formula><mml:math id="M32" altimg="si30.svg"><mml:mi>K</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> in the logistic growth and in the infection transmission, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M33" altimg="si31.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is the transmission or contact rate and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M34" altimg="si32.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> denotes the inhibitory effect whereas <inline-formula><mml:math id="M35" altimg="si33.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is the natural death rate for all the compartment classes in the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M36" altimg="si22.svg"><mml:msup><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> patch. In the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M37" altimg="si22.svg"><mml:msup><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> patch of compartment class of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M38" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M39" altimg="si34.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> denotes the transmission rate from the exposed class to infected class. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M40" altimg="si35.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M41" altimg="si36.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> denote the death due to disease and recovery rate in the epidemiology class of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M42" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> respectively. The intrinsic dynamics of the epidemiology classes in the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M43" altimg="si22.svg"><mml:msup><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> patch is expressed by the above mentioned parameters without their movement among the patches.</p>
              <p id="p0014">On the other hand, the movement of the epidemiology class <inline-formula><mml:math id="M44" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is described by the mean-field diffusive coupling. In the mean-field diffusive coupling, the parameters <inline-formula><mml:math id="M45" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> represent the dispersal rate i.e., coupling strength of compartment class <inline-formula><mml:math id="M46" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. The parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="M47" altimg="si14.svg"><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> describes the mean-field strength of compartment class <inline-formula><mml:math id="M48" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
              <p id="p0015">The interpretations of mean-field diffusive coupling for the epidemic model are as follows: the immigration and emigration of the sub-population is described by the positive and negative terms of the mean-field coupling <inline-formula><mml:math id="M49" altimg="si37.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). The parameters <inline-formula><mml:math id="M50" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> establish the strength of dispersal of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M51" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> among the connected patches. The average distribution of the compartment class <inline-formula><mml:math id="M52" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> among the connected patches is measured through the mean-field density <inline-formula><mml:math id="M53" altimg="si14.svg"><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, which lies between 0 and 1. The considered coupling induces the same qualitative and quantitative behavior as in ref. <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref> with additional epidemiology class of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M54" altimg="si38.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> population. In particular, the dispersion of infected ones will not take place among the selected patches when the value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M55" altimg="si14.svg"><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is 0. It causes that the diffusion out of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M56" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> among the selected patches. The task of balancing the immigration in the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M57" altimg="si22.svg"><mml:msup><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> patch by the emigration from other selected patch will be done when the value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M58" altimg="si14.svg"><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is 1. The important and interesting epidemic relevance occur when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M59" altimg="si39.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> as the immigration and emigration of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M60" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> will take place among the selected patches.</p>
              <p id="p0016">Furthermore, it has been considered that the new born population will be susceptible. It is further assumed that the infection is transmitted only when the susceptible population come in contact with infected population and the disease will be transmitted immediately upon contact.</p>
              <p id="p0017">A network of the epidemic model in which the population is divided into <inline-formula><mml:math id="M61" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> patches is shown in <xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>
. Here, the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M62" altimg="si22.svg"><mml:msup><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> patch is connected to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M63" altimg="si40.svg"><mml:msup><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M64" altimg="si41.svg"><mml:msup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> patch, so the value of the connection link i.e., <inline-formula><mml:math id="M65" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M66" altimg="si22.svg"><mml:msup><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> patch is 3. Since, mean-field diffusive coupling is used so migration will take place in all the patches including <inline-formula><mml:math id="M67" altimg="si40.svg"><mml:msup><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M68" altimg="si41.svg"><mml:msup><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> patch but for the clarity purpose it has been shown only in <inline-formula><mml:math id="M69" altimg="si22.svg"><mml:msup><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> patch as the main motive of <xref rid="fig0001" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref> is to show how the migration takes place. Here, the migration will take place only in the epidemiology class <inline-formula><mml:math id="M70" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> whereas in <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref> it is considered in all the epidemiology classes.<fig id="fig0001"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Schematic representation of the epidemic model consists of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M71" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> patches. A system composed of network with patches, connected by mean-filed coupling for migration. Every patch of subpopulation contains the population of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M72" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M73" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M74" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M75" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> which are shown with different colors.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0001">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig></p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0003">
              <label>3</label>
              <title>Existence of disease-free equilibrium and endemic equilibrium</title>
              <p id="p0018">Since, the governing equations of the model working for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M76" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> patches so for simple calculation purpose and for better understanding, two patches have been taken into account. When the patches will be synchronized with identical epidemiology classes, then we have <inline-formula><mml:math id="M77" altimg="si42.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M78" altimg="si43.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M79" altimg="si44.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M80" altimg="si45.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The analytic solution of equilibrium points is obtained by equating the equations <inline-formula><mml:math id="M81" altimg="si46.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to zero.</p>
              <p id="p0019">The trivial fixed point of the coupled SEIR model is (0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0) and two of the non-trivial fixed points are <inline-formula><mml:math id="M82" altimg="si47.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M83" altimg="si48.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. These two non-trivial fixed points <inline-formula><mml:math id="M84" altimg="si47.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M85" altimg="si48.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> represent disease-free equilibrium (DFE) and endemic equilibrium (EE) respectively, where<disp-formula id="eq0005"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="M86" altimg="si49.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="eq0006"><label>(6)</label><mml:math id="M87" altimg="si50.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ϑ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>ϑ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="eq0007"><label>(7)</label><mml:math id="M88" altimg="si51.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ϑ</mml:mi><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mi>ϑ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>]</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>ϑ</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="eq0008"><label>(8)</label><mml:math id="M89" altimg="si52.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mi>ϑ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>]</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>ϑ</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>and<disp-formula id="eq0009"><label>(9)</label><mml:math id="M90" altimg="si53.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>ϑ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>]</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>ϑ</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M91" altimg="si54.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ϑ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
              <p id="p0020">However, there may exist any other non-trivial fixed points except <inline-formula><mml:math id="M92" altimg="si47.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M93" altimg="si48.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo>*</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> which are difficult to find analytically.</p>
              <sec id="sec0004">
                <label>3.1</label>
                <title>Reproduction number <inline-formula><mml:math id="M94" altimg="si55.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula></title>
                <p id="p0021">The DFE is a very important equilibrium point for any disease model as it determines that the disease is capable of spreading among the entire population or not. The stability of the DFE is investigated through the reproduction number <inline-formula><mml:math id="M95" altimg="si55.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>. The concept of next-generation matrix is used to compute the basic reproduction number <inline-formula><mml:math id="M96" altimg="si55.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>
<xref rid="bib0031" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. The next-generation matrix is partitioned into two matrices <inline-formula><mml:math id="M97" altimg="si56.svg"><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M98" altimg="si57.svg"><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>. The reproduction number <inline-formula><mml:math id="M99" altimg="si55.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is the spectral radius of the next-generation matrix denoted by <inline-formula><mml:math id="M100" altimg="si58.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ρ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. On solving the next generation matrix, the dominant eigen value at DFE <inline-formula><mml:math id="M101" altimg="si47.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is<disp-formula id="ueq0001"><mml:math id="M102" altimg="si59.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>ϑ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:msqrt><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mn>16</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>ϑ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>ϑ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>which is the reproduction number <inline-formula><mml:math id="M103" altimg="si55.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> at DFE.</p>
                <p id="p0022">The DFE is globally asymptotically stable and disease will die out if <inline-formula><mml:math id="M104" altimg="si60.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&lt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> whereas the EE is globally asymptotically stable if <inline-formula><mml:math id="M105" altimg="si61.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">&gt;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<xref rid="bib0032" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>.</p>
                <p id="p0023">The stability can be checked easily from this reproduction number <inline-formula><mml:math id="M106" altimg="si55.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>, by substituting the values of the parameters used in identical epidemiology classes.</p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0005">
                <label>3.2</label>
                <title>Linear stability analysis</title>
                <p id="p0024">The stability of the DFE and EE can also be verified by calculating the eigen values of the Jacobian matrix of the equations <inline-formula><mml:math id="M107" altimg="si62.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.16em"/><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> at these points. The Jacobian of the coupled system of equations (1)-(4) at the DFE <inline-formula><mml:math id="M108" altimg="si47.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is as follows:<disp-formula id="ueq0002"><mml:math id="M109" altimg="si63.svg"><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="right"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>ℶ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mn>13</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mn>24</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mn>33</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mn>57</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mn>67</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mn>77</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>where, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M110" altimg="si64.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mn>13</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mn>57</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
</p>
                <p id="p0025"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M111" altimg="si65.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mn>24</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mn>67</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M112" altimg="si66.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mn>33</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mn>77</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                <p id="p0026">The eigen values of the above jacobian matrix <inline-formula><mml:math id="M113" altimg="si67.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>ℶ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> are as follows:<disp-formula id="ueq0003"><mml:math id="M114" altimg="si68.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="ueq0004"><mml:math id="M115" altimg="si69.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo>;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="ueq0005"><mml:math id="M116" altimg="si70.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>±</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:msqrt><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="ueq0006"><mml:math id="M117" altimg="si71.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>7</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>±</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>[</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo>(</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:msqrt><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula> where, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M118" altimg="si72.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M119" altimg="si73.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                <p id="p0027">The eigen values of the proposed coupled system reduces to the uncoupled system if <inline-formula><mml:math id="M120" altimg="si74.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is substituted in the eigen values <inline-formula><mml:math id="M121" altimg="si75.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M122" altimg="si76.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> i.e, when the system is uncoupled then <inline-formula><mml:math id="M123" altimg="si77.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M124" altimg="si76.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mn>6</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> are the eigen values of the uncoupled system. The new eigen values <inline-formula><mml:math id="M125" altimg="si78.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mn>7</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M126" altimg="si79.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>λ</mml:mi><mml:mn>8</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> are obtained due to coupling of infected class in two patches.</p>
                <p id="p0028">The stability of DFE can be easily checked by substituting the values of the parameters in the obtained eigen values.</p>
                <p id="p0029">Similarly, the stability of EE can be checked after calculating the eigen values at EE point. Since, the calculations are very lengthy in case of EE, therefore it has been skipped. The equations are solved and stability is checked through the softwares Mapple and Mathematica.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0006">
              <label>4</label>
              <title>Results</title>
              <p id="p0030">The dynamics of the coupled SEIR model is studied in this section. The stability of the equilibrium points, obtained in <xref rid="sec0003" ref-type="sec">Section 3</xref>, will be checked by substituting the values of the parameters in the reproduction number and eigen values. The two patches i.e., patch 1 and patch 2 are considered with the assumption that in the absence of dispersal, the sub-population of each individual patch shows oscillatory behavior. In absence of dispersal rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="M127" altimg="si80.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, the SEIR model exhibits the local dynamics. The dynamics of coupled SEIR model are identified when all the parameters are same and some of the parameters are different i.e.,identical and non-identical epidemiology classes respectively. The state of birhythmicity,synchronization, stability and rhythmogenesis is analyzed. The numerical bifurcation is done through Xppaut <xref rid="bib0033" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref> and matcont <xref rid="bib0034" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref> package.</p>
              <sec id="sec0007">
                <label>4.1</label>
                <title>Bistability, synchronization and birhythmicity in identical epidemiology classes</title>
                <p id="p0031">Firstly, identical epidemiology classes of two patches have been considered in which all the epidemiology classes will have same contact rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="M128" altimg="si81.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, inhibitory effect <inline-formula><mml:math id="M129" altimg="si82.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, natural death rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="M130" altimg="si83.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, transmission rate from exposed to infectious <inline-formula><mml:math id="M131" altimg="si84.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, death rate due to disease <inline-formula><mml:math id="M132" altimg="si85.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and recovery rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="M133" altimg="si86.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. In absence of the dispersal <inline-formula><mml:math id="M134" altimg="si87.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, the epidemiology classes of both the patches will be independent and non-synchronized. It exhibits a limit cycle with the parameters <inline-formula><mml:math id="M135" altimg="si88.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M136" altimg="si89.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>20</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M137" altimg="si90.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.25</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M138" altimg="si91.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.8</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M139" altimg="si92.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M140" altimg="si93.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>δ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M141" altimg="si94.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>σ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.96</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M142" altimg="si95.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>γ</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.035</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M143" altimg="si96.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>∀</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. When the patches are coupled using mean-field diffusive coupling, the patches will come to synchronized state, will suppress each other and lead towards the equilibrium points through oscillation quenching mechanism i.e., amplitude death (AD) and oscillation death (OD). The new state birhythmicity is also observed which have not been studied in epidemiology.</p>
                <p id="p0032">Using one parameter bifurcation, the dynamics of the population of epidemiology classes is shown in <xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>
(a)-<xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>(d) for continuous variation in the coupling strength <inline-formula><mml:math id="M144" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Here, the limit cycles are represented by the circles whereas blue circles indicate unstable limit cycle and green circles denote stable limit cycle. The black curves represent unstable steady state and red curves indicate stable steady state. The value of mean-field strength <inline-formula><mml:math id="M145" altimg="si14.svg"><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is fixed as 0.9 and other parameters are same which are chosen to exhibit oscillatory state. In the presence of coupling, all the corresponding epidemiology classes from both the patches will be synchronized. When coupling strength is low, the population of epidemiology classes <inline-formula><mml:math id="M146" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M147" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M148" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M149" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> will show oscillatory behavior and exhibits limit cycle. With more increment in coupling strength <inline-formula><mml:math id="M150" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, the population of epidemiology classes <inline-formula><mml:math id="M151" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M152" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M153" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M154" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> quenches to oscillation death (OD). Here, we have observed one state of OD i.e., OD1. The inhomogeneous steady state of OD1 is created through supercritical Hopf bifurcation HB1. Depending on the initial conditions, the population of the epidemiology classes from both the pathes shows synchrony and stability induced by dispersal. From biological prospective, the inhomogeneous steady state OD represents endemic equilibrium in which the population of all the epidemiology classes co-exist with non-zero density. When coupling strength is high, there will be occurrence of two states of amplitude death i.e., AD1 and AD2. The state of AD1 is created through another supercritical Hopf Bifurcation HB3 which represents another endemic equilibrium state (EE). The state of AD2 is created through transcritical bifurcation (TB1) which represents disease-free equilibrium (DFE). Since, the state AD2 which represents DFE is coupling independent so it reaches to a constant value.<fig id="fig0002"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Identical epidemiology classes: (a), (b), (c), (d) One parameter bifurcation of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M155" altimg="si6.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M156" altimg="si7.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M157" altimg="si8.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M158" altimg="si9.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> by varying coupling strength <inline-formula><mml:math id="M159" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M160" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.9</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></p></caption><alt-text id="at0002">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="p0033">In the figures 2(a)-2(d), the bifurcation points HB, PB, TB and SNLC represent Hopf bifurcation, pitchfork bifurcation, transcritical bifurcation and saddle-node bifurcation of limit cycle respectively. In <xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Figs. 2</xref>(a)-<xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>(d),the green circles originating from HB3 indicates the perfect synchronized oscillation of the population of epidemiology classes <inline-formula><mml:math id="M161" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M162" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M163" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M164" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p>
                <p id="p0034">The state of perfect synchronization is shown in <xref rid="fig0003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>
(a) in which considered coupling strength <inline-formula><mml:math id="M165" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is 0.5 and mean-field strength <inline-formula><mml:math id="M166" altimg="si14.svg"><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is 0.9. In <xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">Figs. 2</xref>(a)-<xref rid="fig0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>(d), there exist one more stable limit cycle at HB1. When the coupling strength is decreased from HB1, the stable limit cycle loses its stability via saddle-node bifurcation of limit cycle (SNLC). There is also co-existence of two stable limit cycles between HB1 and SNLC for the value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M167" altimg="si13.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.59</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. This indicates birhythmic oscillation in coupled SEIR model. Each of the stable limit cycle acquires its own basin of attraction. Birhythmic oscillations are shown in <xref rid="fig0003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>(b) at <inline-formula><mml:math id="M168" altimg="si13.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.59</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> using time series. Two different colors have been used to distinguish between these two time series of birhythmic oscillations. Using corresponding phase portrait, the co-existence of two stable limit cycles is shown in <xref rid="fig0003" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>(c).<fig id="fig0003"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>(a) The synchronized solution for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M169" altimg="si12.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. (b) Time series showing birhythmic oscillations for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M170" altimg="si13.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.59</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Two different colors are used to represent different time series of birhythmic oscillations. (c) Phase portrait with two co-existing limit cycles of the corresponding birhythmic oscillations.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0003">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="p0035">The regions of birhythmic oscillations, monorhythm, AD and OD are shown in <xref rid="fig0004" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>
using two parameter bifurcation diagram of coupling strength <inline-formula><mml:math id="M171" altimg="si97.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and mean-field density <inline-formula><mml:math id="M172" altimg="si98.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. When the coupling strength is stronger and mean-field density is low, the patches of epidemiology classes converges to homogeneous steady states AD1 and AD2. On the other hand, when coupling strength is less and mean-field density is high, the epidemiology classes of both the patches will show oscillatory behavior. Between homogeneous steady states and oscillatory state, IHSS OD state and birhyhthm will also take place. The curves HB and SNLC denotes the curves of Hopf bifurcation and saddle-node bifurcation of limit cycle respectively.<fig id="fig0004"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Two parameter bifurcation in 2D-plane of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M173" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M174" altimg="si14.svg"><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula></p></caption><alt-text id="at0004">Fig. 4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4_lrg"/></fig></p>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0008">
                <label>4.2</label>
                <title>Bistability, synchronization, birhythmicity and rhythmogenesis in non-identical epidemiology classes</title>
                <p id="p0036">Since, the model has many parameters so, it is not possible to check the effect by changing all the parameters one by one and jointly. For this reason, in non-identical epidemiology classes of two patches, the contact rate <inline-formula><mml:math id="M175" altimg="si99.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and inhibitory effect <inline-formula><mml:math id="M176" altimg="si100.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are considered different. These different parameters are <inline-formula><mml:math id="M177" altimg="si101.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.25</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M178" altimg="si102.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M179" altimg="si103.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M180" altimg="si104.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, where as the other parameters are same as in identical case. Likewise identical epidemiology classes, here also the parameters are chosen in such a way that it remains in oscillatory state in absence of coupling. The dynamics of the the epidemiology classes of both the patches is shown in <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Figs. 5</xref>
(a), <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>(b), <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>(c) and <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>(d) using one-parameter bifurcation diagram of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M181" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.<fig id="fig0005"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Non-identical epidemiology classes: (a), (b), (c), (d) One parameter bifurcation of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M182" altimg="si6.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M183" altimg="si7.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M184" altimg="si8.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M185" altimg="si9.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> by varying coupling strength <inline-formula><mml:math id="M186" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M187" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.9</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></p></caption><alt-text id="at0005">Fig. 5</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr5_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="p0037">Likewise identical epidemiology classes, here also the coupled epidemiology classes show synchrony, bistability and birhythmic oscillations. The oscillations are suppressed to inhomogeneous steady state. Two inhomogeneous steady states are observed in this case i.e., OD1 and OD2. The OD1 state and OD2 state are created through supercritical Hopf bifurcation and transcritical bifurcation which are named as HB1 and TB1 in the figures 5(a)-5(d), respectively. As in identical epidemiology classes, here also the birhythmicity occurs between HB1 and SNLC. Furthermore, when the couplimg strength is increased then one more interesting feature takes place i.e., rhythmogenesis which is a new concept in epidemiology. The process of rhythmogenesis occur between the Hopf bifurcation points HB2 and HB3. Between these points, the oscillation are regenerated which were suppressed before. So, the mean-field coupling plays an important role to suppress and regenerate the oscillations. When the coupling strength is stronger the regenerated oscillations suppress to homogeneous steady states AD1 and AD2. At HB1, the density of epidemiology class <inline-formula><mml:math id="M188" altimg="si105.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is nearly zero but <inline-formula><mml:math id="M189" altimg="si106.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> has positive density. The states OD1, OD2 and AD1 represents the steady state of endemic equilibrium as all the epidemiology classes have non-zero density. Since, AD2 state is coupling independent so it is homogeneous steady state and represents disease-free equilibrium where only susceptible class has non-zero and constant density and other classes converges to zero. We have also observed period doubling bifurcation in coupled non-identical epidemiology classes. When the coupling strength is low, the period-doubling bifurcation is exhibiting by the epidemiology classes which is named as <inline-formula><mml:math id="M190" altimg="si107.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in the figures 5(a)-5(d).</p>
                <p id="p0038">The birhythmic oscillations and co-existence of two stable limit cycles at coupling strength <inline-formula><mml:math id="M191" altimg="si15.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and mean-field density <inline-formula><mml:math id="M192" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.9</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> are shown in <xref rid="fig0006" ref-type="fig">Figs. 6</xref>
(a) and <xref rid="fig0006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>(b) using time series analysis. Two different colors are used to indicate the birhythmicity.<fig id="fig0006"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>(a) Time series showing bi rhythmic oscillations for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M193" altimg="si15.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2.1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. Two different colors are used to represent different time series of birhythmic oscillations. (b) Phase portrait with two co-existing limit cycles of the corresponding birhythmic oscillations.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0006">Fig. 6</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr6_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="p0039">Using two-parameter bifurcation diagram of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M194" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M195" altimg="si14.svg"><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, the dynamics of the epidemiology classes is more clearer which has shown in <xref rid="fig0007" ref-type="fig">Fig. 7</xref>
. The epidemiology classes will be in oscillatory motion when the coupling strength is low and mean-field density is high. Between the curves <inline-formula><mml:math id="M196" altimg="si107.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M197" altimg="si108.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, the epidemiology classes will exhibit period doubling and birhythmicity which is observed by increasing the coupling strength <inline-formula><mml:math id="M198" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The epidemiology classes exhibits bistable states, which are inhomogeneous steady states, between Hopf bifurcation curves <inline-formula><mml:math id="M199" altimg="si108.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M200" altimg="si109.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. When the coupling strength is increased more, the epidemiology classes tends to homogeneous steady states.<fig id="fig0007"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Two parameter bifurcation in 2D-plane of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M201" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M202" altimg="si14.svg"><mml:mi>θ</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula></p></caption><alt-text id="at0007">Fig. 7</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr7_lrg"/></fig></p>
                <p id="p0040">Further we investigate the sensitivity of the parameter values on the system dynamics. It is observed that the dynamics of the epidemiology classes will remain unaffected against small variations in all the model parameters. There will be no qualitatively change even when the difference between transmission rate of two epidemiology classes <inline-formula><mml:math id="M203" altimg="si110.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.25</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.55</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is same as the difference between inhibitory effect <inline-formula><mml:math id="M204" altimg="si111.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.2</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> or same transmission rate i.e., <inline-formula><mml:math id="M205" altimg="si112.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="goodbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.25</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is considered. However, if <inline-formula><mml:math id="M206" altimg="si113.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>≈</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> i.e. the difference between <inline-formula><mml:math id="M207" altimg="si114.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M208" altimg="si115.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is small then the dynamics of the population of non-identical epidemiology classes become similar to the case of identical epidemiology classes.</p>
                <p id="p0041">In order to find the interplay between the non-identical patches, the value of inhibitory parameter <inline-formula><mml:math id="M209" altimg="si114.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M210" altimg="si115.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> was considered distinctly otherwise it will be the same as in identical epidemiology classes. Note that the different values considered for <inline-formula><mml:math id="M211" altimg="si114.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M212" altimg="si115.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> also depends on other system parameters. Hence, it is reasonable to conclude that the change in inhibitory effect is more significant for the qualitative change in the dynamics as compared to other system parameters.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0009">
              <label>5</label>
              <title>Conclusion</title>
              <p id="p0042">In this paper, we have studied the dynamics of an epidemic SEIR model in which the population is divided into patches. The four epidemiology classes <inline-formula><mml:math id="M213" altimg="si116.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M214" altimg="si117.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>
<inline-formula><mml:math id="M215" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M216" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> are considered in the patches and the patches are connected through mean-field diffusive coupling. The synchronization and stability for coupled epidemic model SEIR are explored using mean-field diffusive coupling. Different rhythmic processes have also been explored. The epidemiology classes of two distinct patches, which were uncoupled, behave independently and exhibits a limit cycle for the chosen parameters. The dynamics is studied when the epidemiology classes of two patches are identical and non-identical.</p>
              <p id="p0043">In case of identical epidemiology classes, contact rate, inhibitory effect, transmission rate from exposed class to infected class and recovery rate are considered same for epidemiology classes of two patches. When the patches of epidemiology classes are connected through mean-field diffusive coupling, the corresponding epidemiology classes of two patches will synchronize and follow same rhythm. Apart from this, we have observed the following:<list list-type="simple" id="lst0002"><list-item id="lstitem0006"><label>•</label><p id="p0044">There is co-existence of two stable limit cycles between Hopf bifurcation (HB1) and saddle-node limit cycle (SNLC) where each stable limit cycle acquires its own basin of attraction. This indicates birhythmicity which has not been observed earlier in epidemiology.</p></list-item><list-item id="lstitem0007"><label>•</label><p id="p0045">For higher coupling strength, the oscillations suppress and lead to inhomogeneous steady state OD1. Thereafter, OD1 converges to homogeneous steady state AD1 and then to AD2 through Hopf bifurcation and transcritical bifurcation respectively.</p></list-item><list-item id="lstitem0008"><label>•</label><p id="p0046">The state OD1 and AD1 represent the steady state of endemic equilibrium whereas AD2 represents disease free equilibrium. The stability is verified through the reproduction number <inline-formula><mml:math id="M217" altimg="si55.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> as well as through linear stability analysis.</p></list-item></list>
</p>
              <p id="p0047">In case of non-identical epidemiology classes, contact rate and inhibitory effect are considered different for epidemiology classes of two patches. Likewise identical epidemiology classes, the corresponding epidemiology classes of two patches will synchronize, follow same rhythm and birhythmicity occurs too. Moreover, we have analyzed the following results:<list list-type="simple" id="lst0003"><list-item id="lstitem0009"><label>•</label><p id="p0048">Here, we have explored bistable inhomogeneous steady state OD1 and OD2 which are created through Hopf and transcritical bifurcation respectively. Furthermore, two homogeneous steady states are also observed i.e., AD1 and AD2.</p></list-item><list-item id="lstitem0010"><label>•</label><p id="p0049">For low coupling strength, we have also explored period-doubling bifurcation. The states OD1, OD2 and AD1 represent steady state of endemic equilibrium and AD2 represents disease-free equilibrium.</p></list-item><list-item id="lstitem0011"><label>•</label><p id="p0050">Here, the mean-field diffusive coupling acts as feedback for the interesting feature of rhythmicity i.e., rhythmogenesis is explored. In this feature, the oscillations which were suppressed are regenerated.</p></list-item></list>
</p>
              <p id="p0051">We have studied the impact of coupling on the dynamics of coupled SEIR model with mean-field diffusive coupling in which the movement of only infectious class is considered. Apart from dispersal of infectious class, one can study the dynamics by considering the dispersal of all the epidemiology classes. The population of epidemiology classes can disperse through different mechanism which will also be very interesting to study its dynamics. Here, we have not considered the death due to movement of infectious people. One can consider the death of infectious population and other difficulties due to movement. It will also be interesting to study the dynamics when the delay will be considered.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0010">
              <title>Credit author statment</title>
              <p id="p0052">Tina Verma: The implementation of the idea, analysis, and method.</p>
              <p id="p0053">Arvind Kumar Gupta: Proposed the idea, interpret the results and supervised the work.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec sec-type="COI-statement">
              <title>Declaration of Competing Interest</title>
              <p id="p0054">The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list id="bib001">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="bib0001">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0001">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Arino</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Davis</surname>
                      <given-names>J.R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hartley</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jordan</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Miller</surname>
                      <given-names>J.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Driessche</surname>
                      <given-names>P.V.D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Math Med Biol</source>
                  <volume>22</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>2005</year>
                  <fpage>129</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15778332</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0002">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0002">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Earn</surname>
                      <given-names>D.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rohani</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Grenfell</surname>
                      <given-names>B.T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Proc R Soc Lond Ser B</source>
                  <volume>265</volume>
                  <issue>1390</issue>
                  <year>1998</year>
                  <fpage>7</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0003">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0003">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gilligan</surname>
                      <given-names>C.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Adv Botanic Res</source>
                  <volume>38</volume>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0004">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0004">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kuniya</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Muroya</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Appl Math Comput</source>
                  <volume>265</volume>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <fpage>785</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0005">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0005">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bai</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yao</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wei</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Tian</surname>
                      <given-names>F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jin</surname>
                      <given-names>D.Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chen</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Jama</source>
                  <volume>323</volume>
                  <issue>14</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1406</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32083643</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0006">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0006">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Velavan</surname>
                      <given-names>T.P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Meyer</surname>
                      <given-names>C.G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Tropic Med Int Health</source>
                  <volume>25</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>278</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0007">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0007">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Pisarchik</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jaimes-Reátegui</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Villalobos-Salazar</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Garcia-Lopez</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Boccaletti</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Phys Rev Lett</source>
                  <volume>96</volume>
                  <issue>24</issue>
                  <year>2006</year>
                  <fpage>244102</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16907245</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0008">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0008">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goldbeter</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Biochemical oscillations and cellular rhythms: the molecular bases of periodic and chaotic behaviour</chapter-title>
                  <year>1997</year>
                  <publisher-name>Cambridge university press</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0009">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0009">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goldbeter</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Nature</source>
                  <volume>420</volume>
                  <issue>6912</issue>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <fpage>238</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12432409</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0010">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0010">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kar</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ray</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>EPL (Europhys Lett)</source>
                  <volume>67</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <fpage>137</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0011">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0011">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kar</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ray</surname>
                      <given-names>D.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Phys Rev Lett</source>
                  <volume>90</volume>
                  <issue>23</issue>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <fpage>238102</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12857291</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0012">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0012">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Leloup</surname>
                      <given-names>J.C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goldbeter</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>J Theoretic Biol</source>
                  <volume>198</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <year>1999</year>
                  <fpage>445</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0013">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0013">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goldbeter</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Martiel</surname>
                      <given-names>J.L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>FEBS Lett</source>
                  <volume>191</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>1985</year>
                  <fpage>149</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0014">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0014">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Biswas</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Banerjee</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kurths</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Phys Rev E</source>
                  <volume>99</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <year>2019</year>
                  <fpage>062210</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31330633</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0015">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0015">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Biswas</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Banerjee</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kurths</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Chaos: Interdiscip J Nonlinear Sci</source>
                  <volume>27</volume>
                  <issue>6</issue>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <fpage>063110</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0016">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0016">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kwuimy</surname>
                      <given-names>C.K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nataraj</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Structural nonlinear dynamics and diagnosis</chapter-title>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                  <lpage>123</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0017">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0017">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Safonov</surname>
                      <given-names>V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lebedeva</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Human Physiol</source>
                  <volume>29</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <fpage>97</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0018">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0018">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yan</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fu</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.Q.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ren</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>W.X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Phys Rev E</source>
                  <volume>75</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <fpage>016108</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0019">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0019">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goldwyn</surname>
                      <given-names>E.E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hastings</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Theoretic Populat Biol</source>
                  <volume>73</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <fpage>395</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0020">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0020">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lloyd</surname>
                      <given-names>A.L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jansen</surname>
                      <given-names>V.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Math Biosci</source>
                  <volume>188</volume>
                  <issue>1-2</issue>
                  <year>2004</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0021">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0021">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lloyd</surname>
                      <given-names>A.L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>May</surname>
                      <given-names>R.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>J Theor Biol</source>
                  <volume>179</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <year>1996</year>
                  <fpage>1</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8733427</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0022">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0022">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Banerjee</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ghosh</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Phys Rev E</source>
                  <volume>89</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <year>2014</year>
                  <fpage>052912</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0023">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0023">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Koseska</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Volkov</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kurths</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Phys Rev Lett</source>
                  <volume>111</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <fpage>024103</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23889406</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0024">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0024">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Saxena</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Prasad</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ramaswamy</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Phys Rep</source>
                  <volume>521</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <year>2012</year>
                  <fpage>205</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0025">
                <label>25</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0025">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dasgupta</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rivera</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Parmananda</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Chaos: Interdiscip J Nonlinear Sci</source>
                  <volume>20</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>2010</year>
                  <fpage>023126</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0026">
                <label>26</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0026">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Decroly</surname>
                      <given-names>O.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Goldbeter</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source>
                  <volume>79</volume>
                  <issue>22</issue>
                  <year>1982</year>
                  <fpage>6917</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6960354</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0027">
                <label>27</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0027">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wang</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhou</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Liu</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xu</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>X.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>J Biol Dyn</source>
                  <volume>11</volume>
                  <year>2017</year>
                  <fpage>120</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27145100</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
                <note>
                  <p>(sup1)</p>
                </note>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0028">
                <label>28</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0028">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xu</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ma</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Chaos Soliton Fractal</source>
                  <volume>41</volume>
                  <issue>5</issue>
                  <year>2009</year>
                  <fpage>2319</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0029">
                <label>29</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0029">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Zhang</surname>
                      <given-names>J.P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Jin</surname>
                      <given-names>Z.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Appl Math Comput</source>
                  <volume>217</volume>
                  <issue>17</issue>
                  <year>2011</year>
                  <fpage>7053</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0030">
                <label>30</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0030">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Verma</surname>
                      <given-names>T.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gupta</surname>
                      <given-names>A.K.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Phys A: Stat Mechanics and its Applications</source>
                  <volume>541</volume>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>123300</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0031">
                <label>31</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0031">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Driessche</surname>
                      <given-names>P.V.d.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Watmough</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Math Biosci</source>
                  <volume>180</volume>
                  <issue>1-2</issue>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <fpage>29</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12387915</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0032">
                <label>32</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0032">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Driessche</surname>
                      <given-names>P.V.d.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Mathematical epidemiology</chapter-title>
                  <year>2008</year>
                  <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
                  <fpage>179</fpage>
                  <lpage>189</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0033">
                <label>33</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0033">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ermentrout</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <chapter-title>Simulating, analyzing, and animating dynamical systems: a guide to XPPAUT for researchers and students</chapter-title>
                  <year>2002</year>
                  <publisher-name>SIAM</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0034">
                <label>34</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0034">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dhooge</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Govaerts</surname>
                      <given-names>W.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kuznetsov</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>ACM Trans Math Softw (TOMS)</source>
                  <volume>29</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <fpage>141</fpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
            <ack id="ack0001">
              <title>Acknowledgements</title>
              <p id="p0055">The authors convey their sincere thanks to the anonymous reviewers for their insightful comments. The first author is also thankful to Indian Institute of Technology Ropar, Rupnagar, Punjab, India for providing fellowship to pursue Post-Doctoral Studies.</p>
            </ack>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
