<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-03-11T00:54:02Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8128624" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8128624</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-05-18</datestamp>
        <setSpec>milmedres</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="letter">
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mil Med Res</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mil Med Res</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Military Medical Research</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">2095-7467</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">2054-9369</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC8128624</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8128624</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">8128624</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">34001251</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">325</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40779-021-00325-4</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Letter to the Editor</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Predictive modelling for COVID-19 outbreak control: lessons from the navy cluster in Sri Lanka</article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
                  <contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0391-6220</contrib-id>
                  <name>
                    <surname>Wijesekara</surname>
                    <given-names>N. W. A. N. Y.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>novil.wijesekara@gmail.com</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Herath</surname>
                    <given-names>Nayomi</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>nayomiherath1979@gmail.com</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kodituwakku</surname>
                    <given-names>K. A. L. C.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>thuwakku@yahoo.co.uk</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Herath</surname>
                    <given-names>H. D. B.</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>hdbher@gmail.com</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ginige</surname>
                    <given-names>Samitha</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>samithag@hotmail.com</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Ruwanpathirana</surname>
                    <given-names>Thilanga</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>thilangar@yahoo.com</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Kariyawasam</surname>
                    <given-names>Manjula</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>kariyawasammp@gmail.com</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Samaraweera</surname>
                    <given-names>Sudath</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>sudath.samara@gmail.com</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Herath</surname>
                    <given-names>Anuruddha</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>asherath@gmail.com</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Jayawardena</surname>
                    <given-names>Senarupa</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>senarupaj@yahoo.com</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Gamge</surname>
                    <given-names>Deepa</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <address>
                    <email>deepagamage@gmail.com</email>
                  </address>
                  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.466905.8</institution-id><institution>Disaster Preparedness and Response Division, </institution><institution>Ministry of Health, </institution></institution-wrap>385, Rev. Baddegama Wimalawansa Thero Mawatha, Colombo, 01000 Sri Lanka </aff>
                <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.466905.8</institution-id><institution>Epidemiology Unit of the Ministry of Health, </institution></institution-wrap>Colombo, 01000 Sri Lanka </aff>
                <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Sri Lanka Navy, Colombo, 01100 Sri Lanka </aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>18</day>
                <month>5</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>18</day>
                <month>5</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>8</volume>
              <elocation-id>31</elocation-id>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>2</day>
                  <month>9</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>30</day>
                  <month>4</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2021</copyright-statement>
                <license>
                  <ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref>
                  <license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="Abs1">
                <p id="Par1">In response to an outbreak of coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) within a cluster of Navy personnel in Sri Lanka commencing from 22nd April 2020, an aggressive outbreak management program was launched by the Epidemiology Unit of the Ministry of Health. To predict the possible number of cases within the susceptible population under four social distancing scenarios, the COVID-19 Hospital Impact Model for Epidemics (CHIME) was used. With increasing social distancing, the epidemiological curve flattened, and its peak shifted to the right. The observed or actually reported number of cases was above the projected number of cases at the onset; however, subsequently, it fell below all predicted trends. Predictive modelling is a useful tool for the control of outbreaks such as COVID-19 in a closed community.</p>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>COVID-19</kwd>
                <kwd>Predictive modelling</kwd>
                <kwd>SIR model</kwd>
                <kwd>Navy cluster</kwd>
                <kwd>Outbreak management</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
              <custom-meta-group>
                <custom-meta>
                  <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
                  <meta-value>© The Author(s) 2021</meta-value>
                </custom-meta>
              </custom-meta-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <p id="Par5">Infectious diseases in semi-confined places such as Cruise Ships, Military Barracks, and College Dormitories can have rapid spread, coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) being no exception [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>].</p>
            <p id="Par6">While security forces are essential to staying in confined places as per their operational requirements, the spread of COVID-19 could have serious repercussions not only on the staff of the forces, but also on national security. On 22nd of April 2020, a new case from Polonnaruwa district, a navy sailor attached to the Sri Lanka Navy Base at Welisara, on leave tested positive for COVID-19 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Subsequently increasing number of COVID-19 cases were diagnosed from the same Naval Base. Having confirmed an outbreak in the Naval Base, several public health measures were implemented by the Epidemiology Unit of the Ministry of Health together with Sri Lanka Navy based on the findings of epidemiological investigations. It was necessary to predict how the outbreak could spread among the confined space of the Navy Base, in order to understand the health system demand from the infected individuals, as well as to quantify the effects on operational continuity of the Navy. The objective of this joint exercise by the civil and naval health authorities was to predict the possible number of cases within the susceptible population in Sri Lanka Navy Base at Welisara and their associated operational units in the Western Province, to be used primarily for operational planning purposes by the Ministry of Health to control a possible widespread outbreak of COVID-19 in Sri Lanka.</p>
            <p id="Par7">The COVID-19 Hospital Impact Model for Epidemics (CHIME) developed by Predictive Health Care Team at Penn Medicine, Philadelphia, USA, which uses a Monte Carlo simulation instantiation of a susceptible, infected, removed (SIR) model with a 1-day cycle was utilized [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. The model was run on 20th May 2020 for a susceptible population of 10,400, with the number of hospitalized patients on the day of running the model being 357, the first case hospitalized on 22nd April 2020, and social distancing being implemented on 26th April 2020. Social distancing scenarios of 0, 25, 50, and 74% were run with 10 days of infectious period and 30 days of the projection period.</p>
            <p id="Par8">As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, with an increasing social distancing from 0 to 74%, the epidemiological curve flattened, while the peak of the curve shifted right. Further, it could be seen that the observed or actually reported number of cases was well above the projected number of cases up to 7th May 2020. However, beyond this date, the reported number of cases was lower than the projected number of cases from the model under four social distancing scenarios considered. The typical bell-shaped epidemiological curve was not observed among the observed or the actual COVID-19 cases. This could most likely be due to the vigorous interventions carried out to curtail the outbreak by the health and security sectors.
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Projected and observed daily cases<italic>.</italic> The projected daily patients under 0, 25, 50 and 74% social distancing scenarios are shown in blue, green, brown and purple lines respectively. The projected daily patient curve flattens with increasing social distancing scenarios, while the time to the peak prolongs. The red line shows the observed daily cases which continue to be above the projected daily patient lines of all four social distancing scenarios up to 7th May 2020. However, since this date, the red line showing the observed number of cases curve goes below the projected number of cases under four social distancing scenarios considered</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40779_2021_325_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
            <p id="Par9">The practical use of a prediction model made readily available through an online open-source platform for the operational aspects of controlling outbreaks such as COVID-19 in a closed community was evident from this exercise. The findings could be used for strategic planning for curtailing the outbreak and for health system preparedness for the current outbreak, as well as for those in the future. Although active epidemiological surveillance, contact tracing, case isolation, and case management should be the cornerstone of outbreak management, the predictive epidemiological modelling could supplement the above efforts. It is recommended that both health and security personnel are exposed to the use of predictive epidemiological modelling during their outbreak preparedness and response training.</p>
          </body>
          <back>
            <glossary>
              <title>Abbreviations</title>
              <def-list>
                <def-item>
                  <term>COVID-19</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par2">coronavirus disease 2019</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>SIR</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par3">susceptible, infected and removed</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                  <term>CHIME</term>
                  <def>
                    <p id="Par4">COVID-19 Hospital Impact Model for Epidemics</p>
                  </def>
                </def-item>
              </def-list>
            </glossary>
            <ack>
              <title>Acknowledgements</title>
              <p>Not applicable.</p>
            </ack>
            <notes notes-type="author-contribution">
              <title>Authors’ contributions</title>
              <p>NWANYW developed the research methodology, planned and managed the overall research. NH conducted an in-depth analysis of the use of SIR model and along with KALCK did the running of the model. TR, MK, AH collected and collated the reported cases of COVID-19 from Sri Lanka Navy Cluster. HDBH, SJ, TR, MK, SS, SG, and DG contributed methodological and epidemiological improvements. DG has overseen the scientific vigour and quality assurance at all stages. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="funding-information">
              <title>Funding</title>
              <p>Not applicable.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes notes-type="data-availability">
              <title>Availability of data and materials</title>
              <p>The datasets used and/or analysed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p>
            </notes>
            <notes>
              <title>Declarations</title>
              <notes id="FPar1">
                <title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
                <p id="Par10">Not applicable.</p>
              </notes>
              <notes id="FPar2">
                <title>Consent for publication</title>
                <p id="Par11">Not applicable.</p>
              </notes>
              <notes id="FPar3" notes-type="COI-statement">
                <title>Competing interests</title>
                <p id="Par12">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
              </notes>
            </notes>
            <ref-list id="Bib1">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="CR1">
                <label>1.</label>
                <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kak V. Infections in confined spaces: cruise ships, military barracks, and college dormitories. Infect Dis Clin N Am. 2007;21(3):773–84, ix-x.</mixed-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR2">
                <label>2.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Payne</surname>
                      <given-names>DC</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Smith-Jeffcoat</surname>
                      <given-names>SE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Nowak</surname>
                      <given-names>G</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chukwuma</surname>
                      <given-names>U</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Geibe</surname>
                      <given-names>JR</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hawkins</surname>
                      <given-names>RJ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>SARS-CoV-2 infections and serologic responses from a sample of U.S. Navy service members - USS Theodore Roosevelt, April 2020</article-title>
                  <source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>69</volume>
                  <issue>23</issue>
                  <fpage>714</fpage>
                  <lpage>721</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15585/mmwr.mm6923e4</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32525850</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR3">
                <label>3.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Rocklöv</surname>
                      <given-names>J</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Sjödin</surname>
                      <given-names>H</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wilder-Smith</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>COVID-19 outbreak on the Diamond Princess cruise ship: estimating the epidemic potential and effectiveness of public health countermeasures</article-title>
                  <source>J Travel Med</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>27</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <fpage>taaa030</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jtm/taaa030</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32109273</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR4">
                <label>4.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <collab>Epidemiology Unit</collab>
                  </person-group>
                  <source>Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19)—situation</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="CR5">
                <label>5.</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Weissman</surname>
                      <given-names>GE</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Crane-Droesch</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Chivers</surname>
                      <given-names>C</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Luong</surname>
                      <given-names>T</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hanish</surname>
                      <given-names>A</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Levy</surname>
                      <given-names>MZ</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Locally informed simulation to predict hospital capacity needs during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title>
                  <source>Ann Intern Med</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <volume>173</volume>
                  <issue>1</issue>
                  <fpage>21</fpage>
                  <lpage>28</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/M20-1260</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32259197</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
