<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<OAI-PMH xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/OAI-PMH.xsd">
  <responseDate>2022-03-11T00:58:06Z</responseDate>
  <request verb="GetRecord" identifier="oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8529307" metadataPrefix="pmc">https:/www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/oai/oai.cgi</request>
  <GetRecord>
    <record>
      <header>
        <identifier>oai:pubmedcentral.nih.gov:8529307</identifier>
        <datestamp>2021-10-21</datestamp>
        <setSpec>pheelsevier</setSpec>
        <setSpec>pmc-open</setSpec>
      </header>
      <metadata>
        <article xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xsi:schemaLocation="https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/ns/archiving/1.3/ https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/archiving/1.3/xsd/JATS-archivearticle1-3.xsd" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3">
          <processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats">
            <restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by>
          </processing-meta>
          <front>
            <journal-meta>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Health Policy</journal-id>
              <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Health Policy</journal-id>
              <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>Health Policy (Amsterdam, Netherlands)</journal-title>
              </journal-title-group>
              <issn pub-type="ppub">0168-8510</issn>
              <issn pub-type="epub">1872-6054</issn>
              <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Elsevier B.V.</publisher-name>
              </publisher>
            </journal-meta>
            <article-meta>
              <article-id pub-id-type="accession">PMC8529307</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8529307</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmc-uid">8529307</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">33579561</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="pii">S0168-8510(21)00023-3</article-id>
              <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.healthpol.2021.01.006</article-id>
              <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                  <subject>Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
              </article-categories>
              <title-group>
                <article-title>Using newspaper obituaries to “nowcast” daily mortality: Evidence from the Italian COVID-19 hot-spots<sup><xref ref-type="fn" rid="d36e1085">☆</xref></sup></article-title>
              </title-group>
              <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="aut0005">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Buonanno</surname>
                    <given-names>Paolo</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
                  <xref rid="cor0005" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" id="aut0010">
                  <name>
                    <surname>Puca</surname>
                    <given-names>Marcello</given-names>
                  </name>
                  <xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref>
                  <xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="aff0005"><label>a</label>University of Bergamo, Italy</aff>
                <aff id="aff0010"><label>b</label>Webster University Geneva, Switzerland</aff>
              </contrib-group>
              <author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor0005"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author.</corresp>
              </author-notes>
              <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
                <day>27</day>
                <month>1</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.-->
              <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>27</day>
                <month>1</month>
                <year>2021</year>
              </pub-date>
              <volume>125</volume>
              <issue>4</issue>
              <fpage>535</fpage>
              <lpage>540</lpage>
              <history>
                <date date-type="received">
                  <day>3</day>
                  <month>8</month>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="rev-recd">
                  <day>15</day>
                  <month>1</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                  <day>21</day>
                  <month>1</month>
                  <year>2021</year>
                </date>
              </history>
              <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>© 2021 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2021</copyright-year>
                <copyright-holder>Elsevier B.V.</copyright-holder>
                <license>
                  <license-p>Since January 2020 Elsevier has created a COVID-19 resource centre with free information in English and Mandarin on the novel coronavirus COVID-19. The COVID-19 resource centre is hosted on Elsevier Connect, the company's public news and information website. Elsevier hereby grants permission to make all its COVID-19-related research that is available on the COVID-19 resource centre - including this research content - immediately available in PubMed Central and other publicly funded repositories, such as the WHO COVID database with rights for unrestricted research re-use and analyses in any form or by any means with acknowledgement of the original source. These permissions are granted for free by Elsevier for as long as the COVID-19 resource centre remains active.</license-p>
                </license>
              </permissions>
              <abstract id="abs0010">
                <p>Real-time tracking of epidemic helps governments and health authorities make timely data-driven decisions. Official mortality data, whenever reliable and available, is usually published with a substantial delay. We report results of using newspapers obituaries to “nowcast” the mortality levels observed in Italy during the COVID-19 outbreak between February 24, 2020 and April 15, 2020. Mortality levels predicted using obituaries outperform forecasts based on past mortality according to several performance metrics, making obituaries a potentially valid alternative source of information to deal with epidemic surveillance.</p>
              </abstract>
              <kwd-group id="kwd0010">
                <title>Keywords</title>
                <kwd>COVID-19</kwd>
                <kwd>Forecasting</kwd>
                <kwd>Excess mortality</kwd>
                <kwd>Big data</kwd>
              </kwd-group>
            </article-meta>
          </front>
          <body>
            <sec id="sec0005">
              <label>1</label>
              <title>Introduction</title>
              <p id="par0025">Since the first suspected pneumonia cases observed on December 2019 in Wuhan (China), the novel coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2), causing a severe acute respiratory syndrome (COVID-19), has turned into a pandemic and a global challenge (c.f. <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>). In response, policymakers across the world are monitoring epidemiological indicators in real-time aiming to define successful containment measures <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0015" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. Among such indicators, deaths caused by COVID-19, general mortality rates, and excess mortality are three standard epidemiological indicators used by the World Health Organization (WHO) to monitor the spread of an infectious disease <xref rid="bib0025" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>. However, comparing the current total mortality rate to the average mortality rate of previous years, which is the definition of excess mortality, is more reliable compared to “crude” or adjusted case fatality rates (c.f. <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0035" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>). Indeed, the number of deaths caused by an infectious disease may either be underestimated if the health system fails to detect the infection in a dead patient (<italic>censoring bias</italic>), or overestimated if the health system focuses only on severe cases (<italic>ascertainment bias</italic>) <xref rid="bib0040" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0045" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0050" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0055" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>.</p>
              <p id="par0030">While excess mortality does not suffer from such biases, it might be difficult to estimate during a pandemic peak for two reasons. First, vested interests may incentivize some policymakers to hide deaths and cases caused by an infectious disease <xref rid="bib0060" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, which means that the reported number of deaths may under-represent the actual mortality rate <xref rid="bib0065" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. Second, even under the assumption that official statistics do not suffer from any bias, in almost all countries, official mortality records are published with a substantial delay. Indeed, the latest release of the WHO mortality database currently available, was updated on November 15, 2019 <xref rid="bib0075" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. In this respect, the latest Italian National Statistical Institute (ISTAT) release of official mortality data, published on May 9, 2020, which covers the period between January 1, 2020 to April 15, 2020, should be seen as an “early release”. Indeed, ISTAT usually publishes mortality data after at least one year (see Section <xref rid="sec0010" ref-type="sec">2</xref> for further details). This release followed the concern raised by several Italian policymakers during the early stage of the COVID-19 outbreak that the official statistics were not accurately representing the actual number of deaths caused by COVID-19, which was believed to be much higher <xref rid="bib0080" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>.</p>
              <p id="par0035">In this paper we propose a novel approach to deal with the publication delay of mortality data by “nowcasting” daily mortality using newspaper obituaries as an alternative source of information. Using standard forecasting techniques, we compare different models, and find that forecasts based on obituaries outperform autoregressive forecasts based on previous mortality rates according to several accuracy criteria. More specifically, we use obituaries published on the local newspapers of Bergamo (120,000 inhabitants) and Brescia (196,000 inhabitants), both in the Lombardy region, during the interval between February 24 to May 14, 2020. Lombardy is considered the European hot-spot of the first COVID-19 wave, with 88,183 reported cases and 15,974 deaths as of May 25, 2020, over a total population of approximately 10 million inhabitants <xref rid="bib0090" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>. It therefore represents a relevant case study for our research purpose. Our findings show that newspaper obituaries account for, roughly, half of the actual number of deaths and can be a valid, reliable, and timely alternative to official mortality statistics. Indeed, while being a non-uniform representation of a society, obituaries are used across the world and in different cultures (e.g. <xref rid="bib0100" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0105" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>). These results may be relevant for many policymakers and health authorities for the surveillance of new infectious disease outbreaks. The next section presents the data used in our estimates, and the empirical methodology. In the third section we report our results. In the fourth and final section we discuss the limitations of our approach and provide possible policy recommendations.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0010">
              <label>2</label>
              <title>Data and methods</title>
              <p id="par0040">The basic principle of “nowcasting” is to exploit information which is published at a higher frequency than the variable of interest <xref rid="bib0110" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. We thus use this approach to address the delay associated with the publication of official mortality data, and obtain a prediction of COVID-19 severity in almost real-time. We start by describing our dataset and then explore the accuracy of estimates based on newspaper obituaries published in two local newspapers using standard forecasting techniques.</p>
              <sec id="sec0015">
                <label>2.1</label>
                <title>Data</title>
                <sec id="sec0020">
                  <label>2.1.1</label>
                  <title>Newspapers obituaries</title>
                  <p id="par0045">We digitalized obituaries published online by <italic>L’Eco di Bergamo</italic> and <italic>Il Giornale di Brescia</italic>, the two most circulated newspapers in the provinces of Bergamo and Brescia, respectively. In 2019, the daily number of readers of <italic>L’Eco di Bergamo</italic> was 402,000, while the daily number of readers of <italic>Il Giornale di Brescia</italic> was 427,000 (c.f. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://audipress.it/quotidiani/" id="intr0005">http://audipress.it/quotidiani/</ext-link>). Each obituary contains individual characteristics such as name, surname, age, gender, date of death and municipality of death. Our final dataset contains 4054 and 3874 unique individuals from February 24 to May 14, 2020 for the provinces of Bergamo and Brescia, respectively. Newspaper obituaries contain a wide range of information about the victim such as name, surname, gender, age, date of death, and the municipality of death. <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>
displays the daily progression of mortality (solid line) and the number of published obituaries (dashed line) for each of the two municipalities in our sample. By comparing the number of obituaries to the number of actual registered deaths in our sample, we conclude that obituaries represent roughly 56% percent of the total number of deaths. Although obituaries represent only a subset of the officially registered deaths, with a gap increasing during the peak, the correlation between the two measures is glaring, and approximately equal to 97%.<fig id="fig0005"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Deaths vs Obituaries. <italic>Notes:</italic> Daily progression of deaths (solid line) and obituaries (dashed line) in our sample.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0005">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1_lrg"/></fig></p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="sec0025">
                  <label>2.1.2</label>
                  <title>Official mortality</title>
                  <p id="par0050">We combine obituaries data with mortality data at the municipality level released by ISTAT on May 9, 2020. ISTAT data are publicly available online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.istat.it/it/archivio/240401" id="intr0010">https://www.istat.it/it/archivio/240401</ext-link>. The ISTAT dataset contains daily deaths at the municipality level from January 1 to April 15, 2020 for a sample of 4,433 Italian municipalities. The ISTAT sample covers all municipalities belonging to the two provinces of our analysis (243 and 205 municipalities in the provinces of Bergamo and Brescia, respectively).</p>
                </sec>
              </sec>
              <sec id="sec0030">
                <label>2.2</label>
                <title>Methods</title>
                <p id="par0055"><italic>Formulation of the Augmented-ARMA(1,2) model</italic>. We use an auto-regressive moving-average model of mortality <italic>augmented</italic> with newspaper obituaries, which we label <italic>Augmented-ARMA (AARMA)</italic>. We select an AARMA(1,2) specification after inspectiing the autocorrelation and partial autocorrelation plots which display, respectively, a one-lag significant autocorrelation coefficient, and a two-lag partial autocorrelation coefficients (c.f. <xref rid="fig0020" ref-type="fig">Figs. 4</xref> and <xref rid="fig0025" ref-type="fig">5</xref> in Section A). Formally, this writes as<disp-formula id="eq0005"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si3.svg"><mml:mtable displaystyle="true"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:munderover><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:msub><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mover><mml:mo>→</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mover><mml:mi>MA</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M2" altimg="si4.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>deaths</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> is the log-transformed number of deaths observed on day <inline-formula><mml:math id="M3" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M4" altimg="si6.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> is the unconditional mean of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M5" altimg="si7.svg"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M6" altimg="si8.svg"><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the number of model lags, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M7" altimg="si9.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>obituaries</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> is the log-transformed number of newspaper obituaries referring to deaths occurred on day <inline-formula><mml:math id="M8" altimg="si5.svg"><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, which is assumed to be exogenous with respect to the time series <inline-formula><mml:math id="M9" altimg="si10.svg"><mml:mo stretchy="false">{</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">}</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M10" altimg="si11.svg"><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle mathvariant="double-struck"><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>).</p>
                <p id="par0060">In what follows, we compare the accuracy of the AARMA(1,2) predictions to those we would obtain with: (i) an OLS model (i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M11" altimg="si12.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>ε</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>); (ii) an AR(1) (resp. AR(3)) model without information on obituaries, i.e. model <xref rid="eq0005" ref-type="disp-formula">(1)</xref> with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M12" altimg="si13.svg"><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M13" altimg="si14.svg"><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula> (resp. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M14" altimg="si15.svg"><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:math></inline-formula>).</p>
                <p id="par0065"><italic>Accuracy metrics</italic>. The root mean squared error (RMSE), mean absolute error (MAE), mean absolute percentage error (MAPE), and Theil's U of the estimator <inline-formula><mml:math id="M15" altimg="si16.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">ˆ</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> to the target mortality level <inline-formula><mml:math id="M16" altimg="si17.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> are defined, respectively, as<list list-type="simple" id="lis0010"><list-item id="lsti0025"><label>•</label><p id="par0070"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M17" altimg="si18.svg"><mml:mi>RMSE</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">ˆ</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">ˆ</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula></p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0030"><label>•</label><p id="par0075"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M18" altimg="si19.svg"><mml:mi>MAE</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">ˆ</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">ˆ</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula></p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0035"><label>•</label><p id="par0080"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M19" altimg="si20.svg"><mml:mi>MAPE</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">ˆ</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mfrac><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo>∑</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">ˆ</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">|</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula></p></list-item><list-item id="lsti0040"><label>•</label><p id="par0085"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M20" altimg="si21.svg"><mml:mi>Theil</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">ˆ</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>RMSE</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">ˆ</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>RMSE</mml:mi><mml:mi>naive</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></inline-formula></p></list-item></list>where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M21" altimg="si22.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>RMSE</mml:mi><mml:mi>naive</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula> refers to the RMSE of a naive forecast, i.e. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M22" altimg="si23.svg"><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></inline-formula>
<xref rid="bib0115" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. The AIC and BIC are defined, respectively, as <inline-formula><mml:math id="M23" altimg="si24.svg"><mml:mi>AIC</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">ˆ</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M24" altimg="si25.svg"><mml:mi>BIC</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">ˆ</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>, where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M25" altimg="si26.svg"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="true">ˆ</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math></inline-formula> maximizes the likelihood function of the estimated model, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M26" altimg="si27.svg"><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the number of estimated parameters, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M27" altimg="si28.svg"><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the sample size.</p>
              </sec>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0035">
              <label>3</label>
              <title>Results</title>
              <p id="par0090"><xref rid="tbl0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> reports the accuracy of different forecasting models of daily mortality from February 24, 2020 to May 15, 2020, with <italic>Panel A</italic> (resp. <italic>Panel B</italic>) reporting observations for the municipality of Bergamo (resp. Brescia). Specifically, we compare the estimated mortality level to the true mortality published by ISTAT on May 9, 2020 and computed different accuracy metrics described in Section <xref rid="sec0010" ref-type="sec">2</xref>. In addition to these measures, we include the Theil's U, the Akaike's information criterion (AIC), and the Bayesian Information Criterion (BIC). We compare these measures for (i) ordinary least squares (OLS) estimates; (ii) “augmented” autoregressive-moving-average (AARMA(1,2)) estimates with obituaries as exogenous variables; (iii) one-lag autoregressive estimates (AR(1)); (iv) three-lag autoregressive estimates (AR(3)). Lower values of each of these measures correspond to more accurate forecasts. Therefore, according to every performance metric, we report that AARMA(1,2) outperforms all other models, and for both provinces in our sample.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0005"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Comparison of different forecasting models of mortality.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0030">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">Model</th><th align="left">RMSE</th><th align="left">MAE</th><th align="left">MAPE</th><th align="left">Theil's U</th><th align="left">AIC</th><th align="left">BIC</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>Panel A:</italic> Bergamo</td><td align="left">OLS</td><td align="left">0.184</td><td align="left">0.136</td><td align="left">0.032</td><td align="left">0.830</td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M28" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>24.299</td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M29" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>20.396</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">AARMA(1,2)</td><td align="left">0.137</td><td align="left">0.113</td><td align="left">0.026</td><td align="left">0.581</td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M30" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>51.078</td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M31" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>39.370</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">AR(1)</td><td align="left">0.215</td><td align="left">0.165</td><td align="left">0.039</td><td align="left">0.989</td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M32" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>8.131</td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M33" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>2.277</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">AR(3)</td><td align="left">0.210</td><td align="left">0.163</td><td align="left">0.039</td><td align="left">0.961</td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M34" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>6.915</td><td align="left">2.841</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Panel B:</italic> Brescia</td><td align="left">OLS</td><td align="left">0.172</td><td align="left">0.140</td><td align="left">0.033</td><td align="left">0.953</td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M35" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>31.734</td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M36" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>27.832</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">AARMA(1,2)</td><td align="left">0.158</td><td align="left">0.122</td><td align="left">0.029</td><td align="left">0.863</td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M37" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>35.067</td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M38" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>23.359</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">AR(1)</td><td align="left">0.194</td><td align="left">0.151</td><td align="left">0.035</td><td align="left">0.986</td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M39" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>23.034</td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M40" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>17.181</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">AR(3)</td><td align="left">0.191</td><td align="left">0.148</td><td align="left">0.034</td><td align="left">0.981</td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M41" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>19.623</td><td align="left"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M42" altimg="si2.svg"><mml:mo>−</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>9.866</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><italic>Notes:</italic> Metrics of forecast accuracy. AARMA(1,2) refers to model <xref rid="eq0005" ref-type="disp-formula">(1)</xref>. RMSE, MAE, MAPE, and Theil's U are for root mean squared error, mean absolute error, mean absolute percent error, and Theil's U statistic, respectively. AIC and BIC refer to the Akaike's Information Criterion and the Bayesian Information Criterion, respectively.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
              <p id="par0095">We also report in <xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>
the forecasted mortality against the observed mortality, while <xref rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>
displays the daily evolution of the estimated standard errors for each model. In <xref rid="fig0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>, note that the AR(1) and the AR(3) curves overlap. In <xref rid="fig0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>, note that the curves refer both to the in-sample (resp. out-of-sample) forecast, as they refer to the period before (resp. after) April 15, i.e. the last available date for official mortality data provided by ISTAT. Both the AARMA(1,2) and the OLS estimates have a much lower prediction error, and a close inspection of the estimates shows that both AARMA(1,2) and OLS estimates outperform models based only on previously observed mortality data (i.e. AR(1) and AR(3)) over the entire period in our sample.<fig id="fig0010"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Forecasts. <italic>Notes:</italic> Daily progression of each forecasting model with the actual <inline-formula><mml:math id="M43" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">Deaths</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula> (solid green line) on the vertical axis and the corresponding <italic>date</italic> on the horizontal axis. The other lines refer to the forecasted <inline-formula><mml:math id="M44" altimg="si1.svg"><mml:mo>ln</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">Deaths</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math></inline-formula>. (For interpretation of the references to color in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the web version of this article.)</p></caption><alt-text id="at0010">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2_lrg"/></fig><fig id="fig0015"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Prediction error. <italic>Notes:</italic> Daily evolution of the prediction error for each forecasting model. Note that the AR(1) and AR(3) curves overlap.</p></caption><alt-text id="at0015">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3_lrg"/></fig></p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0040">
              <label>4</label>
              <title>Discussion and limits</title>
              <p id="par0100">Our approach, though powerful, is not free from limitations. First, despite being concentrated in the most affected Italian region, our sample refers only to two provinces. Second, since they are costly, newspaper obituaries may under-represent the actual mortality level, in particular for lower income or marginalized communities. This issue becomes more severe during the epidemic peak (see <xref rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). The effect of such under-representation on our estimates, however, is mixed. On the one hand, if obituaries were published for every COVID19 victim, our results would (obviously) be only marginally more accurate, as the sample would virtually coincide with the actual population. It is less obvious, on the other hand, what is the implication of the households-level heterogeneity towards the publication of obituaries on the accuracy of our forecasts. We are also agnostic about potentially heterogeneous behavioral attitudes towards such publications in other locations or cultures. In this respect, the large variance observed in civic attitudes and prosocial behavior across Italian municipalities may play a role in determining this attitude (c.f. <xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>). Understanding how such cultural heterogeneity may affect our conclusions, as well as increasing the sample size so as to include more municipalities, constitutes a valuable path for future research.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="sec0045">
              <label>5</label>
              <title>Conclusion and policy implications</title>
              <p id="par0105">We used newspaper obituaries to “nowcast” daily mortality observed in Italy during the first COVID-19 outbreak peak. We find that forecasting models which use obituaries outperform other models based on previously observed mortality, and we report that obituaries account, on average, for 56% of the actual deaths. Although the results should be interpreted cautiously in light of the assumptions and limitations inherent to our approach, their implications may help health authorities – possibly of any geographical entity – in the interpretation of observed surveillance data and provide indications for the magnitude and timing of possible future epidemic waves. More specifically, collecting newspaper obituaries in a centralized database would provide a valid alternative to official mortality figures, which could be used by health authorities to assess the actual severity of COVID-19 in almost real-time and, in turn, timely implement effective containment measures.</p>
            </sec>
          </body>
          <back>
            <ref-list id="bibl0005">
              <title>References</title>
              <ref id="bib0005">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0005">
                  <part-title>Coronavirus disease (COVID-19) pandemic. Technical report</part-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <publisher-name>World-Health-Organization</publisher-name>
                  <comment>Available online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019" id="intr0015">https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019</ext-link></comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0010">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0010">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Hatchett</surname>
                      <given-names>R.J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mecher</surname>
                      <given-names>C.E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lipsitch</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Public health interventions and epidemic intensity during the 1918 influenza pandemic</article-title>
                  <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
                  <volume>104</volume>
                  <issue>18</issue>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <fpage>7582</fpage>
                  <lpage>7587</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17416679</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0015">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0015">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Yang</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Santillana</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Kou</surname>
                      <given-names>S.C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Accurate estimation of influenza epidemics using Google search data via ARGO</article-title>
                  <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
                  <volume>112</volume>
                  <issue>47</issue>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <fpage>14473</fpage>
                  <lpage>14478</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26553980</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0020">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0020">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Xu</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Li</surname>
                      <given-names>Y.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Beware of the second wave of COVID-19</article-title>
                  <source>Lancet</source>
                  <volume>395</volume>
                  <issue>10233</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>1321</fpage>
                  <lpage>1322</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32277876</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0025">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0025">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>World-Health-Organization</surname>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>Revealing the toll of COVID-19: a technical package for rapid mortality surveillance and epidemic response. Technical report</part-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <publisher-name>WHO</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0030">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0030">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Buonanno</surname>
                      <given-names>P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Galletta</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Puca</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Estimating the severity of COVID-19: evidence from the Italian epicenter</article-title>
                  <source>PLOS ONE</source>
                  <volume>15</volume>
                  <issue>10</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>e0239569</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33002036</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0035">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0035">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Modi</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Boehm</surname>
                      <given-names>V.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Ferraro</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stein</surname>
                      <given-names>G.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Seljak</surname>
                      <given-names>U.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>How deadly is COVID-19? A rigorous analysis of excess mortality and age-dependent fatality rates in Italy</article-title>
                  <source>medRxiv</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0040">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0040">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Atkins</surname>
                      <given-names>K.E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wenzel</surname>
                      <given-names>N.S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>deffo-Mbah</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Altice</surname>
                      <given-names>F.L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Townsend</surname>
                      <given-names>J.P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Galvani</surname>
                      <given-names>A.P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Under-reporting and case fatality estimates for emerging epidemics</article-title>
                  <source>BMJ</source>
                  <volume>350</volume>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <fpage>h1115</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.h1115</pub-id>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25779635</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0045">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0045">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Lipsitch</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Donnelly</surname>
                      <given-names>C.A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fraser</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Blake</surname>
                      <given-names>I.M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Cori</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Dorigatti</surname>
                      <given-names>I.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Potential biases in estimating absolute and relative case-fatality risks during outbreaks</article-title>
                  <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>
                  <volume>9</volume>
                  <issue>7</issue>
                  <year>2015</year>
                  <fpage>e0003846</fpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26181387</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0050">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0050">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Atkeson</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>How deadly is COVID-19? Understanding the difficulties with estimation of its fatality rate. Technical report</part-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <publisher-name>National Bureau of Economic Research</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0055">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0055">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Stock</surname>
                      <given-names>J.H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>Data gaps and the policy response to the novel coronavirus. Technical report</part-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <publisher-name>National Bureau of Economic Research</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0060">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0060">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Guardian staff</surname>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>Global report: Bolsonaro hides Brazil's coronavirus death toll and case totals</part-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <publisher-name>The Guardian</publisher-name>
                  <comment>Available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2020/jun/07/bolsonaro-strips-death-toll-and-case-totals-from-brazils-coronavirus-updates" id="intr0020">https://www.theguardian.com/world/2020/jun/07/bolsonaro-strips-death-toll-and-case-totals-from-brazils-coronavirus-updates</ext-link></comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0065">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0065">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Wu</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>McCann</surname>
                      <given-names>A.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Katz</surname>
                      <given-names>J.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Peltier</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>161,000 missing deaths: tracking the true toll of the coronavirus outbreak</part-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <publisher-name>The Guardian</publisher-name>
                  <comment>Available online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2020/04/21/world/coronavirus-missing-deaths.html" id="intr0025">https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2020/04/21/world/coronavirus-missing-deaths.html</ext-link></comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0070">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0070">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Arnold</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>What we’ll need to find the true COVID-19 death toll</part-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <publisher-name>National Geographic</publisher-name>
                  <comment>Available online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.nationalgeographic.com/science/2020/05/what-we-need-to-find-true-coronavirus-death-toll/" id="intr0030">https://www.nationalgeographic.com/science/2020/05/what-we-need-to-find-true-coronavirus-death-toll/</ext-link></comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0075">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0075">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>World Health Organization</surname>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>WHO mortality database. Technical report</part-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0080">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0080">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Armstrong</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>Italian mayor claims the true death toll from COVID-19 likely to be much higher</part-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <publisher-name>Euronews</publisher-name>
                  <comment>Available online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.euronews.com/2020/03/21/italian-mayor-claims-the-true-death-toll-from-covid-19-likely-to-be-much-higher" id="intr0035">https://www.euronews.com/2020/03/21/italian-mayor-claims-the-true-death-toll-from-covid-19-likely-to-be-much-higher</ext-link></comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0085">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0085">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Invernizzi</surname>
                      <given-names>I.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>Coronavirus, the real death toll: 4.500 victims in one month in the province of Bergamo</part-title>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <publisher-name>L’Eco di Bergamo</publisher-name>
                  <comment>Available online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ecodibergamo.it/stories/bergamo-citta/coronavirus-the-real-death-tool-4500-victims-in-one-month-in-the-province-of_1347414_11/" id="intr0040">https://www.ecodibergamo.it/stories/bergamo-citta/coronavirus-the-real-death-tool-4500-victims-in-one-month-in-the-province-of_1347414_11/</ext-link></comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0090">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0090">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gatto</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bertuzzo</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Mari</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Miccoli</surname>
                      <given-names>S.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Carraro</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Casagrandi</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <etal/>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Spread and dynamics of the COVID-19 epidemic in Italy: effects of emergency containment measures</article-title>
                  <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
                  <volume>117</volume>
                  <issue>19</issue>
                  <year>2020</year>
                  <fpage>10484</fpage>
                  <lpage>10491</lpage>
                  <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32327608</pub-id>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0095">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0095">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Gibertoni</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Adja</surname>
                      <given-names>K.Y.C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Golinelli</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reno</surname>
                      <given-names>C.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Regazzi</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fantini</surname>
                      <given-names>M.P.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>Patterns of COVID-19 related excess mortality in the municipalities of Northern Italy</article-title>
                  <source>medRxiv</source>
                  <year>2020</year>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0100">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0100">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Booth</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The world of obituaries: gender across cultures and over time</article-title>
                  <source>Biography</source>
                  <volume>26</volume>
                  <issue>3</issue>
                  <year>2003</year>
                  <fpage>453</fpage>
                  <lpage>456</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0105">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sbref0105">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Fowler</surname>
                      <given-names>B.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bielsa</surname>
                      <given-names>E.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <article-title>The lives we choose to remember: a quantitative analysis of newspaper obituaries</article-title>
                  <source>Sociol Rev</source>
                  <volume>55</volume>
                  <issue>2</issue>
                  <year>2007</year>
                  <fpage>203</fpage>
                  <lpage>226</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0110">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0110">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Bańbura</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Giannone</surname>
                      <given-names>D.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Modugno</surname>
                      <given-names>M.</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                      <surname>Reichlin</surname>
                      <given-names>L.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>Now-casting and the real-time data flow</part-title>
                  <source>Handbook of economic forecasting, vol. 2</source>
                  <year>2013</year>
                  <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>
                  <fpage>195</fpage>
                  <lpage>237</lpage>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0115">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0115">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Theil</surname>
                      <given-names>H.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>Applied economic forecasting</part-title>
                  <year>1966</year>
                  <publisher-name>Rand McNally and Company</publisher-name>
                  <publisher-loc>Chicago</publisher-loc>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
              <ref id="bib0120">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="book" id="sbref0120">
                  <person-group person-group-type="author">
                    <name>
                      <surname>Putnam</surname>
                      <given-names>R.</given-names>
                    </name>
                  </person-group>
                  <part-title>The prosperous community: social capital and public life. The American prospect, 13(Spring), vol. 4</part-title>
                  <year>1933</year>
                  <comment>Available online: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.prospect.org/print/vol/13" id="intr0045">http://www.prospect.org/print/vol/13</ext-link></comment>
                </element-citation>
              </ref>
            </ref-list>
            <sec id="sec0050">
              <label>Appendix A</label>
              <title>Figures</title>
              <p id="par0110">
                <fig id="fig0020">
                  <label>Fig. 4</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Autocorrelations. <italic>Notes:</italic> Autocorrelation of the natural logarithm of daily mortality for Bergamo (top) and Brescia (bottom).</p>
                  </caption>
                  <alt-text id="at0020">Fig. 4</alt-text>
                  <graphic xlink:href="gr4_lrg"/>
                </fig>
                <fig id="fig0025">
                  <label>Fig. 5</label>
                  <caption>
                    <p>Partial autocorrelations. <italic>Notes:</italic> Partial autocorrelation of the natural logarithm of daily mortality for Bergamo (top) and Brescia (bottom).</p>
                  </caption>
                  <alt-text id="at0025">Fig. 5</alt-text>
                  <graphic xlink:href="gr5_lrg"/>
                </fig>
              </p>
            </sec>
            <fn-group>
              <fn id="d36e1085">
                <label>☆</label>
                <p id="npar0005"><italic>This version: January 13, 2021 (First version: May 29, 2020)</italic>. The authors thank Nunzia Vallini and Mauro Torri at <italic>Il Giornale di Brescia</italic>. The authors also thank Sergio Galletta, Saverio Simonelli, Juan F. Vargas, and one anonymous referee for their comments, and Endri Avduli and Oumar Ben Salha for valuable research assistance. The authors contributed equally to this work. The authors declare no conflicting interests. The authors did not receive funding for this project.</p>
              </fn>
            </fn-group>
          </back>
        </article>
      </metadata>
    </record>
  </GetRecord>
</OAI-PMH>
